hello and welcome to the three action
economy in Pathfinder second edition by
how it's played
in Pathfinder's second edition time is
measured in different ways depending on
the circumstances of the narrative the
downtime between Adventures is measured
in days exploration is measured in
minutes and hours and combat encounters
are measured in rounds and turns I'm not
going to get too deep into the structure
of rounds and turns here make sure you
check out my videos on Initiative for
more information about that but what is
important to know for this discussion is
during each creature's turn they have a
finite number of actions they can spend
in order to describe the things they
wish their character to do during that
turn at the start of each player's turn
they are granted three actions to spend
on their turn and one reaction that can
be spent at any time including during
another creature's turn I find it best
to think of these actions and reactions
as currencies that the player can spend
the think of it like Monopoly money at
the start of every player's turn the GM
gives them three bills Each of which is
worth one action and also a fourth bill
of a different color that is worth one
reaction they have until the end of
their turn to spend the three action
bills any that aren't spent by the end
of their turn are lost and they have
until the start of their next turn to
spend their one reaction bill or it is
lost as well and then the cycle repeats
itself and they're granted three more
action bills in one new reaction bill at
the start of that next turn
Pathfinder uses simple notations to show
the cost of activities which are
represented by a number of Black Diamond
errors and these are displayed in the
descriptions of abilities to note their
cost for example the strike action which
is a basic attack in Pathfinder shows
one black diamond Arrow at the top of
its description which means it costs one
action to perform and yes this does mean
that you can spend all three of your
actions in one turn to attack three
times but there is a drawback to doing
so the strike action also has the attack
trait and any action with the attack
trait is subject to the multiple attack
penalty this is a little outside of the
scope of a conversation about action
economy but the multiple attack penalty
says that there is no penalty for the
first attack made during a turn there is
a negative five penalty applied to the
second attack made during that turn and
a negative 10 penalty applied to every
attack made after the second
it is possible to have more than three
actions to spend in a turn for example
if a character is under the effects of a
haste spell so in that case if they
spent all four actions on strike the
first would have no penalty the second
would have a negative five penalty and
both the third and the fourth strikes
would each suffer a negative 10 penalty
one exception to this is when using a
weapon with the agile trait agile
weapons like daggers suffer reduced
penalties attacks made with an agile
weapon are negative four for the second
attacking round and negative eight for
the third in any following attacks in a
round
so a simple combat example might look
like this Belarus is wielding a long
sword and wishes to attack a goblin that
is standing on the other side of a
fallen column
at the start of his turn he is granted
three actions and one reaction he spends
his first action to perform stride strod
is the standard means of moving in
Pathfinder it costs one action and
allows a character to move up to a
number of feet equal to their speed
score
Belarus has a speed score of 25 so he
may walk up to 25 feet or 5 squares on a
map
the phone column is only four squares
away so he moves up to it and stops
since he cannot walk over the column he
Nick spins another action on leap leap
costs one action and allows a creature
to jump short distances without the need
for an athletic skill check the GM
agrees that vaulting over this ruined
column qualifies and valorous lands in
the Square on the other side and
adjacent to the goblin he now spends his
third and Last Action to perform a
strike and attacks the Goblin
that was a simple example using basic
actions that East cost won but there are
also more complex activities that cost
two or more actions one place you are
likely to encounter this is with spells
most spells have a cost of two actions
for example acid Arrow shows two Diamond
arrows in its casting time so we know it
costs two actions to cast it this is
typical for most spells but there are
exceptions most summoning spells like
summon Elemental cost three actions and
there are even some spells that function
differently depending on how many
actions you wish to spend on them for
example magic Missile can be cast using
one two or three actions with each
action adding an additional missile and
yes this does mean that a wizard could
cast with acid arrow and the one action
version of magic Missile in the same
round
another common example of a spell with a
variable action cost would be heal heal
also can be cast with one two or three
actions and each version Alters the
effects of the spell
for one action the spell has a range of
touch it can only be used to heal the
Caster or an adjacent Ally for two
actions the spell increases its range to
30 feet and also heals an extra eight
hit points and if heel is cast using
three actions it heals all living
targets within 30 feet of the caster
multi-action activities oranges for
spellcasters though lots of classes have
their own special abilities that cost
two or three actions like Hunters aim
for Rangers which costs two actions but
allows them to make a strike that
ignores concealment and gains a bonus to
damage the key to remember with multiple
action activities though is that any
activity you start in around must be
completed in the same round so you can't
begin casting a spell with your third
action on one round and finish casting
it with your first action on the next
round also you cannot start a new action
or activity until you finish the first
so for example you can't spend an action
destroyed or strike in the middle of the
two actions spent to cast a spell nor
could you spin an action to strike in
the middle of moving with a stride
action if you have a speed score of 30
and want to walk forward 15 feet attack
with a melee weapon and then walk
another 15 feet you would need to spend
one action to stride and then stop and
then spend a second action to strike and
then spend your third action destroyed
again you must complete an action before
spending another action so you could not
spend an action to strike in the middle
of a strut action even if you have
enough speed score to cover all of that
movement that's it I should mention that
the game mastery guide does provide some
leeway for James to roll differently in
some cases and I do have a separate
video that covers those exceptions and
it is linked in this video's description
in addition to the three actions a
player may spend on their turn they also
receive one reaction they may spend at
any time including on another creature's
turn reactions are noted by a backwards
turning Arrow like we see here with
retributive strike each reaction also
includes a specific trigger that lets
you know when you can spend your
reaction to perform it here it says
trigger an enemy damages your Ally and
both are within 15 feet of you so if
during a monster's turn it damages an
ally and both that monster and the Ally
that is damaged is within 15 feet of
this character they may spin their
reaction to perform retributive strike
when they do so the Ally gains
resistance to the triggering damage
equal to two plus the Champions level
and if the monster is also Within Reach
of the champion they get to make a melee
strike against it
so if seal of the champion finishes her
turn and then an adjacent monster
attacks an ally within 15 feet of her
she may spend her reaction on
retributive strike if the monster spins
its next action to attack that Ally
again Sila cannot make a second
retributive strike because reactions are
like currency she was granted one
reaction at the start of her turn and
has already spent it she will need to
wait until the start of her next turn
before she is granted another reaction
to spend
there is one last type of action we
should discuss and those are free
actions as the name suggests free
actions are things players can do on
their term that do not cost any of their
actions or reactions saying a few words
yelling look out or dropping an item to
the ground would all be examples of free
actions free actions are also noted in
the book with a hollowed out action
Diamond like we see here with release
this means the player can use release
without spending one of their actions
and is common for free actions to have
triggers so they function like reactions
but without the need to spend a reaction
to do so an example of this would be
divine weapon it has a trigger of you
finish casting a spell using one of your
Divine spell slots on your turn when
this happens the player can use Divine
weapon as a free action which allows
their weapon to deal additional damage
until the end of their turn in general
there is no hard limit to the number of
free actions a player can perform beyond
what the GM will allow and consider
common sense but there are a few
specific limits that you should be aware
of first some free actions have a
frequency listing in their description
like Divine weapon that limits it to
once per turn also when a free action
has a trigger you can only use it one
time per each triggering occurrence so
if theoretically there was a free action
that granted an untyped plus one bonus
to damage with a trigger you couldn't
take infinite free actions to get an
infinite bonus to damage it would be
limited to once per specific triggering
event
and last if a player has multiple
abilities that Grant free actions with
the trigger your turn begins then they
can only perform one of them you can't
use all of them only one free action can
be used when a turn begins
so that's a quick overview of how the
action economy works with reactions a
reaction and free actions there are a
few related topics like subordinate
actions that I think call for their own
videos and I'll save those items for
later discussions
if you have any questions about the
three action economy please leave them
below I will leave links in the
description of this video for any
related topics like initiative delay
you're ready and a text of opportunity
and as always I want to take a brief
moment to say thank you to everyone who
supports me in this channel whether that
be by clicking the like button
subscribing to the channel subscribing
to the patreon buying a super thanks it
all adds up and I greatly appreciate all
of your support
so with that thanks for watching take
care and happy gaming