foreign
Ty in Pathfinder second edition
proficiency is included in virtually all
stats that determine what a character
can do and How likely they are to
succeed at a given action
weapon proficiency is included in a tag
bonuses armor proficiency is used to
calculate armor class saving through
proficiencies are included when making
saving throws and so on typically these
stats and bonuses are all calculated as
an ability modifier like strength or
Charisma plus a proficiency bonus
proficiency is a simple way of assessing
a character's General level of training
and aptitude at a given task and unlike
some other fantasy role-playing games
you might be used to in Pathfinder
second edition proficiency is not one
flat bonus but instead is broken into
five ranks of increasing value untrained
trained expert master and legendary
so instead of having all characters who
are proficient at a skill having the
same proficiency bonus those who are
experts at the skill will have a higher
bonus than those who are merely trained
by default characters are considered
untrained in all proficiencies unless a
specific feature of the game grants them
a higher rank if you are untrained at a
given task then you do not receive any
proficiency bonus at all and therefore
will only receive a bonus from the
associated ability modifier if your
proficiency rank in a given task is
trained or higher then your proficiency
bonus will be your character's level
plus two if you're trained level plus
four if you're an expert level plus six
if you're a master and level plus eight
if you have a legendary proficiency
one important point to reinforce here is
if you are untrained then you do not add
your level to the role you only add your
level if you are at least trained and
therefore the base modifier for
untrained checks will only be the
associated ability modifier for example
let's say a party of three fifth level
characters are attempting to climb a
steep incline the Rogue is trained in
athletics with a strength score of 12
the fighter has expert Proficiency in
athletics and a strength score of 16 and
The Wizard is untrained in athletics
with a strength score of eight athletic
skill modifiers are calculated as
proficiency bonus plus strength modifier
and proficiency bonuses are calculated
as zero for untrained characters and
level plus an increasing bonus for
trained and higher so the Rogue would
calculate their athletic skill bonus as
five for their level plus two for being
trained for a total proficiency bonus of
plus seven and then they would add their
strength modifier to that of plus one
for a final athletic skill bonus of plus
eight
the fighter would calculate their
proficiency bonus as 5 for their level
plus four for expert proficiency for a
proficiency bonus of plus nine and then
add their strength modifier of plus
three for a final Athletics bonus of
Plus 12.
and the poor wizard is untrained so they
would calculate their proficiency bonus
as plus zero and then apply their
strength modifier of negative one for a
final athletic skill modifier of
negative one
proficiency ranks are gained in
increased wind gaining experience levels
at character creation you will gain
Proficiency in a number of qualities you
will usually gain trained Proficiency in
at least one skill from your background
for example acolytes start the game with
training and religion and scribing lore
and bar keeps are trained in both
diplomacy and alcohol lore
in addition every class provides a
sidebar that lists their starting
proficiencies for example clerics begin
the game as trained in perception then
their saving throws clerics are trained
in fortitude and reflex and have expert
proficiency and will next are skills
clerics start the game as trained in
religion and one other skill that's
determined by the god they worship and
then they gain training in a number of
skills of their choice equal to their
intelligence modifier plus two note that
when a source provides strain
Proficiency in a skill you already have
trained or better Proficiency in you are
allowed to choose training in a
different skill of your choice with the
exception of lore skills if multiple
sources provide training in the same
Allure skill then you gain the training
from the First Source and may choose
another Allure skill for the other
sources for example say you select
acolyte as your background and cleric as
your class both of these sources provide
training in religion therefore you would
gain train Proficiency in religion from
alkalite and would be able to choose
training in any other skill of your
choice for cleric but if both sources
provided training in a lore skill then
you would need to select a different
lore skill and note that this only
applies when gaining trained
proficiencies if two different sources
would increase the proficiency rank of
this same skill to expert then you would
not receive any additional benefits or
be able to choose a different skill to
increase to expert
each class's sidebar goes on to provide
starting proficiencies for attacks
defenses and spells clerics are trained
with simple weapons and their deities
favored weapon they are trained in
unarmored defense by default but may
gain proficiency with armor from their
chosen Doctrine and they have trained
proficiency with Divine spells
characters may also gain proficiency
from the Feats they select such as the
armor proficiency skill training and
weapon proficiency Feats and proficiency
ranks are usually increased through
leveling up
each class provides a table that lays
out level advancement like this one for
the cleric here we see that clerics
receive skill increases at third level
and every odd level after that
when they reach each of these levels the
player May either gain train Proficiency
in one skill that they're currently
untrained in or they may increase the
proficiency rank of any skill by one
step but subject to a limit at third
level and fifth levels you can raise one
skill from trained to expert
as 7th 9th 11th and 13th levels you can
increase the proficiency rank of one
skill by one step to a maximum of Master
proficiency and at 15th level this cap
is removed and skills may have their
proficiency ranks raised as high as
legendary
many actions within the game require a
minimum proficiency rank for skills
these requirements are listed within the
skill descriptions as well as on table 4
1 on page 235. skills themselves are not
typically gated behind a proficiency
requirement but different skill actions
are using the thievery skill as an
example anyone can use the palm and
object in steel actions because they do
not state that they require training but
only people with trained proficiency are
better in thievery can use the disable a
device and pick a lock actions this is
further spelled out in the skill
descriptions where we see that it has a
thievery trained actions heading other
actions throughout the game may also be
restricted by proficiency rank this is
usually denoted with the rank either
trained expert master or a legendary
within parentheses for example electric
Lech Rune is a trap that can be placed
on doors next to the disable entry
within a stat block we see it says dc20
thievery and has expert in parentheses
this means you must have at least expert
Proficiency in thievery to succeed at
disabling this trap although the disable
a device action is listed as requiring
trained proficiency this notation of
bumps that requirement up to expert
this should give you a decent
understanding of proficiency if you have
any questions about this video please
leave them in the comments below and as
always I want to take just a brief
moment to thank everybody out there who
supports this channel whether that be by
clicking the like button subscribing to
the channel subscribing to the patreon
buying a super thanks I greatly
appreciate all of your support and with
that thanks for watching take care and
happy gaming foreign