hello and welcome to multiple attack
penalties in Pathfinder second edition
by how it's played in this video I'll
provide an overview of the multiple
attack penalty how it works and ways to
mitigate it including some options for
your third actions that might be wiser
than taking a negative 10 penalty
Pathfinder uses a system of actions that
players are allowed to spend during
their turns to perform various Feats of
heroics generally speaking players are
allowed to spin their three actions per
turn however they wish in each ability
usually works the same regardless of
where in the action order it is used or
if the same action is repeated over and
over but there are a few exceptions and
the most common of those is probably
attacking there are diminishing returns
when making a repeated weapon attacks in
that every attack after the first will
suffer from the multiple attack penalty
with the multiple attack penalty says is
that every attack during a turn after
the first suffers a penalty there is a
negative five penalty applied to the
second attack in a turn and a negative
10 penalty applied to the third and if
you are able to make more than four
attacks on a turn thanks perhaps to the
hay spell then all attacks beyond the
third also suffer the negative 10
penalty there is one notable exception
to this and that is when fighting with a
weapon that has the agile trait like
daggers short swords and Fists
if you use an agile weapon you only
suffer a negative 4 penalty for the
second attack made during a turn and a
negative eight penalty for all further
attacks
so now that we understand what the
multiple attack penalty is the next
question might be what exactly is an
attack well simply put an attack is
anything that has the attack trait for
example if we look at the description
for strike we see that it doesn't make
any mention of this multiple attack
penalty but it does have the attack
trait and it is this trait that notes
was affected by the multiple attack
penalty let's take a look at a few
examples the acid aerospell has the
attack trait therefore it does suffer
from the multiple attack penalty if a
sorcerer wanted to strike an enemy with
their staff using their first action and
then cast acid Arrow at another Target
with their second and third actions then
the staff attack would suffer no penalty
because it's the first attack made in
that turn but there would be a negative
five penalty applied to the casting of
acid Arrow it would be considered the
second use of an attack action for that
turn even though it caused two actions
to use
just for the sake of comparison let's
take a look at another spell electric
Arc it's similar to acid arrow in that
it's a spell that deals a type of energy
damage to enemies but the multiple
attack penalty would not apply here
because electric Arc does not have the
attack trait and it also wouldn't apply
because electric Arc does not call for
an attack roll instead the target rolls
he's sieving through and the multiple
attack penalty does not apply to safes
disarm Force open grapple shove and trip
are all applications of the athletic
skill that also have the attack trait
therefore they each contribute to and
suffer from the multiple attack penalty
if a player tries to trip an enemy and
then stab them while they're prone there
would be no penalty for the trip but
there would be a negative five penalty
applied to the attack or negative four
if they're using an actual weapon
likewise if the player has two adjacent
enemies to them and tries to shove each
of them in the same turn there will be
no penalty for the first Athletics check
rolled for shove but there would be a
negative five penalty applied to the
second
so yes these kinds of combat Maneuvers
and athletic skill checks are
technically considered attacks and they
do suffer from the multiple attack
penalty but it's very important to
remember that even though they are
mechanically speaking attacks when you
pick up and roll that D20 you are not
making an attack role you're making an
Athletics skill check in this
distinction between an attack roll and a
skill check is very important because it
means that anything that modifies attack
rolls will not apply to their skill
checks like grapple shove and trip
in other words spells like bless would
not apply in these situations because
Bliss grants a bonus to attack roles and
these are not attack rules they are
attacks but they do not make attack
rolls instead they use skill checks and
multiple attack penalties do still apply
here even though they're not attack
roles because the text for multiple deck
penalty doesn't specify anything about
roles it only says that the attack must
have the attack trait
and this sort of works the opposite way
as well an ability like an imperial
sorcerer's blood magic would Grant is
bonus to shoving or tripping someone
because it applies to skill checks but
would not apply to a weapon attack now
if having to apply multi-tech penalties
the skills seems a little unfair you
might want to pick up the Assurance feat
for athletics Assurance may not benefit
from the character strength bonus but it
also is not impacted by multiple attack
penalties which might make Assurance
appealing to players wanting to use
these skill attacks I'm not going to go
any further into that in this video but
I do have another video that discusses
assurance and I'll make sure that I
leave a link to that one in the
description if you want more information
about how that works
there are a few ways to mitigate the
multi-attack penalty in addition to
using an agile weapon I'm going to share
just a few of them with you here but
know there are more options available
especially as you level up agile Grace
is a 10th level fighter feat that lowers
the penalty for using an agile weapon
even further to negative three for the
second attack and negative six for the
Third
double shot lets an archers shoot twice
at different targets for a negative two
penalty each and does not increase the
multiple attack penalty until after the
second shot and Rangers with the Fleury
Hunter's Edge make multiple attacks at
negative 3 and negative six or negative
2 and negative 4 if they're using agile
weapons
so I think everyone can agree that a
negative 10 penalty is pretty rough some
people will like attacking three times
at a turn and hope to get a natural 20
on that third roll but a lot of other
people look for better things to do with
their third action that won't apply that
negative 10 penalty so here I want to
give you a few of my own suggestions
first consider using the third action to
move away if you think your opponent is
able to make a text of opportunity then
spend your third action on a step action
that will let you move five feet without
provoking reactions this forces a melee
opponent to have to sacrifice one of
their actions to follow you unless they
have reach
and if you have a higher speed score
than your enemy then they'll be forced
to spin two of their actions to follow
and keep up with you also look for
opportunities where a simple move could
Grant flanking to an ally
next raise a shield if you're a
Frontline fighter with a shield or
you're a spellcaster with the shield
spell use that third action to get your
Shield up
spend your first action in a turn on a
knowledge check this can be especially
helpful for ranged spellcasters start
the round by making a check to identify
the monster and its weaknesses and then
use that knowledge when attacking with
actions two and three and if you have
access to the guidance spell use that
with your third action to Grant a bonus
to an ally
trade is an application of the deception
skill that imposes the flat-footed
condition against an enemy you could
spend your first action on faint if
that's successful then your enemy will
be flat-footed against your next strike
and if you critically succeed then the
enemy will be flat-footed for both of
your attacks this turn as well as any
attacks you make in the following turn
and similar to faint you could also use
demoralize spend your first action to
intimidate your opponent and apply the
fear condition to them and then follow
up with attacks on your second and third
actions
so those are just a few of my
suggestions for things you can do other
than swinging for the fences and
attacking three times every turn when
that third attack is gonna be facing a
negative 10 or negative 8 penalty to it
so that's a look at the multiple attack
penalty as always if you have any
questions please leave those in the
comments also if you have a suggestion
on what to do with that third action
make sure you share it in the comments
as well I'll leave links to all of my
other videos that touch on this topic in
the description and as always I want to
take a brief moment to thank everyone
who supports this channel whether that's
by liking the video subscribing to the
channel joining the patreon or buying a
super thanks I appreciate all of your
support so with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
foreign
[Music]