hello and welcome to criticals in
Pathfinder second edition by how it's
played in Pathfinder most actions result
in one of four degrees of success
success failure critical success and
critical failure success and failure are
often understood but the two critical
results can sometimes cause confusion so
in this video I'm going to cover how to
determine the degree of success for a
chick and specifically how critical
successes work with damage
determining success or failure is fairly
easy each check involves rolling a D20
adding or subtracting modifiers to it
and then comparing that total to a
difficulty class or DC in the case of
most attacks the target's Armor class is
the DC for that check so for example if
an enemy had an armor class of 24 you
would need to roll a 24 or higher for
that check to be a success and hit them
if you roll a 23 or lower you fail and
it's important to note that the person
rolling the die wins the ties that's
pretty straightforward and probably what
you're used to if you've played other
D20 role-playing games but critical
results is where things differ with
Pathfinder second edition here a check
results in a critical when the modified
total is at least 10 more or 10 less
than the DC
so going back to our example if you're
attacking an enemy that has an armor
class of 24 roll a 19 on the die and
have an attack bonus of plus 15 the
total for that check is 34 which is 10
higher than the target DC and therefore
the result is a critical success as
another example let's say the party
wizard is making an untrained Athletics
check they have a modifier of plus 0 and
the DC for the check is 16. they roll a
4 and the nine plus zero so it's also a
total of four which is more than 10
lower than the DC so they critically
failed this check as you can see in
Pathfinder second edition there are more
ways to score a critical success or a
critical failure than rolling a natural
20 or a natural one
as mentioned before there are four
degrees of success from best result to
worst they are critical success success
failure and critical failure it's
important to remember that in Pathfinder
a natural 20 is not an automatic success
or a critical success likewise a natural
one is not always automatically a
critical failure instead a natural 20
means you calculate success as normal
and then increase the degree of success
by one step in a natural one means you
calculate success as normal and then
decrease its degree of success by one
step
for example let's say a player is
attacking an enemy of a significantly
higher level they have a plus 8 bonus to
attack and their enemy has an armor
class of 30. they're rolling natural 20
but that does not mean they scored a
critical hit instead you need to
determine the degree of success as usual
20 plus 8 is 28 compared to an armor
class of 30 the degree of success is
failure but because they rolled a
natural 20 we increased the degree of
success by one step which turns this
into a normal success they hit the enemy
and deal regular damage and a case like
this is impossible for the player to
score a critical hit on the enemy as
another example let's say a player is
attacking an enemy of a significantly
lower level they have a plus 19 bonus to
attack and their target has an armor
class of 18. they roll a natural one
which does not automatically mean that
they critically fail instead we need to
determine the degree of success so one
on the die plus 19 is a total of 20
compared to Armor class 18. now that
normally would be a success but we need
to lure this degree of success by one
step due to Rolling a natural 1 which
moves it from a normal success to a
normal failure and the same applies to
skills saving throws and any other kind
of check but the keys to remember are
that natural 20s and natural ones do not
automatically Grant critical successes
or critical failures but instead move
the degree of success by one step and in
most cases a natural 20 will result in a
critical success and a natural one will
result in a critical failure but those
are not guaranteed results this only
really becomes an issue when there is a
great disparity between the character
making the role in the DC and the times
where you'll most likely see this is
when untrained characters attempt a
skill check or when lower level
characters decide to attack a monster
they really should have left alone but
as long as the players rolling these
checks are near to the level of the
creature they're attacking 20s will most
likely be critical hits and ones will
most likely be critical failures
so now that we know how to calculate
degrees of success let's talk about
results each action skill ability and
the like includes a formatted
description that spells out in black and
white what happens for each degree of
success for example if we look at the
balance application of the acrobatic
skill we see the four degrees of success
spelled out on a critical success you're
not affected by the narrow surface
you're on and move up to your full speed
on a regular success you can move up to
your full speed but you treat it as if
moving through difficult Terrain on a
regular failure you make new progress
and your action is lost and on a
critical failure you fall so this tells
you what happens for all degrees of
success but some actions don't give you
all four in those cases the missing
degrees of success are still possible
but nothing occurs when you roll one for
example strike which is the main way of
attacking a Pathfinder only tells you
what happens on a critical success and
on a normal success this doesn't mean
that it is impossible to fail or
critically fail when you're attacking it
just means that the action is lost with
nothing happening as a result on a
normal success the attack deals is
expected damage and on a critical
success the strike deals double damage
which means this is a great time for us
to go over how critical hits in double
damage works
when an attack scores a critical hit it
deals double the normal damage what this
means is all damage that would occur for
a regular success is doubled and any
damage that only occurs in the event of
a critical hit is not doubled let's take
a look at a few examples to help
illustrate this
in our first example a fighter scores a
critical hit with their long sword this
attack normally deals 1d8 damage for the
sword plus three for their strength
modifier
since all of this damage normally occurs
on a regular hit you roll it as normal
and then double it so if this finder
rolled A3 on the d8 you would add the
strength modifier a plus three for a
total of six and then double that to
find the total of 12 damage and yes this
does mean that static bonuses like the
strength modifier do get doubled in
Pathfinder which is a little bit
different than some other D20
role-playing games out there
in our second example a rogue scores a
critical hit with their dagger this
attack deals 1d4 damage for the dagger
plus two for their strength modifier
plus another 1d6 damage for sneak attack
they roll A3 for the weapon damage plus
two for their strength and 5 Points from
the sneak attack
now you need to determine how much of
this is doubled because of the critical
hit
we know the weapon damage and the
strength modifier get doubled but what
about the sneak attack damage does that
get doubled well ask yourself would this
sneak attack damage count on a regular
hit
the answer is yes it would so that
damage does get doubled for a final
total of 20 points of damage
in our third example a raging Barbarian
scores a critical hit with their glaive
the damage is 1d8 for the glieve plus
four for their strength modifier plus
two for Raging and another 1d8 because
glaves have the deadly d8 trait the
deadly trait says that an extra amount
of damage is provided on critical hits
they roll a six for the weapon plus four
for strength plus two for Raging plus
four more from the 1d8 they rolled for
the weapon's deadly trait again to
determine the amount that is doubled you
just ask yourself how much of this
damage would be applied on a regular hit
well all of this except for the d8 from
the weapons deadly trait would occur on
a regular success a normal hit so all of
that damage is going to be doubled and
the d8 from the deadly trait would only
apply once therefore you calculate this
as 12 plus 8 plus 4 and then add the
four from the deadly trait for a total
of 28. again you would not double the
four from deadly because deadly does not
occur on regular hits since it is
triggered by critical hits it is not
doubled and yes this doubling also
applies to persistent damage unless the
effect specifically States otherwise as
is the case with the acid Arrow Spell
absent of such a statement if you attack
with a weapon that applies a bleed or
other persistent damage and roll a
critical hit that persistent damage will
be doubled when it is applied to the
Target for every round that it is active
see my other videos on persistent damage
for more information about that
there is one less topic I want to cover
in this video and that is how criticals
affect spells and saving throws this
works almost identically to what we've
already discussed but many damaging
spells in the game Do not spell out what
happens with the four degrees of success
for example the fireball spell is very
concise and does not detail what happens
on a critical success a success a
failure or a critical failure instead
the description says saving through
basic reflex and the key word here is
basic whenever the book lists a basic
saving throw you know it will have these
four results on a critical success the
target suffers no damage on a regular
success the target suffers half damage
on a failure the target suffers full
damage and on a critical failure the
target suffers double damage
so when casting Fireball all Targets
within the area of effect must roll a
basic reflex save those who critically
succeed take no damage those who succeed
but not critically succeed take half the
listed 66 damage those who feel the save
suffer the full listed 66 damage and
those who critically fail suffer double
66 damage since these same four results
apply to the vast majority of damaging
spells that call for saving through
paizo was able to save a lot of text and
Page Space by listing them this way
instead of reprinting the same four
results over and over and over again
so that's it for an overview of
criticals and the four degrees of
success if you want to take your
Critical Hits and failures up another
level you can purchase special critical
hit and critical fumble decks from paizo
I won't go into all of the rules using
these optional accessories here but each
card provides new results for critical
hits like blinding your enemy or for
critical failures or fumbles like
accidentally tossing your weapon into
another square if you have any questions
please leave them in the comments I'll
leave links to all of my other videos
that touch on this topic in the
description and as always I want to take
a brief moment to thank everybody who
supports this channel whether that's by
clicking the like button subscribing to
the channel joining the patreon or
buying a super thanks I greatly
appreciate all of the support out there
with that thanks for watching take care
and happy ending