hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of flanking in
pathfinders second edition
flaking occurs when a creature has to
defend itself from enemies on either
side of it their attention is split
which makes them more vulnerable to
those who are threatening it a creature
that is flanked receives the flat-footed
condition which imposes a negative to
circumstance penalty to their armor
class it makes them vulnerable to other
special attacks such as a rogue sneak
attack but note a flint creature is only
flat-footed against those specific
enemies that flank it they do not suffer
those penalties against enemies who are
not flanking them so how do we determine
if a creature is being flanked and
exactly which of its enemies treat them
as being flat-footed in order for a
creature to be flanked the following two
conditions must be met first it must
have enemies on opposite sides or
opposite corners of it in second both of
those enemies must be wielding melee
weapons or be able to make unarmed
attacks and the flint creature must be
within reach of both of its enemies if
both of these requirements are met then
the creature is flanked and suffers a
negative to penalty 2s armor class
against attacks made by only those
enemies that are flanking it
let's take a closer look at the two
requirements for flanking by reviewing
the examples in the core rulebook an
example 1 we have Valor Rose and Cara
battling and ogre are they flanking it
requirement number 1 says the ogre must
have enemies on opposite sides or
opposite corners if we draw an imaginary
line from the center of valor roses
Square to the center of Cairo Square we
see that line clearly passes through
opposite borders of the ogre space so
the first requirement is met and we can
safely assume they are both wielding
melee weapons so the second requirement
is met as well
therefore the ogre is being flanked and
does suffer a negative two penalty to
its armor class when being attacked by
valorous or kyra in the second example
mauricio closes from the north valorous
in Cara are flanking the ogre but what
about Marissa if we draw imaginary lines
from the center of her Square to the
middle of both valor Rose in kyra
squares we see that neither of those
lines pass through opposite borders or
opposite corners of the ogre and
therefore she is not flanking the ogre
although it suffers a penalty to armor
class against Valerie Sin Cara the ogre
is not treated as flat-footed against
Maurizio therefore she makes attack
roles against the ogres full armor class
and may not treat it as being
flat-footed for any special attacks such
as sneak attack
in the third example Sione and a
Hobgoblin join the battle is Sione being
flanked by the ogre and Hobgoblin in
this case yes she is the first
requirement says there needs to be
enemies on opposite borders of her and
if we draw a line from the center of the
ogre to the center of the Hobgoblin we
see it does indeed pass through opposite
borders of her square and the second
requirement says the enemies need to be
wielding melee weapons or capable of
unarmed attacks and be within reach the
Hobgoblin is adjacent and as a large
creature the ogre has ten feet of reach
therefore the second requirement is met
and Sione is flat-footed against both
the ogre and the Hobgoblin likewise we
should check to see if Sione is flanking
the ogre well we have Maurizio on the
ogres opposite border so that first
requirement is met and the second
requirement depends on what weapon Sione
is wielding if she's wielding a dagger
then no because a dagger can only reach
five feet away which is the adjacent
square but if she was wielding a long
spear then she would be flanking the
ogre because long Spears have a reach of
ten feet and at two vertical squares
away the ogre is ten feet away
but what if Sione and the Hobgoblin were
standing over here which Sione still be
flanked by the ogre and the Hobgoblin
yes you would still be flanked even
though two squares diagonally is fifteen
feet and the ogre only has ten feet of
reach there is an exception to the rule
that says attacks with ten feet of reach
may attack any target within two squares
including two squares diagonally
otherwise having reached with your
attacks would have no benefit at all
against an enemy who is approaching you
from one of the four diagonals next
let's consider Sione moves here
is she flanking the ocher no because if
she draws lines from the center of her
square to the center of each of her ally
squares
none of them passed through opposite
borders of the ogre
but if Marissa moved here she and Sione
would be flanking the ogre because now
their line passes through opposite
corners
in this video we examined the flanking
rules in Pathfinder flanking occurs when
a creatures attention is divided by two
or more enemies on either side of it
their attention is split which makes it
more difficult for them to defend
themselves there are two requirements
that must be met in order for flanking
to occur the first says that you and an
allied must be on opposite borders or
opposite corners of the enemy space and
the second requirement says both you and
your ally must be wielding melee weapons
or be able to make unarmed attacks and
the enemy must be within both of your
reaches in most situations this means
the enemy must be adjacent to you but if
you are wielding a reach weapon such as
a long spear then the enemy may be 10
feet away because a long spur has 10
feet of reach large creatures naturally
have 10 feet of reach huge creatures
have 15 feet of reach and a gargantuan
creature has 20 feet of reach if both of
these requirements are met then the
creature is flat-footed against your
attacks this imposes a negative to
penalty to their armor class and makes
them vulnerable to other special attacks
such as a rogue sneak attack and
remember just because you and one Ally
have flanking against an enemy that
doesn't mean that all of your allies
have flanking against it each character
needs to meet the requirements in order
to be granted flanking
that will bring this video to a close if
you found this video helpful please give
us a like and don't forget to click that
subscribe button and the bell so you
never miss out on our future videos
leave us a comment letting us know what
topics you'd like to see covered in our
future videos and we can always be
reached through our Twitter and Facebook
pages too if you'd like to use some of
the maps that we feature in our videos
and your own games you can find them at
maps of mastery a link to that store can
be found in the description thanks for
watching take care and we'll see you
soon with more basics for your favorite
tabletop games