hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of cover in
Pathfinder 2nd edition
when a target is behind any object that
might hinder your ability to attack them
they have cover from you determining if
an enemy has cover from your tank is
fairly simple all you have to do is draw
an imaginary line from the center of the
space that you occupy to the center of
the space that your target occupies and
ask yourself two simple questions does
this line pass through any objects or
terrain if so then the target has cover
from your attack for example if your
enemy is standing behind a low wall or
over turntable or behind a fallen tree
then some of their body is not exposed
and vulnerable to your attack which
makes it harder for you to hit them and
the second question is are there any
creatures between you and your target a
creature is different from objects in
terrain and that they are able to move
around this doesn't have to be a
traditional or even a living animal to
qualify as a quote creature it could be
an undead skeleton a golem and animated
table or anything else that you might
find in the Pathfinder bestiary
but if that line that you're drawing
from the center of your space to the
center of your target space passes
through another space that's occupied by
a creature then your target is going to
have cover on that attack
once you know there is cover the GM will
need to determine what kind of cover the
target has cover comes in three
varieties standard cover lesser cover
and greater cover in most cases when a
target link passes through an object or
terrain the target will have standard
cover this provides a +2 circumstance
bonus to Armour class to reflect saves
against area tax and a stealth checks
made to hide a sneak or avoid detection
one notable exception to this is if the
target line passes through an object
that completely blocks all line of
effect to the target if the target is in
the next room with a solid wall between
you and it then you're not able to
attack that target at all if a target
with standard cover uses one of their
actions to perform the take cover action
then they receive the benefits of
greater cover which doubles their
protection and grants a +4 circumstance
bonus to armor class reflex saves
against area attacks and stealth checks
made to hide greater cover might also be
awarded whenever the GM feels that it
would be significantly difficult to hit
a target even when they are not using
the take cover action this is a judgment
call but one example might be when the
enemy is standing behind a wall with a
narrow slit in it when the target only
passes through a creature instead of an
object the target most likely has lesser
cover lizard cover only provides a plus
one circumstance bonus to armor class
and no bonus and all to reflux safes
also lesser cover may not be used to
make stealth checks to hide or sneak and
provides no bonus to cells checks also
just like with greater cover the GM is
empowered to make judgment calls and
allow lesser cover to be provided by
objects instead of just by creatures for
example a small pile of rubble and a
cave the GM may decide is tall enough to
give a little protection but is too
small to hide or to take cover behind
and therefore
only provides a lesser cover instead of
standard cover also note that if the
creature that is granting cover is at
least two size categories larger than
both the attacker and their target then
the target receives the benefits of
standard cover instead of lesser cover
which is usually what is awarded when
the target line passes through a
creature likewise if the target is
significantly larger than the object
that is granting it cover
then the GM may rule that they receive
no cover benefits from that object for
example if a huge sized dragon is
standing behind a single tree the target
line might pass through that single tree
on the map but the GM may determine that
that is just not enough to provide
significant cover to the dragon and
therefore either provide less recover or
no cover at all
with all of that in mind let's look at a
few examples first we have valorous
fighting and over he is adjacent with
nothing between him and the ogre so
there is no cover in this situation this
is a pretty simple example for the
second example let's consider Sione if
we draw a line from the center of her
space to the center of the ogre space we
see it does not pass through any objects
but it does pass through a creature
which is valorous and therefore the ogre
does receive the benefits of lesser
cover it doesn't matter that valorous is
Sione our allies his presence still
grants the ogre cover in the third
example mauricio wishes to attack the
ogre from around the corner if we draw a
line from the center of her space to the
center of the ogre space we see it does
pass through the edge of the building
and would grant the ogre the benefits of
standard cover that's the rule by raw
but the Rubik also uses this as an
example of the fluid nature of the rules
and the fact that GM's are encouraged to
adjust things as they see fit
for example allowing mauricio to spin an
action before her attack to lean out or
step away from cover to negate the ogres
cover bonus if she started her turn in
this square she could spend her first
action to lean out from the corner her
second action to strike with her appear
and then her third action to use the
take cover action to lean back away and
press her back flat against the wall and
receive greater cover for herself in
tactical terms when making an adjustment
like this you spend one of your actions
and then draw your line from any corner
of your space to the center of your
target space instead of drawing it from
the center of your space to the center
of their space and in our fourth example
Kyra wishes to make a ranged attack we
draw our line and see it clearly passes
through this building next we should
think about line of effect that's an
awful lot of building between her and
the ogre so would it even be possible
for her to hit that target for this
example we'll say that the GM determined
that even at this angle Kyra can see the
ogre and there is narrow line of effect
usually when the target line passes
through an object the target receives
the benefits of standard cover but in
this case the GM would likely determine
this as the vast majority of the ogre is
obscured behind the side of the building
she's going to impose greater cover
against Cara's attack now for the sake
of discussion let's move Kyra to here if
we drove her line again we see the ogre
still has cover from her attack but
sometimes players ask why is she aiming
down the middle this is a giant
Foursquare monster so why not instead
just attack it in this square and that
makes perfect sense
but remember when calculating armor
class you need to take into account the
size of the creature the bigger the
creature the lower their armor class is
going to be so if objects in your way
make it difficult to hit all of that
creature then there should be a penalty
applied when you are only able to target
1/4 of that creature as in this example
and last let's talk about what happens
when there are multiple sources of cover
such as this example
if the target only passes through
valorous this grants the lesser cover in
a plus one circumstance bonus to the
targets armor class and if it passes
through an obstacle like the edge of
this building is going to give standard
cover in a plus two circumstance bonus
to Armour class so does this mean that
the ogre gets to add both of these
sources of cover together for a total
plus three bonus to their armor class no
because these are both circumstance
bonuses and bonuses of the same type do
not stack or add together instead the
ogre would receive the benefit of the
greater of the two bonuses which would
be standard cover in a plus two bonus to
their armor class that said the GM is
always free to rule differently for
example if there is a crowd
between the attacker and their target
she might rule that the target receives
the benefits of standard or even greater
cover instead of lesser cover that is
usually imposed when there is a creature
blocking your shot
in this video we examined the rules for
cover when a target is behind any object
that might hinder your ability to attack
them they have cover from you
to determine if cover exists there must
be line of effect from you to your
target and if you draw a line from the
center of your space to the center of
your target space and that line passes
through an object or a creature then
they have cover against your attack with
the line passes through an obstacle the
target has standard cover this grants
them a +2 circumstance bonus to armor
class reflex saves against area techs
and stealth checks to hide if a creature
with standard cover spins an action to
take cover they instead receive the
benefits of greater cover which is +4 -
armor class reflex saves against area
techs and stealth checks made to hide if
cover is provided by a creature instead
of an object or terrain then the target
only receives the benefits a lesser
cover which only provides a +1
circumstance of bonus - armor class and
no bonus at all - reflex saves or
stealth checks and remember the GM is
able to make judgment calls to grant
more or less cover in various situations
such as if the target is significantly
larger or smaller than the obstacle in
the path of the attack
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature on
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games