hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of perception in
Pathfinder second edition in this video
we will cover what perception is how
it's calculated when players make
perception checks and when the GM's
might make their perception checks for
them in secret as well as several
aspects that modify perception including
the different states of awareness and
lighting conditions note that this video
is meant to lay a foundation for
perception that will be built upon in
future videos we will discuss
invisibility initiative stealth and how
perception applies to those mechanics in
the future
perception measures how a where a
character is it allows you to notice
things search for what's hidden and tell
whether something about a situation is
suspicious all creatures have a
perception score and almost everyone has
a proficiency rank of at least trained
with perception whatever a GM needs to
test a character's ability to notice
something they will call for a
perception check as with other checks
this is a d20 role that's modified by
applicable bonuses and penalties the
base perception modifier is the
creatures wisdom modifier plus their
proficiency bonus in perception so for
example a first level character who is
trained in perception and has a wisdom
score of 14 would have a base perception
bonus of +5 that's a wisdom score 14
granting a +2 modifier and train
proficiency adds to plus the character's
level for a total of +5 some actions
such as sneaking are challenged by the
witness and character's perception DC
which is simply calculated as 10 plus
the character's base perception modifier
for example your character has a small
trinket in their hand that they're
trying to hide from a couple orcs who
are approaching this is a use of the
palm and object application of the
thievery skill so in this scenario you
would roll a thievery skill check which
would be contested by the perception
DC's of everyone who is observing you
the orc step block does not show their
perception deceive but it does list
their modifier as being +5 and we know
that perception DC's are 10 plus the
perception modifier therefore the DC for
this check is 15 you would roll a d20
and add your thievery skill bonus if the
total of that check is 15 or higher then
you succeed and the orcs don't see that
you are hiding a trinket if the total of
the fever check is 14 or lower then you
fail and they can
all creatures and objects exist in one
of four states of awareness when you are
completely unaware that a creature or an
object is present then that creature or
object is considered to be on noticed
the unnoticed condition by itself does
not limit you but anytime a creature is
unnoticed it is also undetected
undetected means you do not know what
space a creature or object occupies this
could be because you're not even aware
that it is present and therefore is both
unnoticed and undetected or you could
suspect that the creatures present but
you don't know exactly where they are in
which case that target would only be
undetected for example you're in a dark
cave and you hear the sounds of movement
nearby but you can't see what's making
the sounds or know exactly where they
are in that case that creature would be
undetected when dealing with an
undetected target you are flat-footed
against all of their attacks and
although you can't see them to attack
them directly you can't take your best
guess as to which square they occupy and
attack into that space when you do so
the GM will make your attack roll for
you in secret as well as also rolling a
flat check vs. DC 11 now the only
exception of this is if you are making
an area attack as area attacks are not
subject to these flat checks and these
flat checks are meant to represent a
50/50 chance that even if the target is
in the square that you are attacking you
will miss them because is very difficult
to hit a target that you just can't see
and flat checks are just straight d20
rolls with no bonuses or no penalties
whatever the dice shows is your result
if that result is a 10 or lure then it
doesn't matter what the result of your
attack role is that attack
not hit the target even if you rolled a
natural 20 on the attack but if the
result of the flex check is a success
then the attack roll functions as normal
the target does not receive and increase
their armor class for being difficult to
see or for being undetected that penalty
is covered with the flat check and again
remember that this special flex check
only applies to direct attacks and not
area effects a fireball spell does not
need to make a flat check against
undetected targets was the GM makes the
attack roll and flex and secret they
will not reveal the result of either of
those rolls but may likely inform you if
you did hit something they might say
something like you hear the sound of
your arrow hit flesh accented by the
Yelp of a goblin or they may say
something like you hear your Arrowhead
strike the stone floor and ricochet back
against the wall but you as the player
will not know if you missed because of a
bad attack roll or because there is
nothing hiding in that square to be hit
in the first place and note that even if
you do succeed in hitting a target that
is undetected you may know they're there
but you are still flat-footed against
them until you can actually see them the
next state of awareness is called hidden
when a creature is hidden from you you
know exactly which space they are in but
you still cannot see them maybe they
just threw sand in your face bleeding
you but you still know they're standing
right there in front of you unlike with
undetected you know exactly where the
target is even if you cannot see them
attacking a hidden creature works just
like it does with attacking an
undetected target except you make the
attack roll in the flat Shaq vs. DC 11
instead of the GM rolling this for you
in secret otherwise it works the same
way as attacking an undetected target
and you are flat-footed against hidden
targets until you can see them
the final state of awareness is called
observed when you can see a target it is
observed there are no special bonuses
penalties or conditions imposed by an
observed target however it is possible
for an observed target to have the
concealed condition if you cannot see
them clearly for example they're
standing in smoke or in fog or maybe
they're in a shadow you can see them but
the GM determines that your vision is
somehow impaired but no that's so much
so that the target would be considered
as hidden or undetected when attacking a
target that is concealed you must make a
flat check exactly as you do when
attacking a hidden target but the DC is
only five instead of eleven also note
that you are not considered to be
flat-footed against concealed enemies
your are only flat footed against
enemies you cannot see and you can see a
target that is observed but still
concealed
when a player wishes to improve their
awareness of a target they use the seek
action when seeking you're actively
alert and trying to find something you
believe might be hidden within your
field of view this cost one of your
three actions that round and a
perception check is rolled that is
contested by the stealth DC's of any
hidden or undetected creatures in your
field of view this works like most any
other check except it is not ruled by
the player instead this is one of those
times where the GM will make that role
for you in secret without you knowing
what the total of the role is making
this role in secret can sometimes
confuse players or even lead to
accusations of the GM quote cheating but
let me try to explain it this way in the
real world the results of a seek action
are very binary with only two outcomes
you either notice something or you do
not notice something in the real world
you don't know if you failed on a
perception yet to notice something so
let's think about how this works at the
game table in the real world you don't
know if you failed on a perception
can notice something because that
something might not actually be there to
be noticed in the first place let's say
the GM doesn't roll this check in secret
and you do it yourself like in most
checks of the game if you roll a four on
that check this tells you that you don't
notice anything but it also tells you
that you failed to check which could
make you even more suspicious of your
environment it doesn't mean there's
nothing hiding it only means that you
failed at spotting something and that is
more information than what you would
have in a real-world situation likewise
if you roll a 19 you can feel confident
that you succeeded on the check and not
only did you not notice anything but
your positive there is nothing hiding
there at all which can lead you to
behaving in a much more confident
approach than what you would probably
have in a real-world situation but when
the GM
makes the role for you in secret they
don't tell you what number was rolled or
if you succeeded or if you failed
they simply tell you if you notice
something or not in a player without
knowledge of if they succeeded or failed
is going to proceed in a more realistic
fashion then a player who knows for
certain if their perception check was a
massive success or a critical failure
regardless when you take the seek action
your perception check is rolled in
secret and compared against the stealthy
C's of all targets in the area that are
not already observed by you any creature
that has the undetected state of
awareness that you succeed against
becomes hidden from you and any hidden
creature that you succeed against
becomes observed by you essentially
success on a seek action moves the
target one step closer in awareness to
being observed and on a critical success
the target moves two steps and becomes
observed this however is limited
according to which since the character
is using to seek and also by the
lighting conditions of the area if
they're using vision
senses are defined as either being
precise imprecise or vague precise
senses allow you to perceive your
surroundings in detail and only a
precise sense can be used to observe a
target and the only precise is that
humans have is vision in priests
licenses allow you to perceive the
presence of something but not with the
accuracy in detail of a precise sense
for example humans have hearing which is
an imprecise sense we can use hearing to
know that someone is present and may be
able to even know where they're standing
but aiming an attack based on hearing
alone is going to be difficult you
cannot observe a target with an
imprecise sense so if you detect an
enemy on hearing alone they would have
the undetected or hidden conditions
instead of observed the third category
of senses is vague senses and best vague
senses can be used to make an unnoticed
creature become undetected but you can't
use a vague sense to make a target
hidden or observed smelling is a vague
sense for humans if you can't see or
hear a target there is a chance that you
might be able to smell them but this
wouldn't allow you to accurately place
their location or any great details
about them therefore that target would
be considered as undetected instead of
hidden or observed and is worth noting
that using smelling or any other vague
sense is largely up to the
interpretation of the GM to allow or
interpret how it will function in any
given situation
the last major element that a fixed
perception is lighting there are three
broad categories for lighting and
Pathfinder bright light is the default
norm and is created by sunlight and
other fix like spells and lanterns
simply put in bright light conditions
aime creature are odd
that's not trying to avoid attention
should be able to be clearly seen by
anyone with average vision or better
although most creatures function
normally in bright light some monsters
may have difficulty for example drow
elves suffer from light blindness that
inflicts them with the dazzled condition
while within areas of bright light dim
light is an area that has illumination
provided by a light source that is
weaker than bright light candle lit
rooms a clear night sky lay with a full
moon and stars out and standing 30 feet
away from a lit torch are all examples
of dim light conditions creatures and
objects in dim light can be observed but
have the concealed condition unless the
creature observing them has a way to
overcome poor lighting for example
creatures with low light or dark vision
can see in dim light as if it was bright
light therefore targets in dim light are
not concealed to creatures who are using
low light or dark vision also note that
when an item or spell lists the amount
of distance that it produces bright
light it also produces dim light for an
equal number of feet beyond the range of
bright light so for example a torch is
listed as producing bright light for 20
feet therefore it also produces dim
light from 21 to 40 feet away in the
third category of lighting is darkness
any creatures are objects within an area
of darkness gain the hidden or
undetected conditions unless the seeker
has dark vision or a precise sense other
than vision creatures without dark
vision gain the Bullington condition
when perceiving areas of darkness
okay perception census in states of
awareness can be confusing to a lot of
players especially since terms like
unnoticed undetected and hidden can mean
the exact same thing to most people but
I'm going to try my best to pull it all
together so that it makes a little bit
of sense here say there is a sneaky
Goblin in the same room as you but you
have no idea they're there that goblin
has the unnoticed condition being
unnoticed has no real mechanical effect
on you or any of your actions
but being unnoticed allows the Goblin to
use certain abilities that it has
against you that require the user of
those abilities to be unnoticed by their
victim since you have no idea the Goblin
is there then that goblin is also
undetected the Goblin in this case has
both the unnoticed and undetected
conditions at the same time in fact any
time a creature is unnoticed it will by
definition also be undetected however
the opposite is not always true anytime
a creature is undetected it will not
necessarily also be unnoticed undetected
means you don't know where a creature is
this could either be because you have no
idea that there's a goblin in the room
with you and therefore it is both
unnoticed and undetected or you might
suspect a goblin is in the room with you
but not nowhere in the room is hiding
maybe you are chasing it and it ran into
this room you followed it in so you know
is hiding somewhere in this room but you
don't know exactly where in this case
the goblin would be undetected but it
would not be unnoticed because unnoticed
applies only when you have no clue that
that creature is anywhere nearby moving
forward with this example let's say you
follow the Goblin into the room the
rooms cluttered with supply crates and
bear
and is lit by torches the torches make
this a brightly lit room so you face no
penalties due to poor lighting you
perform a seek action to try and find
that goblin you tell your GM what your
perception bonus is and they roll the
check in secret the GM does not tell you
if you succeed or feel the check they
only tell you that you do not see a
goblin anywhere in the room now you saw
the Goblin run in here and there's no
other doors so you know it's here
somewhere a barrel in the corner strikes
you as suspicious so you walk up and
stab your longsword straight through
that barrel this creates a moment that I
like to call Schrodinger's Goblin there
are only two possible realities here
either the Goblin is hiding in the
barrel or the Goblin is not hiding in
the barrel and you don't know which of
those possibilities is correct because
you can't see what's inside the barrel
by running your sword through the barrel
you're not attacking a goblin instead
you are attacking the space that you
believe the Goblin is in since the
Goblin is undetected being that you
don't know its location the GM makes
your attack ro and secret as well as
also making a flat check vs. DC 11 the
GM does not tell you if your attack was
successful or not only that your sword
pierced through the barrel without
striking flesh that was the outcome but
let's go back to our two possible
realities in reality one the Goblin is
hiding in the barrel which means you
missed it either the attack roll was
lower than the goblins armor class or
the attack roll was a success but the
flat check that the GM rolled was lower
than 11
either way you did not hit the Goblin
which means that the Goblin got lucky in
the blade pierced through the barrel
without cutting it impossible reality
number two the Goblin isn't even in the
barrel so it doesn't matter what the GM
rolls in secret for your attack or for
that flat check the key here is that all
you as a player knows is that you did
not stab a goblin when you pushed your
sword through the barrel you don't know
if that's because the Goblin is inside
the barrel and you missed it or if the
Goblin was never inside the barrel in
the first place you won't know which of
the two possible realities is correct
until you actually open up the barrel
and look inside of it on the gun was
turn you hear frantic footsteps scurry
behind a row of crates you're not sure
exactly which of the crates the Goblin
is behind but take another seek action
using your hearing to track it the GM
rolls this in secret and tells you you
can hear fate whimpering behind the
leftmost crate you succeeded on the
perception check for seeking which moved
the goblins state of awareness one step
from undetected to hidden and again
hidden means you know the exact location
of a target but you cannot see them and
since you are seeking with hearing which
is an imprecise sense that's the most
beneficial state of awareness you can
have you cannot observe a target with
hearing alone
so you know for certain the Goblin is
behind the left crate so you walk around
that crate and you look down you're now
perceiving a poor frightened Goblin with
vision which is a precise sense
therefore the goblins awareness
condition increases to observed and you
can now interact with that goblin freely
without any penalties or flat checks in
this video we discussed the basics of
perception as a reminder this video has
served to lay a foundation for future
videos that will dive deeper into
concepts like invisibility initiative
and stealth perception is a measure of
how aware a character is and is role to
determine if they notice something the
base perception bonus is the character's
wisdom modifier plus their perception
proficiency bonus a creatures perception
DC is 10 plus their perception bonus
this score is used to contested temps by
others to avoid that creatures attention
creatures perceive each other
according to four states of awareness
the first state is called unnoticed and
it applies to any creature you have
absolutely no idea is present you cannot
interact directly with an unnoticed
creature but having the unnoticed
condition may allow that creature to use
certain abilities that function only
when the user is unnoticed by their
target the next stage of awareness is
undetected undetected means you do not
know a creatures location if you do not
know a creatures location cause you're
not even aware of that it's present then
that creature is both unnoticed and
undetected if you know a creature is
present but not its exact location maybe
because you hear a suspicious sound in a
dark room then the creature is only
undetected when a creature is undetected
you are flat-footed against its attacks
and since you do not know where the
creature is you cannot attack
get directly but may choose to attack
the space where you think it is when
doing so the GM Rose your tech for you
in secret along with a DC 11 flat check
the results of the check being if it is
a success or a failure is not revealed
to the player the player is only told if
they hit something or did not and note
that flat checks are not required for
area effects like for example a fireball
spell the next state of awareness is
called hidden when a target is hidden
from you you know exactly what space
they are in but you cannot see them the
hidden condition works exactly like
undetected except the player rolls their
own attacks and the DC 11 flat check
instead of the GM rolling those in
secret and the final state of awareness
is observed when you can see your target
it is observed there are no special
penalties applied when you are observing
your target but it is worth noting that
if you can see them but not see them
perfectly clear
then the GM may grant that target the
concealed condition when you attack a
concealed target you must pass a DC 5
flat check or your attack automatically
misses no matter what was rolled on that
attack even if it's a natural 20 the
seek action is used when a character
wishes to improve their awareness of a
target this is done with a perception
check contested by the stealth DC of
anything hidden in that field of view
unlike with moose checks in the game
rolls for seeking are made secretly by
the GM who then tells the player what
they see or what they don't see the
result of the roll and if it was a
success or failure are not revealed to
the player with a successful seek action
the awareness state of the target
increases by one step from undetected to
hidden to observed critically succeeding
seek action increases the awareness by
two stages however the highest level of
awareness you can have with a creature
is limited by what since you are using
to detect them and if you are using
vision then you are further elimi 'td by
the area's lighting since has come in
three varieties precise imprecise and
vague precise in psa's like vision are
the only sense is able to observe a
target when using an imprecise sense
like hearing you are limited to the
hidden state of awareness at best you
can know where a target is by hearing
alone but you cannot see them and
therefore cannot gain the observed
awareness state vague senses like smell
might be able to remove the unnoticed
condition from a target and make them
only undetected but likely would not be
able to improve your awareness of the
target to hidden and this is all largely
up to the GM to determine exactly what
is possible with a vague sense there are
also three levels of light conditions
areas of bright light are bright enough
that details can be clearly seen in most
creatures suffer no penalties seeking a
target in bright light areas with poor
illumination are dimly lit candlelight
or outdoors under a full moon for
example would be dim light conditions
you can still see and observe targets in
dim light but unless you have low light
or dark vision all targets in dim light
are going to gain the concealed
condition when a target has the
concealed condition you must pass a DC v
flat check for any direct attack against
them just like with attacking an
undetected or hidden target if you fail
that flat check then it doesn't matter
what you roll on your attack roll it
automatically misses that target and
lasts in areas of darkness you can't see
at all unless you have dark vision
and this means that without dark vision
the best state of awareness you can have
with a target in darkness is hidden and
not observed
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature in
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games