hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of stealth in
Pathfinder second edition
before we get started with stealth it
might be a good idea to do a quick
review of the different states of
detection there are four states of
detection
the first is unnoticed and it applies to
any creature you have absolutely no idea
is nearby
the second is undetected a creature is
undetected when you do not know where it
is by definition all unnoticed creatures
will also be undetected but if you know
a creature is in the area but you just
don't know its exact location then it is
undetected but is not unnoticed the
third state of detection is called
hidden and it applies when you know a
creatures exact location but you can't
see it in the last state of detection is
called observed and it applies to any
creature that you can see but note that
if you can see a target but not clearly
maybe because you're in dim lighting or
the target is standing in fog then that
target is observed but also has the
concealed condition this is material
that we discussed in great length in our
video about perceptions so it is highly
recommended that you go watch that video
before continuing here as we will be
relying on information from that video
as we proceed a link to the video on
perception is included in this video's
description
when a character wishes to avoid being
noticed they use the stealth skill the
key ability score for stealth is
dexterity and all applications of
stealth can be used on trained when your
attempt to hide is contested the
searching characters perception check is
challenged by your stealth DC and
stealth DC is calculated as 10 plus your
stealth skill bonus this works pretty
much the same as perception DC the key
to remember when deciding if he should
make a stealth role or use your stealth
DC is you only roll on your turn when
you use an action and when it's not your
turn and you're defending against
someone else's action then they compare
their role to your stealth DC in normal
circumstances there would not be a
challenge of roles where one person
rolls their stealth skill and another
person rolls their perception
there are three stealth actions included
in the core rules the first of which is
called conceal an object this can either
be something that you are carrying with
you like a dagger up your sleeve or it
could be something you hide in the
environment like a secret note planted
underneath the roots of a stump if you
are hiding a small item that you are
carrying the GM rolls your stealth skill
and secret and compares that total to
the perception dc's of everyone you are
hiding the item from if your check total
is higher than their perception disease
then they do not notice that you're
hiding anything and no you only roll
this check one time not once for each
creature you are hiding the object from
if a creature is actively searching you
for example there an alert garden
they're keeping a watchful eye out then
they roll a perception check against
your stealth DC instead of relying on
their perception DC for example you walk
up to the door of a ballroom with two
guards standing outside they're checking
guests before they enter for weapons and
you have a dagger hidden on you on your
turn when you approach the guards your
stealth check would be a road which
would then be contested by their
perception DC's then on the guards turns
one of them takes the seek action to
actively look you over before letting
you pass this guard would then roll
their perception and that total would be
challenged by your stealth DC note that
whatever you rode on your turn when you
took conceal an object is now irrelevant
when it's the guards turn and they are
using seek to search you then it is
their perception challenged by your
static stealth DC this works much the
same way when hiding an object in the
environment instead of carrying it with
you except in this case you would not
roll any stealth check instead he's been
one action to hide the object and if
anyone performs a seek action in that
area then their perception check will be
challenged by your stealth
and note that conceal an object is for
hiding something that you already
possess if you want to pick something up
without anyone noticing that you're
picking it up you would use the palm and
object application of thievery instead
of using the stealth skill
the second stealth action is called hide
hide is used when you wish to lower your
state of detection from observed to
hidden when you take the hide action you
roll a stealth check and compare the
total to the perception disease of
anyone who is observing you as long as
you are either concealed from them or
have a source of cover between you and
them if you are not concealed or do not
have a source of cover then you have
nowhere to hide and the attempt
automatically fails if you do have cover
then you add the covers bonus to your
stealth check but only for those
creatures who are observing you from the
other side of that cover this is
basically common sense if the cover is
not between you and them then it doesn't
give you any benefit and likewise if you
lose your cover or concealment you
instantly become observed again you also
immediately become observed if you use
any actions other than sneak step or
hide now there are two exceptions to
this and the first is the strike action
if you strike a target while hidden you
resolve the attack first and don't
become observed until after the attack
this means the target is flat-footed for
the attack and therefore the attacker
can use abilities like sneak attack with
their strike but once the attack is
resolved the hiding character instantly
becomes observed
and the second of the two exceptions to
the rule that states any action other
than hide sneaker step instantly makes
you observed is the provision in the
rules that states unless the GM
determines otherwise the GM might allow
you to perform an unobtrusive action
without being noticed possibly requiring
another stealth check the key word here
is unobtrusive for example the seek
action if the hidden character wishes to
perform the seek action I think in
virtually all cases the GM would agree
that seeking meets the definition of
unobtrusive and not make you instantly
become detected when you performed
action but it is up to every GM to
decide on if an action is considered
unobtrusive or not also note that you
may not move out of your current space
as part of a hide action hide is just
for staying in place and changing your
state of detection from observed to
hidden
disappearing behind cover or any blanket
of darkness is one way to lower your
state of detection from observe to
hidden but another option is to trick
those people observing you into looking
the other way you can accomplish this
with the create under version use of the
deception skill when using create a
diversion
you do something to trick any onlookers
into momentarily turning their backs on
you and hope by the time they turn back
around you'll have disappeared this
requires a deception check contested by
the perception disease of everyone
observing you your detection state
lowers from observed to hidden for
anyone whose perception DC is equal to
or lower than the total of your
deception check this hidden condition
lasts until the end of your current turn
or if you perform an action which would
reveal you same as we discussed with the
hide action any creature observing you
whose perception DC is higher than the
total of your deception check not only
continues to observe you but is also
fully aware that you tried to trick them
regardless of success or failure once
you use create a diversion on a creature
they receive a +4 circumstance bonus to
their perception disease against any
future attempts by you to create another
diversion for one minute
but once your detection state is hidden
either by causing a destruction
performing the hide action or by other
means you can then you sneak to lower
your detection state to undetected and
move away from your location in order to
take the sneak action you must first be
hidden or undetected in other words if
any of the people you are trying to
sneak past can see you then you can't
use the sneak action you would need to
spin an action first to hide thus
lowering your detection state from
observed to hidden and then another
action to sneak away want you to clear
that you are sneaking you may move up to
half your speed at the end of your
movement the GM rolls your stealth check
for you in secret and compares the
result to the perception dc's of
everyone who you are undetected or
hidden from at the start of the sneak
action if you have cover or greater
cover throughout the entire movement the
GM adds your cover bonus to the stealth
check that they roll in secret at the
end of your movement you instantly
become observed by any creature who you
do not have cover from or the concealed
condition against everyone else has
their perception dc's compared to your
stealth check total and you gain the
undetected state with anyone you wrote a
success against or you keep the
undetected state if you are already
undetected before taking the sneak
action in just a point here as a
technicality when you take the sneak
action if you are hidden you instantly
become undetected at the start of the
sneak action and you maintain the
undetected state throughout your
movement to the ending square where you
stop your sneak if your check fails
against a creature that you do have
cover or concealment against in that
last Square then you become hidden to
them they can't see you but you must
have made a sound they gave away your
location if you critically fail then the
creature is able to observe you as long
as they have a line of sight to that
space and just like with the actions
we've already discussed once you are
undetected following a sneak action you
become observed as soon as you take any
action other than hide step or another
sneak unless the GM rules that the
action is unobtrusive and if you strike
then your target is flat-footed for that
attack and you become observed as soon
as that attack is resolved with any
other actions you become observed before
the action is resolved
let's look at a few examples will be
using Mauricio for these she's a fifth
level rogue she has a speed score of 35
feet a plus 11 bonus to perception and
plus 13 to stealth this also makes her
perception DC 21 and her stealth DC is
23 in this scenario
Mauricio is sneaking through a wizards
Academy to steal a rare tome she
believes it to be in the collection of
one of the teachers and has arrived at
the corridor outside a dormitory with
cloth partitions separating the students
beds and the teacher's office to the
west she sneaks to the window and stops
she spots a student sitting on his bed
reading since he is not making any
attempt to be undetected she instantly
observes him since she ended her sneak
in this space the GM rolls her stealth
check in secret and contests the total
with the perception DC's of anyone with
line-of-sight to her the GM also as a
bonus to her check for the cover that
she's behind her total is well over
there reading students perception DC so
the GM tells her that she doesn't
believe that she's been spotted her
detection state is unnoticed and
undetected with her first action on the
next round
she takes another sneak action and moves
to the door as with before she would
need the GM to roll a stealth check in
secret but it's fairly trivial here
given that no one is able to observe her
from the other side of the doors being
extra cautious she presses her ear to
the door and listens this is a seek
action if there are creatures on the
other side of this door who are trying
to avoid attention her perception check
would be contested by their stealth and
DC's if there are creatures on the other
side of the door who are not trying to
avoid attention then her perception
check is contested by a lure DC as
deemed appropriate by the GM Mauricio
tells the GM that her perception bonuses
plus 11 and the GM rolls this check in
secret they then tell Marissa's player
that she can hear voices on the other
side
the door but can't quite make out what
they're saying or their exact location
in the room with her third action she
declares that she wants to open the door
quietly in peer in this is an interact
action and would be up to the GM to
determine if it is considered to be
unobtrusive or if it would instantly
reveal her presence to the room where I
the GM here I would ask mariscos player
to role a stealth check as part of the
interact action that I would then
compare to the perception disease of
creatures in the room I would also grant
her a small bonus to that check if she
took additional measures to be quiet
like applying oil to the doors handle
and hinges she rose one day 20 + 13 and
the GM tells her two things first once
the door opens she can hear two voices
talking on the other side of a cloth
partition says the two students were not
trying to stay hidden she automatically
detects them since she is perceiving the
to chatting students with hearing which
is an imprecise since they have the
hidden detection state but the GM
determines there is narrow line-of-sight
to their reading student so she is
observing him she however is both
unnoticed and undetected - all three of
them had she failed her stealth check
opening the door she would likely rule
that she becomes hidden to the chatting
students but might be observed by the
reading student with the first action of
the next round
Mauricio takes the sneak action the
first requirement for sneaking is you
must be either hidden or undetected
before you can attempt it she is both
unnoticed and undetected so she meets
that requirement the second requirement
is she must have cover or concealment
against all targets he's sneaking past
at the start of her sneak if we draw
target lines from the center of her
square to the center of each student
square we see each of them passed
through a solid object which means she
has cover with the sneak action she can
move up to half her speed in Russo's
case a speed of 35 feet me
she can move three squares while
sneaking she quietly steps into the room
and ends her movement here the last
requirement for sneak is that you must
end your movement in a space that has
cover or concealment you only need to
have cover or concealment in the space
where you start the sneak and the space
where you end it by raw you do not need
to maintain cover or concealment
throughout the entire movement however
if you do have cover for the entire
movement you get to add is cover bonus
to your stealth check for example when
Marissa enters this square the GM could
rule that she no longer has cover or
concealment
from the student who is reading however
the rule is you only need cover or
concealment when you start and when you
end your movement so she can pass
through this square without issue in the
narrative she waits until the student
reaches for a new book or erupts his
eyes or yawns or does something else
that would distract him for just an
instant and allow her to pass through
that Square at the end of her movement
the GM rose her stealth check in secret
and reports that no one seems to be
aware of her presence she is still
unnoticed and undetected by all three
students the reading student is observed
by her and the chatting students are
hidden to her since she knows their
locations but can't see them a creature
that is undetected instantly becomes
observed if they take any action other
than hide sneak or step unless the GM
rules the action is unobtrusive if
Marissa will wish to attack either of
the students adjacent to her she could
spin an action to do so the student she
attacks would be flat-footed since she
is undetected by them and she would have
to pass a DC 11 flat check since the
target is hidden to her at the end of
the attack she then becomes observed she
decides instead to take a step action
and move closer to the door
with her third action Mauricio attempts
to quietly open the door just wide
enough for her to peer in this is an
interact action and the GM determines it
is unobtrusive especially since none of
the three students have line of sight to
the door her stealth check is compared
to the perception dc's of everyone in
the area and the GM tells her that no
one seems to have noticed she's now able
to look into the next room she doesn't
need to take a siik action to notice the
teacher standing over a table brewing a
potion her stealth check when opening
the door was higher than his perception
DC so he is unaware that she's there he
is observed by her and she is unnoticed
and unaware to him that's the end of her
turn but while she's waiting for her
Knicks turn to come around a guard walks
the length of the hall he's patrolling
and using the seek action as he walks so
when he passes this window the GM would
roll his perception check this total is
contested by marechals stealth DC of
23+2 for the cover that she receives
from the crate that is between them if
the total of the guards perception check
is 25 or higher he notices her for the
sake of brevity we'll say that his check
failed and he walks away now for
discussion let's say instead of a guard
walking past who's actively using the
seek action instead a couple of students
pass in the hallway as long as they are
not actually using the seek action they
have no chance of detecting mauricio at
all you would not roll their perception
checks if they are not using the seek
action nor would you compare their
perception disease to any of these
stealth rolls that Mauricio has already
made but it's also worth mentioning that
Mauricio would be instantly spotted by
the students if she ever lost the cover
between her and them if a student ever
walked into the dorm with her in Clear
View she would instantly become observed
things have been going pretty smooth
former CEO so far but for the sake of
discussion lists say she was spotted on
her way out of the Academy she's being
chased by a guard in hopes to lose him
in the stacks of the Academy library at
the start they are both being observed
by each other
Marissa does have cover here so her
player may be tempted to say that
they're just going to take the sneak
action and move away but unfortunately
one of the requirements to sneak is you
must be hidden or undetected at the
start of that action and she is observed
so in this case Marissa would need to
spend her first action to hide she would
rule her stealth skill plus cover bonus
and the GM would compare that total
against the guards perception DC will
say he has a perception bonus of +6 so
her total needs to be a 16 or higher for
her to hide that's a pretty easy check
with a plus 13 bonus and cover will say
she's exceeded which then lowers her
state of detection from observed to
hidden the guard can no longer sear but
no she's in that square hiding behind
the shelf of books now with her second
action she can sneak and move away at
the end of her move she still has cover
so the GM Rosie stealth check once more
against the guards perception DC will
say she's succeeded again and with her
third action takes another sneak action
to move here
she still has cover and another stealth
check is rolled as before the guard has
a speed score of 20 feet in his armor so
with his first action he strikes two
here he has no line of sight to mauricio
so she is still undetected to him he
takes another stride action and moves
here determined to find the thief he
spins his third action to seek and rolls
a perception check against Marissa's
stealth DC of 23 Plus cover bonus note
again that this role is against her
static stealth DC and not the total of
her last stealth check if he succeeds on
this chick mariscos detection state
moves one step and she becomes hidden ho
be able to know her location by hearing
her but cannot see her if he critically
succeeds then the Geum could rule that
there is narrow line of sight from his
space to hers and in that case she would
become observed if that happens Marissa
would need to spend her first action
hiding again and then her second action
to sneak away once more and if on his
third action had the guard decided not
to seek but instead took another stride
action and moved here he would have
instantly observed mauricio as she no
longer has cover or concealment against
the guard
in this video we discussed the stealth
skill the key ability for stealth is
dexterity and all stealth actions can be
used untrained when a character's
attempt to hide is challenged during
another characters turn the seeking
character rolls their perception which
is challenged by the hiding characters
stealth DC stealth DC is calculated as
10 + stealth bonus when it comes to
stealth skill in stealth DC the rule of
thumb is if it is your turn
you roll stealth contested to buy other
people's perception DC but if it is not
your turn then they roll their
perception and that is contested by your
stealth DC there are three stealth
actions
the first is conceal an object if you
hide the object on yourself you're still
throw is contested by the perception
DC's of anyone who you do not want to
notice it if another character uses the
seek action on their turn they roll
their perception versus your stealth DC
to notice the hidden object if you hide
the object in the environment you do not
roll anything but if someone uses the
seek action in that area their
perception roll is contested - by your
stealth DC
the second stealth action is hide and
this is for when you want to lower your
detection state from observed to hidden
you must have cover or concealment to
hide and your stealth check is
challenged by the perception disease of
anyone observing you if successful you
become hidden but do not move from your
space as part of the action another way
to lower your detection from observed to
hidden is my creating a diversion with
the deception skill in this case you
roll a deception contested by the
perception disease of others and if
successful you become hidden until the
end of your current turn if you fail the
check not only are you still observed
but they also know you are trying to
trick them and regardless of success or
failure once you attempt to create a
diversion those targets gain a +4 bonus
to any other attempts to by you to
create a diversion for the next minute
the third stealth skill is sneak if you
are hidden or undetected and you have
cover or concealment against your
enemies you can move up to half your
speed after which your stealth skill is
compared to the perception disease of
enemies in the area if you have cover
throughout the entire movement you add
the covers bonus to your stealth check
if you do not have cover or concealment
in the square that you ended your
movement you instantly fail against
those enemies with unobstructed lines of
sight to you and become observed if you
succeed the check
you are undetected if you fail the check
you become hidden if you critically fail
you become observed
while hidden or undetected you instantly
become observed if you attempt any
action other than hide step or sneak two
exceptions to this are any actions that
the GM rules are unobtrusive or when you
take the strike action in which case the
target is flat-footed for the attack and
you become observed after the attack is
resolved
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature in
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games