hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of initiative and
surprise in Pathfinder 2nd edition
before we begin I want to give a quick
shout out to everyone on the
piezoelectric or for helping me get my
head around some of these rules if
you're not participating in the official
forums then you're really missing out
it's a very welcoming in supporting
community and without them I would
probably still be trying to figure out
how surprise works so thanks again to
everyone who helped out also I want to
mention that since we will be discussing
what happens when players are taken by
surprise I highly recommend that you go
watch our videos on stealth in
perception before watching this one
links to those videos may be found in
the description and with all of that
taken care of let's go ahead and talk a
little bit about initiative
initiative dictates the order in which
characters and other creatures act
within a round determining this order is
often what triggers that transition from
exploration mode to encounter mode and
it should be the first step of any
individual encounter creating the
initiative order is main ease by having
everyone roll an initiative check this
is done the same as most any other check
in the game but there are a few
exceptions first there is no DC for an
initiative check and like most other
checks in the game the total of your
initiative check is not challenged by a
DC or target number but instead all of
the initiative totals are ranked highest
to lowest the character who rolled the
highest gets to act first in each round
and the person who rolled lowest acts
last geum's may choose to roll
initiative individually for each
creature they control or they might
choose to group certain creatures
together for example if the players are
fighting a bugbear in three goblins it
might be easiest for the GM to have the
bugbear act on its initiative and then
roll initiative once for all of the
other goblins acting together on their
singular initiative total there is no
right or wrong approach but I would
caution GM's to not have too many
enemies act on the same initiative
number say for example the players are
fighting 10 goblins rolling initiative
once in having all 10 goblins act at the
same time can be pretty brutal as the
players will have to weather 30 actions
before they have a chance to heal or
take some other defense with a group
that large you might want to break it up
into say 2 groups of 5 or maybe break it
up as 2 groups of 3 and one group of 4
as opposed to having all 10 act at the
same time
in case of a tie between a player and a
creature that's controlled by the GM the
GM wins that tie and the creature is
slotted in to initiative ahead of that
player in case of a tie between two
players then those players get to decide
between them which of them will act
first in the initiative order
the second major difference between
initiative checks and other chicks in
the game is there is no definitive
initiative bonus and this can really
throw off some experienced players
especially if they played first edition
in Pathfinder second edition what bonus
you roll for your initiative is based on
what you were doing at the time that the
GM calls for the initiative check by
default initiative is based on how soon
you recognize danger not on how fast you
can draw a sword and therefore
perception checks are usually rolled for
initiative but there will be times from
the GM might call for a different check
to be made so here are a few examples
from the court rulebook when sneaking or
using the avoid notice exploration
activity you would likely use your
stealth skill for your initiative
another example might be a character is
negotiating with a cobalt King and then
decides to suddenly attack them that
character might role deception as their
initiative while the rest of the party
who might also be caught off-guard by
this sudden attack they would each role
perception
if combat begins with a character
surprising her foes by dropping down
from a chandelier on top of them then
she might roll acrobatics as her
initiative and if a player agrees to
have a friendly wrestling match with an
NPC they might roll their athletic skill
as their initiative check the rule of
thumb is to roll whatever is the most
obvious choice if the character sneaking
they use their stealth total for
initiative if the character starts a
fight by sucker punching someone then
they would roll deception but in most
cases a perception check is what you
will roll for initiative
let's look at an example of how this
might work and I should mention up front
that I'm going to be speaking in
generalities and not going into some
details of exploration mode and
exploration activities as those topics
will be covered in a future course in
this example we have a Zirin lynnie and
Mauricio they are brand new first level
adventurers and they're traveling down
the road their GM asks each player to
describe what they are doing as they
travel
Ezrin reminds the other players that
town folk warned them that this stretch
of road is popular with bandits so they
should be alert as they travel Mauricio
agrees and says she'll be keeping a
watchful eye out for danger and liddy
says that she's examining the forest
around them as they walk to see if she
spots anything unusual in the woods they
come upon four goblins blocking the road
demanding that the players pay at all
before they can pass instead the players
decide to draw their weapons and the GM
calls for initiative to be rolled since
everyone is out in the open this is
going to be a fairly standard encounter
all participants are all perception as
their initiative bonus the goblins have
perception bonuses of +2 and their
totals are 21 for the first Goblin 12
for the second goblin five for the third
goblin and 9 for the fourth goblin and
for the players
lynnie gets a 24 Maurice your roles a 9
and Ezrin also roles a 9 everyone is
then sorted from highest to lowest but
we see here that there is a three-way
tie between goblin number 4 Mauricio and
ezrin since they all scored a total of 9
with her chicks in case of a tie
creatures controlled by the GM win so
the GM effectively changes goblin 4
score to 11 and then Mauricio and
ezrin's players decide amongst
themselves who should go first between
them although there are no official tie
breakers they decide that Mauricio
should go
first since her perception bonus is
higher than ezrin's so the GM changes
her score to ten from here combat begins
with characters acting in this order now
this example was clean and simple and I
really want to stress that in the vast
majority of my experiences initiative
really is this easy to figure out but
things do become far more tricky when
one group doesn't know the other group
is hiding nearby
so let's look at this example again but
this time the goblins aren't standing in
the open and having a dialogue with the
players instead they're hiding in some
brush we're going to look at a few
different examples all using this same
basic scenario and I should mention that
I will be using a map and tokens on the
screen representing characters and this
is done strictly for illustrative
purposes and in an actual game as long
as the players are in exploration mode
and initiative hasn't been rode yet then
there probably wouldn't be a need to
actually have a physical map on the
table and likewise the Goblin tokens
wouldn't be on the table until they are
actually being observed by a player in
this example the goblins do not plan to
attack the players and instead they wish
to hide and let the players pass so that
they can then sneak across the road
without being detected when the PCs
entered the general area of the goblins
they are instantly observed by the
goblins and the goblins start as both
unnoticed and undetected by the players
if you're not familiar with these terms
I highly recommend you go watch our
course on perception before you continue
here the GM then role is a stealth skill
check in secret for each goblin with a
+2 bonus for being in cover and then
compares those totals to the perception
DC of each player in fact the gia might
want to go ahead and pre-roll those as
part of their game preparation for that
session and the fewer actual dice you
need to roll in front of the players
behind your screen is probably for the
better the goblins role stealth checks
plus two more because they have cover
and they receive totals of 25 20 19 and
17 these totals are then compared to the
players perception DC's ezrin has a
perception DC of 14 Linney's perception
DC is 17 and Mauricio has a perception
DC of 16
because the goblins are the ones rolling
here the only need to meet or beat
Linney's perception DC of 17 in order to
succeed so goblin number 4 does win the
tie with a stealth check of 17 and all
four goblins succeed on their stealth
checks so in this scenario all heroes
walk right past the goblins without ever
noticing them because the goblins do not
plan to confront the characters there is
no need to call for initiative or even
put a map on the table this is no
different than when players try to sneak
past opponents there is no conflict here
and that means there's no need to call
for initiative to be enrolled now let's
see how this might be different if the
goblins didn't want to sneak across the
road and instead wish to ambush the
players in attack this is the exact same
scenario as before when the players
enter the general area of the hiding
goblins they are instantly observed by
the goblins and the goblins are both
unnoticed and undetected by them the GM
rolls a stealth check and secret for
each of the goblins and compares the
totals to the perception DC of each
player will keep the same roles that we
had in the previous example so the
goblins succeed their checks and the
players are blissfully unaware that
there are any goblins nearby in the
woods the key difference this time
however is the goblins wish to ambush
them
so as the players move up and closer to
them it becomes time to roll Rick a roll
for initiative
Ezrin and marissa overall perception
checks while the GM gives Linney the
choice of either rolling her perception
or her nature skill since she
specifically says she was watching the
forest for any unusual signs maybe she
notices birds fly away from the bushes
where the goblins are hiding just a
moment before they attack
thus alerting her of danger before she
actually sees them
this is just one possible narrative
example of how the nature skill might be
used for an initiative check but the key
here is that this player lynnie
declared that she was watching the
forest for any unusual signs before
initiative was called so the GM allowed
her the choice of either perception or
nature if the player had not specified
that she was doing that then when it
came time to roll initiative she likely
would have been forced to use just
perception and the geums should not give
that player the opportunity to choose
another skill what's initiative his code
for you are either doing perception or
you are using a skill that you already
declared so in this scenario
Ezrin rolls in 11 Linney gets a 25 with
her nature check and Maurice your roles
and 18 for perception the goblins do not
rear all their initiative here and
instead use their already rode stealth
checks for their initiative score this
is a provision of using avoid notice but
is also a benefit of winning their
stealth checks they get to keep their
higher roles and use them for initiative
to
everyone is then ranked highest to
lowest which is goblin number one then
lynnie then goblin number two then
goblin number three then mauricio goblin
number four and then finally Ezrin
lynnie may have failed to spot the
Goblin while they hid but thanks to her
nature skills she's alert and very quick
to react when they spring their trap it
is very much worth noting here that
although the characters are taken by
surprise there is no such thing as a
quote surprise round such as those are
found in other RPGs in place of that the
goblins get to use their stealth skill
as their initiative which is often even
more beneficial because of cover bonuses
so succeeding on the stealth check
increases the odds
you will act first in combat which in
some ways can be compared to having a
traditional surprise round and that
there is a good chance you will act
before your enemies have a chance to
react also at first level rogues get a
class feature called surprise attack
which lists them treat enemies as being
flat-footed
if those enemies have not acted yet in
the first round but only if the rogue
used stealth or deception as their
initiative check
goblin number one starts the round and
as soon as it attacks or moves towards
the hero out of its cover it instantly
becomes observed by all three players on
Liddy's turn she is only observing
goblin number one and is still not aware
that there are three other goblins
nearby by the time things come around to
Marissa's turn she can attack goblins
one three three assuming each of them
made their presence known on their turns
but cannot directly attack goblin number
four since no one knows that that goblin
is there yet
okay let's reset this encounter again
and make another tweak to it this time
we'll say the goblins all succeeded on
their stealth checks but Marissa Oh
crushed her perception roll for
initiative enrolled a critical success
for a total of 26 using all the other
same roles as before that would make the
initiative order
Marissa Oh first then goblin number one
because it would win the tie at 25 and
then Lenny then goblin number two
goblin number three goblin number four
and finally ezrin so the kink here is
mauricio gets to go first in initiative
but she doesn't know there are any
enemies nearby remember all four goblins
beat her perception DC with their
stealth checks and even though she used
her perception bonus to roll initiative
that was an initiative check which is
not the same thing as taking the seek
action which is what would be needed to
spot hiding enemies so strictly by the
rules as written mauricio gets to take
her actions first but what is she
supposed to do with those actions take a
moment and put yourself in that player's
shoes you're sitting at the table your
GM calls for initiative roles and you
get your first natural 20 of the night
that probably feels pretty good right
now that GM lays a map in front of you
and put your mini on it but no enemies
what do you do at that moment
if you say you want to take a Sikh
action some GM's I know would tell you
that that's metagaming because your
character doesn't know that she just
wrote initiative as far as she knows
she's just walking down a road and
therefore you should just keep walking
down that road like nothing was out of
the ordinary I don't know about all of
you but that hardly sounds fun to me it
might be the most correct inaccurate
application of the rules as they are
written but if I was that player who was
on a high from rolling a crit and then
the gym told me I couldn't really do
anything with it I'd likely be a little
annoyed so let's talk about some other
options here the first option would be
the GM tells Marissa's player that she
gets to go first in initiative but since
her character doesn't know that she
destroyed initiative and probably
therefore doesn't know that she's in
some form of danger her options are
going to be limited but the GM could
also remind her that she can use the
delay action until something develops
and then decide to take her actions that
might be a better option within the
rules as written then just telling
Marissa's player that she can't really
do anything after she one initiative and
if you're not familiar with the delay
action that will be explained in our
next Pathfinder course
another option although not entirely
within the rules as written would be to
tell Marissa's player that she hears
something from somewhere in the woods
but she can't quite place it
or she just has a feeling that something
is off let the goblins all still be
undetected but reward Marissa for having
that high initiative role and give her a
reason to take the seek action again
that is bending the rules as written but
I think a lot of people find that to be
a more fair and fun option than just
telling the player that they can't do
anything in this course we discussed
initiative and surprise initiative
dictates the order in which creatures
act during an encounter this is
accomplished by rolling initiative
checks which are then ranked from
highest to lowest the creature with the
highest total acts first and the
creature with the lowest acts last in
case of a tie between the GM and a
player the GM's creature wins and when
players tie they get to choose which of
their characters act first perception is
typically used for initiative checks but
some skills may be used instead
depending on what the character is doing
when the GM calls for initiative if the
character is sneaking they would use
their stealth skill if the character
starts a fight by sucker-punching an
enemy they would roll a deception and
other skills may be used as allowed by
the GM but generally speaking perception
will be used for initiative
when players are surprised by hidden
enemies the total of those enemies
stealth checks are also used for their
initiatives they do not roll these again
and there is no such thing as a surprise
around in Pathfinder second edition but
the better a creature is able to hide
themselves the higher they will be in
the initiative order which also
increases the likelihood that they will
be able to attack another creature
before it can take an action to defend
itself when a character's perception DC
is beat by a sneaking enemy but that
same character rolls higher on their
initiative check using perception they
get to act first but they still do not
know that there is any enemy there in
these cases that player might wish to
use the delay action and delay their
turn until the enemy reveals itself or
the GM might wish to bend the rules a
little bit and give that player a reason
to use the seek action
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature on
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games