hello everybody I have something a
little bit different for you all today
this is a portion of the initiative and
surprise video that was previously
published that I had cut out and removed
at the eleventh hour of putting that
video together in that video I provide
four different examples of how the
initiative in surprise might work using
the same scenario for each of the four
different examples and originally it was
five examples and I actually created a
fifth example recorded audio for it put
all the timings into the video and so
forth and then in the 11th hour decided
you know what this example really has
less to do with initiative in surprise
it is really all about perception and
how perception is based on a creature to
creature basis instead of a universal
basis so I removed it from the published
official initiative in surprise video
but I don't know I've been sitting
around thinking I've made it it is
together and who knows maybe somebody
out there would find benefit in seeing
it so I've decided just to kind of
quickly and formally throw it together
and put it up and if people like seeing
a previously cut footage or small
examples um then let me know and this
might be something that becomes a
regular topic or segment for the channel
and as always always appreciate to you
folks so giving me your thoughts and
feedback and suggestions on what you
would like to see in the future as well
so without any further ado here is the
previously unreleased and cut v example
from the initiative and surprise video
let's reset the scenario one more time
the heroes are walking down the road and
a group of goblins are waiting in the
woods to ambush them but this time we're
going to take things from the top and we
are going to re-roll everything just
like before once the players enter the
general vicinity of the hiding goblins
the GM rolls stealth checks for the
goblins and secret
they have stealth skill bonuses of +5
and they receive another +2 because they
are in cover goblin number one gets a 22
goblin number 2 gets a 12 goblin number
3 gets a 16 and goblin number 4 gets a
21 these stealth totals are then
compared to each player's perception DC
ezrin has a perception DC of 14 Lily's
perception DC is 17 and Marissa has a
perception DC of 16 so in this case
goblins 1 and 4 succeed there still
check against all of the players but
goblin 3 failed is stealth check against
Linney and goblin number 2 failed its
tell check against all three players
this reveals the presence of something
to the players and the GM calls for
initiative to be rolled as before the
goblins keep their stealth checks and
use them as their initiative totals
meanwhile is Romero's perception and
gets a 7 Linney has given the choice of
either rolling perception or nature and
chooses to roll nature for a total of 25
and Marissa rolls perception for a total
of 24 all participants in the encounter
are then ranked by their initiative
totals highest to lowest
which means Linney goes first then
mauricio goblin number 1 goblin number 4
goblin number 3
goblin number 2 and finally poor old
Ezrin at the end of initiative yet again
that should all feel familiar but things
get a little bit tricky here
states of awareness are established on a
creature to creature basis so in this
example goblin number one and goblin
number four are undetected by all of the
players in goblin number two is hidden
to all of the players but goblin number
three is undetected to ezrin and Maurice
you'll but it is hidden to Linney
none of the goblins are being observed
yet by the heroes as feeling a stealth
check while undetected only makes you
hidden not observed so instead of
placing goblin tokens on the map the GM
instead places a generic token in one
Square and then tells the players you
see a brief flicker of movement
somewhere around here in the brush and
then places another generic token and
says Linney you also hear the sound of a
twig snapping in this space but only you
Ezrin and merci oh you don't know
anything is here no goblins are placed
on the map since none of the players
know what exactly is lurking in the
woods yet so at the top of the
initiative order Linney goes first which
is fortunate because she's the only one
here who knows something is up with
generic token number three space with
her first action Linney seeks she rolls
a perception check with her bonus of
plus seven and gets a total of 22 this
is then compared to each goblin stealth
DC of 17 as she succeeds as a result the
state of awareness for each of the
goblins moves one step
goblins one and four which were
undetected are now hidden to Lenny
so the GM places generic tokens and
their spaces and again reminds Marissa
and ezrin only Lenny knows that there
are creatures hiding here and goblins
number two and number three are now
being observed by her
the GM then reminds Astrid Mauricio that
they do not know that there is a goblin
in goblin number two space as it is
still hidden to them and they still do
not know anything as present where
Linney is observing goblin number three
with Lenny second action that turn she
uses point out to make goblin number one
hidden to everyone and with her third
action she uses point out again to make
goblin number four hidden to her allies
as well that's the end of her turn and
the encounter proceeds as normal from
there
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature in
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games