hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents delay and ready and Pathfinder
2nd edition in the previous course we
discussed how initiative is used to
determine the order in which characters
act during encounters and this video is
going to follow up on that by discussing
two of the most common ways that
characters can adjust when they act
within that order
the first is by using the delay action
at the start of a player's turn if they
don't know what they want to do or if
they believe it would be better if one
of their allies went before them then
they may choose to delay their action
when a player delays the essentially
step aside as far as initiative is
concerned and allow others to pass them
after each other character finishes
their turn the delaying player may
announce that they are done waiting and
wish to jump back into the initiative
order there at that time they take their
entire turn meaning all three of their
actions and from that point forward for
the rest of the encounter they use this
new placement in the initiative order
essentially what this means is at the
start of every turn a player can
voluntarily lower their initiative score
they can always move backwards and
initiative but have to live with that
new place in initiative for the rest of
the combat unless they choose to delay
yet again and keep moving further
backwards and if they delay all the way
to the end of the round
they may continue to laying into the
start of the next round if they delay
for an entire round meaning that they
are still outside of the initiative
order when their next turn comes around
they immediately stop delaying are
placed back into initiative order at
their usual spot and their next turn
begins when this happens they take their
turn as usual with three actions they do
not get to take six actions as the three
from the previous round have been lost
in their starting a new turn fresh
that's it in a nutshell but there are a
few other specifics that are worth
mentioning first when you declare that
you are delaying you effectively step
out of the initiative order while doing
this you cannot take any reactions so if
an enemy does something that would
normally provoke one of your reactions
while you are delaying then you're out
of look you cannot respond to that
trigger with your reaction
you have to wait until you finish
delaying and move back into the proper
initiative order before you can use your
reaction which would then require that
trigger to happen again also is very
important to know that any damage or
other negative effects that normally
occur at the start or end of your turn
instead happen immediately when you
declare that you are using the delay
action in other words Oh damage from
poison or other persistent effects that
occurs when you step out of initiative
order not when you step back into
initiative order this is to prevent
players from avoiding negative
consequences by delaying in hopes that
one of their allies can aid them during
that period poison isn't that polite is
not going to wait for you now that
covers negative effects that occur at
the start or end of your turn
however if a negative effect is
scheduled to end at the end of your turn
that still doesn't happen until after
you've finished delaying and complete
your turn again you cannot avoid
negative consequences by using the delay
action and likewise you can't make a
beneficial effect less longer than
intended by delaying although negative
effects that are scheduled to cease at
the end of your turn
continue working after you finish the
lane beneficial effects that are
scheduled to end at the start or end of
your turn and when you declare the short
delaying and stepping out of initiative
order just like damage from poison does
again you cannot avoid negative effects
or prolong beneficial effects by
delaying
let's look at an example horse and Sela
encounters some zombies horst's
initiative score 17 the zombies act on
initiative 13 11 and 10 and Cielo is
less in the initiative order with an 8
horse cos hiding and the zombies have
not detected him he's worried that if he
opens fire with his crossbow at the
start of the round who will be overrun
by zombies it would rather have his big
tanky friend Cielo out in the middle of
the fight drawing a ger before he
reveals himself so on the start of his
turn Hirst announces that he is delaying
this is a free action and is available
because it's trigger states the start of
the users turn and if he was suffering
any effects that occur at the start or
end of his turn such as damage from
poison then they would deal their damage
right now
likewise if he was under the effects of
a beneficial spell that's due to end at
the start or end of his turn that spell
was cease functioning right now when he
steps out of initiative order the
zombies then take their turns and they
all attack Cielo because she is the only
target they see after each of their
turns Hirst could announce that he is
done delaying and jumping back into the
initiative order but he decides not to
and instead lists the zombies take all
of their turns
at this point her skin ounces that he is
done delaying and he jumps back into the
initiative order he now gets to take his
full turn he gets to take all three
actions and his new place in initiative
is right ahead of Cielo and he'll stay
at this place an initiative for the
remainder of the encounter unless he
decides to delay again horse was able to
change his place in initiative by
d'Alene but there is another method he
could use to make sure that he doesn't
open fire until after the zombies take
all of their turns and that would be by
using the ready action
when you use the ready action you are
essentially saying that you want to take
a single action leader during another
character's turn during your turn you
announce a single action or free action
that you wish to take and also state a
conditional trigger for that action
essentially you're saying if X happens
then I will do Y this costs two of your
actions and allows you to later use your
reaction to perform the specific
activity that you named with the trigger
if the trigger you stated occurs before
the start of your next turn you
immediately respond with the action that
you ready and note the rules say that
the conditional trigger lasts until the
start of your next turn not before the
end of the current round therefore when
you use the ready action
it does persist through the end of the
current round and into the start of the
next round and until the start of your
turn in that round if the action you
readied is an attack then you apply the
multiple attack penalty you had at the
time you declared the ready action
also note the Fioretti action costs two
actions and allows you to letter use
your reaction for the event that you
ready some people misinterpret this to
mean that you spin two actions for the
ready action and that allows you to save
your third action for a later in the
round but that's not the case
readying an action costs two actions and
then you use your reaction later in the
round after the trigger occurs the
reason one way this distinction is
important is it means you still have one
action that you can use on your turn in
addition to readying however that action
must be used before you declare that you
are using the ready action because the
text here states that your turn ends
immediately after you declare that you
are using ready for example you could
use one action destroyed into position
and then use your remaining two actions
that turn in order to ready
okay let's look at an example shafy and
pug are playing goblin ball pug is
behind home plate wielding his dog
knocker and chuffy is on the mound pug
is first an initiative with a score of
15 and chuffy is second in initiative
with a score of 11 at the top of the
round it spooks turn he thinks chuffy is
going to throw the goblin ball at him
and he wants to hit it with his dog
knocker but he can't take that action
right now during his turn because
there's no goblin ball within a reach
for him to strike so he decides to use
their ready action this costs him two of
his three actions that turn and he
announces that if a goblin ball comes
within reach of his dog knocker he's
going to strike it it's now Chevy's turn
and he throws the ball at puch which
triggers his ready to action and allows
pug to spend his reaction to swing his
dog knocker and send that goblin ball
flying into the stands Polk was able to
act even though it is technically
Tuffy's turn if Chaffee had decided not
to throw that goblin ball at pug the
triggering condition would not have been
met and pood would effectively have
wasted two actions that turn
other times when you might want to use
the ready action might include preparing
yourself in case an enemy approaches you
might say I'm readying an action if an
orc
comes through that door I stab it or you
could say if a bandit steps on the trap
door I'm going to pull this lever or you
can ready an action to move you could
say I walk over to the base of the cliff
and take the ready action if any kobolds
cross the bridge I start climbing in
this video we discuss two of the ways a
character might adjust when they act
within a combat round the first is by
using the delay action when delaying the
character declares at the start of their
turn that they wish to delay when they
do so they first resolve any negative
effects that are slated to occur at any
time during their turn and they also end
any beneficial effects that are
scheduled to end at any time during the
turn as well they then step out of the
initiative order play continues as
normal but after every creatures turn
the delaying character may choose to
stop delaying and re-enter the
initiative order at that spot if they do
so they keep that place in initiative
for the remainder of the encounter also
note that while delaying a character may
not take any reactions they must
re-enter initiative order after they
finished delaying before they can use
that reaction and if you do not stop
delaying and re-enter the initiative
order by the start of your next turn you
are returned to that place an initiative
lose the three actions granted in the
previous round and you start a brand new
turn the second way to adjust when you
act is by using the ready action using
the ready action cost two of your
actions that turn but allows you to
state a triggering condition and a
response to that trigger that is only
one action or one free action
if that stated condition is met before
the start of your next turn you may
spend your reaction to perform the
activity that you specified
if the readied action is an attack you
apply the multiple attack penalty that
you had at the time that you declared
the ready action
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature on
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games