hello and welcome to Hero points in
Pathfinder second
edition hero points are a special
currency available to players in
Pathfinder second edition they can be
spent in two ways neither of which cost
any kind of action and can always be
spent even if the character is otherwise
unable to act first a single hero Point
may be spent to roll a check and the
second result must be taken even if it
is worse than the original roll as a
reminder a check is anytime a D20 is
rolled modifiers are applied and the
total is compared to a DC so hero points
can be spent to roll attack rolls skill
checks saving throws or any other time
that a D20 is roll and compared to a DC
the only checks I've seen that are
exempt from this are secret checks that
the players are not aware of for example
if the GM rolls a fortitude save in
secret to resist poison that the player
does not know is in their cup then later
on once the player does become aware of
the poison in that cup they can't then
declare that they want to spend a herar
Appo to roll it and note that the rules
do not specify that the decision to roll
must be made prior to knowing the result
of the check so a player can wait until
the GM tells them if the check was a
success or a failure before announcing
that they want to use a hero point to
roll also hero points may be spent to
roll your checks or checks made by your
animal companion or your
familiar another thing to keep in mind
with hero points is spending them is
considered a fortune effect Fortune
effects modify roles such as rrolling or
rolling twice and taking the higher
result while Misfortune effects also
modify rolls but not to the benefit of
the player the key to remember here is
that any single check cannot be subject
to more than one Fortune effect and more
than one Misfortune effect and if the
role is subject to both a fortune and a
misfortune effect then they cancel each
other out and the check is rolled as
normal what this means for spending hero
points is if a check benefits from a
fortune effect and you don't like the
result you cannot spend a hero point to
roll it as it has already benefited from
one Fortune effect for example if you
cast true strike which is a fortune
effect and still miss your attack you
can't then spend a hero point to roll it
again this also means that you cannot
spend more than one hero point to keep
rrolling over and over until you get a
result you like or you run out of hero
points the second way hero points can be
spent is to avoid death this costs all
of your hero points assuming you have at
least one and can be declared at any
time your dying condition would increase
when you do so you lose the the entire
dying condition you stabilize at zero
hit points and your wounded condition
does not change normally the value of a
character's wounded condition increases
by one when recovering from the dying
condition but not when using hero points
now you have zero hit points but are
stable meaning you are unconscious but
do not need to roll death saves also
note that because this rule interacts
with the dying condition by raw hero
points can not be used to avoid instant
death like that which occurs with
massive damage or with effects that have
the death
trait players start every session with
one hero point and additional hero
points must be awarded by the GM this is
entirely at the discretion of the GM but
the core rules suggest awarding them for
Heroic accomplishments and at a rate of
one hero Point per hour of play and this
is a single hero point for a single
player not a hero hero point for every
member of the party every hour and note
that players are limited to a maximum of
three hero points and these are awarded
per session meaning it's use them or
lose them any hero points not spent at
the end of the session are lost there's
not a lot of hard guidance provided for
when a hero point should be awarded but
the book does suggest things like Brave
last stands in using smart strategies in
my opinion their best suggestion is this
last T line that says look for those
moments when everybody at the table
celebrates or sits back in awe of a
character's accomplishments that's your
cue to issue that character a hero point
in my games I extend this to moments of
laughter if a player makes a joke that
cracks up the whole table that might be
worth a hero point and some GMS myself
included find it difficult to remember
to award hero points so here are a few
suggestions that might help out set an
hourly reminder on your phone encourage
players to remind you and ask if
something they did was worthy of a hero
point at the end of each encounter have
the players decide who the MVP of that
encounter was and award that player a
hero Point award hero points for out of
game events like bringing pizza or
snacks or helping the GM with tasks like
managing the initiative tracker for them
or for special occasions like a
players's birthday and if you forget to
award hero points in one session award
two to everyone at the start of the next
session again these are just suggestions
not rules but they have helped others
remember to award hero
points also here are a number of
possible house rules for managing hero
points this is just a small sample feel
free to leave a comment on this video
with your own suggestions for secret
checks that the player does know about
like recall knowledge or stealth
announce your spending the hero point
before the check is rolled the GM Will
Roll both and take the highest result in
secret hero points may be spent to roll
enemy attack rules provided the player
is being affected by said role spending
hero points to avoid death grants one
hit point thus allowing the character to
rejoin a fight award three hero points
for three different reasons the first
point is not awarded to everybody
automatically at the start of the
session and instead is only awarded to
those players who arrive to the game on
Time the second Point can be earned for
doing something outside of the game like
bringing snacks while the third Point
can be earned for doing something inside
the game like a heroic act if a session
ends mid encounter all Hero points
persist through the start of the next
session and are reset following that
encounter hero points can be spent to
survive massive damage if the player can
provide a heroically appropriate
explanation for it and some GMS enhance
hero points by granting a plus 10 to the
reroll if the number on the die is 10 or
less this reduces the chance of players
being disappointed after spending a hero
point and speaking of alternate ways to
manage hero points p does produce a deck
of hero Point cards these cards are
awarded and function the same way as
normal hero points but each card also
provides an additional way it can be
spent for example a card might Grant a
character a fourth action on their turn
to stride or it might allow them to heal
an ally through prayer or even deal
extra damaged ice following a successful
strike this can add a little more fun
and flavor Beyond Simple roles if you're
interested in getting a deck it can be
purchased through the piso webset for
$14.99 or the pdf version for
$9.99 before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
if you would like to support this
Channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that is by subscribing and
clicking the Bell icon so you get
notified when new videos release and I
can always be reached through Twitter
and Facebook too thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming h
[Music]