hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of character
alignment in Pathfinder second edition
in this presentation you'll learn about
the traditional alignment system used in
Pathfinder and many other role-playing
games will introduce the alignment
system review all nine alignment
categories and discuss when it makes
sense for a player to act outside of
their characters alignment but before we
begin I do want to make a small
disclaimer this same alignment system
has been around since Gary Gygax first
published D&D and has been used in many
many different role-playing games
although there is a wealth of
information discussion and essays
written about this topic very few
specifics are provided in the Pathfinder
second edition core rules so what
follows in this video is drawn from many
different sources not all of which are
official pathfinder books but all share
the same original pedigree of Gygax is
creation your GM may disagree with some
of the interpretations that I share here
but that's okay
because one of those few specific rules
that are included in the core rules is
that it is up to every single GM to
decide how alignment works at their
table so now that we have those
disclaimers out of the way let's start
by going over exactly what character
alignment is
alignment is a snapshot of a character's
sense of morality and principles is your
character an altruistic hero willing to
sacrifice their own life to save others
or are they more selfish in only looking
out for themselves does your character
hold to society's laws but would they
rather just watch the world burn
although the alignment system has been a
staple of role-playing games since the
1970s it's one of the most misunderstood
elements of D&D and is children RPGs
such as Pathfinder and star finder let
me just get this out of the way you're
right at the start your alignment is
written in pencil on a paper character
sheet it is not etched in stone
a character's alignment helps in making
decisions that would be suitable for
their personality but should never be
treated like a straitjacket to control
or limit a character few people in
reality are so a rigid minded and
two-dimensional that they can be boxed
into any one single alignment at all
times
and characters should be free to step
outside of their alignment box on
occasion we'll see some examples of that
later on
the classic representation of alignment
is a three by three grid with nine boxes
total one axis represents a character's
ethics and morality and that's called
the good to evil spectrum while the
other axis represents the character
sense of order or rebellion and that is
noted along lawful to chaotic by lining
up each axis we can label the nine
alignments neutral good lawful neutral
or chaotic evil for example and the
middle of both axis is labeled true
neutral
let's tackle the good-versus-evil
spectrum first this represents a
character's willingness to help others
good characters have a respect for life
and freedom while evil characters are
willing to torture kill or enslave to
further their own goals when working
with new players
I often paint the picture like this
you're walking down the road and you
encounter a stranger you don't know them
and they are in dire need of help you're
able to provide this help but must
sacrifice something fairly valuable to
do so and I don't describe the scenario
beyond that I don't get into specifics I
don't even get into what kind of trouble
they're in or what you'll have to
sacrifice to help them you don't want to
get bogged down in details as this is
just meant to be a quick gut check after
I present that very very brief scenario
I give them three options option a do
you sacrifice from yourself and help the
stranger option B do you strike a deal
with the stranger you're you're willing
to help them but only if you get
something in return
or option C do you take advantage of
this helpless stranger do you sacrifice
from them to better yourself in this
case maybe you robbed them while they're
vulnerable if you choose option A you're
likely good aligned if you chose option
C you're evil and if you chose B then
you could be in that gray neutral zone
of the spectrum when it comes to good
versus evil selfish actions often fall
within the neutral alignments and fact
with two exceptions whenever you see the
word neutral you should probably be
thinking selfish in a lack of any real
commitment to good or evil could also
constitute a neutral alignment
the other axis notes a character's
preference for law versus chaos many
players both new and experienced mistake
law for meaning good and chaos for
meaning bad neither of these terms are
inherently good or bad law versus chaos
represents a character's preference for
structure and order in their lives are
you more likely to obey or to rebel
where does your character get their
sense of right and wrong is it from an
external source such as a city's laws or
the tenants of your religion or does
your sense of right and wrong come from
an internal source maybe you do what you
feel is just because that's how you feel
and to hell with all the laws in the
rules you're going to follow what your
heart tells you is right and just if
your sense of right and wrong comes from
clearly defined rules such as a
government's regulations or a church's
laws then you're probably lawful if your
sense of right and wrong comes from
within regardless of any rules or laws
then you're probably chaotic also
chaotic characters often favor living
out in the wild amongst nature while
lawful characters may prefer living
behind the walls in the structure of a
city
let's look at the nine alignments in
turn and starting with lawful good
lawful good characters value structure
order and laws they might have even
sworn an oath to a church or a cause
that they believe in they also are
forces for good
there are willing to help those in need
and protect the weak and although they
tend to obey Authority they always play
some goodness first and would not
blindly follow rules or superiors orders
if doing so would unjustly inflict harm
on others lawful good characters are
honest and trustworthy their award is
their bond and they would avoid telling
a lie even to an evil opponent some
examples in popular culture of lawful
good characters might be the fabled
knights in shining armor or noble
samurai in fiction you can find other
examples such as Superman Ned Stark or
Optimus Prime
a neutral good character is dedicated at
doing what's right and helping others
they generally obey the law and they
work well with authority figures but the
neutral good character does not feel
beholden to those laws they always try
to work within the law if possible but
they are willing to bend those rules if
that's what's needed to serve the
greater good neutral good characters
believe a society needs laws to function
but if the laws are too many or too
rigid
then they pose too great a limitation on
personal freedoms they believe in doing
the right thing but don't bother with
enforcing any kind of ideology the way a
lawful good character probably would a
neutral good character would keep their
ward too good in neutral and characters
but have no problem lying to someone who
is clearly evil some people view neutral
good as a sort of transitional phase
that's typical of young heroes who are
still trying to find their place and
haven't fully fallen into either the
lawful good or a chaotic good categories
yet some examples might include cops who
don't go by the book like Axel Foley in
Beverly Hills Cop or Captain James T
Kirk who generally obeys Authority but
he's not afraid to bend or regulation
here or there if that's the right thing
to do or to be in a no-win scenario and
perhaps the most popular example of a
neutral good character is spider-man who
believes with great power comes great
responsibility and he is definitely a
force for good but he works outside of
the law although he greatly respects
that law
chaotic good characters follow their
conscience they believe in upholding
good and doing what's right
but they really don't care about any
rules or laws they follow their own path
not the one that's laid out for them by
governments or religions or other
organizations chaotic good characters
have strong beliefs in freedom and
individuality they oppose anyone who
would seek to take away another person's
freedom at times a chaotic good
character may be selfish and a little
greedy but they would not seek to harm
anyone who didn't have it coming chaotic
good characters often work alone as they
do value their freedom but they're
willing to help those in need and do so
on their own terms
chaotic good characters have a strong
dislike for Authority and may freely
break laws but always do so in the
pursuit of what is good and just they
would not harm an innocent person and if
they ever kill you you'll be awake
you'll be facing them and you'll be
armed they won't kill for pleasure and
they won't torture but are more than
willing to intimidate to get what they
need
chaotic good characters only lied to
evildoers and would never ever betray an
ally or a friend
examples of chaotic good characters
include Captain Malcolm Reynolds from
Firefly Robin Hood and a Wolverine
the lawful neutral alignment is often
referred to as the judge these
characters view right and wrong as being
clearly defined with little or no shades
of grey between them they hold order
above concerns of doing good or evil the
law is the law they believe structure
and civilization to be of paramount
importance and will usually put the
needs of a community over the needs or
the freedoms of an individual lawful
neutral characters believe the world is
black and white right and wrong they
enforce the rules without regard for
good or evil if someone steals a loaf of
bread to feed their starving family then
that's a crime and they should be
punished accordingly they also hold
personal honor very high they are
trustworthy figures who would never tell
a lie examples of lawful neutral
characters might include Judge Dredd
most depictions of death or the Grim
Reaper and perhaps the best example of
lawful neutral in my opinion is sergeant
Joe Friday from dragnet
truly neutral characters are the most
difficult to define and pin down
they prefer good to evil but they're
really not interested in going out of
their way to enforce either they can
come off as distant uncommitted or aloof
they're often perceived as being a
slacker or just not caring neutral
characters can be selfish and almost
always place their own interests ahead
of a groups but not to the point of
inflicting harm to the group most non
stinking creatures are truly neutral
they act purely on instinct or
programming without any awareness of
good versus evil or law versus chaos
although true neutral characters can
hold very fluid outlooks on the world
and frequently change their mind this
online not be considered as some kind of
wild card or loophole that will allow a
player to do whatever they want whenever
they want without concern for the
alignment system true neutrality is not
a way to get around the rules
examples of truly neutral characters
include the dude from The Big Lebowski
computers and artificial intelligence
that simply perform the functions that
they are programmed to do without any
awareness of good or evil for example
maybe a starships computer from Star
Trek and all non-sentient animals except
for the family dog because they're good
boys and girls chaotic good but still
good
chaotic neutral characters are often
viewed as being extremely selfish but
not to the point of committing acts of
evil frequent examples of chaotic
neutral characters would be criminals
who don't really want to harm others by
their crimes or a common example are the
more heroic pirates those who might raid
and steal but they're more likely to
taunt and humiliate their victims then
kill them chaotic neutral characters are
free spirits who are concerned with
themselves first and foremost as with
chaotic good characters those who are
chaotic neutral also fiercely value
freedom and independence but whereas
chaotic good characters will fight
against the oppression of others chaotic
neutral characters look out for number
one and they tend to only care about
their own freedom a chaotic neutral
character may work with organizations
but only as long as doing so it benefits
them and will quickly sever those ties
without a hint of regret although they
do not embrace traditions or care one
whit about governments chaotic neutral
characters are not anarchists who would
lead a revolt or conspire to burn down
an institution they simply don't care
about such things as long as they're
left alone chaotic neutral characters do
not place limitations on themselves like
being entirely honest or always keeping
their promises but of course would if
doing so further their own interests and
although they don't see any value in the
laws of a society they would not break a
law just simply for the sake of doing so
and would not commit evil acts such as
torturer or slavery chaotic neutral
characters are rarely the protagonists
of the story but there are a few good
examples like Captain Jack Sparrow
Catwoman or Danny ocean from the Ocean's
eleven series of films
before we move into discussing the evil
alignments it's worth mentioning that
the six that we've already discussed are
considered the standard for player
characters in most role-playing games
and the remaining three were developed
with the adversaries in mind that's not
to say that evil characters can't be
remarkable interesting and fulfilling
player characters but it's advised that
GM's especially new ones proceed with
caution before allowing a player to have
an evil alignment will start our
discussion of the evil alignments with
one other more misunderstood of the nine
alignments and that's lawful evil I
frequently hear new players ask how can
someone be both lawful and evil doesn't
being evil go against following laws
well maybe let's go back to our
discussion of what lawful means
characters who are lawful value order
and structure and their sense of justice
often comes externally from the tenets
of a cult or oppressive government for
example and as we discussed before evil
characters seek personal benefit at the
expense of others whereas a lawful good
character believes the laws of their
city the will of their king or the rules
of their church exists to benefit others
lawful evil characters will wield those
laws and tenets as a weapon to control
and oppress others individuals who wish
to dominate and impose their will on
others are lawful evil in societies
which cater to authoritarian rule with
harsh punishments for for seemingly
minor crimes or do societies which
promotes slavery as being acceptable
would also be labeled as lawful evil a
lawful evil character values order
tradition loyalty and obedience but
shuns notions of freedom and
independence lawful evil characters
value hierarchies and seek to place
vulnerable communities such as ethnic
racial or social minorities at the
bottom of those hierarchies so that
aime rise in power they are the Masters
in the less fortunate should be their
servants laws are valuable because they
are a means to seize hold of and
maintain power over others slavery
public executions and oppressive caste
systems are all laws that they would
dutifully uphold and view notions of
equality and personal freedom as signs
of weakness lawful evil characters value
allies and loyalty and will impose Swift
and fatal punishment on those who might
betray them lawful evil characters often
have codes that they perceive as moral
and that separate them from common thugs
but usually allow themselves a few
loopholes for example their personal
code might be to never kill an unarmed
foe but they'd order one of their
minions to do it for them or they might
never tell a lie but would mislead or
intentionally withhold information they
have no problems using torture to get
what they need but they likely find the
practice a little distasteful and would
not torture just for pleasure a few
examples of lawful evil characters might
be certain depictions of the devil
especially those where mortals sell
their souls by signing a contract
leaders of cults and corrupt churches or
governmental dictators would also be
lawful evil specific examples might
include Emperor Palpatine general Kuvera
from The Legend of Korra or the kingpin
from Marvel Comics
if chaotic neutral pirates are the
heroic sorts who like to playfully tease
and humiliate their opponents the
neutral evil pirates are the Black Bart
of the world who would hang severed
heads from the bowels of their ships or
torture defeated captains in front of
their cruise or maim their ships with
enslaved townspeople neutral evil
characters tend to be selfish criminals
who have no qualms about harming or
killing innocent people to get what they
want they do whatever they can get away
with and indulge in a variety of
hedonistic acts for their own pleasure
without concern for how those activities
might harm others they lie they torture
and kill not simply for the sake of it
but because they benefit from doing so
neutral evil is the most selfish of the
nine alignments neutral evil characters
will work with others so long as doing
so furthers their goals but will also
stab those allies in the back for the
same reasons more than truly partnering
with others neutral evil characters
would use others as tools to reach a
desired outcome neutral evil characters
never feel a responsibility to keep
their ward they will kill innocents and
unarmed foes and in general they do
whatever they need to do to benefit
themselves some examples of possible
neutral evil characters are Lex Luthor
Hans Gruber from die hard and Eric
Cartman
some people just want to watch the world
burn in role-playing games
we call them chaotic evil chaotic evil
characters embrace destruction for the
sake of destruction and evil for the
sake of evil they may not even benefit
from the pain and suffering they cause
but instead derive pleasure from the
sheer chaos that they have created
they avoid being in groups as any form
of organization goes against the chaos
that they desire they are demonic forces
of pure evil in the bane of everything
the good and righteous represent they
value personal strength and view laws in
order as tools for only the weak serial
killers and the most cruel and depraved
of criminals fall into this category the
most frequently cited example of a
chaotic evil character is the Joker but
a few others might be Bellatrix
Lestrange Kid Buu from Dragon Ball and
the evil midnight bomber what bombs at
midnight from the tick
while reviewing the nine alignments I
wouldn't be surprised if some of my
examples raise an eyebrow it seems like
arguing over what alignment category
certain movie and comic-book characters
fall into has become an obsession over
the Internet and I'll be the first to
admit that it's a subjective process in
the examples that I use may not be the
same that others would and a large
reason for that is that new interesting
and compelling character from fiction
spins their entire career trapped inside
of one alignment box never ever just
like real people they face situations
and make decisions that cause them to
behave like another alignment at times
but generally speaking they only do so
occasionally and rarely move more than
one step away from their default
alignment I've even seen it argued that
over the five seasons of Breaking Bad at
one point or another the protagonist
Walter White assumes every single one of
the nine alignments which is appropriate
given that he's a fascinating character
in the overarching plot of Breaking Bad
is exploring what it would take for a
good and noble person to become a
ruthless villain so interesting
characters should not be caged into any
single alignment but they should be able
to shift when it's appropriate let's use
Captain Picard as an example not only
because he's a well known figure but
he's also one of the most frequently
debated characters when it comes to
alignment some people argue that he is
lawful good after all he values law
order and structure and he will gladly
sacrifice from himself to benefit others
but other people point out that in one
episode whom Ward Captain Picard is
willing to let the entire population of
a planet die because he's bound by the
prime directive in favoring the letter
of the law over the well-being of
millions of innocent people
that makes him lawful neutral right and
there are other times when Captain
Picard
that's more in line with a neutral good
philosophy directly opposite of lawful
neutral and that he's blatantly ignoring
rules and regulations because obeying
them would cause the death of an
innocent person this was the case in the
episode penpals went Picard allows
commander data to visit an alien child
and save her planet from cataclysmic
disaster even though doing so is a clear
violation of Starfleet prime directive
the exact same law that he previously
was willing to let an entire planets
population die to preserve
so what alignment is Captain Picard is
he lawful good is he neutral good is he
lawful neutral is he something else I
would place his default alignment as
lawful good and note that he
occasionally shifts one step on the
chart into neutral good and lawful
neutral occasional shifts moving one
step on the chart aren't just acceptable
they should be encouraged this is what
makes a character believable and
enhances the story that you and her
fellow players are creating but moving
more than one step on the chart should
only happen very briefly and in very
rare circumstances I can't envision
Captain Picard ever becoming so selfish
that he would be chaotic neutral and it
would take truly extreme circumstances
for him to move all the way to lawful
evil say being assimilated into the Borg
collective
occasional shifts of one step are common
but characters can and should grow over
time which could lead their default
alignment to change as well
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature on
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games