hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of damaged part 1
for Pathfinder 2nd edition
in this video we will discuss the four
step process for calculating and
applying damage and in part 2 we'll
expand on that discussion by covering
some of the more interesting twists such
as precision damage and persistent
damage
during an adventure players are likely
to find themselves in conflict with all
manner of dangerous enemies and if
they're like my players this conflict
will probably result in someone getting
stabbed and when that happens damage is
inflicted as you are probably already
aware every creature has a number of hit
points and when that total Falls to zero
really bad things happen a future video
titled the basics of life and death
will cover how that works but for this
conversation was important to understand
as damage is the mechanism by which hit
points are reduced and there's more
going on there than just simple
subtraction there is a four-step process
for resolving damage step one is
determine the base damage any effect
that applies damage should include a
number of dice to roll to determine the
base damage in rare cases the effect
will provide a flattened number without
the need to roll dice but generally
speaking you will make a damage roll
step two is determined the damage type
we'll talk about this more in a bit but
there's no such thing as generic damage
in Pathfinder all damage has at least
one type for example slashing damage or
fire damage this is important to know
when you're dealing with step three
which is adjust the base damage for any
immunities resistances or
vulnerabilities the target might have
and in step four you apply the damage
whatever total is remaining at the end
of step three is subtracted from the
targets current hit points
in the first step we calculate the base
damage of the effect and the best place
to start that discussion is with weapon
damage damage from weapon attacks is
pretty straightforward if it's a melee
attack like swinging an axe then base
damage is equal to the weapons damaged
ice plus the attackers strength modifier
and if it's a ranged attack is just the
weapons damaged ice you do not add any
ability modifier to the damage for our
ranged attack for example you do not add
dexterity to a ranged attack as is done
in some other games and there are a few
ways to adjust this damage even further
weapons with the thrown trait like
javelins add your strength modifier to
their damage even though they're
arranged attacks but there is one
notable exception to this weapons with
the splash trait like acid flasks or
bombs do not have any strength modifiers
added to them even though they may be
thrown if the weapon has the propulsive
trait like slings and composite bows you
add half your strength modifier to the
damage or all of your strength modifier
if that is a negative number and if the
weapon has the two-hand trait the
damaged ice increases to the listed
value for example bastard swords have a
base damage of 1d8 but when they're
wielded with both hands that increases
to 1 d12 and this is a change to its
base damage die so any effect that
further modifies as dice are based off
of d12 for example a badger sword with a
striking rune deals to d12 damage when
wielded with both hands so in the first
step we begin with a damage role for the
effect but it's important to note that
in Pathfinder 2nd edition there are only
three instances that are defined as
quote damage rolls and they are the
damaged dice for a weapon unarmed
attacks and for spell attacks I
sometimes refer to this as the base
damage to distinguish it from anything
that's added on for example is a
you have a flaming Warhammer if you hit
a monster with it you might roll one die
for the weapon damage and a roll another
die for the extra fire damage but
technically speaking the only quote
damage role would be for the weapon and
the reason this is important is four
times when you see abilities like
inspire courage that granted bonus to
quote damage rolls this only applies to
the weapon damage dice unarmed damage
dice and spell what damage dice and not
to any other effect that's tagged on to
that base damage so inspire courage
would add +1 to the damage of the
flaming Warhammer not +2
there will be times when you need to
double the damage or cut it in half for
example when you roll a critical hit the
damage is doubled this is pretty simple
you just roll the damage as normal with
all the usual bonuses such as a strength
bonus for a melee attack and then you
multiply that total by 2 and then any
extra damage that only applies to
critical hits is added on top of that
for example weapons with the deadly
trait inflict additional bonus damage on
critical hits so say you have a strength
modifier of +2 and score a critical hit
with a rapier rapiers deal when d6
damage and have the deadly d8 trait on a
critical hit you would roll the normal
damage of one d6 + 2 and then double
that total and then add the extra 1 d8
for the deadly trait the key to remember
is you never double damage that only
occurs on critical hits so you wouldn't
double the one d8 from the deadly trait
because it only applies to critical hits
in the first place
next let's consider a rogue using their
dagger to sneak attack someone again
will say they have a +2 strength
modifier and their sneak attack deals 1
d6 damage if this rogue score is a
critical hit with a sneak attack the
damage would be the daggers usual 1 d 4
+ 2 + 1 d6 for the sneak attack and then
that entire total is doubled because
sneak attack damage is not dependent on
there being a critical hit it does get
doubled and there will be times when you
need to cut the damage in half such as
when the target of a spell succeeds on
their reflect save in these cases you
simply divide the damage by 2 and
rounded down remember the rule of thumb
for Pathfinder is that you always round
down unless you are specifically told to
do otherwise
damage and Petfinder is not generic in
each source of damage should list its
damage type there are many different
damage types and we'll be covering the
more common and straightforward of those
in this video
and the remaining damage types will be
discussed in part two first there are
three kinds of physical damage which are
bludgeoning like being hit with a club
or hammer piercing like being shot with
an arrow are stabbed by a spear and
slashing like being cut by an axe the
damage listing for weapons show a letter
B P or s next to the damage dice to
represent the damage type so when you
strike a skeleton with a war hammer you
don't deal six points of damage rather
you deal six points of bludgeoning
damage energy damage works much the same
way with acid cold electricity fire
force in sonic damage so if that
Warhammer I was just mentioning was a
flaming war hammer it might deal six
points of bludgeoning damage and four
points of fire damage it's important to
keep those separate rather than simply
saying you hit the skeleton for ten
points of damage and you'll see why it's
important to keep those two damage poles
separate when we get into step three
the material a weapon is made out of is
also important to note for example
weapons made from adamantine cold iron
or silver because of this some weapons
will have more than one trade assigned
to a single damage effect so let's
consider that Warhammer and the skeleton
again if it was a flaming silver
Warhammer and it struck a skeleton we
would note that it did six points a
blitzing damage that also has the silver
trait and in addition to that also
inflicted four points of fire damage
when a weapon is made of a special
material like silver or cold iron that
trait is applied to the weapons based
damage type so it's silver and
bludgeoning for six points of damage but
the fire damage is merely fire damage
and not silver fire damage those are the
most common damage types that we will be
using in this discussion about the
four-step process for managing damage
but there are a few more including
alignment damage positive damage
negative damage and precision damage
that all will be covered in part two
once you determine the type of damage
being inflicted you can then check for
any special resistances or weaknesses
the target might have and it's important
to note that these conditions are
applied in a very specific order first
you apply any immunities then you apply
any weaknesses unless you apply
resistances so first immunities when a
creature is immune to a damage type
damage of that type is completely
ignored but only that specific type so
if a creature that is immune to fire is
hit by a flaming silver warhammer that
deals six points of silver bleaching
damage and four points of fire damage
they'll ignore all of the fire damage
but still suffer the six points of
silver bludgeoning some creatures like
uses might be immune to critical hits
and I think that that is poorly named it
might be better to think of it as
immunity to critical damage because when
a creature that is listed as being
immune to critical hits is tricked by a
critical hit it does normal damage
instead of double damage and that's the
only change if the critical hit includes
other effects like a grapple then that
target is still grappled so the critical
hit occurs but not the critical damage
that's how it works by raw however many
argue that any damaging effects caused
by a critical hit should also be ignored
if the hit is immune to critical hits
for example the extra weapon damage dice
that are granted with weapons that have
the deadly trait after all if the use is
immune to critical hits because it
doesn't have any vital organs then is
there any reason why a weapon with a
deadly trait would be more effective
against it
bottom line rules as written states that
the only change is you do not double the
damage in everything else triggered by
the critical hit still occurs but as
always jams can in shooter in the combat
however makes the
most sense after immunity's you apply
weaknesses witnesses will include a
value in their listing such as fire five
whenever such a creature suffers fire
damage you simply add five points to it
so say you strike a monster that has a
weakness of fire five with are flaming
silver warhammer and raw six points of
silver bludgeoning damage and four
points of fire damage that would
increase the fire damage by five making
it nine points of fire damage for a
total of fifteen when a creature has a
weakness to more than one trait of a
single damage effect they only suffer
the single highest weakness value and
this can be a little tricky so if a
creature has two weaknesses say they
have the witness silver ten and the
weakness pledging five and you hit it
with a flaming silver war hammer that
deals six points of silver bludgeoning
damage and four points of fire damage
then that creature will suffer sixteen
points of silver bludgeoning damage not
21 and four points of fire damage for a
total of twenty because when more than
one trait applies to the same damage
effect in this case both silver and
bludgeoning apply to these six points of
weapon damage then you only apply the
highest weakness and neither of those
traits apply to the fire damage effect
so it is not changed by the weaknesses
even though fire was caused by a weapon
that has those traits for its physical
damage type but if a creature has the
witness's fire fawn life and silver ten
and is struck by our hammer it will
suffer both of those weaknesses because
they are separate damage roles in
separate damage effects even though
they're from the same attack the key to
remember here is that this almost never
occurs except when a creature is
vulnerable to both a type of physical
damage like bludgeoning piercing or
slashing and also weak to the material
the weapon is made of like adamantine
cold iron or silver because then is one
damage role but two traits that trigger
two weaknesses and last after applying
immunities in weaknesses you then apply
resistances this works much the same way
as weaknesses except you subtract the
value listed from the damage instead of
adding it so if you attack a creature
that has resistance to bludgeoning ten
and deals six points of bludgeoning and
four points of fire damage with your
trusty flaming Warhammer they will
suffer 0 bludgeoning damage but would
still take the four points of fire
damage this is why we keep those damage
poles separate and not add them together
until step four and one more type of
resistance that's worth mentioning is
resistance to non magical attacks and a
case like that you apply the resistance
to normal weapon attacks but not to
magical weapon attacks so say you're
fighting a creature that has resistance
five to non-magical weapons if you hit
it with a normal hammer and roll six
points of damage that will be reduced to
only one but if you hit it with a plus
one war hammer it has the magical trait
and therefore none of his damage is
reduced by resistance to non magical
attacks
so just to bring this all together
remember that damage is applied in four
steps step one is calculate the damage
you roll the damage dice and add all the
usual modifiers to it step two determine
the type of damage at this step you're
mostly just making note of the different
traits of the attack for use in the next
step which is step three where you apply
immunities and then you apply witnesses
and last you apply resistances and last
in step four you reduce the targets hit
points by whatever amount of damage
remains after step three this would also
be when you would apply the hardness of
an object or shield the value of the
hardness is deducted from the final
total of damage and not individually for
each different type is important to
understand these steps so that you can
answer questions like if I critically
hit a monster that has a weakness to
fire with my flaming war hammer do i
double the extra damage from that
weakness and the answer is no you don't
even though a critical hit doubles all
the damage that is not dependent on
there being a critical hit that doubling
occurs in step one and you don't adjust
for a weakness or a resistance until
step three
so know that extra damage from the
weakness is not doubled because that
doubling happens in step one which is
before the weakness being applied in
step three and that's the basic
foundation for how damage works in path
wonder once again if you would like to
learn about some of the more interesting
twists to the system make sure you check
out damage part 2 and that video covers
persistent damage precision damage
alignment damage non-lethal damage
positive damage and negative damage
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder