hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of damaged part 2
for Pathfinder 2nd edition
in part 1 we discussed the four step
process for determining damage and in
this video we're going to expand on that
by covering a few of the u.s. familiar
damage types starting with alignment
damage
alignment damage is a special kind of
damage often associated with divine
spellcasters in fiends there are four
types of alignment damage chaotic evil
good and lawful when a damaging effect
applies alignment damage only creatures
of the opposite alignment can be harmed
so for example the clear of a good
aligned deity attacks an enemy with
divine lance in the description for the
spell we see it deal with alignment
damage based on the casters chosen deity
in this case the spell inflicts good
alignment damage which means it will
only harm a creature that has one of the
three evil alignments if the clerk is a
devil with divine lance it will harm it
because Devils are evil but if the same
clerk shoots a divine Lance at a vicious
cloaker it won't have any effect at all
because clickers are a chaotic neutral
and only evil creatures can be harmed by
good alignment damage however lawful
alignment damage would harm a clicker it
is important to note that alignment
damage comes from an effect and has
nothing to do with a character's
alignment take for example a good align
cleric uhit's a monster that has the
weakness good 5 with their hammer this
attack will not trigger the monsters
weakness because hammers deal blunt
damage it doesn't matter what alignment
the person wielding the hammer is the
fact that their line is good does not
trigger the monsters weakness too good
but if that clerk was wielding a holy
war hammer that deals an extra 1 d6 good
damage then that would trigger the
monsters weakness and apply an extra 5
points of damage
positive and negative are two special
types of energy damage these names can
be confusing the new players but they're
actually pretty simple positive damage
only harms the undead and has no effect
at all on living creatures or objects
other game systems might call this holy
aura radiant energy and negative damage
is just the opposite of that negative
damage only harms living creatures and
has no effect at all on the undead or on
objects other games you have played
might have called this unholy or
necrotic damage and some effects like
heal and harm spells can also rejuvenate
some creatures while at the same time
harming others for example a heal spell
can release a burst of positive energy
that will heal any living creatures in
the area while at the same time harming
any undead in that area this how it
works when dealing with positive energy
or negative energy but when the effects
specifically says the word damage like
with positive damage then it has no
healing effects at all and can only be
used to harm Undead
another damage type worth discussing is
precision damage precision damage is
additional damage offered by some
special abilities in effects that
increase the damage of a regular attack
the key to remember here is that with
precision damage it increases the base
damage type for example the rogue sneak
attack deals precision damage if a first
level rogue performs a sneak attack with
a dagger it will deal 1.d4 piercing
damage for the dagger and 1 d6 precision
damage for the sneak attack but these
are not two different pools of damage
you wouldn't apply one D for piercing
for the dagger and then 1 d6 precision
damage for the sneak attack instead the
precision damage increases the base
damage meaning this work would deal 1 d
4 + 1 d6 piercing damage when they
scores snake attack with a dagger the
distinction of increasing the base
damage instead of applying it as 2
separate pools of damage is important
when dealing with resistances and
weaknesses for example say this rogue
used their sneak attack against a
skeleton with resistance 5 versus
piercing damage if he treated the
piercing and precision damage separately
and the rogue rolled a 2 for the daggers
piercing damage and a 6 for the sneak
attacks precision damage you might be
tempted to say that the skeletons
resistance to piercing a 5 would nullify
the daggers damage but the skeleton
would still suffer the 6 precision
damage from the sneak attack and that's
not correct
instead precision damage raises the base
damage type of the attack that is
associated with so in this case it would
be 1 D 4 + 1 d 6 piercing damage to on
one die and 6 on the other would be 8
piercing damage which is then lowered by
5 due to the skeletons resistance to
piercing leaving only 3 points of damage
another kind of damage worth discussing
because it functions a little
differently is persistent damage
persistent damage is a condition that
causes damage to reoccur more than once
things like bleed damage acid or being
set on fire could all be examples of
persistent damage when you are under the
effect of persistent damage you will
suffer the listed amount of damage at
the end of each of your terms
after which you roll a DC 15 flat check
and if successful you remove the
persistent damage condition for example
if you're hit with an attack that
applies five points of persistent fire
damage then at the end of your next turn
you will suffer five points of fire
damage and roll one d20 says this is a
flat check there are no bonuses or
penalties applied to this role it's just
a straight one d20 if the die shows a 15
or higher then the persistent game is
condition goes away and if the die shows
a 14 or lower then it continues and at
the end of your next turn you will
suffer another five points of fire
damage and roll another DC 15 flat check
the good news is you're not at the mercy
of one flat check every round to remove
the condition you can also use assisted
recovery assisted recovery can be taken
by yourself or by an ally and cost two
actions when you take the assisted
recovery action you explain to the GM
which you would like to do to stop the
persistent damage and they determine
what effect your action will have the
normal result of assisted recovery is
the afflicted character immediately
makes an extra DC 15 flat check to end
the persistent damage but the GM may
grant additional bonuses depending on
your specific circumstances say you're
on fire and suffering persistent fire
damage if you spend two actions on
assisted recovery and explain to the GM
that you're patting yourself down with
leather gloves to smother the fire they
may grant you an immediate DC 15 flat
check
if you say you open your water skin and
you pour it on you they may lower the DC
of that check to ten and if you spend
the two of your actions to jump into a
river then they may rule that the fire
automatically goes out without the need
for any additional flight check the GM
is also free to make any other judgment
calls that they think are appropriate
such as increasing or decreasing the
number of actions needed or
automatically ending bleed damage once
you're healed toufool also immunities
resistances and weaknesses all applying
to persistent damage in are considered
separate from an effects initial damage
so for example if you have a flaming
warhammer that deal with 1d8 bludging
damage plus 24 points of persistent fire
damage and the target has vulnerability
5 to both bludgeoning and fire they will
suffer 1d eight plus five glittering
damage on the hit and another one before
plus five fire damage at the end of
their next turn as well as at the end of
every other turn until the persistent
condition ends that said the GM may rule
that the persistent damage doesn't apply
in some situations for example if
attacking with a sword that deals
slashing and persistently damage if the
target has resistance to slashing and no
actual damage is applied by the sword
attack then the GM may rule that the
additional persistent bleed damage
doesn't occur at all as always the GM's
are empowered to make whatever judgment
calls they believe are appropriate for
each given situation and last is good to
remember that double damage caused by a
critical hit does double the damage of
any persistent damage also caused by
that effect so if an alchemist throws an
acid flask that deals 1 d6 persistent
acid damage and scores a critical hit on
that attack the unfortunate target of
that attack is going to suffer to d6
acid damage at the end of each in every
one of their turns until the persistent
condition goes away
in this video we discussed a few of the
less common features of the damage
system alignment damage is a type of
damage that only harms creatures with
the opposite alignment of the damage
good damage only harms evil creatures
chaotic damage only harms lawful
creatures and so on
positive and negative damage our types
of energy damage positive damage harms
the undead and has no effect at all on
living creatures or objects and negative
damage harms the living but has no
effect on undead creatures or objects
precision damage increases the base
damage of an attack emphasis on
increases a dagger that deals extra
precision damage represents all of that
damage as piercing is just more piercing
and persistent damage is damage that
reoccurs at the end of each of the
victims turns after which they roll a DC
15 flat check to make it go away they or
an allied can spend two actions to
perform assisted recovery to grant more
of these checks before suffering the
damage at the end of their term
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting the vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the link
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder