hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents part 1 of the basics of death
in Pathfinder 2nd edition
in this video we'll be covering the
basic process for determining when a
character dies and in part 2 of the
series we'll expand on that by
addressing a few special situations
as is pretty common with role-playing
games Pathfinder uses hit points to
measure the health of a creature when
most creatures are reduced to zero hit
points they die or they're destroyed in
the case of undead and constructs the
exceptions to this are players their
companions and any other creatures that
the GM believes are significant enough
to exclude from instant death this can
also include monsters with special
abilities that could bring them back
into a fight after being reduced to zero
hit points like a trolls regeneration
when a player is reduced to 0 hit points
they're knocked out and fall unconscious
and 0 is as low as hit points go there's
no such thing as negative hit points in
Pathfinder 2nd edition the basic process
works like this first you're reduced to
zero hit points you are knocked out and
fall unconscious second your initiative
score is moved to immediately before the
current turn third you gain the dying
condition with a value equal to one plus
the value of your wounded condition if
you are reduced to zero hit points as a
result of a critical hit
or because you critically failed a
saving throw then you increase your
dying condition by one more fourth if
this makes your dying condition dying
four or higher you instantly die fifth
you must attempt a recovery check at the
start of each of your turns remember
when you're reduced to zero hit points
your place and initiative moves to a
right before the current turn so this is
important because this guarantees you
will have one full round to receive
assistance from your teammates before
you're forced to roll that first
recovery check and the result of that
check will determine if you inch closer
to death or stabilized that's the basic
structure and with that in mind let's
zoom in and look at a few of these
pieces in greater detail
when you're reduced to zero hip points
you fall unconscious and being
unconscious has several additional
effects first you fall prone and you
drop whatever you're holding second you
cannot take any actions third you suffer
a negative four penalty to armor class
perception and reflex saves and fourth
you gain the blinded and flat-footed
conditions if you receive hit point
healing of any kind then you lose the
unconscious condition and may act
normally starting on your next turn
as mentioned before when you are reduced
to zero hit points you gain the dying
condition and if the value of your dying
condition reaches dying for than your
dead first you can only have the dying
condition while you are also unconscious
so if you lose the unconscious condition
for example if someone heals you while
you're down then you also lose the
dining condition it's possible to be
unconscious but not dying but it's not
possible to be dying and not unconscious
if you suffer any additional damage
while at zero hit points you increase
the value of the dulling condition by
one the amount of the damage is
irrelevant but if the attack is a
critical hit then the value of the dying
condition is increased by two instead of
one at the start of every turn while you
have the dying condition you must
attempt a flat check versus a DC equal
to 10 plus the value of your dying
condition so if you are dulling one at
the start of your turn you must roll a
flat check against DC 11 and as a
reminder flat checks are just straight
one to 20 rolls with nothing added this
is not a fortitude saving through if
successful the value of your dying
condition lowers by one if failed the
value of your dying condition increases
by one critical successes lower the
condition by two and critical failures
increase the dying condition by two
again if it ever reaches 94 you die but
if it ever is reduced to donning zero
then you lose the dying condition and
stabilize your still unconscious and
have zero hit points but you do not need
to make any more recovery checks at the
start of your turn unless you suffer
more damage and therefore regain the
dying condition again if that happens
you start the process all over again
which means you will skip past dying 1
because you now have the wounded
condition
anytime you lose the dying condition the
value of your wounded condition
increases by one so if you're dying in
someone cast a healing spell on you you
lose the dying condition but you gain
wounded one the next time that happens
it increases two wounded two and so on
anytime you gain the dying condition you
increase its value by the value of your
wounded condition so if you get in a
fight and you're reduced to zero hit
points you gain the dying one condition
then someone heals you which removes the
dying one and unconscious conditions but
you gain wounded one a few rounds later
you get reduced to zero hit points again
you're knocked out and gain dying too
because whenever you gain the dying
condition its value is 1 plus the value
of your wounded condition and one more
if is a critical hit or if you
critically fail to save will say the
clerk heals you again which removes
dying too but increases your wounded
condition to wounded to the next time
you get knocked out you start at dying 3
and so on
fortunately there are a couple of ways
to remove the wounded condition although
you can't really do so in the heat of a
battle the first is by being healed to
your maximum hit point and then spending
10 minutes of rest afterwards you lose
your entire wounded value and are
effectively reset to wounded zero the
second way to lose the wounded condition
is through the treat wounds application
of the medicine skill if someone uses
treat wounds on you and succeeds on the
check to provide healing even if it's
only one hit point you lose the entire
wounded condition now note per the
errata the battle medicine feat that
allows you to use treat wounds during
combat does not remove the wounded
condition
so just to recap when a character is
reduced to zero hip points that they
fall unconscious and gain the dying
condition this will be dying one unless
they also have the wounded condition in
which case they will skip over dying one
and start at a higher dying value and
that value will be the same as their
wounded condition plus one if they fall
to 0 hip points because of a critical
hit or because they rolled a critical
failure on a save then they're dying
score increases by one more if they ever
reach dying for they die
assuming they're not dead yet their
place in initiative is moved to directly
before the current turn in other words
all of their allies will get to take a
turn before the dining character is
forced to roll their first recovery
check when that does come around and at
the start of all the following turns as
long as they still have the dying
condition they will need to roll a
recovery check this is a flat check with
a DC equal to 10 plus they're dying
value so at 9 1 they will need to roll
an 11 or higher to succeed on a success
their dying condition lowers by 1 on a
critical success it lowers by 2 if they
fail their recovery check then they're
dying a condition increases by 1 and
increases by 2 if they critically fail
if their dying condition ever it's 4
again they die and if it ever drops to 0
they stabilize a stable character is
unconscious and has zero hit points but
loses the dying condition and therefore
does not need to roll any more recovery
checks if a stable character suffers
more damage the process starts over
again they gain the dying condition with
a value equal to 1 plus their wounded
value their initiative is moved to
before the current turn and they begin
making recovery checks again whenever a
creature loses the dying condition
including if they become stable they
increase their wounded condition by 1
and their entire are wounded can
may be removed if they receive any
healing from tree wounds or if they are
healed to their hip when maximum and
then rest for ten minutes that's the
basic framework for determining when
someone dies in part two we're going to
expand on this by covering topics such
as heroic recovery suffering massive
damage instant death effects non-lethal
damage that die hard feet the doomed
condition and more
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receives special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the link
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder