hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents part 2 of the basics of death
in Pathfinder 2nd edition in the last
video we discussed the basic process for
determining when a character dies and in
this video we're going to expand on that
with a number of topics starting with
ongoing effects
one of the biggest questions about death
and Pathfinder is what happens to all of
my conditions in other effects when I
get knocked unconscious for example if
I'm a wizard and have spills active do
they remain active while I'm knocked out
in making recovery chicks once a spell
is cast it lasts until is listed
duration ends let's look at wall afire
we see here it has a duration of one
minute so if you cast wall of fire and
then get reduced to zero hit points or
even if you die then that death will
have no effect on the wall it will
persist until one minute has passed from
the moment that you cast it but on the
other hand let's say you cast protectors
sphere and then get knocked unconscious
does that mean the sphere goes away and
your allies lose their damage resistance
well if we look at its duration we see
it says sustained up to one minute
sustain means the spell ends at the end
of your next turn unless you use an
action to sustain it for another round
in the case of protector sphere it can
be sustained up to one minute
so we'll say you cast the sphere and
then get reduced to zero hit points in
knocked unconscious the sphere does not
go away immediately and instead it
continues to operate until the end of
your next turn which should be a full
round because when you're not
unconscious your place and initiative is
moved to immediately before the turn in
which you are reduced to zero hit points
if someone heals you before then so you
have hit points in our conscious you
can't sustain the spell on your next
turn just like normal but if your next
turn comes around and you're still
unconscious then the sphere will go away
and everyone will lose their dr at the
end of that turn that's what happens to
use spell effects when you're knocked
out but what about afflictions well if
you're suffering damage every round from
a poison and full unconscious bad news
but that poison is going to continue
damaging you every round until you
succeed under saving throws or its
maximum duration passes
and Amy's totals don't matter while
you're on college isn't dying so this
would just increase the value of your
dying condition like normal and the same
is true for persistent damage and other
conditions like being paralyzed being
knocked unconscious has no effect and
they all continue as normal
in the previous video we discussed the
Dunning condition and the unfortunate
result of reaching dying for is your
death dying for is the default dying
threshold but there are a couple ways to
adjust that first is through the doomed
condition when a character is suffering
from the doom to condition their dying
threshold is lowered by the value of the
doomed condition so if you get struck by
a Grim Reaper scythe you gain doomed 1
this means you will die at dying 3
instead of dying for if you get hit
again you're doomed of value increases
to doomed to which in turn means you'll
die at dying too if you're dumb
threshold is ever reduced to dying 0
then you instantly die even if you have
full hit points fortunately there is a
way to move the dying threshold in the
other direction - and that's with the
die hard feat this is available to
everyone at first level and raises the
dying threshold so that you die at dying
5 instead of dying for
it's also possible to be killed in one
hit without even dealing with the dying
condition at all for example if you
suffer massive damage when you suffer
twice your maximum hit point you
instantly die so if you're a first level
character with 16 hit points and an
enemy deals 32 points of damage in a
single attack then you die instantly
heroic recovery is one more option to
save you from death if you have at least
one hero point you can spend all of your
hero points to stabilize when you do so
you lose the die condition and remain as
zero hit points but you do not have to
make recovery checks also when
recovering this way you do not increase
your wounded value by 1 this is a very
rare exception to the rule the states
your wounded value increases by 1
whenever you lose the dying condition
this can be done at the start of your
turn or whenever your dying condition
would increase normally this is a last
resort when you're at dying 3 and fail
the recovery check at the start of your
turn
and not directly tied to death and dying
but I thought this might be a good time
to talk about non-lethal attacks most
weapons are designed to kill but some
are attended to incapacitate their
enemies without killing them these
weapons are noted with the non lethal
trait and include fists SEPs whips and
blow guns damage inflicted by a
non-lethal weapon lowers their targets
hip points just like being hit with any
other weapon but if an attack from such
a weapon reduces the target to zero hip
points that target falls unconscious but
does not gain the dying condition and
other weapons can also be used to
incapacitate an enemy by taking a
negative to circumstance penalty to
their attack roles so for example a
fighter or wielding a longsword wishes
to knock out a bandit so that they can
question them later that fighter would
try and strike the bandit in the head
with the palm of their sword instead of
stabbing them with the blade their
attack role would suffer a negative -
penalty but if successful would deal is
normal damage and if that damage is
enough to reduce the bandit to zero hit
points they would fall unconscious
instead of being killed
in this video we discussed a few of the
miscellaneous rules surrounding death
and Pathfinder first when you fall
unconscious any magical effects poisons
curses or other ongoing effects or
conditions do not instantly go away
instead they progress as normal effects
caused by magical spells will persist
until their duration passes in the case
of sustained spells they will persist
until the end of the unconscious
characters next turn if they regain
consciousness before then they can spend
an action to sustain the spell and keep
it going as usual that a fault dying
threshold is dying for meaning that when
the value of your dying condition
reaches four you die but there are a few
ways to adjust this threshold including
the doomed condition which lowers the
dying threshold by the value of doomed
and the dying threshold can be increased
to five by taking the die hard feat a
character instantly dies if they suffer
massive damage massive damage occurs
when a target suffers damage that is at
least twice their maximum hit point
total characters with the dying
condition can avoid death by using
heroic recovery they must have at least
one hero point to do so and this costs
all of the hero points they have but
they will stabilize meaning they remain
at zero hit points but lose the dying
condition also characters do not
increase their wounded value by one when
losing the dying condition by using
heroic recovery and last non-lethal
attacks attacks made with weapons that
have the non-lethal trait function like
any other weapon except when they reduce
a target to zero hit points that target
falls unconscious but does not gain the
dying condition and non-lethal attacks
can be made by any weapon that does not
have the non lethal trait by suffering a
negative tooth penalty to their attack
roles
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the link
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder