this video is brought to you by roll for
combat and the rpg superstar contest
create up to three of your own
pathfinder second edition monsters for a
chance at winning several prizes
including the publication of your
creations in an upcoming battlez
bestiary enter now at rpgsuperstar.com
hello and welcome to rest in daily
preparations and pathfinder 2nd edition
once every 24 hours characters can rest
for 8 hours to heal refresh abilities
and resources and avoid fatigue
by raw all eight hours need to be spent
sleeping however is not uncommon for gms
to allow two of these hours to be spent
on other activities such as eating or
conversing rather than sleeping as long
as the entire time is spent in a state
of peaceful calm
these eight hours do not need to be
consecutive and may be interrupted and
after that interruption rust may resume
until a total of 8 hours of sleep is
achieved when a character gets 8 hours
of rest they regain a number of hit
points equal to their level times their
constitution modifier which is always
treated as being a minimum of 1 for this
purpose so for example when a 5th level
character who has a 14 constitution
rests for 8 hours they heal 10 hit
points a 14 constitution equals a plus 2
constitution modifier so 5 for the level
times two equals ten if this fifth level
character had a constitution score of 11
which equals a con modifier of zero they
would still heal five hit points when
resting five for their level times one
for their constitutional modifier
because the formula for resting is level
times con modifier with a minimum con
modifier of 1.
and this assumes that the character is
resting with a reasonable degree of
comfort in other situations such as
resting outdoors with no shelter
characters regain only half the usual
number of hit points note again that
resting may only be performed once every
24 hours so staying in bed for 16 hours
would not double this amount instead you
would need to take a long term rest when
a character spends an entire day resting
usually in bed they regain double the
number of hit points healed with normal
rest so using our previous example of a
5th level character with a 14
constitution they would heal 10 hit
points with 8 hours of rest receive no
additional benefit for 16 hours of rest
but would heal a total of 20 hit points
if they spent the entire day resting as
that counts as a long term rest
during adventures players are likely to
need to make camping areas that are not
completely safe when they do so they'll
want to set a rotating watch so at least
one character is safeguarding the team
while the rest sleep this time spent on
watch does not count towards the 8 hours
needed and therefore having a watch will
extend the total time needed beyond 8
hours the core rulebook provides a
simple table to determine how much time
each person is spending on watch and the
total amount of time needed to ensure
all characters have eight hours of sleep
depending on the party size
while sleeping characters have the prone
flat-footed and unconscious conditions
which impose a negative for penalty to
their perception scores
if a surprise encounter does occur
during rest the gm can either roll
randomly to determine whose watch it is
before the encounter begins or if the
enemy is very clever they might wait
until a specific player is on watch
before they launch their attack
when a sneak attack is sprung during a
rest all participants in the encounter
roll their initiatives as normal the
attacking creatures will roll stealth
for their initiatives any players awake
and on watch will roll perception for
their initiatives and any sleeping
characters will role perception -4 for
their initiatives
sleeping characters do not automatically
awaken when this initiative is rolled
but they may attempt perception checks
-4 at the start of each of their turns
to see if they are awakened by the sound
of combat the dc for any check to see if
a character wakes up will be up to the
gm to determine but the book does offer
that the sound of nearby combat is only
dc5 to detect
in addition to rolling for initiative
when the sneak attack is sprung the gm
might also require the ambushers to roll
stealth checks against the player's
perception dcs as they approach the camp
one of the main consequences of not
getting proper rest is the fatigued
condition
when you're fatigued you suffer a
negative one status penalty to armor
class and all safes you also cannot use
any exploration activities while
traveling you'd be too tired to hustle
and wouldn't be able to hold your focus
long enough to properly use follow the
expert nor would you be able to keep
your eyes open long enough to use the
learn a spell activity while riding in
the back of a wagon
there are two main ways to gain the
fatigued condition
first is if you go more than 16 hours
without at least 6 hours of rest
and the second usual way of being
inflicted by fatigue is by sleeping in
armor you can rest while wearing your
armor and gain all the benefits of
resting but unless that armor has the
comfort trait like padded armor or
explorer's clothing does then you would
gain the fatigued condition when you
wake up
and the fatigue condition is removed
after you get 8 hours of rest unless of
course you rest in armor that does not
have the comfort trait in which case you
just continue to have fatigue
and on the topic of sleeping and armor
is worth noting that it takes one minute
to put on light armor and five minutes
to put on medium or heavy armor and it
only takes one minute to remove any kind
of armor
after daily rest is complete characters
spend roughly one hour on their daily
preparations characters of all classes
participate in this and use this time in
different ways clerics usually use this
time in prayer bards practice playing
their instruments wizards study their
spell books fighters sharpen their
blades and so on
mechanically speaking this is typically
when player abilities refresh and other
daily resources are spent for example if
your game is tracking rations then this
is when each person in the party would
consume one day's worth of rations for
simplicity you can track food in water
once per day during daily preparations
and you're not required to track it
throughout the day although the gm may
choose to adjust this when adventuring
in a harsh environment like a desert
after daily preparations spellcasters
regain their spent spell slots and focus
points any items or abilities that have
restrictions such as once per day are
also refreshed after daily preparation
so they may be used again and during
this time you may invest up to 10 magic
items and you also equip your weapons
and armor at the end of daily
preparations you are considered ready to
adventure and keep in mind that this
time of daily preparations may only
occur after a full period of rest if
you're unable to rest then you do not
get to perform your daily preparations
and since you can only benefit from rest
once every 24 hours you can only perform
daily preparations once per day
so no resting for eight hours
adventuring for one or two more and then
resting for another eight hours to get
all of your spell slots back in the same
day
we close i'd like to take a moment to
thank all of my patrons these videos
would not be possible without their
continued generosity and support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover if you would like to
support this channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too thanks
for watching take care and happy gaming