hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
the basics of runes in pathfinder 2nd
edition
in this first part of the series we're
going to cover what runes are and how
they work
and in part 2 we'll examine other
related topics
like how to upgrade a rune how to remove
a rune from its item
or transfer a rune from one item to
another
most magic weapons and armor gain their
special properties
through runes runes represent ancient
secrets and magical science that bestow
power to items that they're engraved
upon
and they take two forms fundamental
runes
and property runes fundamental runes
provide the most
basic and common magical effects
for weapons these runes increase attack
bonus and damage
and for armor these runes provide a
bonus to armor class and saves
and property runes grant many
other effects beyond the basic
enchantments provided by fundamental
runes
for example making a pseudo of armor
resistant to acid damage
or setting a long sword on fire
let's take a closer look at fundamental
runes first
there are two kinds of fundamental runes
for armor and those are
armor potency runes and resilient runes
armor potency runes grant an item bonus
to armor class
and the number of the bonus also
indicates the maximum number of property
runes that the item can have so a
suit of plus one leather armor means
it is a suit of leather armor and gets a
plus
one item bonus to armor class in
addition
the potency rune makes the armor magical
and
it will register the spells like detect
magic and redora
the plus one potency rune also means
this leather armor may have
one property rune etched on it as well
the second fundamental rune for armor is
resilient resilient runes grant a bonus
to all saves
and come in three varieties resilient
greater resilient and major resilient
each of those runes increases the
bonuses saves by one
so resilient runes are plus one to saves
greater resilient runes are plus two and
major resilient runes are plus three
remember
when you see the name of a suit of armor
the plus value in the name refers to its
armor potency rune and is also the bonus
it receives to armor class
that plus number has nothing to do
with a resilient rune and its bonus to
saves
instead the armor will have the word
resilient
for a plus one to saves the name will
say
greater resilient for a plus two to
saves or
major resilient for a plus three to all
saves
fundamental runes for weapons function
in much the same way
the first fundamental rune for weapons
is weapon potency
when a potency rune is added to a weapon
it is shown as a plus number in the
weapons name
so a plus two battle axe has
a plus two weapon potency rune etched on
it
and that plus number is both the item
bonus
added to attack rules as well as the
number of
property runes the weapon can have and
remember that plus value is
only added to attack rolls it does not
grant
a bonus to damage instead to
increase the weapons damage you'll want
to etch the second kind of weapon
fundamental rune
which is called striking
striking runes can increase the number
of damage dice
rolled with the weapon a striking rune
increases the weapon's damage to two
dice
a greater striking rune increases base
damage
to three dice and a major striking rune
increases base damage to four dice
so if you add a striking rune to a long
sword
it will deal 2d8 damage on a hit instead
of 1d8
and remember this is an increase to the
weapon's base
damage dice so anytime the weapon dice
are modified
the extra damage from striking are also
modified as well
for example the two hand trait changes
the weapons based damage dice
so a plus one striking broadsword does
2d8 damage when used with one hand and
2d 12 damage
when used in both hands not one d12 plus
1d8
and the damage due to striking is also
increased if the effect
specifically says it is for example the
deadly trait
states that its damage is increased if
the weapon has a greater or
major striking rune therefore the number
of delhi dice are
increased but not if the weapon has just
a regular striking rune but striking
runes do
not increase the damage dice of damaging
effects that are in addition to the base
physical weapon damage
like bonus damage from a sneak attack
would not be
increased because of a striking rune or
fire damage caused by a flaming weapon
that also would not be increased
due to a striking rune
as mentioned before there are two kinds
of runes
fundamental runes are the core runes
that provide
basic enhancements and the second type
of runes are property runes
simply put property runes let the armor
or weapon
do all kinds of other cool stuff beyond
the basic things that come
from fundamental runes want to give your
sword the vorpal quality or
wear armor that can turn you invisible
then you need to add
property runes when you look at a
property rune stat block you will see
some effects
are passive and always occur when the
item is in use
for example armor etched with a shadow
rune
grants its benefit whenever the armor is
worn
and invested but other runes like the
shifting rune
require you to activate the item in this
case
it takes a single action to use the
shifting runes special properties
there are way too many property runes to
go over
all of them here but it's pretty simple
you would just treat those property
runes
in a very similar way that you would any
other magical item
the key difference being that runes
cannot be used on their own
they must be attached to another item
it's also important to remember that
there are limits to how many runes a
single item can have etched on it
each weapon or suit of armor can have
one
potency rune and either one resilient
rune
if it is armor or one striking rune if
it is a weapon
and then can have as many property runes
as the bonus
provided by its potency rune so for
example
a plus one longsword has a plus
one weapon potency rune etched on it
a plus one striking longsword has
a plus one weapon potency rune and
a striking rune and a plus one
striking flaming longsword has a plus
one weapon put in surun a striking rune
and a flaming rune this longsword cannot
gain
a second property rune until it first
increases its potency rune to plus two
and since the striking rune is a
fundamental rune
it does not count against the number of
property runes
the sword can have and note that an item
cannot have
more than one of the same type of rune
so
you couldn't have two plus one potency
runes
and instead would start with a single
plus one potency rune
and then upgrade it to plus two we'll
talk
more about upgrading runes in the next
video of this series
in this video we discussed the basics of
runes
runes are used to grant magical
properties to weapons and armor
there are two types of runes fundamental
runes and property runes
the fundamental runes for weapons are
weapon
potency runes that provide an item bonus
to attacks
and are noted in the item's name by a
plus value
and striking runes that increase the
number of damage dice that are rolled
with the weapon
the fundamental runes for armor are
armor potency
and resilient armor potency runes
provide an item bonus to armor class
and are noted in the item's name as a
plus value
and resilient runes grant a bonus to all
saves the second type of runes
are property runes these add a wide
variety of
other magical effects to the item each
magical item
may have one potency rune either
one striking or one resilient rune
depending on if it is a weapon or
armor and may have no more property
runes
than the plus value of its potency rune
also magical items may not have multiple
copies of the same kind of rune
for example two resilient runes or two
flaming
runes in the next video this series
we will expand this conversation by
covering topics
such as how to upgrade a rune how to
remove a rune from an item
and how to transfer a rune from one item
to another
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the basicsforgamers patreon
community receive special benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad
free before everybody else visit the
link shown on the left of the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release
and we can always be reached through our
twitter and facebook pages too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder