hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
the basics of runes part two
in the previous video we discussed the
foundation for runes and pathfinder
primarily the relationship between
fundamental runes
and property runes and in this video
we're going to expand on that by
covering a few of the other additional
rules
including how to etch or create a magic
rune
how to upgrade runes and how to transfer
runes from one
item to another this video does rely
heavily on the crafting rules so if
you've not already viewed our videos on
crafting
it's highly recommended that you do so
before continuing here
links to those videos are provided in
the description
the term etching arun is just a formal
way of saying
creating a rune and adding it to an item
this follows the same system as crafting
anything else
the only real difference is you're not
making an entirely new item
you're just adding to an already
existing item
so if you want to etch a plus one
potency rune to a long sword
you would first need to be at least
expert proficiency in the crafting skill
and have the magical crafting feet you
also need the long sword you plan to
etch the rune on
you need to have a formula for plus one
weapon potency runes
and you would need to have half of the
runes price available in raw materials
in this case it would be half of 35 gold
which is 17 gold and 5 silver from there
you spend
four days of work as usual with crafting
and after that you make a skill check
and if successful
you can pay the balance to finish the
project or invest more time in lowering
the balance
again check out our videos about
crafting for more
details on how all of that works
some runes typically fundamental runes
allow you to upgrade lower level
versions
into higher level versions if a rune is
eligible to be upgraded
it will say so in its description here
the description for armor potency rune
spells it out for you
the process is simple it works just like
etching a rune except the price is
discounted
by the price of the existing rune that
is being replaced
so if you wanted to upgrade a suit of
plus one chainmail
to plus two chainmail you would treat it
the same as crafting
a plus two armor potency rune from
scratch
you need a formula for plus two armor
potency runes
you must be at least 11th level and have
master proficiency in crafting
you need the craft magical items feat
and you must provide
50 of the runes price upfront in raw
materials
the difference with upgrading though is
the normal price for this roon
is 1060 gold but when upgrading
you discount it by the original runes
price
of 160 gold making the upgrade price
900 gold pieces you pay 50 percent of
that up front or
450 gold spend four days of downtime
working
and then make a crafting skill check as
usual
then assuming you succeed the check you
can either pay off the remaining
balance of 450 gold or spend more days
of down time
lowering that balance further
you can also use the crafting skill to
move a rune from one item to another
or swamp a rune on one item with a room
that's on
another item doing so takes one day of
downtime
and costs 10 percent of the roon's price
if you're swapping runes between two
items
then you only use the price of the
highest level roon to determine the cost
you don't have to pay 10 of the price of
each of the rooms being swapped
only the higher level one
aside from being one day instead of four
this
is otherwise identical to crafting or
etching a roon
you pay half the cost which is five
percent of the rent's price upfront
make your crafting check and can choose
to pay the other half
or continue working as normal with
crafting
there are a couple additional rules to
be aware of
first if swapping runes they must both
be fundamental runes or
both must be property runes and the
final item
or items must be legal for example you
can't
transfer a wounding rune from a dagger
onto a mace because this rune requires
it to be attached to slashing or
piercing weapons
and maces are bludgeoning weapons
one tweak to be aware of is when
transferring potency runes
it's possible you might end up with an
item that has
property runes on it that can no longer
function
because they require a potency room
that's no longer present
this doesn't prevent you from
transferring the potency rune
but affected property runes go dormant
until they're either transferred to an
item
that does have the necessary potency
rune
or until you edge the appropriate poetry
onto the item that is bearing those
dormant runes
at which time they reactivate and can
function again
i also want to mention runestones
runestones cost
three gold pieces each and they
essentially provide a way of
transporting a rune without requiring it
to be etched onto a weapon or suit of
armor
these are a great way for gm's to
distribute runes to players
so that those players can decide how
best to use the runes
rather than giving them runes already
etched to equipment
that they may not want to use or may not
even be able to use
runestones work like any other item for
the purposes of crafting or transferring
a rune
you can etch a rune onto a runestone or
you can transfer a rune
off of an item and onto a runestone
the big difference is that our
runestones are consumed
and destroyed as soon as its rune is
removed
off of it and transferred to another
item and
that transfer has no cost associated
with it
under normal circumstances when you
transfer a rune off of an item
you have to pay 10 percent of its price
if that item is a runestone
there is no cost associated with
transferring it from that runestone
and onto another item in this video we
discussed the rules for etching
upgrading and transferring runes the
process of creating a rune and applying
it to a weapon or armor
is called etching the mechanics for
etching arun
are identical to the rules for crafting
any other magic item
except that the rune must be applied to
another already existing item
such as a weapon suit of armor or a rune
stone
some runes especially fundamental runes
can be upgraded from lower level
versions to higher level versions
this process is the same as etching a
rune
except the price of the new rune is
discounted by the price of the older
roon that is being upgraded
rooms can also be transferred from one
item to another
or two runes from different items may be
swapped
at the same time when transferring runes
all items must be legal after the
transfer
for example a rune that requires a melee
weapon
may not be transferred onto a ranged
and if after the transfer some property
runes
are no longer valid with their new
potency rune
those property runes go dormant until
they are either transferred to a new
item
or the required potency rune is etched
onto the affected item
at which time they reactivate and can
function as normal
transferring runes requires one day of
downtime to work
and cost 10 percent of the marines price
if swapping two runes the cost is ten
percent of the higher
level runes price only otherwise this
works in a
similar fashion to normal crafting after
the day of work you make a crafting
skill check
and may pay the remaining balance of the
project or spend another day working to
lower that balance
as usual
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity
and support members of the basics for
gamers patreon community receive special
benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad free before
everybody else visit the link shown on
the left of the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our twitter and facebook pages
too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder