hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
the basics of armor in pathfinder second
edition
but this time i'm not alone with me
today is my friend
and fellow pathfinder youtuber nonat
howdy everyone
nunet has a great channel dedicated to
tabletop gaming and pathfinder
and you can find his channel linked in
the comments if you like my content
then there's a good chance you're going
to like us too so go check it out
he and i decided to join forces to
tackle the subjects of weapons
and armor with me taking the lead on
armor here
and you'll be able to find the companion
video to this one
that's all about weapons over on his
channel
armor and pathfinder is pretty
straightforward
especially if you're familiar with other
d20 rpgs
all creatures have an armor class which
is the dc that must be met or surpassed
by an attack role in order to deal
damage to them
the base calculation for armor class is
plus the armor's ac bonus plus your
proficiency bonus
plus your dexterity modifier up to the
armor's limit and we'll talk about that
piece in just a second
this total can be further modified by
any other
special circumstances or situations
but for our purposes this is the
calculation that we're going to use when
discussing the base
armor class so let's say your second
level
with a 14 dexterity and trained in
medium armor
if you wear chain mail your armor class
will be 10
plus chainmail's ac bonus of four
plus your proficiency bonus of four
that's two
for being trained plus two more for
being second level
and finally plus one more for your
dexterity
although a dexterity score 14 has a
modifier of plus
two we see here that chainmail
has a dexcap of plus one
meaning that's the highest bonus you can
receive for dexterity
so in this case it's a plus one instead
of the plus two you usually get
for a dexterity of fourteen so
ten plus four plus four for proficiency
and plus one for dexterity equals an
armor class score of nineteen
if you're not wearing armor then your ac
is calculated the same way
but with no ac bonus provided by armor
and
you use your unarmored defense
proficiency
on table 6-3 you can find explorer's
clothing
which doesn't grant a bonus to armor
class but
does impose a deck's cap of plus 5
so you may be wondering why you would
want to wear explorer's clothing in the
first place
and the answer to that is because of
runes
explorer's clothing may be etched with
magic runes
just like armor can but technically is
not
armor which means a monk for example can
wear
explorer's clothing and receive full
benefit of magic runes
while still being technically unarmored
while armor is worn for benefit it
should be noted that most armor comes
with penalties if certain requirements
are not met
while any character can wear any armor
if they don't meet or exceed the
strength score listed for the armor
they're wearing
they will take a penalty to all strength
and dexterity skill checks
except for those with the attack trait
in the core rulebook the penalty
is -1 for light armor -2 for medium
armor and -3 for heavy armor
the only exception to this is padded
armor which incurs no
check penalty even if the character has
less than 10 strength
on top of this the character will also
take a penalty to their speed
light armor incurs no speed penalty but
medium armor will reduce the character's
speed by 5
feet and heavy armor will reduce it by
10 feet
so when you're shopping for armor always
be sure to double check the strength
requirement before you buy a new set
there are a couple more rules to keep in
mind when wearing armor
first it takes time to get into and out
of armor
it takes one minute to put on light
armor
or five minutes to put on medium or
heavy armor
and it takes one minute to remove any
kind of armor
that's 10 rounds of combat to get into
your leather or
50 rounds of combat to get into your
skill mail
which is an eternity if the enemy
strikes while you're sleeping
so your solution might be to just sleep
in your full plate
so you'll be ready in case of an attack
but
not so fast because sleeping while
wearing
armor imposes the fatigued condition
this lowers your armor class and lowers
all saves by one
and prevents you from using any
exploration activities
such as those found on pages 480 and 481
of the core rules
you cannot recover from fatigue until
you get a full
night's rest without wearing armor
some armors also provide additional
benefits or penalties
noted in the traits column of table 6-4
the first of those is bulwark which
applies to full plate
when wearing this armor you can choose
to add plus
3 to reflex saves instead of adding
your dexterity modifier to those saves
the second trait is comfort which
applies to explorer's clothing and
padded armor
these suits are so comfortable that you
do not
suffer the fatigue condition after
sleeping in them
the third trait is flexible which
applies to chain shirts and chain mail
you do not suffer any check penalty to
athletics or acrobatics checks
while wearing chain and last
is the noisy trait which also applies to
chain armor
when wearing noisy armor you suffer its
check penalty to stealth
even if you meet the required strength
score
in this video we discussed the basics of
armor
armor class is the difficulty class or
dc
that must be met by an attack role to
score a hit
and is calculated as 10 plus the armors
ac bonus
plus proficiency bonus plus
dexterity modifier up to the armor's
dexterity cap
explorer's clothing is not technically
armor and uses the unarmored defense
proficiency
but may be etched with runes in the same
fashion that armor is
most armors impose a check penalty to
all
strength and dexterity based skills
except for those with the attack trait
and medium and heavy armors also reduce
the speed of those wearing them
however armors also have a strength
score displayed on the armor table
if the wearer has a strength score equal
to
or greater than the armors listing they
do not suffer
any check penalties and the speed
penalty is reduced by
5 feet it takes 1 minute to put on light
armor and five minutes to dress in
either medium or heavy armor
and it takes one minute to remove any
kind of armor
sleeping in armor imposes the fatigue
condition
unless the armor has the comfort trait
there are three other armor traits to be
aware of bulwark
allows the wearer to add plus three to
reflex saves
instead of their dexterity modifier
flexible armor does not impose a check
penalty to athletics or acrobatic skill
checks
and noisy armor imposes its check
penalty to stealth
even if the wearer meets the armor
strength requirement
i'd also like to take one last moment to
thank nonat for partnering with these
videos
again you can find the companion video
that's all about
weapons over on his channel which is
linked in the description
and let me know in the comments if you'd
like to see more partnerships like this
in the future
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the basics gamers patreon
community receive special benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad free before
everybody else visit the link shown on
the left of the screen and in the
description if you'd like to know more
about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release
and we can always be reached through our
twitter and facebook pages too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder