hello and welcome to basics of
archetypes for Pathfinder 2nd edition
archetypes allow players to customize
their characters beyond the initial
abc's of ancestry background and class
they can be used to specialize your
character within their class essentially
multi class by gaining abilities found
in other classes or flesh out the
characters place within a spatial
organization class feats and in rare
cases skill feats are used to purchase
archetype feats so you have to sacrifice
one of your class abilities for each new
ability you want to gain from an
archetype say you're playing a range if
we look at their advancement chart we
see rangers gain class feats at first
level and every even level after that
the rule of thumb is all characters
receive class feats when they reach even
levels and if your class does not cast
spells at first level then you get a
class feat at first level instead and I
should mention that although class feats
are what are usually thought of as the
currency for purchasing archetypes in
some cases you will use skill feats
instead of class feats for example if we
look at the entry for forced entry we
see that it is an archetype feat found
in the Pathfinder agent archetype tree
but it also has the skill trait meaning
you would use a skill feat instead of a
class feed to purchase it otherwise it
works the same as any other archetype
feat so when you level up you can either
spend your new feats to gain an ability
from your class or spend them on an
archetype but there are some limitations
you should know about
you can think of archetypes as a sort of
ability tree each of these trees begin
with a special feat called a dedication
feat dedication feats are the doorways
to the archetype and you cannot gain any
other feat within the archetype until
you first take the dedication feat in
dedication feats are aptly named because
once you dedicate yourself to an
archetype you will be locked out from
gaining other archetypes until you
satisfy the requirements listed at the
bottom of the dedication feed listed
under special so if you are a pathfinder
and wanted to gain the abilities of a
scroll master you would first need to
take the scroll master dedication feet
to do so you would need to meet the
prerequisites of having expert
proficiency in at least one lore skill
and also be a member of the Pathfinder
society affiliated with the school of
Scrolls
if you meet both of those requirements
you can spend a class feat of six level
or higher to gain scroll master
dedication but once you do that you lock
yourself out from gaining any other
dedication feats until you have gained
two other archetype feats from the
scroll master tree you could take any
regular class feats and you could choose
any feast from an archetype you unlocked
before scroll master but could not
choose to unlock another archetype until
first having three feats from the scroll
master tree including the dedication
feet
there are two very special types of
archetypes we need to discuss and the
first of those is class archetypes class
archetypes represent a specialization
within a class that diverges fairly
significantly from the default base
class at the time of this recording no
class archetypes have been released for
second edition so I have no concrete
examples to offer you but the core
rulebook does lay out a few basic rules
for these archetypes first you must be
the same class as the class archetype
say there is a class archetype called
stardancer and it is listed as a bard
class archetype in that case you must be
a bard in order to take any feats from
the stardancer archetype and it may be
possible to take a class archetype at
first level even if your class does not
have class feats to spend at first level
in this case you must spend your class
fee that's granted a second level to
purchase that archetypes dedication feet
and the last restriction for class
archetypes is that you may never belong
to more than one class archetype so if
you're a bard who chooses the stardancer
class archetype you are forever locked
out from all other bard class archetypes
the other special kind of archetype and
probably the reason why you're here is
the multi class archetype these allow
members of one class to gain abilities
normally restricted to members of
another class but is important note that
multi class archetypes are wholly
different from class archetypes class
archetypes require you to be the same
class as that archetype while multi
class archetypes require you to be of a
different class if you're a bard you
cannot take the bard multi class
archetype to gain more bard abilities
otherwise they work just like any other
archetype but I would caution people not
to make assumptions when you multi class
you get what the feats say you do
nothing more and nothing less
if the dedication feat doesn't mention a
skill or a proficiency or access to some
other ability that you assumed you would
get from multi classing well then you
don't get it but look for other feats
within that multi class archetype and
maybe you'll find those abilities there
some archetypes especially multi-class
archetypes grant the ability to cast
spells the bard cleric druid sorcerer
and wizard multi-class archetypes all
grant the ability to cast spells from
their class but there are a few
limitations and key points to understand
first when you take a spell casting
archetype you gain the ability to use
Scrolls stabs and wands in the same way
that a member of that spell casting
class can also when you take a spell
casting dedication you will learn how to
cast can trips from that class but do
not progress your spell casting further
unless you select additional feats these
feats are called
basic spell casting expert spell casting
and master spell casting basic spell
casting grants a first level spell slot
at 4th level a second level spell slot
at 6th level and one third level spell
slot at eighth level also at 6th level
if you are a spontaneous spell caster
you can select one of these spells as a
signature spell what this means is you
can select one spell that can be cast by
that archetype and casts it as a
heightened spell without needing to
learn each individual level of the spell
again this only applies to spontaneous
spell casters not prepared spell casters
and you gain one more signature spell
when you take the expert spell casting
feet and you gain a third signature
spell when you take master spell casting
all of the spells lusts granted by a
spell casting archetype must be used to
cast spells from that class's list for
example if a sorcerer takes the bard
multi class archetype all spell slots
granted by bard basic spell casting must
be used to cast bard
occult spells even though that character
may also be able to cast sorcerer occult
spells
expert spell-casting grants expert
proficiency in the relevant
spell-casting tradition and also grants
a single fourth level spell at 12th
level a fifth level spell slot at 14th
level and a 6th level spell slot at 16th
level master spell casting grants of
master level proficiency and gives you a
seventh level spell slot at 18th level
and an eighth level spell slot at 20th
level
those are the basic rules of archetypes
but let's bring it all together in one
more time
archetypes are powerful tools that allow
you to customize your character by
specializing within their own class by
morty classing into another class or by
gaining access to abilities normally
restricted to members of a particular
organization trade or other specialized
group an archetype is essentially a
group of feats that requires you to take
a unique dedication feat in order to
access the other feats within the
archetype once you take the dedication
feat of one archetype you will not be
able to take the dedication feet of
another archetype until you meet the
special requirements listed in that
dedication feet this limitation usually
requires you to take two more feats from
the archetype you just dedicated
yourself to before you can select the
dedication feet of another archetype
class fees which are typically gained
when reaching even-numbered levels are
used to select archetype feats unless
the feet has the skill trait in which
case you would use a skill feet to
select it class archetypes require you
to be a member of that archetypes class
in order to select it you may never
belong to more than one class archetype
and some class archetypes allow you to
select them at first level when creating
your character if you do so
you must spend your second level class
feet on that archetypes dedication
another type of archetype with
mentioning is the multi-class archetype
unlike class archetypes you must be a
different class than the class
represented as a multi class archetype
and some archetypes grant the ability to
cast spells the dedication feats for
these archetypes grant the ability to
cast can trips from that archetypes
class in tradition in order to cast
higher-level spells you will need to
purchase other spell casting feats from
that archetype these are labeled as
basic expert and master of spell casting
feats and any spell slots gained from a
spell casting archetype may only be used
to cast spells from that archetypes
class and tradition and likewise any
spell slots that you received from your
base class cannot be used to cast spells
Gaede from an archetype they must be two
separate poles
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting the vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the link
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder