hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
the basics of identifying monsters in
pathfinder 2nd edition
when players encounter a creature they
do not recognize
or more appropriately when their
characters encounter such a monster
as separating player knowledge from
character knowledge is very important
here
they may attempt skill checks to see
what information they know about the
creature
this is a recall knowledge check
requires one action
and can be attempted untrained on a
success the player learns the name of
the target species
and the single most commonly known but
so far
unrevealed trait about the creature
this is entirely up to the gm to
determine
but the rule book uses trolls as an
example
on a successful recall knowledge check
the player
learns that the target creature is a
troll and that they have regeneration
that can be haunted by acid or fire on a
critical success
they also learn an additional
little-known piece of information about
the target
again this is entirely up to the gm to
decide
but continuing the example of a troll on
a critical success
the character might also learn that
trolls are known to make attacks of
opportunity also note that the gm may
limit the knowledge given according to
the proficiency level of the character
making the check
for example an untrained character may
not be able to reveal
very obscure information about the
target no matter how high they roll
there are new concrete rules for
determining
what information is granted at each
proficiency level
and this will require the gm to make a
judgment call
regarding what is appropriate
information for each proficiency level
and although not spelled out in the
rules so consider this a house rule
some gm's will also reveal the
creature's type and subtype traits
on a successful check and the type and
subtype traits are going to be the
traits found in
red when looking at a monster stat block
in the case of trolls they belong to the
giant type and the troll
subtype on a failure the player learns
nothing
and on a critical failure they learn
incorrect or misleading information
maybe they mistake the troll for a march
giant and therefore
don't know that it has regeneration
abilities
but before rolling that check you need
to know which skill to use
by default the skills you use to
identify a creature are based on its
traits
the table on page 505 spells it out for
you
arcana is used to identify beasts
constructs dragons and elementals
crafting is used to identify constructs
nature is used to identify animals
beasts
elementals fey fungi and plants
occultism is used to identify
aberrations
astral beings creatures with the
ethereal trait
oozes and spirits religion is used to
identify celestial beings
fiends monitors such as psychopomps
and the undead and society
is used to identify and know details
about the various humanoid ancestries
that inhabit gulerian
and note that we're talking about the
humanoid trait here
not the creature's shape a zombie may
have two
arms two legs and a head but they're not
considered to be
quote humanoids in game terms
so for example if players encounter a
manticore
they could use either the arcana or
nature skills to identify it
since manticores have the beast's trait
in addition players can also use the
appropriate lore skill to identify
creatures
so as another example either religion
or lore undead could be used to identify
a vampire
at the gm's discretion they may also be
able to use
other related skills hags are humanoids
and therefore you would use society to
identify them
but hags are also known for their occult
spell use
so a gm might allow occultism in place
of society
it is also possible to gain knowledge
about a creature using skills other than
the listed knowledge and lore skills
this will be
entirely up to the gm but if a character
has
the ability or skill that they are
trying to assess
then they might be able to use a skill
to see if the target creature has the
same ability or to what degree
for example if a character is trained in
athletics
and wants to know if they can outrun a
monster
they might be able to roll athletics
instead of a knowledge skill
but they would use their intelligence
modifier for the bonus
instead of strength for that check
once you know what skill needs to be
rolled the next question is what dc
needs to be beat to score success
this is fairly easy simply compare the
level of the creature to table
10-5 found on page 503 of the core rules
and then modify by the creature's rarity
common creatures use the listed dc
increase the dc by 2 for uncommon
creatures
by 5 for rare creatures and by 10
for unique creatures and then lower
the dc if a lore skill is being used
instead of one of the general knowledge
skills
this reduction is either two points
lower or five points lower
at the gm's discretion for example
nileth's are common tenth level
aberrations
so identifying one would call for a dc27
occultism check
cyclops are uncommon fifth level
humanoids
so it would take a dc 22 society check
to identify one of them and if using the
lore
cyclops skill instead of society the dc
may be lowered to 17.
things get a little more tricky when
talking about
unique creatures rules as written
unique creatures have a dc that is 10
higher than what's listed for their
level on the table
but i think this is one of those areas
where the gm
really needs to leverage their own
insights
if the creature has the unique tag
because they are
an individual member of a species like
warble bubble brasher is then by
raw the dc to identify her is 25.
15 for being first level plus 10 more
for having the unique trait
although not spelled out in the rules i
believe the intention here
is for it to be a dc-15 society check
to know that you're looking at a goblin
and a
dc 25 check to recognize her as a
specific
goblin named warble bubble brasher
and the gm may lure the dc to know that
warble is a goblin due to the standard
goblin
being a level negative one creature
again
this is all up to the gm to make a
judgment call
the gm also needs to ask themselves if
warble
is a goblin of great renown in the
community
then wouldn't it be easier to identify
her
if that's the case the dc may be lower
to know her name
but would likely still be dc25
to know that she's deadly accurate when
throwing her heavy books as ranged
weapons
again the gm will need to use some
common sense and their own
interpretations
when managing the dc's to identify
unique creatures
that's the gist of how to identify a
monster you use recall knowledge with an
applicable skill versus a dc that's
based on the creature's level and rarity
if successful you know what kind of
creature they are
and their name if they're unique and
also the single most commonly known
piece of information about them
and if you critically succeed you also
learn one piece of
little known information too but what if
that's not enough
what if you need to know more
information you can continue to spend
one action and make one skill check but
with two restrictions
first as soon as a character fails a
recolonology check
they cannot make any further checks on
that subject
at that point the gm has revealed all
the information they know about that
creature
and second the dc increases by one
difficulty level with every additional
check
so for example if you succeed your first
check against the regular dc
you learn the monster's name and the
most commonly known piece of information
about it
if you spin another action this becomes
a hard check
increases the dc by two and if
successful
the gm provides the next most commonly
known piece of information
if they succeed they can make a third
check at plus
five if they fail that check they're
done
but if they succeed they can make one
last
check at incredibly hard difficulty with
a plus
10 dc this is the last check that they
can make
regardless of success or failure after
they make this check
the gm will have revealed all the
information they know about this
creature
and note that if the character is using
a lore skill
then they start at either easy or very
easy on this chart this is where that
negative 2 or negative 5 reduction to dc
i previously mentioned comes from which
means you have
more potential checks that can be made
with lore skills
as it will take a person starting at
very easy
six recall knowledge actions to max out
their knowledge of a creature
versus four attempts when using a
general knowledge skill
in standard dc
although the rules provide an excellent
framework
for learning the names and abilities of
monsters
it is a process that relies heavily
on gm interpretation and judgment calls
so next i want to share a few house
rules i've seen gm's use to manage the
system with their groups
and as always when discussing house
rules remember
these are not official and what works
for one group
may not be what works best for yours
the first house rule is the gm rolls
these checks in secret
much like how perception and stealth
checks are always rolled in secret
the main advantage to this is the player
doesn't know when they've critically
failed a check
otherwise when they do roll a critical
failure
they usually know that the information
the gm is giving them is false
another house rule i've seen used is
awarding more information
based on degrees of success instead of
success granting the most commonly known
piece of information
and a critical success being that plus
one piece of little-known information
the gm provides the creature's name and
one piece of information for succeeding
plus one more for every five
points they beat the dc by and for
repeated checks the dc becomes the
previous checks total
so they have to keep beating their
previous roles to gain
more information this can speed up the
process
and rewards the players for making
excellent roles
but might feel unbalancing to the gm due
to potentially awarding lots of
information for only one spin action
and the last house rule i want to share
addresses the biggest frustration i see
at the table
which occurs when a player succeeded or
even critically succeeds the check
but are not awarded with the information
they really want
if a player desperately needs to know if
a creature is immune to fire damage
before they use their highest level
spell slot to cast a massive fireball
it can be frustrating to have to burn
multiple actions in
making numerous noise checks until the
gm decides that the monster's immunities
would be the next most commonly known
piece of information
and then awards it so in this variation
instead of the gm granting information
based on what they feel is most
commonly known they instead invite the
players to ask questions
if the player succeeds their check then
the gm will provide the monster's name
and also say i will answer any one
question you have
about this monster and then let the
player spin that opportunity
to ask if the monster is immune to fire
damage
this method is definitely more powerful
than what is provided in the rules
but some groups prefer it and in my own
experience
this greatly reduces player frustration
and can also be fun
when that player asks a question out of
left field
in this video we discussed the basics of
identifying monsters
players may attempt recall knowledge
checks to reveal secret information
about a creature
on a success they learn the creature's
species
and possibly its name if it is unique
and
also learn one piece of unrevealed
information
this is determined by the gm and should
be the most commonly known
but so far unrevealed detail about the
target
on a critical success the player also
learns one little known
unrevealed piece of information on a
failure
they receive no information and may not
attempt
any further checks to identify the
target
and on a critical failure they receive
incorrect or misleading information
as determined by the gm the skill that
is used for these checks
is primarily based on the target's type
trait
as per the table on page 505 of the core
rules but may be substituted for a
different skill
possibly with a different dc at the gm's
discretion
the dc for the check is based on the
creature's level
per table 10-5 found on page 503
and further modified by its rarity
also when using a lure skill instead of
one of the general
knowledge skills the dc should be
reduced
by either 2 or 5 making it either
an easy or very easy difficulty check
players may spend additional actions on
more recall knowledge checks
each success providing the next most
commonly known
but so far unrevealed piece of
information
with each additional check the dc is
raised by
one difficulty level until either the
player rolls a failure
or after they attempt one incredibly
hard
difficulty check
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the basicsforgamers patreon
community receive special benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad free before
everybody else visit the link shown on
the left of the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release
and we can always be reached through our
twitter and facebook pages too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder