hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
the basics of identifying magic items in
pathfinder second edition
when a character discovers an item be it
a weapon suit of armor
crystal cube or whatever they may not
know if it is a mundane item or a
magical one
and if it is magical exactly what it
does however there is a method that
players can use to learn information
about an item in much the same way that
they can learn the traits of an
unfamiliar monster
in fact if you've already viewed my
video on identifying monsters
this may feel very similar the basic
format is the same
you perform and identify magic check
using a skill versus a dc
based on the target item's level and
rarity the first step is you must
discover an item
is in fact magical before you can
attempt to identify it
this can take several different forms
and is largely up to the gm to decide if
you have enough information to attempt
and identify magic check
but the two most common methods of
determining if an item is magical
is by seeing it being used or by casting
read aura on it
i have another video all about the
spells detect magic and read aura
that i'll link in the description and
may be worth taking a look at to
understand more on how
those two spells work attempting the
check
takes 10 minutes but may be reduced to
only one minute with the quick
identification feat
when you attempt this there are a couple
things the gm needs to do
first they need to determine which
skills can be used for the check
this is determined by the item's traits
if the item is magical it will have a
trait that identifies to which magical
tradition it belongs
the table at the bottom of page 238
lists each magical tradition and a
corresponding skill
so for example if a player wishes to
identify horseshoes of speed
we see it has the primal trait which
means it would be
a nature skill check to identify them
other items like bracelets of dashing
don't have any of these traits but
instead
has the magical trait the magical trait
is just an easy way of saying
all of the above and items with this
trait can be identified
using any of the four general magic
skills
also note that you must be at least
trained with the skill in order to use
identify magic but there are no class
requirements
a rogue who cannot even cast spells may
be able to identify magic items
if that rogue is trained in one of these
skills
next the gm needs to determine the dc
for this check
this is based first on the item's level
and then modified by rarity
for example we see that oil of potency
is a second level magic item
which means it is a dc-16 to identify
but a breach of shielding which is also
second level
has the uncommon rarity trait this means
we need to increase the dc
according to the table found on page 504
and uncommon rarity increases the dc by
making this a dc 18 check
at the gm's discretion the difficulty of
the check may be further adjusted
for example the gm may allow a skill
other than the skill noted by the item's
trait
but at a higher dc horseshoes of speed
have the primal trait but the gm may
allow someone to use
arcana religion or occultism to identify
it
but at a higher dc there's no hard
guidance on how much to increase the dc
for using a different skill
but i tend to think that it is plus two
if there is a strong connection between
the skill and the item
for example a dagger that has the occult
trait
but is used by the church of norgerber
in assassinations
might allow someone to identify it using
religion at plus two
but it would be plus five to identify it
with arcana or nature
since identify magic has this secret
trait these checks are made in secret by
the gm
in fact the gm might not even inform the
player what skill they're using
but the check itself is like any other
you roll 1d20
add the appropriate bonus and then
compare that total to the dc
on a success the player gets a sense of
what the item
does and how to activate it but does not
necessarily know
all of the details and mechanics about
the item
on a critical success the player learns
the item's name
and everything listed in its stat block
on
a failure they do not learn anything and
cannot attempt another check
until a day passes and on a critical
failure
the gm provides them false information
and a quick note about identifying
scrolls
if the spell that's written on the
scroll is either one you know
or is both common rarity and on your
spell list
then you can spend a single action for
recall knowledge
and automatically identify the scroll
no roles are needed but if that's not
the case
then you need to use identify magic just
like any other magic item
i should also take a moment to mention
cursed items
identifying cursed items works mostly
the same as anything else but there are
a few tweaks
first you always treat them as
incredibly hard difficulty when
calculating the dc
meaning you add plus 10 to the normal dc
for their level
although not spelled out in the text i
believe this is intended to be in place
of the normal penalty for rarity and not
in addition to it
so for example if someone wants to
identify a suit of medusa armor
you would start by calculating the
standard dc for its level
so dc 32 and then increase it by 10
because it's cursed and all cursed items
are incredibly hard to identify
making its final dc 42
the other important note about
identifying cursed items
is not only are they super rare and hard
to identify
but they're intentionally designed to
trick people into using them
so not only is the dc incredibly hard
but only a critical success will reveal
that the item is cursed
if the result of the check is a regular
success
the identifying player is told that the
cursed item is something helpful or
completely benign but again a
critical success reveals both the
presence of the curse
and the exact nature of the curse so
you would need to either roll a natural
20 or a total identify magic check of 52
or higher
to recognize that this armor is cursed
and i also have a few house rules to
share as with all the house rules i
share in my videos
these are not official rules and i am
not endorsing them
i'm only sharing a few that i've seen
used before
and you should exercise caution before
using them in your games
the first is that a successful identify
magic check
basically acts the same as a critical
success
meaning if you succeed the check you
learn exactly what the item is
instead of just having a vague sense of
what it does
players often want to hear this is a
wand of fireball
and not it's a wand and you have a sense
that when you activate it
it will produce some manner of heat for
a lot of tables the official version of
being
vague on a normal success is a lot of
fun but i know
others who find it a little bit annoying
the second house rule
is once you've identified something you
automatically succeed
future checks to identify that item
again
for example once you successfully
identify a healing potion
you don't have to keep making checks to
identify every potion you come across
once you know the look smell and taste
of a healing potion
you'll recognize it again in the future
another house rule that deals with
automatic success
is if the item's level is five levels
lower than your character level
you automatically identify it and
instead of character level
it could also be based on skill
proficiency if you have
master proficiency you automatically
identify
magic items of 4th level and lower with
legendary proficiency
you automatically identify magic items
of 9th level and lower
this also helps with high level play
where plus 1
striking weapons becomes standard issue
for enemy characters
and you don't want to slow the game down
by forcing a skill check in 10 minutes
every single time you need to identify
each and every sword and dagger you come
across
and the last is a house rule that
addresses how you identify
magic items when no one in the party is
trained in one of these required skills
the quick and easy method is to treat
this as an
earn income activity such as those found
on page 236.
for items that are level 8 and lower you
use the
expert proficiency column for items
level 9 through 15
you use the master proficiency column
and for higher level items
you need to hire someone with legendary
proficiency
so if you want someone to identify a
level 5 magic item
they'll examine it and say that'll cost
you one gold piece
if it's a 10th level item it'll cost 6
gold pieces to identify
and if it's 17th level it will cost
55 gold pieces and keep in mind
that the settlement must have a high
enough settlement level to provide this
service
and it might also require gather
information checks
to find someone who is able to identify
the item as well
and the gm might increase the cost for
higher rarity items
or decrease it since the listed prices
on the table
represent an entire day's work
in this video we discussed the basics of
identifying magic items
identifying magic items calls for an
identify magic check
this takes 10 minutes requires train
proficiency and is rolled in secret by
the gm
the skill that is used is determined by
the item's traits
if it has the arcane divine occult or
primal traits
then you use that trait's corresponding
skill
if it has the magical trait then you can
use any of those four
skills the dc is based on the item's
level
and increased due to rarity the dc may
be further increased if a different
skill is used for the check
if successful the player gains a sense
of what the item does
and how to activate it on a critical
success
they learn all the details about the
item on a failure
they learn nothing and cannot try to
identify it again
for one day and if they critically fail
then the gm provides
false information when identifying
scrolls
if the spell is either one you know or
is both
common rarity and on your spill list
then you can spend a
single action for recall knowledge and
automatically identify it
cursed items work the same way but are
extremely
difficult to identify they are always
treated as being incredibly hard
which raises the dc by 10 and only a
critical success
will reveal that the item is cursed on a
normal success
the gm tells the player it is either a
helpful
or harmless item
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the basicsforgamers patreon
community receive special benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad free before
everybody else visit the link shown on
the left of the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release
and we can always be reached through our
twitter and facebook pages too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder