this video is brought to you by roll for
combat
and the fall of plaguestone an official
piezo actual play podcast
join peru cade brixley and celeste as
they band together to save the village
of plaguestone from utter destruction
listen now to the fall of plaguestone at
royal4combat.com
hello and welcome in this house played
video we'll be walking through the
process
of building and designing an animal
companion the content in this video will
be building upon the information
delivered
in my previous overview of animal
companions video
so make sure you give that a look first
before proceeding
we'll start by selecting a base animal
i'm going to choose
badger its basic stats are included in
the coral rules
so let's type them into the animal's
character sheet
it's a small sized animal and has a plus
two ability modifier for strength
dexterity constitution and wisdom and a
negative four ability modifier for
intelligence next let's look at hit
points
the badger type says eight hit points
but that's not
total hit points that's more like the
animal companions
ancestry hit points its starting hit
points are calculated as the hit points
from its animal type
plus six plus its constitution modifier
so for a first level badger that would
be eight
plus six plus two for a total of sixteen
hit points
next we'll add the animal companions
proficiencies all animal companions are
trained in unarmed attacks
unarmored defense boarding perception
acrobatics athletics and all three
saving throws
and in addition to those each animal
type is usually trained in one more
skill as well
for badgers this extra skill is survival
so let's check those boxes on the sheet
from here let's just go down the sheet
and fill in as needed
first there's armor class armor class is
calculated as 10 plus dexterity modifier
plus proficiency bonus plus item bonus
batters have a dexterity modifier of
plus 2 and his proficiency bonus
is going to be calculated as 2 for being
trained
plus its level which is 1 for a total
proficiency bonus of
3 and add that to the dexterity modifier
of 2
gives it a total armor class of 15.
next we have saving throws all animal
companions start as trained in all three
saves
so that makes each saving throw bonus
equal to 3 plus the relevant ability
modifier
conveniently a badger's constitution
dexterity and wisdom
all have the same modifier of plus two
which grants it a plus five bonus to all
three saves
likewise perception will be wisdom
modifier plus proficiency bonus
so train proficiency is three plus the
wisdom modifier of plus two
gives it a total perception bonus of
plus five
but that's not all the badgers test from
the book also
lists low light vision and scent as an
in precise sense within 30 feet
so we'll add that notation to the sheet
too
next is speed this is taken straight
from the badger animal type stats as
well
a base walking speed of 25 feet plus it
can also
burrow or climb at 10 feet per action
that brings us to his melee attacks
badgers have two attacks
jaws and claws so we'll transfer that
information to the character sheet
i've added the information from the
badger animal type entry in the core
rules
but there are still a few holes here
first let's calculate the attack bonus
for jaws
the sheet shows that the calculation for
an attack bonus
is strength modifier plus proficiency
plus item bonus
for a badger that's two for strength
plus three for trained proficiency at
first level
and there is no item bonus here making
it a total plus five attack bonus
now for jaws damage we just add the
strength modifier of
2 for a total damage of 1d8 plus 2 for
jaw attacks
filling it in for the claw attacks works
the same way
but note that claws have the agile trait
making them more accurate with the
second or third attacks in a turn next
are skills we've already marked the
skills that the badger has training in
to calculate their bonuses we just add
the skills relevant ability modifier
plus the proficiency bonus of plus three
conveniently that makes
all three of a badger's trained skills
plus five
if the badger uses any other skill like
stealth
then it does so at his ability modifier
with no additional bonus for level or
proficiency
and last i'm going to add is support
benefit there's not
really a great place for that on this
character sheet so i'll just type it in
under notes and that's all there is to
it
you may notice that the badger stats
include one more entry for advanced
maneuver
but those advanced maneuvers are not
available at first level
and are gained later on by choosing
feats
okay so we have a first level badger so
next let's level him up and see what
changes first thing we need to do
is increase all of the proficiency
bonuses by one
remember proficiency bonuses are
calculated as level
plus proficiency type which is two for
trained so whenever your level increases
so does anything that has a proficiency
bonus
basically everywhere on the badger sheet
with an entry for proficiency
needs to change from plus three to plus
four
this gives it a new armor class of 16
and all of the previous plus five
bonuses
for perception saves melee attacks and
so on
are now plus six the train skills are
also all plus six now
except for stealth since that is not a
trained skill
is not increased on level and remains at
plus two
that leaves hit points when an animal
companion increases in level
their max hit points increased by six
plus their constitution modifier
the hit points included in the animal
type stats which was eight for a badger
are only for first level when the
companion is created
and not added again when leveling up so
the badger had 16 hit points at first
level
and we now add to that six and then two
more for the badgers constitution
modifier
giving it a new maximum hp total of 24.
okay so let's now skip forward a little
bit more
we'll say the badgers master is now
fourth level
and takes the mature animal companion
feat
first thing we'll do is level the badger
up to fourth level as normal
and now that we have the badger leveled
to fourth we'll add
all of the benefits of being a mature
animal companion
on top of those first we increase is
strength dexterity constitution and
wisdom modifiers by one
and note that this is an increase to
their modifiers
which essentially is the same as
increasing each ability score by
two so strength dexterity constitution
and wisdom
are all effectively now sixteens with
modifiers of plus three
this means we will need to adjust
anything on the sheet that has
one of those ability modifiers in this
calculation which is pretty much
everything
for now i'm just going to update the
notations and we'll get to the updated
calculations
in just a second next it says to
increase
unarmed attack damage from one die to
two
so the damage for jaws is now 2d8 plus 3
piercing
and the damage for a claw attack is now
2d6 plus 3 slashing
and then we increase its perception from
trained to expert
the proficiency bonus for expert is 4
plus level which means the proficiency
bonus for perception
increases from plus 6 to plus 8
and adding the 3 from wisdom gives our
badger a new perception bonus of plus
11.
likewise now that our badger is mature
all of its save proficiencies
also increase to expert which gives them
plus 8 proficiency bonuses
and final modifiers of plus 11 since
conveniently
badgers have the same ability modifiers
across the board here
if skills also get a boost intimidation
and stealth gain train proficiency
and survival becomes expert acrobatics
and athletics remain at train
proficiency
and we update all of the skilled bonuses
accordingly
likewise the proficiency level of its
attacks have not changed
so we calculate them as usual plus three
for a strength modifier
plus six for proficiency gives our
badger attack bonuses of plus nine
and we also need to adjust the hit
points again thanks to its increase in
constitution
is important to remember that when
constitution increases
you calculate the character's hit points
as if it had always had
the higher constitution score
essentially making it retroactive
so the hit point calculation here is
eight for the hit points provided by the
badger animal type
and then an extra six plus three
more for the constitution modifier per
level gives the badger a total of 44 hit
points
and last when an animal companion
becomes mature
its size increases by one step if it was
already small or medium
which makes our badger now medium size
okay let's jump forward in time once
more this badgers master is now
8th level and has taken the incredible
companion feat
as before we'll level the badger up as
normal
before applying any of the benefits of
incredible companion
and now thanks to incredible companion
we get to make a choice of how the
badger evolves further
the core rulebook provides options for
making it a nimble or
savage companion and page 123 of lost
omens legends
provides more options to make genie
touched companions
like wind chasers and wildfire scorchers
as much as i'm tempted to make a flaming
badger companion
i think for the purposes of this video
i'll stick to the core rules
and make them a savage companion thanks
to being savage
our badger increases his strength
modifier by two
and its dexterity constitution and
wisdom modifiers
by one each and then we need to update
anything that is affected by those
increases each saving throw bonus
increases by one
armor class increases by one perception
hit points increases by one per level
because constitution increases
again are retroactive therefore our
badger gains
eight more for a total of 88 hit points
and melee attack bonuses and damages are
also increased by two
also the text for savage says to
increase melee damage bonuses by another
three
making is john's deal 2d8 plus
8 damage and clause deal 2d6 plus 8
damage
in addition to increasing skill bonuses
due to the increase in ability modifiers
we also need to increase the badgers
proficiency level in athletics to expert
giving it a final athletics bonus of
plus 17.
thanks to the incredible companion feat
our badger finally gains access to their
advanced maneuver
which is called badger rage and
two last items to note our badger
increases
in size to large which gives it 10 feet
reach with his attacks
and those attacks also become magical
for the purpose of ignoring resistances
so that's how you build and level up an
animal companion
from first to eighth level while
applying the additional features of
bonuses
for being a mature or savage companion
all that said there is still one last
thing to do before we call this build
complete
and that is we need to name the badger
so leave a note
in the comments for what you think would
be a great name for it
and whichever gets the most likes i may
use as my own badger animal companion in
a future game
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover
visit the link shown at the top of the
screen and in the description if you'd
like to know more
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release
and i can always be reached through
twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming