hello and welcome to the basics of
familiars in Pathfinder second edition
familiars are specialized animals that
are magically bonded to their masters
they typically are common animals like a
witch's cat or a Wizards owl but can
also be for more unusual creatures like
a druids leshi familiars are typically
gained through class feats such as the
familiar feet which may be taken at
first level by alchemists druids
sorcerers and wizards and let me just
get this out of the way at the start the
first rule of familiars is that stat
blocks do not matter there may be times
when you have a question about what your
familiar can do like what the damage for
their attacks are and you might want to
go look up the stat block for that
familiars animal type but don't do it
because rule number one stat blocks do
not matter so say you're a familiar is a
tiny demon you might be tempted to go to
the bestie airy and look up the stats
for causes and then you'll see its stats
and think wow if my familiar is a closet
it can fly it speaks two languages has a
really high dex can cast spells can heal
itself every round changes shape can
poison my enemies and do a bunch of
other stuff but unfortunately step
blocks do not matter and your familiar
can only use the abilities that you give
it and this is also true of animals that
are more common than a closet if your
familiar is a cat or a raven then the
stat blocks with animals have no bearing
on your familiar instead of using a
creature stat block you will build the
familiar yourself which is great because
unless the feet you took to gain the
familiar limits you in some way like how
a druid familiar feat specifies that it
must be alesci then you can custom
create your familiar to be anything you
can imagine familiars all share the same
basic stats and are differentiated by
special familiar and master abilities
for example all familiars have hit
points equal to five times their masters
level it doesn't matter if it is a frog
or a bear cub
if his master is fourth-level then it
has 20 hit points also note that if
familiars hit points are not modified by
their constitution score because
familiars don't have Constitution scores
nor do they have dexterity intelligence
or any other ability modifiers they are
capable of thinking and moving they just
don't have scores associated with theirs
abilities familiars are exactly as
strong or as smart as the GM determines
them to be familiars are also all size
tiny regardless of the animal type or
species a familiars save bonuses and
armor class are equal to the Masters
unmodified scores so if a master has an
armor class of 17 then their familiar
also has an armor class of 17 but if the
master receives a bonus recover to their
armor class increasing it from 17 and 19
then the familiars armor class will
still be 17 unless it moves into cover
as well so basically the familiars of
fit scores are going to be the same as
what's written on the Masters character
sheet and not modified by any
circumstances within the game also what
we're on the topic of armor class is
worth mentioning the familiars may never
benefit from item bonuses so they won't
receive any benefits from barding or
from many other magical items the
familiars perception acrobatics and
stealth modifiers are equal to their
masters level plus the master spell
casting modifier so a fourth level
wizard with training and acrobatics an
intelligent score of 16 and a dexterity
score of 14 would have an acrobatics
bonus of +8 but they're familiar would
have an acrobatics bonus of +7 the
Masters dexterity score in training
proficiency are not applied to the
familiar instead is just a master's
level plus spell casting modifier which
is intelligence for wizards
if a familiar wishes to use any skills
other than acrobatics or stealth their
bonus is equal to their master's level
with no other modifiers this is also the
same calculation for any attacks made by
the familiar when you gain a familiar
you must choose if you want it to have a
land speed of 25 feet or a swim speed of
25 feet familiars all have low light
vision and can communicate and Pathak
aliy with their masters as long as they
are within one mile of each other in
note that empathic communication is
simply a sharing of emotions familiars
neither speak nor understand languages
by default so they can't say I see six
goblins ahead but you might feel them
suddenly become scared and know
something is up those are the common
traits that are shared by all familiars
but what makes each spellcasters
campaign and special is how they are
customized through familiar and master
abilities
familiar abilities and master abilities
give you flexibility in how you
customize your familiar and note as we
mentioned before familiars have no
abilities except those that you grant it
any stat blocks for similar creatures
are completely irrelevant each day
usually part of that day's preparations
you may select two abilities familiar
abilities grant features to the familiar
like giving them dark vision flight or
the ability to speak language and master
abilities modify how you can use your
familiar for example using the familiar
to deliver a touch spell for you or
using the familiar to store a spell
slaughter focus point that you can later
use in combat I'm not going to go over
each and every one of the options here
but they may be found on page 218 of the
core rules and the key to remember is
that each day you get to pick two of
them they don't have to be the same
every day as part of each day's
preparations you can change the
abilities granted to your familiar the
one exception to that is that if your
familiar is an animal that already has
one or more of these abilities if your
familiar is a raven then you must choose
the flyer ability every day if your
familiar is a badger then you have to
take the borrower and climber abilities
because Badgers naturally have both of
those movement types and this is further
unlimited by your number of available
abilities so if your familiar is an
animal that naturally has wings dark
vision and 40 feet of movement then you
need to limit yourself to choosing only
two of those per day fortunately there
are ways to increase the number of
abilities you can choose every day
for example the enhanced familiar feet
is available to several classes at
second level this feat increases the
number of available abilities to four
each day Wizards who choose the improved
familiar attunement arcane thesis also
gain one more ability at first sixth
12th and 18th levels and although not
explicitly mentioned in the rules the
inn
about duplicate effects in ambiguous
rules that you can find on page 444
implies that you cannot select a
familiar or master ability more than
once
so no selecting spell battery four times
to get 4 extra spell slots
and just like animal companions
familiars have the minion trait which
means you will have direct control over
them and they will act during your turn
in the initiative order familiars do not
act on their own instead you will need
to spend one action to issue them a
verbal command there is no skill
associated with this you are not using
command and animal when giving orders to
your familiar and no roles are required
after you spend your one action to issue
the verbal command you're familiar gains
to actions that they can spend during
the same term familiars are completely
limited to those two actions they do not
receive three actions per turn like most
other creatures and during encounters
you're familiar begins each turn with
zero actions and no reactions either if
you don't spend an action to command
them then the familiar will only defend
itself or move away to avoid obvious
harm as the GM decides is appropriate
otherwise they just sit still waiting
for your orders and if a full minute
passes without you issuing a command
familiars will stop waiting for your
commands and begin following their own
instincts this is a little hazy as to
what it means in terms of combat but
since combat encounters are unlikely to
last over a minute I believe this
provision is simply meant to say that
familiars will follow along and do
animal things outside of combat without
you needing to constantly declare that
you are issuing them orders and in a
similar line of thought it's worth
noting that familiars do not panic at
the first sign of danger and therefore
do not suffer the frightened and fling
conditions at the start of combat like
most normal animals do
a lot of questions about familiars seem
to revolve around how they work in
combat specifically what happens when a
familiar attacks an enemy and the answer
to that's pretty simple generally
speaking nothing happens because
familiars have no real ability to attack
by raw they do have an attack bonus as
we've mentioned before but familiars
have no ability to deal damage you do
not use the step block of the familiars
animal type as step locks again don't
matter and instead all familiar stats
are derived from the common rules shared
by all familiars and this is going to
make the question why even have an
attack bonus if you can't attack
anything well there are a couple of good
uses for it first if you select the
spell delivery master ability you can
cast a spell with a range of touch on
your familiar and have them deliver it
to do so you first cast the spell which
usually is going to be two of your
actions and then spend your third action
that turn to command the familiar this
grants that familiar two actions that
they spend moving to the target and
touching them if the spell requires an
attack role you use the familiars attack
bonus not yours and second familiars can
also use their attack bonus to escape
from attempts to grapple them beyond
that using familiars and combat will
require some creativity on the part of
the GM to rule how things play out
familiars have no intelligent score so
the GM will decide if the familiar is
smart enough to scout familiars have no
strength score so the GM will decide
what that familiars carrying capacity is
if a player tells you that they want to
use their out familiar to gouge up
bayonets on eyes out don't tell them
that familiars have no damage entry and
therefore can't even attempt to claw at
an enemy that's a really good way to
turn a player off from the game instead
maybe think about effects other than
damage if this was my game I'd counted
as an attempt to aid you or one of your
allies per the aid action on page
or 70 the owl is in the bandits face
distracting them and making them more
vulnerable to attack now it is worth
mentioning that allowing a familiar to
use aid does conflict with the rules as
written because familiars do not have
reactions but in my opinion this is
within the spirit of the rules and is a
better option than just shutting a
player down to sum up familiars are not
intended to be combat companions and
second edition to quote James Jacobs the
game's creative director familiars don't
have their own attacks in second edition
they're not intended to be combat
buddies that's the role of an animal
companion not a familiar in time as we
expand the game will eventually expand
familiar options as well and that might
include the option of giving them a text
but as of the base game familiars don't
have attacks again because they're not
intended to be combat buddies in that
way
in this video we discussed the basics of
familiars familiars are specialized
animals that are magically bonded to
their masters they are typically gained
through class feats instead of using the
stat blocks for the same type of animal
familiars use the same worlds for
calculating their stats regardless of
what kind of animal or more exotic
creature the familiar is a familiars
defenses are equal to their masters
unmodified scores there saves in Armour
class are the same under normal
conditions but if the master has cover
or somehow has their defenses reduced
the familiar is not also affected
familiars may never benefit from item
bonuses familiars all have low light
vision and may communicate empathically
with their master within one mile and
Pathak communication is a sharing of
emotions by default familiars cannot
speak or understand any languages every
day you can choose to familiar or master
abilities familiar abilities grant the
familiar new features such as the
ability to fly and master abilities give
you new ways to use the familiar like
storing spell slots or focus points for
you you can choose new abilities each
day but if your familiar is an animal
that naturally has one or more of these
abilities such as flight then you must
choose those before you can choose other
abilities and it is possible to use more
than two abilities each day through
feats and also through the wizard class
familiars have the minion trait and
begin each round with no actions in
Newry action you must spend one action
issuing a verbal command to your
familiar to grant them two actions that
they can spend during that same turn an
familiars are not intended for use as an
additional fighter in combat encounters
they have an attack bonus for situations
like delivering touch attack spells but
do not have any natural attacks of their
room
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder