this video is brought to you by the
battle zuo bestiary a new book featuring
100 award-winning monsters and the
monster part system that allows players
to harvest resources from their fallen
foes and craft into custom gear the
battle bestiary is now available at
battlez
zoo.com hello and welcome to snares in
Pathfinder second edition before I get
started I do want to mention that the
content in this video builds upon the
information shared in my previous video
about traps hazards stealth and crafting
so you may want to go view those videos
before you continue here links to all of
these topics may be found in the
description snares are simple one-use
traps that characters can use to hinder
or harm their prey they're usually
thought of as traps one might use when
hunting animals in the wild and
therefore are often employed by Rangers
so although snares are a type of trap
and have the Trap trait they do function
a little bit different than other
hazards which can cause some confusion
so let's walk through how snares
work mechanically speaking snares are
single-use consumable items and
therefore share some similarities with
other consumables like alchemical elixir
but there are a few differences as well
unlike other consumables that can be
carried snares must be used immediately
after they are crafted is not uncommon
for people to assume that they can craft
the snare first carry it around like any
other piece of gear until it's needed
and then find a good place to set it up
or they think that they can create it
and then hand the snare off to a friend
to go set it up but that's not how it
works in Pathfinder the character must
craft the snare in the Square where it
will be set and it cannot be moved from
that square essentially crafting the
snare and setting the snare are the same
thing in Pathfinder crafting a snare
works much the same way as crafting
anything else and has many of the same
requirements to craft a snare a
character must be an experience level
equal to or higher than the snare item
level the character must have a formula
for the snare they must have appropriate
tools in this case they need a snare kit
and they must Supply an amount of gold
equal to the snare listed price as well
as any other special materials that
might be listed in the snare description
provided the character meets all of
these requirements they can spend 1
minute building the snare at the end of
which they must roll a crafting skill
check against a DC set by the GM in most
cases this DC will be a standard level
based DC per the table on page 503 of
the core rules and further adjusted by
Rarity and other circumstances on a
success ESS the snare is created on a
failure the snare is not created but the
character doesn't lose any of the money
or other resources they dedicated to
setting up the Trap and on a critical
failure not only do they not set up the
Trap but they also lose 10% of all of
the resources they had
invested snares can also be crafted for
a reduced price but requires at least 4
days of downtime labor this works
exactly the same way as crafting normal
items so I'm not going to cover those
rules here and we'll instead direct you
to my other videos on Crafting which
again are linked in the
description snares are designed so that
they are hidden and hard to spot until
they're triggered detecting a snare
Works in much the same way as spotting
any other Hazard except you will not
find a stealth DC listed in the stat
block of a snare the same way you might
find them listed for typical traps
instead all snares use the crafting DC
of the person who created the snare as
the stealth DC for that snare and the
minimum perception proficiency required
to spot the snare will be one step lower
than the crafting proficiency level of
the crafter so for example if a ranger
has a crafting skill bonus of plus 17
and Master Level Proficiency in crafting
then any snare they set will have a
stealth DC of 27 and this also means
that only creatures with at least expert
proficiency and perception will have any
chance of spotting
it if a creature does spot a snare
before triggering it they may attempt to
disable it again this works much the
same way as disabling a typical trap the
person wishing to disable the snare will
need to use the disable a device action
this costs two actions and will call for
a thievery skill check to be rolled
against the crafting DC of of the person
who placed the snare and just like with
detecting snares the minimum thievery
proficiency required to disarm a snare
will be one step lower than the crafting
proficiency level of the person who
created the snare also note that the
person who created the snare can
automatically disable it with one
interact action and no skill check and
because completed snares can never be
moved if a person succeeds in disabling
a snare they can't just pick up the
snare and add it to their inventory they
might pick up the raw materials that
were used in creating the snare and then
rebuild the same snare someplace else
but would still need a formula for the
snare a snare kit and a successful
crafting skill check in order to do
so unless otherwise stated in its
description all snares are triggered
immediately when a creature of small or
larger size enters the square so this
means that creatures that are size tiny
or smaller will not set off the snare so
no worries about a rabbit or Mouse
accidentally setting off a trap that was
designed for enemies at least as tall as
a goblin now when a creature that is at
least small size enters the square any
effects listed in that snare description
take effect immediately and the snare is
destroyed note that the rules say enter
so by raw it doesn't matter what means
of locomotion the creature is using
flying into a space will trigger the
snare just as easily as walking into
that space But that said GMS are
encouraged to make other rulings as they
believe make sense for the type of snare
and the creature that is triggering
it so those are the general rules
surrounding snares there are also a few
Feats that a ranger can take to enhance
the way snares work snare specialist
adds options to your formula book and
allows you to prepare snares as part of
daily preparations quick snares and
lightning snares allow you to build
snares faster and Powerful snares can
increase the DC that victims need to
pass with their safes and also the snare
crafter archetype can further enhance
the snare crafting abilities of any
character before we close I'd like to
take a moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support if you would like to support
this Channel and help it grow the
easiest way to do that is by subscribing
and clicking the Bell icon so you get
notified when new videos release and I
can always be reached through Twitter
and Facebook too thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]