hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of downtime in
Pathfinder second edition in this video
we will review the basic concept of
downtime and the first half of downtime
activities as well and in the next
course we will examine the remaining
downtime activities
time--and Pathfinder is organized
according to one of three modes of play
when the GM feels that time needs to be
measured very precisely according to six
second rounds they will place the game
in encounter mode when they believe time
is best measured in terms of minutes or
hours they will place the game in
exploration mode and when the GM feels
time will be best managed in terms of
days then they will place the game in
downtime mode downtime is the portion of
the game that often serves as a break
between adventures the GM might say
something like it'll be six days until
your ship is ready to leave port how
would you like to spend your time and
then the players would each declare one
downtime activity they wish to perform
each day
not unlike declaring an action in
encounter or exploration moves also note
that although not every activity
specifies a time requirement most state
that a day spent performing that
downtime activity is eight hours which
means each player should be able to
perform one downtime activity every day
and still have time available for minor
things like shopping drinking at the bar
visiting a temple and so on but the key
to remember here is under normal
circumstances players should not be able
to perform more than one downtime
activity per day it's as if they have
one action to use per turn and each turn
is one day long over this video and the
next we're going to detail the different
downtime activities that are currently
available each activity uses a skill and
unless otherwise noted you must be at
least trained in that skill in order to
use its corresponding downtime
activities and at the geums discretion
several members of the party may assist
on these checks as usual
crafting is the first of the downtown
activities and if you've been following
this channel then you may already know
that we have a complete three-part
series that details everything about
crafting already so I'm not going to go
into a lot of detail about crafting here
other than acknowledging that if you
wish to forge weapons or armor or craft
magic items like scrolls and potions
then you will need to spend at least
four days of downtime on the crafting
activity if you want more detailed
information about how crafting works
check out our videos on that topic you
can find links to those in the
description players can also use their
downtime to earn a little extra coin the
first step is choosing a skill in
defining what kind of work you wish to
do typically this will be either the
crafting skill lure or performance if
you want to work for a local blacksmith
helping them fill orders you might use
crafting if you want to sing at the
local tavern you would use performance
and most other situations you would use
one of the lower skills working as a
bartender would be alcohol or helping a
town design and build a drawbridge might
be engineering lore working that docks
would be sailing lore and so on and
although those are the three most common
skills used for earning income it is
possible for players to use other skills
too like rolling your religion skill if
you want to help administer church
services during your downtime
so now that you know what you want to do
and what skill you want to use the next
step is to find someone who's willing to
pay you for it the GM will have to use a
lot of discretion in what they allow as
not every community is going to have a
market for every single good or service
in most cases it should be easy to find
work that is one to two levels lower
than the settlements level and also keep
in mind that characters may attempt any
job they are offered they are not
limited by their character level so for
example let's say we have a character is
fifth level and they want to use their
business lower skill to make money
dealing and trading at the local market
the town they're in is a sixth level
settlement that player should have no
trouble finding a job that is considered
a fourth level task or lower but and I
should point out that this is not a hard
rule but in a sixth level settlement
sixth level jobs are likely reserved for
those who have special connections so in
this case the character looking to find
work if they want to spend their
downtime trading in the market as a
fifth or sixth level task the GM might
require them to use their diplomacy
skill to gather information and maybe do
a little role-playing to prove their
worth before they're offered one of the
town's best paying jobs and just because
their fifth level this does not prevent
them from taking a job that the GM
determines is a sixth level task it just
means that it is harder and increases
the likelihood that they'll fail the
task can be fired once you've found a
job and the GM has assigned a test level
to it the next step is to spend a day
working at that job at the end of that
first day you will roll a skill check
against a secret DC that is set by the
GM
this DC can be adjusted with extra
preparation in some cases the GM may
allow a player to spend days of downtime
getting ready for the job before they
start it this will lower the DC by an
amount determined by the GM but the
player will not be paid for those days
of preparation an example of this would
be rehearsing a play before you perform
it in front of a paying audience to
determine the result of the skill check
we need to reference the table found on
page 236 of the core rules in the first
column you find the tasks level of the
job if you fail the skill check you
receive the amount of money that is
listed in the failure column and at the
gioves discretion you might also be
fired from the job and unable to
continue working there
if that's the case you will need to
spend at least one day of downtime job
hunting to find your next job but if you
were successful then you move to the
right on the table until you find your
proficiency level and you earn that
amount of money for the day's work
additionally you can continue working at
the job every day afterwards and you
will earn the same amount of money each
of those days and you will not roll any
additional skill checks what you earned
on your first day is what you will be
paid for every day on the job after that
this lasts until the job is complete
until your adventure resumes or until
the GN determines the demand for your
service has dried up
if you roll a critical success you gain
money as if the task level was one level
higher and on a critical failure you
earn no money and are immediately fired
from the job furthermore your reputation
in that community has been harmed and it
might be more difficult for you to find
future work
let's illustrate this by walking through
the example from the rule book Hearst is
third-level
and has a tell or skill bonus of +7 his
GM tells him he has 30 days of downtime
to spin before his party is able to
continue their adventure and asks how he
wishes to spend those 30 days Hart says
he wishes to use his tail or skill to
work at a prestigious teahouse he is
spending his downtime in a level 5
settlement and the GM gives him two
options he can either work as the tea
masters assistant in brewing tea which
is a level 5 task or served tea to
customers which is a level 2 task note
that the example from the book offers
both of these jobs upfront but a GM
could offer only the second level tasks
and require harsh to spin a day or more
researching and using social skills to
build a relationship at the tea house
before they would offer him a job as
prestigious as assistant tea master
anyway he decides he wants the more
difficult and higher paying job of being
the tea masters assistant at the end of
the first day of work
Hearst must roll a teal or skill check
and compare it to a secret DC set by the
GM in this case the GM sets the DC at 20
he rolls a for the dye plus 7 for his
bonus giving him a total of 11 he fails
but did not critically fail if we check
the table we see failing a level 5 task
earns him two silver pieces for the day
of work after the first day he can
continue working additional days at the
C house but does not reroll the check
for every day he works he will earn two
silver pieces he decides to keep working
as the assistant team master and after
the fourth day the GM tells him that the
team master likes him but just doesn't
think he's ready to serve as his
assistant so the tea master gives him an
option he can either finish
out the week and then be let go from the
tea house to go find another job or he
can't continue working at the tea house
as a server effective immediately
he accepts the offer to become a server
and at the end of his first day in the
new job
he must roll a new teal or skill check
against a new secret DC set by the GM
this time the GM says the DC at only 16
because it is a lower level task horse
corrals a natural nineteen plus his
bonus of seven giving him a total of 26
which is a critical success if we look
at the table again we see that a
second-level task usually pays three
silver per day but since he got a
critical success we treat it as if it
was a level three task increasing his
pay to five silver per day the tea house
is so pleased with his high level of
service that they keep him employed
throughout the rest of his available
downtime at the end of the month he
earns a total of 13 gold and 8 silver
pieces
you can also use downtime treating
someone suffering from a disease after
eight hours you make a medicine skill
check against the diseases DC on a
success the diseased creature gains a +2
circumstance bonus to its next save
against that disease on a critical
success the bonus is increased to +4 on
a failure nothing happens and on a
critical failure
the creature suffers a negative two
penalty to its next saving thorough
against the disease after you attempt to
treat a disease regardless of its
outcome you can't try again until after
that creatures next save against the
disease if you would like more
information about diseases and how they
work check out our video on afflictions
which is linked in the description
in this video we covered the basics of
downtime and the first half of the
available downtime activities downtime
occurs whenever the GM feels that time
is best tracked in terms of days rather
than minutes or rounds each day players
should be able to participate in one
downtime activity that takes eight hours
of the day and leaves them time left
over for other events and rest
the first downtime activity is crafting
which we do explore in detail with
another series a link to those videos
may be found in the description players
can use the earn income activity to make
some money during their downtime when
doing so you will need to work with the
GM to find a job which they will set a
task level for after your first day of
work you will roll a skill check against
a secret DC set by the GM the result of
that check is compared to the table on
page 236 to learn how much money is
earned and from there you can continue
working the job earning the same amount
of money every day without rolling
additional checks until either time runs
out the job is finished or your
employment is terminated and last treat
disease is used to grant a bonus to
someone else's saving throws against
disease this can be attempted only once
per saving through attempt regardless of
how many days pass between those roles
in the next video we will cover the rest
including subsist long term rest
retraining also known as respecting and
also how to create forged documents
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder