hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents part 2 of the basics of
downtime in Pathfinder 2nd edition in
the previous video we discussed the earn
income and treat disease activities and
in this one we're going to examine the
remaining downtime activities including
long-term rest retraining and subsist
but to get us started we're going to
talk about how to create forged
documents
if a player wishes to make a fake but
official looking document they can do so
with their downtime first you have to
have already seen a copy of the document
you wish to fake and you also need
access to all of the common-sense
materials so you might need paper ink
wax for a seal and so on then you spend
at least one day of down time working on
the copy the total number of days needed
to complete the work is determined by
the GM but should always be at least one
day after you spend those days working
the GM will roll a DC 20 society skill
check for you in secret so you won't
know how convincing your fake is until
you try and actually pass it off as the
real thing the GM will also grant up to
a +4 bonus that role depending on the
situation if you haven't just seen the
document before but actually have the
real thing with you as you make your
forgery
then the GM will likely give you a bonus
for that but the GM will also impose
penalties as they deem appropriate for
example if the forgery requires a
specific person signature then they will
raise the DC and also require that you
have a copy of that person's actual
signature as you attempt to make the
forgery if you fail this check then the
forgery can be spotted by passive
observers anyone who looks at the
forgery regardless of if they're just
glancing at it or if they're really
checking it hard they will have the hire
of either their perception DC or their
Society DC compared to that Society
check that the GM rolled in secret when
making the document as a reminder a
skilled EC is just ten plus their bonus
so if a character has a society skill
bonus of plus nine then their society DC
will be 19 and if either of their
perception DC or Society DC is higher
than that total of the Society skill
check that it was rolled with making the
document then they're going to realize
that they are looking at a fake
that's what happens when you fail the
original skill check but if you succeed
then passive observers can never spot
the fake no matter how high their
perception DC or society DC's are
however this how it works for passive
observers but active observers will
always have a chance of realizing the
document is fake regardless of what you
rolled on your original skill check to
make that force document a passive
observer is someone who just looks at
the document and takes it at face value
an active observer is someone who
scrutinizes the document they
intentionally look at it and they're
checking for signs of a forgery they
might hold it up to the light feel the
texture and weight of the paper check
the quality of the ink and so on
regardless of the initial skill check if
someone is actively checking the
document for signs of a forgery that
character roles the hire of either their
perception or society skills and
compares that total against your society
DC not the total of the skill check that
you rolled but your society DC if they
beat your society DC then they will spot
that it is a fake this is a little bit
trickier than I think a lot of people
expect so if you need more information
about forgeries make sure you check out
our companion video that's linked in the
description it has a full example of how
forgeries work
if you're really beat up after an
adventure you can use your downtime to
rest and heal up when you spend an
entire day and night of downtime resting
you recover a number of hip points equal
to your Constitution modifier times
double your character level and as with
other forms of rest your Constitution
modifier is considered to be at least
one for this purpose so a six level
character with a +3 Constitution
modifier would heal 36 hip points and if
the same character had a negative two
Constitution modifier they would still
heal 12 hip points from a day of
long-term rest
if you find yourself wishing you had it
taken a certain feat when you level it
up or would prefer to have an ability
that comes from a newly published book
then you can spend your downtime to
retrain yourself and change some aspects
of your character
retraining can be used to change your
feats your skills and some class
features but not some other aspects of
your character like class or ability
scores what can and cannot be retrained
is ultimately up to East GM to decide
for example some GM's may allow a
sorcerer to change their bloodline or
they might require some really
significant event to occur first before
that character can do something like
that again it's going to be up to the GM
retraining requires a teacher or some
form of instruction this may incur a
cost as well which will be determined by
the GM and when you retrain you can only
gain an ability that you meet all the
prerequisites for and war at a high
enough level to use when you originally
took that ability for example if you're
a fourth level and have a second level
feat that you took when you reached
second level think of that second level
feet as occupying a slot
it's occupying a second level feet slot
you can use retraining to replace that
feet with a first level or second level
feet but couldn't replace it with a
fourth level feet even though you're now
fourth level because the slot used to
take the original feet is only second
level one week of downtime is required
to swap one feet for another as usual
you cannot perform any other downtime
activities during this time and at the
end of the week you swap the old feet
for the new one you can also spend a
week of downtime to swap out a skill
increase at the end of this time you
lower the proficiency rank of one of
your skills by one step and increase the
proficiency rank of another skill by one
step but the catch here is the new
proficiency rank
has to be equal to or lower than the
proficiency rank you traded away so for
instance if your bard is a master
interception and a master in diplomacy
and an expert in intimidation you could
reduce that character's proficiency and
diplomacy to expert and then become a
master in intimidation but you couldn't
reassign that skill increase to become
legendary and deception and you can use
retraining to swap initial skill
proficiencies from character creation so
making one skill untrained and then
another skill trained
retraining class features works mostly
the same way you can only change class
features that you select when leveling
up so a ranger could choose to change
from the Florrie hunter's edge to
precision but could not change their
first level weapon proficiencies because
you don't choose this proficiencies only
features that you choose can be changed
and even then again everything with
regards to retraining is subject to GM's
approval the GM will also decide how
long it takes to retrain a class feature
but should always be at least a month of
downtime they will also determine cost
and the need for instruction as with the
other features of retraining
if you're spending downtime in the wilds
then you can use the subsist activity to
provide food and shelter for yourself
and possibly for one member of your team
as well this requires a survival skill
check and the GM will determine the dc4
that check based on your location and
situation the GM will also determine if
a minimum proficiency rank is needed you
should be able to use subsist untrained
if you're in a lush forest but your GM
might require master proficiency if you
want to find food and shelter in a
desert
if successful then you are able to
provide protection from the elements in
enough food to qualify as the
subsistence standard of living for
yourself standards of living can be
found on page 294 of the rules on a
critical success you can either provide
that subsistence level of living for
yourself and one other person or you
provide comfortable accommodations for
just yourself on a failure you don't
have enough food and protection from the
elements and become fatigued until you
do find food and protection from the
elements on a critical failure you don't
find any food at all or you are
completely unprotected from the
environment you suffer a negative -
penalty - checks to subsist for one week
and you are also in danger of starving
or dying of thirst if you keep failing
subsists can also be used in urban
environments you just use the society
skill instead of survival
if you're feeling like subsists is awful
stingy you're not only but the good news
is you can easily increase the rewards
of subsist by taking the forager feet
with this feat you can never fail or
critically fail a survival check to
subsist instead you are treated as if
you succeeded on the check in on a
success you provide food and shelter for
you and for other people instead of just
yourself and that number doubles every
time you raise the proficiency rank of
survival so experts in survival can take
care of eight extra people masters can
feed and shelter sixteen other people
and those with legendary proficiency can
take care of thirty-two more people on
one subsist check which makes subsist a
whole lot more viable for most parties
in this video we discussed the second
half of down time activities from the
core rules create forgery is used to
falsify a document you must have at
least seen an original document and will
get a bonus to your check if you have
that copy with you while you're making
the forgery after at least one day of
downtime your GM will roll a society
skill check for you in secret the dc4
this check is 20 but may be adjusted due
to unfavorable circumstances if you
succeed that check only active observers
will notice that something is wrong with
your fake an active observer is someone
who scrutinizes the document and they're
trying to determine his authenticity
when doing so that person will roll
either their perception or society
skills whichever is higher and that will
be contested by your society DC if they
are successful then they realize that
the document is fake if you fail your
check to make that forged document then
both passive and active observers have a
chance to notice that is fake when
someone passively observes the document
the GF compares that character's
perception or society deceit against the
total of the society skill check that
the GM wrote for you in secret if their
DC is higher than they realize it's fake
when a character arrests for 24 hours
straight they receive the benefits of
long-term rest after a day of a
long-term rest the character heals a
number of hit points equal to their
Constitution modifier times double with
their level as with normal resting the
constitutional modifier is always
treated as being at least 1 for this
purpose and Retraining or respecting
will also allow you to spend Elly's one
week of downtime to lose one feet class
feature or skill proficiency rank and
then replace it with another feet class
feature or proficiency rank of the same
level and subsist allows you to find
food and shelter this requires a
survival check if you are in the wild or
a society check if you're in a city
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder