hello and welcome to pathfinder
encounters part 1
by how it's played this series will
provide gm some guidance when creating
encounters for their games
and will consist of three parts in this
first part of the series we will discuss
encounter design and specifically a
checklist of items to be considered when
deciding what elements to include in an
encounter
part 2 will cover the mechanics of
encounter design for example
how to set and manage an encounter
budget of experience points
and part 3 of the series will discuss
encounter rewards
this three-part series will focus on
combat encounters
and social encounters will be discussed
at a later time
there is far far too much information
available about encounter design to cram
into one video
in fact there are entire books available
on the subject
but in this video i will share the
simplified design process i have used
for the past decade
which was first introduced by chris witt
and david velagas of the order 66
podcast
specifically this process for encounter
design comes from
episode 37 and although order 66
is a star wars role-playing podcast most
of their advice for encounter design is
perfectly applicable to pathfinder as
well
in that episode they provided what they
call the list
eight items that should be considered
when designing an encounter
these are not items that must be
included in each encounter but again are
items that should be considered as part
of the thought process when designing an
encounter
especially when designing encounter maps
the first item on the list is the rule
of six
leave at least six squares of space
between most threats and points of
interest on the map
the rule of six basically means spread
your enemies out
and there are two reasons to do this the
first is many of the area effects in the
games are based on either 15 or 30 foot
sizes and multiples thereof so having
six spaces between
threats threat groups and other points
of interest
reduces the odds of players ending the
fight before it even starts
by nuking everything with aoe at the
very beginning
and the second reason to spread threats
and points of interest
out is that it encourages players to
spread out to address these challenges
one of the possible pitfalls of tactical
rpgs is
players and enemies can get so grouped
up that they stop
moving all together and instead just
stand still
bludgeoning each other until one side
dies which can make for a rather boring
in mundane experience
so spreading the enemies and points of
interest out helps reduce the odds of
this happening
one obvious way to help spread things
out is to use a large
area for the encounter obviously this
will not always be an
option but when possible plan to provide
a large enough space to accommodate the
players and threats
while leaving enough empty space for
people to maneuver around
the rule of thumb is encounter maps
should be no smaller than
2 inches wide and 2 inches tall per
player
so with a party of 4 pcs you would want
the encounter space to be
at least an 8 by 8 inch area
make sure the encounter map is not a
flat open area
provide some texture by placing
furniture shelves
statues to lag mites and other obstacles
for the players to move around
not only does this add a little
personality to the area but it also
encourages players to think tactically
the presence of cover allows pcs to
sneak and hide
and arranged characters can use the
cover for defense as well
another way to add texture and
personality to a battlefield is to think
about
lighting find ways to add concealment to
the encounter
if it's in a dungeon maybe a few torches
along the wall have burned out
or their light doesn't reach all the way
into the corners
or maybe there's a bubbling cauldron
that spreads a thick fog into adjacent
squares
give your players and their enemies more
places to hide
as well as reward those players who
invest in ways to overcome concealment
such as having dark vision
one more tip to consider with cover and
concealment is to place those items
near the entrance this will aid stealthy
characters and playing up those
abilities
instead of everyone simply rushing in to
stab the bad guys
another way to add texture to an
encounter area is to include
difficult terrain uneven flooring debris
stairs mud shallow pools when you're
making
a map for the encounter try and include
one or two small patches of difficult
terrain
and consider where these should be you
might want to place difficult terrain
in the most direct path from where you
expect the players to begin
and where their enemies will be this is
one more way to encourage the players to
split up and move about the map
instead of just standing still
the sixth item to consider is where the
points of entry and exit will be on the
map
and how many will there be probably the
biggest point here is to make sure
there are at least two doors on the
encounter map
far too often encounters especially
those in dungeons
take place in rooms with only one
doorway that the players will bottleneck
and control the battle from there
that makes perfect sense and is good
tactics for the players
but as a gm you should question if that
makes for the most
fun and interesting combat encounter in
my experience
this adds an incentive for players to
dig in and
eliminates the need to move about the
encounter map
so include a second point of entry to
the map that either the players will
need to split to defend
or the enemies can use to exit through
to summon more allies or
loop around to the player's backs and if
the plane is for the enemies to rush
into a room and be the ones engaging the
players
don't have all of them come through the
same single doorway
instead split them up and have them come
in through different
directions but when making decisions
like these always keep in mind the plan
here
is not to make the battle more difficult
or to make it feel
unfair the goal is to make the battle
more interesting
by encouraging the players and their
enemies to be more
movable and not rooted in place
therefore you might want to consider
lowering the level of the enemies in
some of these encounters as well
the next item on the list is hazards
when discussing hazards most people
think of traps but hazards can take
many different forms weather conditions
lava flows or a haunted room
the main goal here is to give the
players something to pay attention to
other than the monsters ideally these
hazards would affect
everyone involved in the battle both
players and their enemies
and always make sure there is some way
that the players can either defeat
or escape the effects of the hazard
which brings us to the next
item on the list
encounters should not only be about
combat and killing monsters
when you design your encounters include
ways that players can use their wits and
skills
as well as their swords and magic if you
include a hazard as previously discussed
make sure players can use their skills
to overcome it
maybe they can use athletics to knock
over a pillar to form a bridge across
the lava flow
or they can make a religion check to
calm the spirits that haunt the room
or they can use thievery to jam close a
pipe that is spilling water into the
chamber
again too many adventures are basically
enter a room
kill everything repeat so give your
players especially the skill
monkeys a way to break up that monotony
by using their skills to overcome
obstacles the items i've discussed so
far
are the ones included on the order 66
list of things to consider when
designing encounters
but i have one more of my own to add and
that is to
think in phases as mentioned before
players are accustomed to opening a door
and finding all of their enemies there
just waiting to be killed but consider
that it might make for a more
interesting encounter if that's not
really the case so think of the
encounter
in terms of phases phase 1 starts like
any normal battle but at some point
something occurs that causes the battle
to transition into a new phase that's
noticeably different from how the battle
began
maybe the evil druid summons an owl bear
from the surrounding wilderness or
the fight begins with a giant but once
he's slain his body falls through the
floor or through a wall
and introduces some kind of new danger
to the fight that the players were not
expecting
before or maybe if the players are
fighting a swarm of 12
giant insects in their den instead of
having all 12 of them already waiting on
the map when the pcs arrive
you start with 6 and every round 2 more
burrow through the cave walls and join
the fight
the general idea here is to break the
monotony that is common when all of the
enemies on the board at the
start of the fight are all of the
enemies the players need to contend with
in order to complete the encounter
and instead bring them in a little at a
time to keep the players on their toes
and a more advanced form of this concept
is instead of simply adding more enemies
in each phase
think of how the environment itself can
change with each phase
maybe after the first batch of enemies
are almost finished with
one of them opens a valve that floods
the chamber and hurls the players into a
completely new environment
they weren't expecting from the
remainder of this battle
also think of your favorite final bosses
from video games
often they go through several changes
and phases before they're finally
defeated
there's no reason why you can't do the
same in pathfinder
just think of the fight in terms of
phases instead
each phase of the final boss as a
different monster
and if you want to go the extra mile
once you draft the different phases of
an encounter
write in triggers for each phase in ways
the players might be able to prevent
those
or actions the enemy must succeed at in
order to trigger the next phase
give the player something to think about
and do other than
simply killing everything in the room
as mentioned at the beginning of this
video there is far far too much
information available to really dive
deep into encounter design but the items
laid out so far should give you a few
things to consider
so that your encounters feel alive and
cinematic
again those items are the rule of six
space out the enemies so there are at
least
six squares between groups or major
individuals
use a large area the encounter space
should be at least two squares wide and
two squares tall per pc
use cover don't make your map a big
open empty space fill it with obstacles
and
items that ranged combatants and sneaky
rogues can use for cover
also use concealment provide some form
of visual concealment whether it's fog
dim light or something else difficult
terrain
use patches of difficult terrain to
provide some texture to the battlefield
multiple doorways make sure there are at
least
two points of entry and exit to the
encounter to prevent the players from
bottlenecking the
one doorway the goal is to get them to
move
about the map not dig their feet in and
stand still the whole time
provide some hazards use traps and other
hazards to provide challenges to be
defeated
other than the monsters always provide
ways that players can overcome these
challenges
skills provide ways that skillful
players can aid their allies or hinder
their foes
and last think in terms of phases
instead of having all the enemies on the
map at the start of the fight
consider having them enter in phases or
even change the environment itself with
each
phase as well again most of these
suggestions come from the order 66
podcast
i will leave a link to their website in
the description and make sure you come
back for part two of the series
where we will get into topics such as
encounter budgets and making sure you
balance the encounters appropriately for
your player characters
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the house played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content
and getting to vote on the topics i
cover if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming