this video is brought to you by three
rings adventure
an official piezo actual play podcast of
the extinction curse adventure path
listen to three rings adventure today at
rollforcombat.com
hello and welcome to pathfinder
encounters part 2
building encounters by howitz plate in
the previous video we discussed how to
design
combat encounters so that they're
engaging for your players and in this
video we'll cover the mechanics of
managing an encounter budget
once you've decided on a basic theme for
your encounter and is placed in the
overall story
the next step is to decide on a threat
level encounters and pathfinder are
categorized by how much
danger they are expected to pose to a
typical four-player party
trivial threat encounters should pose
new threat to the players
and are used mostly as warm-ups at the
start of adventures
or as opportunities for the players to
revel in how much power they've obtained
do not ignore trivial threatened
counters just because they're easy they
definitely have their place in the story
too
low threatened counters are not expected
to be difficult
the players are expected to win but may
need to spend a few of their resources
like spell slots and potions in order to
do so
moderate threat encounters are expected
to seriously challenge but not overwhelm
most parties
players are expected to use both good
tactics and resource management to
overcome these encounters
severe threat encounters are the most
challenging combat encounters that
players are expected to defeat
these will require sound tactics and a
significant amount of resources to
overcome
and a little bit of bad luck could
swiftly turn the tables against the
players
severe threat encounters are typically
reserved for boss fights and
other significant moments in the story
and the highest threat level is
extreme threat these threats are
intended to be
a true challenge for fully healed and
arrested parties
and are intended for moments where the
players can go all out
using all their available resources
without need to save anything for later
as such extreme threatened counters
should be structured
so that they are the only combat
encounters the players will face that
day
to help you determine what a good spread
for encounter threat might look like
i reviewed three set pieces from a
published adventure path
one at fifth level one at tenth level
and another at fifteenth level
and i discovered that all three of these
set pieces
had six combat encounters one low threat
four moderate threats and one severe
threat for the dungeons boss
conveniently these six encounters also
equal 500 experience points
or half an experience level for players
so two of these locations would level up
a standard four player party
listen that once you take into account
accomplishment xp
once you set a threat level for the
encounter compare that
to table 10-1 on page 489 to set your
encounter budget
the encounter budget is the total amount
of xp awarded for each creature included
in the encounter
so for example moderate threat
encounters have a budget of 80 xp
meaning the battle could consist of one
enemy that's worth 80 experience points
two monsters that are each 40 experience
points four monsters that are
20 experience points each and so on
ideally the total of all the enemies and
hazards included
should not exceed the budget but going
just a little over or under
should be alright in most cases these
budgets assume there are 4
players in the party but you can easily
adjust them if you have more or fewer
people at the table
all you need to do in those cases is
refer to the character adjustment column
and add that amount to the budget for
every pc over 4
or subtract that amount if you have
fewer than 4 players
but note that increasing or decreasing
the budget due to the number of players
does not affect the amount of experience
points that's awarded for defeating the
encounter
so for example a moderate threatened
counter for 6 players would have a
budget of 120
xp but would still only award 80 xp
to each of those players for defeating
the encounter
next you need to calculate the game's
party level which is easy if all the
players are the same level
but if you have some pcs who are higher
or lower than the others in the group
then it's a little more complicated if
everyone playing is the same character
level
then that is also their party level
that's what i do and i
recommend others do as well because it
just makes life easy
but the rules do provide some guidance
if you want to have a party made of
different level pcs
this is not an exact science and is
largely up to the gm to make judgment
calls
as to what is an appropriate party level
if not everybody is the same level
first if only one or two players are
slightly behind the rest
then set the party level as equal to the
highest level players
for example say you have three 5th level
players
and one or two fourth level players in
that case
you would set the party level as fifth
and if only one or two players are
slightly higher than the rest
then set the party level as the lowest
pc's level
but add one extra player's worth of xp
to the budget for every two character
levels over the party level
so say for example you have three third
level players
and one fifth level player in that case
the party level would be
third but you would add one extra
player's worth of xp to the budget
if you were designing a moderate
threatened counter for this group
it would have a budget of 100 xp 80 as a
base
plus 20 more because one of the players
is two levels higher than the party
level
and if this party was made up of three
third level players
and two fifth level players then a
moderate threat budget would be 140 xp
80 as the base plus 20 for having 5 pcs
instead of 4
plus another 40 xp because there are
4 extra player levels and last if the
player levels are all over the place
the best guidance from the book is to
calculate the average of all
of their levels and use that as the
party level
whether you round up or down is entirely
up to the gm to decide
ideally you want there to be no more
than two levels of difference between
the party's highest level character and
its lowest
also note that any character that is a
lower level than the party level
will receive double the usual experience
points
for defeating the encounter and there is
no reward adjustment for those who are a
higher level than the party level
now that you have a budget set it's time
to start spending that xp by selecting
creatures for the players to battle
unlike with many other rpgs pathfinder
does not use
static xp for its creatures instead each
creature's xp value
is set relative to the party level as
per table 10 2
on page 489 if the creature's level is
the same as the party level
then it costs 40 points from the
encounter's xp budget
if the creature's level is one lower
than the party level then it costs
30 points and so on note that the table
only spans
four levels lower than and four levels
higher than the party level and the
system is not designed to accommodate
enemies
outside of this scope including hazards
like
traps in the encounter works the same
way except there is a different xp cost
depending on if it is a
simple or complex hazard refer to table
1014 on page 521
for example if a traps level is one
higher than the party level
then it costs 12 points from the budget
if it's a simple hazard
or 60 points from the budget if it's
complex
if you're not sure whether a hazard is
simple or complex
just check its traits complex hazards
will have
the complex trait and see my video on
hazards for
more information i'll make sure to
include a link to it in the description
also as you begin selecting creatures
consider how many you want to use
the standard guideline is to try to have
as many enemies as there are players or
close to that and even in boston
counters you might want to consider
lowering the boss by a level or two to
pay for a couple of lieutenants or
minions the game mastery guide provides
these
as sample encounter groups assuming the
party is made
of four pcs if facing a boss in their
lackeys
that would be a severe threatened
counter for 120 xp
and include one enemy that's two levels
higher than the party level
and four enemies that are four levels
lower than the party level facing a
troop of enemies
which is not to be confused with the new
troops that are presented in bestiary 3
this would be a moderate threatened
counter worth 80 xp
and would include one enemy the same
level as the party
and two more enemies that are each two
levels lower than the party
and so on there are far far more
possible combinations
but this page from the game mastery
guide just gives you a
simple template for putting encounters
together quickly
and a few other things to consider are
that the rules for building counters
are only based on party level creature
level
and threat level but there are some
things that might
impact the difficulty of a fight beyond
these three items
for example difficult terrain there's no
rule that says that difficult terrain
costs
20 points of the budget and greater
difficult terrain costs
40 points or whatever instead you as a
gm will need to make a judgment call to
determine if your
use of difficult terrain in the
encounter is severe
enough that it should be treated as
another creature in the encounter budget
the game mastery guide suggests that if
the difficult terrain is significant but
not equal to
another enemy then you might want to not
adjust the encounter
budget but slightly increase the xp
reward for defeating the encounter
instead
likewise anything else that might impact
the difficulty of the encounter
should be considered as well if you're
building the encounter to include
different phases then you'll want to
consider that when setting the budget
if not all of the enemies are present at
the start of the encounter
then you might increase the budget
slightly and if there is
an increased likelihood that two or more
encounters might get
pulled together for example if they're
in adjacent rooms
and might be alerted by the sound of
combat then you might want to
decrease the budget for each of those
encounters to reduce the odds of the
players becoming overwhelmed
you might also want to decrease the
budget if the fight isn't entirely
fair for example if all the enemies are
positioned in hard-to-reach locations
using arranged weapons from behind cover
this is not an exact science and there
are no hard rules for how much xp
should be deducted from the budget for
situations like these
you'll just have to use your best
judgment and be prepared to improvise if
things do not go as planned
so those are the basic mechanics for
building an
encounter i will also be publishing a
step-by-step example video
showing how to build a normal encounter
and part three of this series
will discuss how to manage rewards
following the encounter
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the house played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive
content and getting to vote on the
topics i cover if you would like to
support this channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming