this video is brought to you by roll for
combat an official piezo actual play
podcast
join atron hap alhara riley darius and
the entire
circus of wayward wonders as they save
the starstone isles from the dreaded
extinction curse
listen now to three ring adventure at
roll4combat.com
hello and welcome to how it's played
presents encounters part three
treasure in previous parts of this
series we discussed how to design
encounters
and how to build them mechanically and
in this part we're going to dive into
the rewards players might receive
after their encounters
treasure represents all of the material
rewards players earn during their
adventures
loot taken from fallen foes a dragon's
hoard of gold
and compensation received from quest
givers are all common types of treasure
the first step in determining what
treasure to give your players is to
check
table 10 9 on page 509 party treasure by
level this table shows how much treasure
should be awarded to a group
of four pcs over the course of an entire
experience level
the total value column shows you the
total value of all treasure to be given
over that level of experience
for example if your players just reached
sixth level
then you should provide them a total of
two thousand gold with a treasure
between now and when they reach seventh
level
and that is two thousand gold for the
entire party of four
not per player you can divide that 2000
gold anyway you want
but the next three columns in the table
provide a standard recommendation
the permanent items column suggests the
number of permanent magic items to award
the party
again for a six level party you would
award two
seventh level magic items and two six
level magic items
note that for first level parties
instead of magic items you might want to
award non-magical items worth 10 to 20
gold
for example maybe one of your players is
a fighter who wants a suit of half-plate
armor
but couldn't afford it when they rolled
their character in addition to those
permanent items
you would also award a number of
consumables these are any item with a
consumable trait like potions or scrolls
here we see that during their journey
from level six to level seven
this party would receive two seventh
level consumables
two six level consumables and two
fifth level consumables and then in the
party currency column
we see how much money the players should
receive this is
in addition to the magic items already
mentioned
so again with our sixth level party they
would receive 500 gold in currency
this could be received in gold or given
out in some form of asset like
gems or works of art maybe this party is
offered
75 gold pieces each for the quest and
that counts for 300 gold
and then during the quest they find an
assortment of gems worth 125 gold
a circlet worth 20 gold and a fine
tapestry detailing the history of the
kingdom that's worth 55 gold to the
right person
the key with currency is to try not to
use it to purchase more gear
and remember gear sells for fifty
percent of its value
whereas gyms are in other assets sell
for a hundred percent
so basically everything listed in these
columns
roughly adds up to the total in this
column
so you can choose to use either their
recommended distribution
or take the lump sum and divvy it up
however you wish
as previously mentioned the table is
intended for parties of four players
but is fairly easy to adjust things for
more or fewer people
for each additional pc over four you
would add
one permanent magic item that is of a
level no higher than one greater than
the party level
two consumable items one that is the
party level in one that is a level
higher than the party level
and increase the amount of party
currency by the amount
shown in the currency per additional pc
column of the
table so for example if our six level
party had five players
the players would receive five permanent
magic items
two that are seventh level two that are
six level
and one that may be either sixth or
seventh level
they would also receive eight consumable
items
three seventh level three six level and
two
fifth level and we would also add 125
gold to the party currency
making it 625 gold worth of money
gems are in other assets when you have
fewer than four players
you can subtract the same amount for
each missing character
but the book does advise proceeding with
caution
if there are fewer than four players
they may need more
and better gear to handle encounters
since they may not have the variety of
skill sets between the two or three of
them to handle
most challenges so letting them have
more treasure might help to offset that
that's the basic process for determining
encounter rewards but this can be as
much
an art as it is science and there are a
few remaining things you want to keep in
mind
first remember that any items gained
from monsters and other enemies
should be taken from the party's total
allotment and not be added to that
amount of permanent magic items
for example the stat block for a grave
knight says that it wears a suit of plus
one resilient full plate armor
this is a level 8 item so if your
players were 8th level
and budgeted to receive 2 8th level
permanent magic items per the party
treasure table
then this grave knight's armor would
count as one of those two
items and not be awarded in addition to
the two items from the table also while
i'm on the topic of monsters the sign
bars in the bestiary often include
advice for what treasure fits the theme
of the monster
for example in the section on angels it
includes a
sidebar about angelic treasure that says
they often wear objects of exquisite
beauty
including fine clothing and jewelry this
could be a signal that this would be a
great place to include some of that
party currency budget
in gems jewelry and other works of art
remember just about anything can be
handed out as treasure
if you have a crafter in the party then
provide some formulas
if you have spell casters include a
spell book that they can learn new
spells from
remember any spell or item with a rarity
other than common
should not be readily available for
purchase the best way for spellcasting
characters to gain new uncommon and rare
spells is by receiving them
as treasure and trying to tie the item
or spell into the encounter
if the players defeat a powerful druid
maybe they find a journal detailing an
uncommon primal spell
if they defeat a necromancer maybe their
spell book has
a rare necromancy spell the players
otherwise would never have access to
another point to keep in mind is to be
intentional about when and how you award
treasure
if you are planning to award a magic
weapon you might consider awarding it
earlier
so that they have it with them for the
final boss fight
likewise with healing potions if you
expect players will need them
award them early if you fear they may go
through them too quickly
maybe you'll want to hold them until
later and include
some way for the players to be able to
sell any items they don't want
and purchase ones that they do remember
magic items and similar gear
sell for 50 percent of their listed
price and gyms
art objects and other assets sell for
their full value
the easiest way to do this is in a city
where there are shops that specialize in
magic
but if your game takes place far away
from civilization
you might need to get creative and
speaking of selling items
if you wish you can include magic items
that are
lower level than those suggested in the
table if you do so
count them as only half their price
against the party currency column of the
table
and assume the item will be sold instead
of kept long-term
last be aware that no matter how well
you plan
things will not work out perfectly the
players may decide to not explore a room
that you had treasure in
or fail a perception check to find the
hidden compartment in a desk that holds
a magic item
or just not want to use the items that
you award them
so you'll want to stay on top of what
items they have and adjust accordingly
if they miss treasure in one room and
some to another
and you might want to consider
periodically auditing their sheets
to ensure they're each carrying an
appropriate amount of magic items
if they're not then you may want to add
one or two magic items to bring them
up the pathfinder second edition system
assumes the characters are properly
geared for the encounters
so if a player is under geared you'll
want to correct that
quickly before we close i'd like to take
a moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the house played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release
and i can always be reached through
twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming