hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of afflictions in
Pathfinder 2nd edition
an affliction is any condition that
infects a character over a period of
time and progresses through stages the
most common examples of afflictions are
curses diseases and poisons all
afflictions start with a saving throw
which is usually fortitude but could
also be will especially in the case of
curses when you are first exposed to an
affliction you attempt the listed save
if you succeed then the affliction has
no effect but if you feel it then you
become infected or a poisoned or cursed
some but not all afflictions have an
onset period this is basically a delay
if an affliction lists an onset period
of one hour then if you fail the initial
savings through nothing else happens
into an hour passes think of it as an
incubation period like when you get the
flu you don't start feeling the effects
of catching the flu for about two days
so the flu has an onset period of 48
hours but mechanically all you need to
know about onset periods is nothing
happens for this amount of time you
don't suffer any negative effects during
this period nor do you roll anymore same
as throughs in fact you may not even
know you've been infected with an
affliction but that's entirely up to
your GM to decide and if there is no on
set period listed then the affliction
takes effect immediately is essentially
an onset period of zero seconds next
let's talk about stages afflictions are
divided up into a number of distinct
stages usually three each stage has an
effect listed followed by an amount of
time shown in parentheses so when you
fail the initial seems through you then
wait through the duration of the onset
period and once that passes you gain
stage one of the affliction you
immediately suffer the effects of that
stage and then treat the amount of time
in parentheses sort of as if it's
another onset period so if the
affliction says Stage one
1.d4 poison damage in sickened one and
in parentheses one minute then as soon
as you gain stage one you suffer one D
for poison damage you gain the sickened
one condition and then nothing else
related to the affliction happens for
another minute you do not suffer a one D
for poison damage every round during
this minute nor do you continue rolling
saving throws during this time the
period shown in parentheses is again
sort of like the onset nothing happens
during this time but once that time is
up then you have to roll a new saving
throw if you succeed then you lose your
current stage and you gain one stage
lower if you fail then you lose the
current stage and gain one stage higher
so if your stage one and fail then you
become stage two when that happens you
suffer the listed effects of stage two
now that's what happens when you fail
the save but if you succeed then you
lose your current stage and gain one
stage lower and if you ever gain stage
zero then you're cured and the
affliction has no further effects also
is worth mentioning that critical
successes and critical failures count
double when you critically succeed a
savings throw you lose your current
stage and gain the stage that is to
lower and when you critically fail as
savings through you lose the current
stage and gain the stage that is to
higher but note that you never go to a
stage higher than that afflictions
listed maximum if stage three is the
highest the affliction lists then
failing are critically failing a savings
throw while at stage three means you
lose stage three and then you gain stage
three again you repeat its effects but
you wouldn't create a theoretical Stage
four
in the final key stat that we should
talk about is maximum duration as you
might suspect from the name this is the
longest period of time you can be
infected by an affliction an important
note here is that the maximum duration
does not include the time spent during
the onset period it only covers the
amount of time that you're actually
suffering from the affliction so if an
affliction has an onset period of 30
minutes and a maximum duration of two
hours then two and a half hours after
you fail your initial savings through
the affliction automatically wears off
and ends okay with the basic terminology
out of the way let's see how this works
with an example here we have the stats
for belladonna the block is divided into
two halves the top half is familiar
territory so we're not going to spend
too much time there but it is worth
noting that in the traits we see poison
and that's important to know because it
informs us of what type of affliction
this is then down in the bottom half of
the stat block we find the information
that's most relevant to this
conversation here we see all the stages
and effects of belladonna so let's
tackle this bit by bit first we have
some flavor text nothing too surprising
here for belladonna but always make sure
you read this because sometimes they do
put mechanical information in the flavor
text area too then they list the savings
Thoreau as DC 1942 so when a player is
first exposed to belladonna
they must make a fortitude saving throw
and this could be a road in secret by
the GM especially if the player doesn't
know that they've been poisoned if the
total of that savings throw is 19 or
higher then you don't suffer any effects
of the poison but if you roll lower than
a 19 then you are poisoned by the
belladonna when that happens we look at
the onset period belladonna has an onset
period of ten minutes so nothing happens
for ten more minutes
after you fail that initial savings
through
for example you do not really fortitude
save every round for these 10 minutes is
just business as usual during the onset
period if no onset period is listed for
the affliction then the effects are
immediately dealt after a failed savings
through next we see the maximum duration
for belladonna this is 30 minutes now
keep in mind this does not include the
onset period so it's 30 minutes after
you begin suffering from this affliction
that it wears off or a total of 40
minutes after you fail the initial semi
through when the initial savings through
has failed and the onset period has
passed you then gain stage 1 and suffer
the effects of that stage immediately at
this time you become dazzled and stay
dazzled for 10 minutes nothing else
happens during this time but after 10
minutes have passed
you must attempt another DC 1942 saving
through if you succeed then the
affliction is reduced from stage 1 to
essentially stage 0 and you're cured if
you fail to save though then you lose
stage 1 and you gain stage 2 as before
with stage 1 you immediately suffer the
effects of the new stage in this case
you suffer 1d6 poison damage and becomes
sick and 1 stage 2 also has a
parenthetical of 10 minutes so nothing
else happens until that passes at which
time you must attempt another DC 1942
saving through if you succeed then you
lose stage 2 and gain stage 1
if you fail the save then you lose stage
two and gain stage three at that time
you take 1 d6 poison damage become
confused and keep the sick into one
condition because that is shared in both
stage 2 and stage 3 the parenthetical on
stage 3 is only one minute and at that
time you would be required to roll
another fortitude saving through also
note that this affliction ends as stage
3 there are new stages higher than that
so if your stage 3 and fail or
critically fail your fortitude save you
suffer stage 3s effects again and do not
theoretically move to a stage 4 or 5
this is important when tracking how many
successes you need in order to cure
yourself from this affliction
there are a few other circumstances that
we should discuss
for instance what happens when you are
exposed to an affliction while you're
already suffering from that same
affliction this is one of the rare times
where it's important to know what kind
of affliction you're dealing with if
it's a curse or a disease then multiple
exposures of it have no effect at all
but if it's poison then multiple
exposures require a new saving throw per
exposure and if you fail you lose your
current stage and gain one higher or on
a critical fail you lose the current
stage and gain the stage that is to
higher this also counts during the onset
period if you get shot with a poison
arrow and fail its initial savings
through and then get shot by another
poison arrow during the onset period and
you fail that savings through then the
onset period continues as normal at the
end of which you gain stage 2 instead of
stage 1 suffering the same affliction
while in the middle of the onset period
does not reset that onset period nor
does it automatically end the onset
period instead the onset period
continues as normal which will be one
stage higher when it ends
we should also talk about the conditions
you received from afflictions for
example The Belladonna we looked at
earlier imposes the sick in the
condition on his victims if we look at
the description for sickened we see that
you can spend one action to roll if for
to save to wretch and remove the
sickened condition was important to note
here is that this action removes the
sickened condition it does not remove
the belladonna affliction so if you are
suffering stage two of belladonna and
retch to remove the sickened condition
ten minutes later you would still need
to roll another saving throw and if you
fail you lose stage two and gain stage
three which includes 1d6 poison damage
the confused condition and becoming
sickened one again and the vice-versa of
this is also true curing and affliction
does not necessarily also cure the
conditions that that affliction caused
if you suffer a condition from an
affliction and that condition has a
longer duration than the maximum
duration of the affliction that caused
it then the condition persists even
after that affliction has gone away
for example the drained condition
requires nights of rests in order to
recover from it so if an affliction that
has a five-minute maximum duration
causes you to suffer the drained
condition then you will still be drained
after five minutes has passed and that
affliction has ended
in the last special circumstance that we
should discuss here is virulent
afflictions these are especially nasty
afflictions that operate the same way as
normal afflictions except they require
two consecutive successes to remove the
current stage and gain one stage lower
or one critical success to lose the
and again these must be consecutive
successes you have to get two successes
in a row to move one stage lower
a mix let's look at an example that
ruined many an adventurous day during
the Pathfinder second edition play test
and that is giant centipede poison
although the stat block for afflictions
is very concise and it saves a lot of
space on the page the first thing I like
to do is sort of visualize it in my head
like it is a progression save on set
stage effect delay stage delay repeat
for this example we'll say
Ezrin has been stabbed with a dagger
covered with giant centipede venom when
he is first exposed to it he must make a
DC 17 fortitude safe if he succeeds then
the process ends here with no further
effects but if he fails his initial save
then nothing happens until after the
onset period passes there is no onset
listed for centipede venom so he
immediately gains stage 1 when he gains
stage 1 he suffers 1 d6 poison damage
nothing else happens until after the
listed delay which is one round
if the listed delay was 30 minutes then
nothing else would happen until half an
hour passed but on the next round when
the listed delay has passed he must make
another DC 1742 saving through let's say
he critically fails this one in that
case he loses stage 1 and gains the
stage that is to higher so he gains
stage 3 here he immediately takes 1 d12
poison damage and suffers the clumsy one
and flat-footed conditions note that he
does not suffer any of the effects of
stage 2 because he effectively skipped
over that stage
nothing happens over the delay period of
one round but then he must make another
sing through he fails it which usually
means that she lose the current stage
and gain one stage higher but he's
already at stage three which is the
maximum for centipede venom so instead
he repeats stage 3 again and suffers
another one d12 poison damage the clumsy
one condition and flat-footed
nothing happens for the Knicks delay
period but when that's up he has to roll
another sim through this time he
succeeds so he loses his current stage
which has stage three and gains one
stage lower which is stage two he
immediately suffers one d8 poison damage
and is flat-footed again nothing happens
during the delay and on the next round
he rolls another fortitude safe this
time he critically succeeds
which means he loses the current stage
and gains two stages lure which brings
him effectively to stage zero when a
character gains stage zero they're cured
and the affliction no longer has any
effect on them unless they are exposed
to it again note that the critical
success took him from stage 2 to stage 0
he does not suffer any of the effects of
stage 1 as he has simply skipped over it
thanks to the critical success
now Azrin is cured of the poison but had
he not been able to shake it off it
would automatically end after six rounds
since that's the maximum duration for
giant centipede venom
in this video we discussed afflictions
afflictions are debilitating effects
that function over time and progress in
stages curses diseases and poisons are
all examples of afflictions when first
exposed to an affliction a character
must make a saving through if they
succeed they are not affected by the
affliction but if they fail they gain
stage 1 after the onset period has
passed onset is a length of time after
failing the initial save that must pass
before any effects are dealt to the
character
nothing happens during this time no
savings throws are rolled and the
character suffers no effects of the
affliction yet afflictions are divided
into multiple stages each stage has an
effect in an amount of time listed in
parentheses when you gain a stage you
immediately suffer that stages effects
then nothing else happens until the time
in parentheses has passed at which point
you must make another saving through if
successful you lose the current stage
and gain the stage that is when lower if
you fail you lose the current stage and
gain the stage that is one higher
critical successes in critical failures
caused you to lose or gain two stages
when you gain stage 0 you're cured when
the maximum duration passes not
including the onset period the
affliction wears off
when you are exposed to an affliction
that you are already suffering from
nothing happens if it is a curse or a
disease but if it is a poison then you
lose the current stage and gain one
stage higher if you cure a condition
that is caused by an affliction it does
not cure the affliction and if you gain
a stage that inflicts that condition
then you gain that same condition again
and the opposite of that is also true
when you cure an affliction you do not
necessarily also cure the conditions
that it caused when a condition caused
by an affliction has a longer duration
then the affliction that caused it it
persists even after the maximum duration
of that affliction has passed and
virulent afflictions are especially
difficult to shake off and require two
consecutive successes or one critical
success in order to gain one stage lower
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature in
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games