hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of hazards in
Pathfinder second edition before we
begin is worth mentioning that this
video builds upon information that is
delivered in a few of our other videos
notably our video on the thievery skill
that explains how this able device is
used to disarm traps and the videos on
perception and stealth discuss what it
takes to notice something which is
important when trying to detect a trap
so you are encouraged to go watch those
videos if you haven't already done so
links to them may be found in the
description
hazards are a group of dangers that
players may face during their adventures
other than creatures and they tend to
fall into one of three broad categories
environmental hazards hauntings and
traps environmental hazards are
typically products of nature such as a
hurricane or a patch of quicksand Hantz
are a cult hazards that one might expect
to find in a haunted house or a haunted
graveyard and tramps are probably what
most people think of when it comes to
Pathfinder hazards a giant stone rolling
down the hallway or even a magical trap
like a set of exploding rooms hazards
are further divided into two types
simple hazards and complex hazards a
simple hazard is like a landmine it
fires once and then it's done but
complex hazards persist past their first
activation and continue to run every
turn according to a set routine
every hazard has some manner of trigger
condition for an environmental hazard
like a tornado the trigger might simply
be in close proximity to the tornado and
often these triggers are intentionally
hidden like with most traps so it's
important to know how a player goes
about noticing if there is a hazard in
their area characters should have an
opportunity to spot a hazard before it
is triggered the difficulty for this
check is listed as the hazard stealth DC
and sometimes will require a minimum
proficiency rank in perception in order
to be detected if there is no minimum
proficiency listed then the GM should
roll a perception check for each
character and compare it to the hazard
stealth DC as long as there is no
minimum proficiency listed then these
checks are made for free and do not
require the character to take the seek
action first however if the hazard does
have a minimum proficiency listed with
its stealth DC then two things are going
to happen first no perception checks are
made for free if there is a minimum
proficiency listed then characters must
take the seek action in order to spot
the hazard in second these attempts
automatically fail if the seeking
character does not meet the minimum
proficiency rate in perception no matter
how high their chick roll might be for
example if a hazard stat block says
stealth DC 20 for expert then anyone who
is untrained or trained in perception
automatically fails there seek action
and doesn't spot the hazard also this is
one of those times where a GM might want
to make these checks in secret and since
checks are automatically enrolled for
hazards that do not have a required
perception proficiency you might even
fake roll these at random times when
players enter a room or a hallway just
to keep them on their toes and a quick
note about magical hazards if the hazard
is magical and does not have a minimum
listed perception proficient
then his presence can be detected by
using the detect magic spell but this
only reveals the presence of magic in
the area and nothing else
and again the tech magic only works if
the hazard does not require a minimum
perception rank to spot if it requires
DC 34 trained the detect magic is not
going to work on it at all it doesn't
matter if your perception rank is higher
than trained or your spell casting
proficiency is higher none of that
matters if there is any rank listed next
to the stealth DC then it is impossible
to spot with the detect magic spell each
hazard step block shows what needs to
occur for it to be triggered if the
condition is to enter an area or step on
something in a character's path then it
is assumed that the character does so
when they move through that space but if
the trigger calls for something to be
manipulated like opening a door or
pulling a lever then the trigger only
occurs if the character specifically
performs that action also triggers are
either going to be listed as reactions
or as free actions the key distinction
here is that hazards like most
characters only have one reaction per
turn so if the hazards trigger is a
reaction like a trapdoor opening to
reveal a pit then is only going to fire
once no matter how many times players
might perform the triggering action now
compare this to something like quicksand
the trigger for quicksand is a free
action which means it can occur over and
over again in this case each player who
steps into the zone of the quicksand
triggers it mechanically this is only
possible because the trigger is a free
action
when a simple hazard is triggered it
performs the listed effect and then is
rendered disabled unless someone resets
it but when a complex hazard is
triggered it persists and runs a
predetermined routine usually when this
happens the GM is asked to roll
initiative for the hazard if the players
were not already in encounter mode then
they roll initiative - and the encounter
begins if the players were already in
initiative order then the GM rolls
initiative for the hazard and then slots
it into initiative as appropriate and
note that unless the hazard step block
says otherwise it's the hazard stealth
bonus that is rolled for his initiative
score but once this happens then the
hazard acts on his turn just like a
monster except the GM does not directly
control the hazard instead the hazard
follows is predetermined routine
since the most common hazard you will
face our mechanical traps the disable
device application of the thievery skill
is often the best way to manage a hazard
however there will be times when a good
set of thieves tools won't help you like
when dealing with the aforementioned
quicksand a druid or a ranger who is
trained in nature or survival may be
better equipped to deal with that and in
the same way a cleric who is skilled in
a cult ism or religion may be your best
bet for handling a haunted house each
hazard will list in a step block what
actions can be used to disable it this
will usually be a skill followed by a DC
and will often show a minimum
proficiency rank in parentheses next to
it so for example if a trap lists
disable thievery DC 26 expert then a
fevery check is needed to disable the
trap and if the player is not at least
expert in fevery then they automatically
fail that's simple enough
but one point that's often overlooked is
that the step block shows the skill that
is needed but not necessarily the action
in this case it shows thievery the skill
but the application of thievery that you
would use is called
disable device and as a blow device is a
two action activity therefore in order
to disable this trap is not just a
thievery skill check but the player
would need to spend two actions in
Eustis able device in order to disarm
the trap and magic traps can often be
disabled by counteracting them for the
purposes of this video I'm not going to
go too deep into counteracting but we
should definitely look at the most
common method of dealing with magical
traps which is by casting the spell
magic when dispelled magic is cast on a
magical trap the caster attempts a
counteract check the base modifier for
this check is the same as the casters of
base spell attack modifier which is
spell casting ability modifier + spell
casting proficiency bonus
however this counteract bonus may differ
from the characters final spell attack
bonus because the base bonus is only
further modified by conditions that
specifically affect counteract checks
not by conditions that modify spell
attacks the DC for the counteract check
should be included in the hazard stat
block and the last bit of information
you need to know is the hazards
counteract level this should also be
included in the stat block but if for
some reason is not you can use the
hazards level divided in half once you
cast dispel magic enroll your counter
act check you then compare that total to
the counteract DC in the hazard stat
block on a success the trap is disabled
if that traps counteract level is no
more than 1 higher than your counteract
level and in this case your counteract
level is the level of the spell slot
that is used to cast dispel magic dispel
magic is a second level spell but if you
heighten it and cast it from a fourth
level spell slot it could disarm a
magical trap with a caster level of 5 or
lower on a successful counter act check
on a critical success you disarm the
magic trap if it is no more than three
levels higher than the spell slot you
use to cast a spell magic on a failure
you still automatically disarm that
magical trap if the traps counteract
level is lower than the spell slot you
use to cast dispel magic and on a
critical failure nothing happens and
although not specifically mentioned in
the section on counteracting I think it
would be reasonable for the GM to rule
that the trap is triggered and goes off
when you critically fail a counter act
check using dispel magic just like when
you critically fail to disable device
using thievery
with all of this in mind let's look at a
few examples the first one is pretty
straightforward a common poisoned lock
the first line displays the hazards
traits in this case a poison lock has
both the mechanical and trap traits
second is the stealth DC it says DC 17
trained which tells us a couple of
things first no perception chicks are
made for free to spot this trap because
it shows a required proficiency rank if
it just said DC 17 without anything in
parentheses then the players would
receive a free proficiency check to
detect the trap but because it requires
trained proficiency and perception only
characters who use the seek action have
a chance of spotting it anyone who is
untrained in perception can use the seek
action but will automatically fail when
they do so then we have a description
that provides an explanation of the
hazard and a little bit of flavor and
then after the Lynbrook we see some of
the more combat focused stats first it
shows the requirements to disable it in
this case a character who is at least
trained in the thievery skill can
perform the disable device activity
which cost again two of their actions
and if they roll a 17 or higher on their
check the trap is disabled if they
critically fail the check then the trap
is triggered under that we have the
defense scores for the trap in case
someone tries to use brute force and
break the trap rather than disable it
this trap has an armor class of 15 and a
plus 8 bonus to fortitude saves and a +4
bonus to reflexes
the next line shows is hardness
hitpoints break threshold and immunities
I don't want to go too deep into the
weeds here but an object's hardness is
an amount of points that are subtracted
from every damage role against the
object whatever damage is left over is
subtracted from its hit points and when
the object is reduced to its break
threshold and hit points it becomes
broken a broken trap no longer functions
but can still be repaired and if the
trap is reduced to zero hit points it is
completely destroyed and cannot be
repaired in most cases a trap will
automatically be triggered the first
time it is hit unless that single attack
does enough damage to break it
continuing down the stat walk we see the
trigger conditions here it is a reaction
and an attack that is triggered when
someone tries to unlock or pick the lock
if either of those occur then the trap
is triggered and we then look at the
effect which is a spine extends to
attack the triggering creature from
there we just keep going down the stab
block and see the attack is a plus 13
melee attack that deals one piercing
damage and poison and below that are the
stats for the poison and I'm going to
stop there for now but if you would like
to learn more about how poisons work
check out our video on afflictions
with our next example let's look at a
magical trap here we have an electric
latch room trap this is very similar to
the poison lock trap but we see there
are a few more traits detailing the
magic that is involved the stealth
heading says DC 20 train so remember
that even though this is a magical trap
because it requires trained proficiency
and perception it cannot be detected by
casting detect magic only hazards with
no proficiency requirement at all may be
affected by casting detect magic and
under disable we have two options the
first requires an expert thief to use
this able device against DC 20 and the
second allows a spell caster to use a
spell magic to counteract the traps
magic and when dispel magic is cast you
first need to know what spell slot was
used as that determines the caster's
counteract level and then the casseroles
a counteract check which is one day 20
plus their spell casting ability
modifier plus their spell casting
proficiency bonus this is basically the
same as making a spell attack role
except it can be further modified by
certain abilities and bonuses that only
affect counteract chicks and would not
be modified by anything that modifies a
spell attack role we see in the stat
block this trap has a counteract level
of second and a counteract DC of 18 so
if dispel magic is cast with a spell
slot that is third level or higher then
only a critical failure will prevent the
caster from disarming the trap if dispel
magic is cast from a second level spell
slot then the caster must roll an 18 or
higher on their counteract check in
order to disarm the trap
those were both simple traps so Knicks
we're going to look at a complex one
here are the stats for a poisoned dart
gallery this trap works very close to
how the previous ones work but there are
a few special points we need to make
note of first we see a stealth heading
is different than what we're used to
seeing by default
complex traps display a stealth bonus
instead of a stealth DC and then leaves
it to the GM to calculate the stealth DC
which is 10 plus the stealth bonus
therefore this trap can only be detected
if a character with at least expert
proficiency and perception takes the
seek action enrolls a 26 or higher
however this one is a little extra
tricky because it shows not only a
stealth bonus but also a stealth DC of
31 Master so in this case it takes a
perception check with expert proficiency
of 26 to notice that there is a trap
present in you're in danger but in order
to actually disable this trap you would
need to make a perception check with
master proficiency against DC 31
as we continue down the step block we
see the description disabled requirement
and defenses all look normal but things
become different again once we look at
the trigger condition here the trigger
is a reaction and an attack just like
with the poison lock the trigger says a
creature enters the hallway or ends its
turn in the hallway so when either of
those occur the trap triggers in the
effects occur now if you're wondering
how a creature can end its turn in the
hallway without first entering that
hallway save that thought and I promise
we will get to that before we're done
here anyway once the trap is triggered
we look at the effect the trap makes a
poison dart strike against the
triggering creature and then rolls
initiative and this is the biggest
difference between simple and complex
hazards when a simple hazard like a
poison block is triggered it is one and
done but when a complex trap like here
when it's triggered it persists when
this happens the GM rolls the trapped
stealth bonus of plus sixteen for its
initiative that the players were already
in encounter mode then the poison dart
gallery is slotted into the already
existing initiative order and if the
players were not already in encounter
mode then they need to roll initiative -
and the encounter then begins witness
the traps turn the GM looks at its
routine the first thing we see here is
that it only has one action per turn
hazards are not like creatures and are
not limited to three actions like
players are this one only has one action
per turn but other hazards might have
four actions per turn or six or more and
every turn the trap spins is action to
fire one dart against every creature in
the gallery the stats for that or below
plus 21 to attack with 3d for piercing
damage and poison it also notes that the
trap does not
suffer a multi attack penalty so all of
those attacks are made with a plus 21
bonus in addition to that we also see it
has a free action code continuous
barrage every time a character within
the gallery completes an action not
completes their turn but every time they
complete an action this hazard fires
another dart at them so if they take
three actions while inside the gallery
then this hazard attacks them three
times during their turn in addition to
the one time the hazard attacks them
during its turn and below that we see
the stats for the poison that may be
inflicted with the dorms last at the
very bottom of the stat block we see it
says reset the trap deactivates and
resets after one minute what this means
is once the trap is triggered it remains
active for one minute or ten encounter
rounds so if the characters leave the
gallery and come back to it during that
minute the trap is still active but one
minute after it is first triggered the
trap stops and resets meaning it must be
triggered again before it will operate
this is also aware of that effect
condition that says a creature that
enters the hallway or ends is turn in
the hallway triggers the trap this is
where that comes into play it is
possible for a creature to have already
entered the hall when it's minute is up
in every sense which means if they are
still inside the hall when they finish
their next turn they trigger the trap
again if the trigger condition only said
creatures that enter the hallway then
anyone who is already in the hall at the
time it resets would be immune from
triggering it again
in this video we discussed hazards
hazards are dangers in the game other
than creatures and typically fall into
one of three categories environmental
hazards like storms and earthquakes
hauntings like a haunted mansion or a
ghost ship and traps and hazards are
further divided into two types simple
hazards and complex hazards simple
hazards are triggered once and then
become inert unless they are reset again
complex hazards persist after they are
triggered they are placed in iniciative
order just like a monster and they run a
predetermined routine when it is their
turn detecting hazards functions much
the same way as spotting anything else
all hazards have a stealth DC for a
complex hazards this is usually
displayed as a stealth bonus and the GM
needs to know that the stealth DC is 10
Plus that bonus unless otherwise noted
in the stat block if the hazard does not
list a required minimum proficiency for
perception then all players receive a
free perception check when they enter
the general area of the hazard this
mostly applies to environmental hazards
a hailstorm isn't trying to hide from
anyone but if the hazard has any
requirements for perception then a
player must take the seek action and
meet the minimum perception requirements
to spot the hazard also note that if a
magical hazard does not have a minimum
perception requirement that it may be
found by casting the tech magic but that
spell only informs the caster of the
presence of magic and does not provide
any assistance in disabling the hazard
each hazard step block lists a
triggering condition that needs to be
met in order to activate the hazard
these are listed as either reactions or
free actions the important distinction
here is if the trigger is a free action
then it fires repeatedly every time the
triggering condition is met whereas if
it is a reaction then the trigger only
fires once after the trigger occurs the
GM applies the listed effects of that
trigger for complex hazards this usually
includes a rolling initiative for the
hazard which unless otherwise noted in
the stat block is is stealth bonus for
these complex hazards they will perform
the listed routine every round on their
turn and note that hazards have no limit
to the number of actions they have per
turn instead each step block should list
the number of actions the hazard
receives and how to spin them every turn
hazards also display conditions to
disable them for environmental hazards
these are usually nature or survival
checks for haunts these are occultism or
religion checks and for mechanical traps
you usually use the disable device
application of the thievery skill which
don't forget is two actions not one if
the hazard is magical you might also be
able to disable it by casting dispel
magic when you do so you roll a
counteract check comparing your
counteract level which is the level of
the spell slot used to cast dispel magic
versus the counteract level listed in
the hazard step block you then roll a
counteract check which has the same base
bonus as a spell attack role except it
is only further modified by conditions
that specifically say they modify
counteract checks and then compare that
total to the counteract DC listed in the
hazard stat block
hazards especially traps might also be
disabled through brute force in
attacking them traps are triggered the
first time they are hit by an attack
unless the attack drops it below is
break threshold or to zero hit points if
the trap does not display a break
threshold then it must be reduced to
zero hit points with the first hit to
prevent it from triggering and some
hazards display reset information as
well that details what needs to occur
for the hazard to return to his default
state and be ready to trigger again
with that we'll bring this video to a
close if you found this video helpful
please give us a like and don't forget
to click that subscribe button and the
bell so you never miss out on our future
videos leave us a comment letting us
know what topics you'd like to see
covered in our future videos and we can
always be reached through our Twitter
and Facebook pages too if you'd like to
use some of the maps that we feature in
our videos and your own games you can
find them at maps of mastery a link to
that store can be found in the
description thanks for watching take
care and we'll see you soon with more
basics for your favorite tabletop games