hello and welcome to monster abilities
and Pathfinder second edition part one
by how it's played over the course of
this new series we're going to discuss
the most common monster actions in the
game we're going to start with grab and
related abilities like constrict in this
video and we'll be covering engulf
ferocity frightful presence knockdown
push Ren swallow haul and trample in
following
segments one of the more controversial
editing decisions in Pathfinder second
edition
was moving common abilities shared by
many monsters to the back of the books
this means that step blocks sometimes
feel incomplete and require you to go
hunt for an explanation of what the
ability means this glossery which is
included in both of the bestiaries
provides the general rules for each of
the abilities that are shared by several
monsters when reviewing these keep in
mind that what you see in the glossery
provides a foundation and each specific
monster can modify these rules further
so whenever there is a discrepancy
between a monster stat block and the
ability as it is shown in the glossery
follow the instructions provided by the
monster stat block this can be a bit of
a pain but if you have access to the
internet when gaming you can go to pf2
doy to.es and search for the monster
here and then if you Mouse over the name
of these common monster abilities and
click it will expand to provide you the
full text explanation of those abilities
which is a very nice feature that saves
me from having to flip through the books
during a
session the first Monster ability I want
to cover is grab in order to use grab
the monster must first score a hit with
an attack that includes the word grab in
its damage entry for example a giant
octopus can make a melee arm attack that
deals 2 d8 plus 9 buing damage plus grab
this can be a little misleading because
what it sounds like is when the octopus
hits it deals the damage plus
automatically grabs the target Target as
well and that's not exactly right the
term plus grab doesn't mean it
automatically grabs it means it has the
option of grabbing but must spend one
more action in order to do so so two
actions total one to strike and gain the
option of spending another action to
grab if they do so they apply the
grabbed condition to the Target one
quick note this pertains to the regular
grab ability if the monster has improved
grab then they automatically grab the
Target on a successful hit and do not
need to spend a second action to do so
the grab condition is explained on page
620 of the core rules a grabbed creature
is flat-footed and immobilized meaning
when you're grabbed you suffer a -2
circumstance penalty to Armor class and
cannot take any actions that have the
move trait furthermore if you attempt
any action that has the manipulate trait
while you're grabbed you must pass a dc5
flat check or the action is lost this
would include actions like casting
spells that have anything other than
just a verbal component and most other
activities that require motion or the
use of your hands if the check fails
then you lose any actions or other
resources that were dedicated to the
action such as spell slots so with
grabbed you cannot move and taking any
other actions are more difficult but not
impossible this should not be confused
with restrained which means you can't
even attempt any actions with the attack
and manipulate trait unless there
attempts to escape the grab lasts until
the end of the monster's next turn but
using the grab action extends the
duration of grabbed for all creatures
that are grabbed by the monster one use
of the grab action extends the duration
of all grabbed creatures not one action
per grabbed creature so say this octopus
already has two people grabbed at the
start of its turn it uses its first
action to make a melee arm attack
against a third player in hits it
applies his damage and has the option of
spending its second action to grab the
player it just hit the octopus does so
and in doing so not only grabs the third
player but also extends the duration of
the grab condition it already had
applied to the other two players that
were grabbed at the start of its turn
note that this duration was extended by
the octopus spending its second action
to grab the third player extending the
duration is automatically applied when
grabbing the next
Target and note that improved grab
allows a monster to automatically grab a
creature it hits with a melee attack but
this does not also automatically extend
the duration of the grabbed condition
the monster would still need to spend
another action to do so fortunately
there are a few ways to get out of being
grabbed the first as already mentioned
is the duration the grabbed condition
lasts until the end of the grabbing
creature's next turn unless they use the
grab action again on that turn and
extend the duration another way to break
free from a grab might be if you're
pushed by an external Force the legality
of this is a little debatable by raw so
you might want to consider this a house
rule but under the immobilized condition
which is applied when grabbed it says if
an external force would move you out of
your space then that Force must succeed
at a check against the DC of the effect
holding you in place or the relevant
defense which is usually fortitude DC
how this all plays out is completely up
to the GM to interpret and make a ruling
on let's say you're grabbed and another
player throws you a rope and tries to
pull you free the GM could rule that
this would call for their athletic skill
versus the grabbing creatures Athletics
DC
but they might instead consider this as
an application of the aid activity and
just use the rope as justification to
Grant a circumstance bonus to the
grabbed player's next Escape check is
entirely up to the GM to decide how
these attempts work but the rules do
suggest the possible option of having an
external Force free the grabbed
character as long as it beats the
Athletics DC or fortitude DC of the
grabbing monster as appropriate the
grabed condition is also removed if the
grabbing creature moves away in note
that by a raw when a large or huge sized
monster with reach attacks grabs a
character they do not pull their victim
towards them and into an adjacent space
nor are characters knocked prone when
they're released by a large grabbing
creature again raw does not apply hard
rules to these situations but instead
leaves it up to each GM to review the
situation and determine for themselves
if any of these situations are purpose
and how to apply them and of course
there is one more way to get out of the
grab condition and that is by using the
Escape
Action attempting to escape costs one
action and allows you to roll your
choice of either acrobatics Athletics or
an unarmed attack against the DC of the
effect that's grabbing you for Monsters
this DC will either be 10 plus their
athletic skill modifier or will be a DC
spelled out in their stat block
this giant octopus has an Athletics
modifier of plus 20 making their
Athletics DC 30 therefore it would take
a dc30 acrobatics Athletics or unarmed
attack check in order to escape on a
success the grabbed effect immediately
ends with a critical success you break
free and also get to stride 5T on a
failure nothing happens and on a
critical failure nothing happens and you
cannot try to escape again until your
next turn and two more things to note
about Escape actions Escape has the
attack trait so each attempt to escape
does contribute to the multiple attack
penalty for that round even if you
choose to use acrobatics or Athletics it
still counts as an attack and also be
aware that each escape attempt is versus
one specific grab effect so if you're
grabbed by two or more opponents you
will need to make multiple Escape checks
to fully break
free under normal circumstances a
monster cannot use a limb to both grab
and attack once it's grabbing someone
that limb is dedicated to keeping that
Target held but some creatures can use
constrict to squeeze and damage their
grabbed prey for example giant scorpions
have an entry that says constrict one
action for 1d6 Plus for bludgeoning dc20
at first glance this might appear
incomplete but if we flip to the back of
the bestiary we see the Monster ability
entry for constrict says the monster
deals the listed amount of damage to any
number of creatures gred or restrained
by it each of those creatures can
attempt a basic fortitude save with the
listed DC so in the case of the giant
scorpion it would use one action to make
a melee attack that attack has the word
grab listed in its damage entry so if
that attack hits it can use its second
action to grab the target of the attack
and now that it is grabbed it can use
its third action to constrict when doing
so the grabbed creature would roll a
basic fortitude save against dc20 to
avoid suffering 1d6 plus4 bludgeoning
damage on a successful save the creature
would still suffer half damage as usual
with basic saving throws and again also
note that one use of constrict affects
all grabbed creatures so if this was a
giant squid who had three different
creatures all grabbed at the same time
one action to constrict would apply the
constrict effect and damage to all of
those grabbed creatures not one action
per before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the how play patreon
community receed special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics I cover visit the link shown
at the top of the screen and in the
description if you'd like to know more
if you would like to support this
Channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that is by subscribing and
clicking the Bell icon so you get
notified when new videos release and I
can always be reached through Twitter
and Facebook too thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming