this video is brought to you by roll for
combat
an official piezo actual play podcast
visit rollforcombat.com today to listen
to agents of edgewatch
and join basil dougie gomez and loming
as they protect and serve the citizens
of absalom from a mysterious and
diabolical plot
welcome to battle breakdown by how it's
played the series that examines famous
scenes from movies and television
through the lens of a role-playing game
and illustrates how these events might
play out at the game table
in this edition we'll be looking at an
encounter from 2001's
the fellowship of the ring as if it was
an encounter in pathfinder second
edition
specifically we'll be using this as an
example of a monster using their grab
ability in this scene the fellowship has
opened the gates to the minds of moria
and discovered that the stronghold has
been decimated by the armies of sauron
after a brief moment of shock at this
discovery the four hobbits begin backing
out of the mines entrance
and are attacked by a monster referred
to in the books
as the watcher in the water which for
our purposes
has the following stats when the gm
calls for initiatives to be rolled
all members of the fellowship role
perception and the watcher roll
stealth for its initiative it has a
stealth bonus of plus 17
and gm tolkien decides to grant an
additional plus 4
due to the dark and murky state of the
water it's hiding in
giving the watcher a total stealth bonus
of plus 21.
incidentally none of the members of the
fellowship noticed the watcher hiding in
the water during their approach to the
mine
because none of their perception roles
for the seek action beat the watchers
stealth dc of 31.
the watcher wins initiative and with its
first action it makes a melee arm attack
against frodo
this hits and deals 2d8 plus 9
bludgeoning damage
the damage entry for this attack also
says plus knockdown and
improved grab which means on a hit the
watcher can grab the victim as a free
action
this is only possible because it has
improved
grab and because of this frodo is now
suffering the flat-footed and
immobilized conditions
and he must also pass a dc5 flat check
to use any actions with the manipulate
trait
and since the attack was a success and
has knocked down
listed in his damage entry 2 the watcher
is able to use its second action to
impose the prone condition on frodo
and then spins its third action to drag
the hobbit one square closer
gm talk increase this the same as
dragging an object
one action to drag one square and thanks
to the watcher having a strength
modifier of plus six
and frodo being a small sized creature
he doesn't really worry about bulk
limitations and just keeps the game
moving
now the fellowship takes their turns in
a flurry of activity
mary and pippin are next and perform the
same actions they both strive to frodo
first
and then use their second actions to
prepare to aid
the aid basic action allows you to spin
an action on your turn to prepare to
give a leader to another character
during their turn but you must spend
your reaction at that time to do so
now when frodo's turn further spends his
first action to try and escape from the
watcher's grab
this calls for his choice of rolling
acrobatics
athletics or an unarmed attack against
the watchers athletics dc
the watcher has an athletic skill bonus
of plus 20 which means his athletics dc
is 30.
frodo decides to use acrobatics and
before he rolls the die
mary and pippin both announced that
they're using their reactions to aid
frodo
they're able to do this because each of
them spent an action during their turn
to prepare to aid gm tolkien decides
they will need to roll athletics checks
for this
to represent them grabbing hold of frodo
and trying to pull him
out of the watcher's grasp the dc for
their checks is 20
and both mary and pippen succeed but
this does not mean they succeed in
pulling them free
what this means is they grant a plus one
circumstance bonus to frodo's escape
check
not plus two because this is a typed
bonus
and typed bonuses do not stack frodo has
an acrobatic skill of plus 10
plus one more from his friend's aid
makes this a total check of 1d20 plus 11
versus dc30 meaning frodo needs to roll
a 19 or 20 on the die to break free from
the watcher's grab
frodo rolls a 14 for a total of 25 and
fails this check he doesn't break free
from the grab
but he can try again with his second
action he attempts to escape again but
this time without the plus one from
marion pippen's aid and
also suffers a negative 5 multiple
attack penalty
remember even though frodo is using the
acrobatic skill here
the escape action has the attack trait
therefore
each use of escape counts towards it is
affected by the multiple attack penalty
he rolls wendy 20 plus 5 versus dc 30
and gets a 7 on the die for a total of
12.
since this is more than 10 lower than
the dc
he critically fails the check which
means he cannot attempt to escape
again until the next round so with his
third action
frodo complains to gm tolkien that this
encounter is not
fair next in initiative is sam
he starts his turn by calling for help
this is a free action it doesn't cost
him anything
he then strikes a photo with his first
action and makes a strike at the
tentacle grabbing photo with his second
action
the watcher in the water has a feature
called grasping tentacles this says
a creature can sever a tentacle with a
target attack that hits
ac25 and deals at least 11
slashing damage this doesn't deal any
damage to the watcher in the water
itself
though it can no longer attack with a
severed tentacle
sam's attack hits but fails to deliver
11 points of slashing damage
so with his third action he tries again
he makes another melee attack roll
-5 due to the multiple attack penalty
rolls a hit and deals enough slashing
damage
to cut off the tentacle and free frodo
boromir gandalf gimli legolas and
strider's turns are not shown in this
clip
but consist of a mix of seek recall
knowledge
interrupt and stride actions to assist
the situation and
rush to the hobbit's aid at the top of
the second round
the watcher uses writhing arms
this ability costs two actions and
allows the watcher to make
up to four attacks with different arms
each at a different target
in this case the watcher targets each of
the four hobbits
it hits all four hobbits dealing 2d 8
plus 9 bludgeoning damage to each of
them
and the last line of the ability says if
the watcher in the water subsequently
uses the grab
action it can grab or knock down any
number of creatures it hit with writhing
arms
the watcher does this with his third
action and chooses to grab
frodo and knock down mary pippen and sam
so frodo once again gains the grabbed
condition
and the others gain the prone condition
as we see in the clip
once frodo is grabbed the watcher pulls
him three squares
and holds him high over the water frodo
complains as a free action
saying it's not fair that he was singled
out to be grabbed
while the others were merely knocked
down and reminds gm tolkien
that there is nothing in raw that says
when a creature is grabbed by a large or
huge sized monster
that the monster can freely pull their
grabbed target closer
in this case the watcher was not
dragging frodo as it had before
and the grip ability does not allow for
this kind of force movement by raw
now gm tolkien strongly believes that
pulling frodo a few squares closer and
holding him over the water is
exciting cinematic and will add tension
to the scene
and he really doesn't care if raw
doesn't allow for it
he's the gm and he's empowered to do
whatever he believes is appropriate
to provide for a fun and exciting game
now the rest of the fellowship has
arrived
and is legolas's turn he spins his first
two actions to stride
out of the mine and with his third
action he attempts to free frodo as sam
had done before
by attacking the tentacle that's holding
him he rolls a success for the attack
and hits the tentacle
but unfortunately the text for grasping
tentacles says
it takes 11 points of slashing damage to
free a grabbed creature
and legolas bow deals piercing damage
so gm tolkien says sorry it was a good
idea but piercing damage won't work for
this
strider and boromir both spin their
first actions to stride into the water
which counts as greater difficult
terrain at this depth
boromir then spins his second and third
actions to make melee sword attacks
against the watcher
both attacks hit and deal damage to the
monster's hit points
and gm tolkien describes this damage in
the narrative
as boromir lopping off stray tentacles
just not the one that is holding frodo
then on strider's turn after he moves
into the water
he makes two attacks against the
tentacle that's holding frodo captive
the first attack hits but he rolls once
for the damage and is not
enough to cut through the tentacle but
with his third action
he attacks again hits rolls more than 11
points of slashing damage and
finally frees frodo and now in the third
round of the encounter
the fellowship wisely flees into the
mine
it takes strider and boromir two stride
actions to walk
out of the greater difficult train
imposed by the water and their third
actions to enter the mine
while legolas is able to spend one
action to attack the monster before he
has to flee
he makes a range attack rolls a natural
20 and gets to draw a card from the
critical hit
deck his bow deals piercing damage and
the piercing effect
on the card he drew is titled eye patch
for you
this attack deals triple damage and the
watcher in the water
will be dazzled until healed it's a
solid hit but not
enough to put the monster down so
legolas spends the rest of his actions
to flee into the mine with the others
and on the watcher's turn it collapses
the mine's doorway behind them
now let's watch that encounter one more
time
my god
that's one way this could have gone but
there are others
food for thought for everybody viewing
in my version of events
gm talking hand waved the usual
restrictions of raw
and allowed the watcher in the water to
use the grab action
to force movement upon frodo would you
have handled that situation
any differently in your games leave your
thoughts and reasoning in the comments
as a follow up to this video i will
leave links to my full rule explanation
videos on the grab
action stealth and damage in the
description and please leave your
suggestions for future battle breakdowns
in the comments
and as always i want to thank all of my
patrons and everyone else who supports
me by subscribing and liking these
videos
until next time take care and happy
gaming
i have no memory of this place