hello and welcome to monster abilities
and pathfinder second edition part two
swallow hull and engulf presented by how
it's played
in the previous video of this series we
discussed the grab
action and now we're going to continue
that discussion with one of the actions
available to some monsters after they
grab the creature with their mouths
swallow whole as grabbing an enemy is a
requirement to use swallow hull
it is encouraged that you watch my video
on the grab action before continuing
here
a link to that video is provided in this
video's description
let's look at the dinosukis or giant
crocodile as an example
it has a melee jaw attack and includes
plus grab in its damage entry
it can spin an action to perform this
attack and if that attack hits
then it can spend a second action to
grab the victim of the jaw attack
if it does so it can then spin its third
action to perform
swallow hull here we see swallow hall
has the attack trait
followed by large 2d eight plus seven
bludgeoning damage and
rupture 18. the attack trait is
self-explanatory
using swallow hull contributes to and is
affected by the multiple attack penalty
the next part says large this is the
largest size creature it can attempt to
swallow
also note that it can only swallow one
creature of the listed size
but there is no hard limit to the number
of smaller creatures it can have
swallowed at any given time so this
dinosuukis only has room for one horse
in a stomach
but can fit as many humans and goblins
as the gm allows
when a monster uses swallow hull they
roll their athletic skill
versus the reflex dc of their victim in
the case of donosukis
it has an athletics bonus of plus 20 so
he would roll 1d20
plus 20 versus the reflex dc of the
creature being swallowed
and the reflex dc will be 10 plus the
victim's reflex save bonus
this attack roll is further modified as
usual so
if the donosukis attempted to swallow a
creature in the same turn that it
grabbed that creature in its jaws
it would suffer a negative 5 multiple
attack penalty to this swallow hull
attack
making it plus 15 versus the target's
reflex dc
but if the donosukis waited until the
start of his next turn and the creature
was still grabbed by its mouth
then it would not face any multiple
attack penalty then
on a success the grabbed creature is
swallowed and suffers the listed damage
in this case 2d a plus 7 blushing note
that although this is being defended by
a reflex save dc
this is not the same thing as a basic
saving throw
therefore no damage is rolled or halved
on a failure
it's all or nothing the victim either is
swallowed or it is not
also the victim suffers this damage not
only when they are swallowed
but they suffer it again at the end of
each of their turns
no additional attack rolls are required
once the creature is swallowed it
automatically suffers this damage
at the end of each of its turns
once a creature is swallowed it suffers
the grabbed and slowed one conditions
slowed one means that the victim only
has two actions per turn
instead of three while they're swallowed
and they must hold their breath
or they begin suffocating a creature can
hold his breath for a number of rounds
equal to 5 plus their constitution
modifier at the end of each turn this
count is lowered by a 1 if they did not
attack or cast spells during their turn
and it is lowered by 2 if they did
attack or cast a spell
also note that if a creature that is
holding its breath speaks or attempts to
cast a spell that has a verbal component
then they lose
all of the remaining air when a creature
runs out of air they fall unconscious
and begin suffocating under normal
circumstances when a creature that is
unconscious but still has hit points
suffers any amount of damage they wake
up and lose the unconscious condition
but not in this case when swallowed
whole
once you become unconscious that
condition cannot be removed until you
are free from whatever swallowed you
and once you're unconscious you must
attempt a dc20 fortitude save at the end
of each of your turns
on a failure you suffer 1d10 damage in
addition to the damage applied by the
swallow hall effect
and on a critical failure you die
not gain the dying condition but you
skip past that entire mechanic
and you die on every round after the
first the dc of this check increases by
five
and the damage applied for failing the
save also increases by an additional
1d10
once you have access to arrogan you stop
suffocating and lose the unconscious
condition
if you are still above zero hit points
and all this begs the question of once
you're swallowed how do you get out
the first way to free yourself is with
the escape action
this works just as described in the
previous video about the grab action
euro acrobatics athletics or unarmed
attack versus the monsters athletics dc
and on a success you free yourself by
climbing back out of the monster's mouth
and ending in a space adjacent to the
monster if the monster happens to have
another creature grabbed in its mouth
when you do this
then you free both yourself and the
other creature that's grabbed by the
monster's mouth
the second way to free yourself is by
cutting your way out
a swollen creature can attack the
creature from the inside
using either unarmed attacks or weapons
of light bulk like
daggers and sickles the monster is
flat-footed against these attacks
and all damage is subtracted from the
monster's hit points as usual
but if a single attack deals an amount
of piercing or slashing damage
equal to or greater than the monster's
rupture value
then you cut yourself free you can also
try to blast your way free by casting a
spell but
remember if the spell has a verbal
component you lose
all of your remaining air and if has any
other kind of component then it has the
manipulate trait
and you must pass a dc5 flat check due
to being grabbed
also just like with a weapon attack only
piercing or slashing damage can be used
to cut your way free with a spell
and note that the rules specifically say
that the swallowed creature can
attempt to cut their way out by raw new
rules are provided if an
ally of the swallowed person wants to
cut them free from the outside
so each gm will need to evaluate the
scene and make a decision for themselves
for example the gm might require players
to pass an appropriate recall knowledge
check about the monster to know where
their stomach
is before they can try to cut their
friend free they might also increase the
monster's armor class if their stomach
is in a hard to target location
for example the dinosukis like a
crocodile probably has his belly flushed
to the ground
making it harder to hit from the outside
but
that's all assuming the monster is still
alive
once the monster is dead allies can free
a swallowed creature from the monster's
corpse by spending a combined total of
three actions cutting the monster open
those are the general rules for swallow
hull but there is another related
monster ability that we need to discuss
and that is engulf engulf works much the
same way as swallow hull
except instead of grabbing a victim in
their mouths first and then
swallowing them when a monster uses
engulf
they simply need to move through their
victim space
they basically fold their bodies around
their victim
completely enveloping them for example a
gelatinous cube doesn't have the mouth
or jaws needed to swallow a victim
and instead has the engulf ability
then golf entry for a gelatinous cube
says dc19
2d6 acid escape dc19
rupture 7. that should look pretty
familiar
except it has an assigned dc and it does
not list a maximum
size for the victim using engulf takes
two actions
and allows the monster destroyed up to
double his speed score
and freely move through the spaces of
any creatures in its path
in the case of a gelatinous cube it has
a speed score of 15 feet
so it moves 30 feet when using a golf
when it enters another creature space
if that creature is of equal size or
smaller than the engulfing monster
that creature has to make a reflex save
versus the engulf effects dc
in the case of a gelatinous cube its
size large
so it can freely move through any
creature space while using engulf
and if that creature is size large or
smaller
it would roll a reflex save versus dc19
if that creature is size huge or larger
then the gelatinous cube can still move
through its space but it cannot affect
it with engulf
if the targeted creature succeeds the
saving throw then they can choose to
either jump
into a square to the side of the
engulfing creature's path
or they can choose to be pushed in the
front of the monster's movement
and be placed in an empty square in
front of wherever the monster stops
and note that a monster can only attempt
to engulf the same creature once per
engulf action so they can't snake around
in a circle trying to pick up the same
enemy over and over again
if a creature fails this saving throw
then they're engulfed by the monster and
from here things function
almost the same as if they had been
swallowed whole the victim gains the
grab to slow down conditions
they have to hold their breath or start
suffocating and they suffer the listed
damage
when they're engulfed and again at the
end of every turn following
they can attempt to escape by rolling a
check versus either the listed escape dc
or the monsters athletics dc and they
can attempt to cut themselves free
by exceeding the monster's rupture value
with a single attack that deals slashing
or piercing damage
and note that the engulfing creature can
only engulf
as many creatures as it can fit in its
space
so for a large sized gelatinous cube it
can engulf
either one large sized creature or four
creatures that are medium or small
the only real difference between being
engulfed and being swallowed whole
is when you are swallowed whole when the
monster dies your allies can spend three
actions to cut you out
whereas with engulfing creatures when
they die you're automatically freed as
their body loses cohesion
swallow hull and a gulf are very similar
but their mechanics are different so
let's break it down like this
swallow hole takes one action but can
only be performed if the monster
already has a victim grabbed in their
mouth or jaws
engulf takes two actions but the monster
gets destroyed at twice its speed and
move through any occupied squares
when using swallow hull the stat block
states the maximum size creature it can
swallow
it can only swallow one creature of this
size or
any number of smaller creatures allowed
by the gm
the stat line fern golf does not include
a maximum size entry
instead the maximum size that can be
engulfed is equal to the monster size
and it must be able to fit all of its
engulfed creatures
in its squares when using swallow hole
the monster attacks their victim by
rolling their athletic skill versus the
victim's reflex dc
on a success they swallow the victim and
on a failure nothing happens
within golf is not the monster who makes
the role
but instead each creature of its size
are smaller that the creature moves
through the space of needs to roll a
reflex safe
against the dc listed in the engulfed
stat line
on a success they either jump into a
free space to the side of the monster
or let the monster push it until it
stops and ends in an empty space in
front of it
once a creature succeeds on this check
the monster cannot attempt to engulf
them again
until the next turn and on a failed save
the monster engulfs them once a creature
is swallowed or engulfed the mechanics
are mostly the same
they suffer the listed damage when they
are consumed and again
at the end of each of their turns they
have the grabbed and slowed
one conditions and must hold their
breaths or start suffocating
they can free themselves by either
succeeding at an escaped check or by
cutting their way out
they can only attack the creature with
unarmed attacks or weapons of light bulk
and if a single attack deals an amount
of slashing or piercing damage that is
equal to
or greater than the rupture value they
cut their way out of the monster and
free themselves
spills can also be used for this purpose
but remember the limitations due to
holding breath
and also having the grabbed condition
and the last way a victim can be freed
differs between the swallowed hole and
engulf abilities
with swallow hull when the monster dies
people outside of the monster
can spend a cumulative total of three
actions to cut the victim out of them
and with engulf it loses cohesion and
anyone engulfed by it is instantly freed
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content
and getting to vote on the topics i
cover visit the link shown at the top of
the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more if you would like to support
this channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming