hello and welcome to monster abilities
and pathfinder 2nd edition part 3.
in this video we'll be discussing
ferocity frightful presence and trample
ferocity is an ability commonly found in
orcs cyclops and animals such as badgers
and boars and allows the creature to
stay conscious and in the fight even
after being reduced to zero hit points
the ability costs one reaction with the
trigger the monster is reduced to zero
hit points
and with the effect the monster avoids
being knocked out
and remains at one hit point but his
wounded value increases by 1.
when it is wounded 3 it can no longer
use this ability
so the way it works is the first time a
creature with ferocity suffers enough
damage that would normally kill it
it can spin its reaction to instead stay
alive at one hit point
and when it does so is wounded value
increases by one
in most cases monsters are considered
dead at zero hit points
and you don't need to worry about the
wounded and dying conditions unless the
gm
feels they need to for example if it's
an orc that is also a prominent npc
then the gm might want to track their
wounded and dying conditions
but in most cases this notation that
says that ferocity increases wounded by
one
is just a counter that places a limit on
how many times a creature can use
ferocity
after their third use they're done now
this doesn't mean that the first three
times there reduces zero hit points they
get to shrug it off and stay fighting
always remember that this costs their
reaction and each creature only gets one
reaction per turn
so if one player reduces an orc to zero
hit points
that orc might spend their one reaction
to use ferocity and stay alive
but if another player hits that orc and
deals them a
single point of damage before that orcs
next turn then they can't use ferocity
and will be killed or knocked
unconscious of the gm perfers
reactions are granted at the start of
each turn so a creature cannot use
ferocity
more than once per round likewise this
reaction might be shared among different
abilities
for example if an orc uses their
reaction to perform an attack of
opportunity
then they will not be able to also use
ferocity until the start of their next
turn
frightful presence is an ability common
to dragons and some undead like liches
this is an aura ability that creates a
zone around the monster and strikes fear
in the heart of anyone who approaches
them
the first time a player enters this zone
they must make a will
save versus the listed dc for example
young red dragons have an entry that
says frightful presence
90 feet dc 27 whenever someone moves
within 90
feet of a young red dragon they must
roll a will save versus dc27
once a player is subjected to a
monster's frightful presence they are
immune to its effect for one minute
which is typically long enough for most
combat encounters so you shouldn't need
to roll this more than once per fight
even if the player leaves and re-enters
that aura
and this is a per-monster effect so if
the party was fighting three red dragons
they would need to roll three saves each
made when the player
enters 90 feet of that dragon on a
critical success
nothing happens they shrug it off if
they roll a success
they still receive the frightened one
condition
on a failure they receive frighten 2 and
on a critical failure
they receive frightened 4. contrary to
somewhat common belief
the frightened condition does not make
you turn and flee from the monster
instead it applies a penalty equal to
its value to all
checks in all dc's so while frighten 2
you subtract 2 from basically every time
you roll a d20
including all of your attack rolls skill
checks and saving throws
and also subtract 2 from all of your
dc's including armor class
save dc's and the spell dc that others
roll against to resist
your spells at the end of every turn the
frightened condition reduces by 1 until
it wears off
and last when it comes to metallic
dragons and other good online creatures
that have frightful presence
some gms may prefer to describe this
effect within the narrative
as an overpowering sense of awe and
majesty
instead of fear but mechanically it
still
counts the same as frightful presence
and does impose the frightened condition
and some creatures typically large
animals like dinosaurs and elephants
have an ability called trample that
allows them to charge
through an area stomping any smaller
creatures unfortunate enough to be in
their way
when using trample the creature spins
three actions and then strides
double its speed during this action it
can freely move through the space of
creatures of a listed size
and those creatures must roll a basic
reflex safe
versus a listed dc or suffer the effects
of a listed strike
for example the brontosaurus has an
entry that says trample
three actions huge or smaller foot
dc 29 it can spend
all three of its actions on a turn
destroyed at doubles speed
which would be a total of 70 feet for a
brontosaurus and can
freely move through the space of any
creature of delicious size
in this case the listed size is huge or
smaller
so the brontosaurus can move 70 feet and
trample over all creatures in its path
that are size huge or smaller
and each of those creatures must pass a
basic reflex save versus dc dc29
or face the effects of a listed strike
in this case the listed strike is
foot so basically trample allows the
brontosaurus to make a foot attack
against everyone whose square it moves
through but instead of it making attack
rolls
all of the targets roll reflex saves and
these are basic reflex safes
so on a failure they suffer 2d8 plus 13
damage
on a critical failure they suffer double
that and on a success they
still suffer half that and on a critical
success they suffer
no damage before we close i'd like to
take a moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content
and getting to vote on the topics i
cover visit the link shown at the top of
the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more if you would like to support
this channel
and help it grow the easiest way to do
that is by subscribing and clicking the
bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming