hello and welcome to monster abilities
in pathfinder 2nd edition part 4.
in this video we'll be discussing knock
down push and
rend knockdown allows certain attacks to
not only damage an enemy but
also knock the target to the ground this
works in much the same way as the grab
monster ability that we discussed in
part one of the series when a monster
successfully hits an
enemy with an attack that includes the
words plus knockdown in his damage entry
it does not automatically knock the
target prone
instead what plus knockdown means is the
monster has the
option of imposing the prone condition
on the target of the attack
but must spend one extra action to do so
while prone the character is also
flat-footed and suffers a negative two
circumstance penalty to both armor class
and attack rolls
the only move actions a person can use
while prone are crawl and stand which
immediately removes the prone condition
and while you're prone you can spend
one action on the take cover action and
receive the benefits of greater cover
against range attacks
even if you don't meet the usual
requirements of having an object to hide
behind
this grants a plus 4 circumstance bonus
to armor class against
range attacks only but remember you're
still
flat-footed also which imposes a
negative 2 penalty
meaning when you are prone and use the
take cover action
you receive a net plus 2 to your armor
class against range attacks
and suffer a negative 2 penalty against
melee attacks
also note that this cover bonus while
prone only applies to armor class and
does not apply to reflex savings throws
like with the normal greater cover bonus
so the key to using knockdown is to
remember it costs
two actions one to attack with an
ability that includes knockdown in its
damage entry
and if that hits you can spend a second
action to apply prone to the target
this is with normal knockdown but there
is an
advanced form called improved knockdown
which works exactly like a regular
knockdown
except it can be used as a free action
so basically when an attack hits with
improved knockdown then in that case the
target is
automatically rendered prone
next up we have push which functions a
lot like knock down and grab
when you see an attack that has a damage
entry that says
plus push x mini feet it doesn't mean
that the target of the attack is
automatically pushed back when they're
hit
it means that the monster who made the
attack has the option of spending
one action more in order to apply the
push
effect and if they have improved push
instead of regular push then it works
just like with knockdown and improved
knockdown
meaning improved push can be used as a
free action
if the monster does apply the push
effect then the target of the attack is
moved back the listed number of feet
which defaults to 5
feet if no distance is listed and on a
critical hit
the amount of distance moved to back is
doubled this is a form of forced
movement
so the gm determines the path the target
follows which should be legal as long as
it's a fairly straight line
and each square the target moves through
is further away from the monster than
the previous square
the victim of a push can be moved
through difficult terrain which counts
double as usual and may be pushed into
harmful spaces such as
being pushed off a ledge should this
happen the victim should have an
opportunity to spend their reaction to
grab an edge as usual
also if the pushed victim reaches a
space where there are no further
legal spaces to move into for example
they're pushed 15
feet but there is a long wall five feet
behind them
they move as far as they can and then
they stop
by raw they are not knocked prone
damaged or moved into an illegal space
but as always with raw the gm is free to
impose
any of these complications if it makes
sense for that particular scene
and the last monster ability i want to
discuss here is rend
when you see an entry for rend it's very
simple
it's literally just the word rend and
the name of one of the monster's attacks
and without flipping to the back of the
book it can be hard to know exactly what
this means
rand simply means that if the listed
attack has been used twice already this
turn
and both hit the same target then the
monster doesn't need to make an attack
roll for the third attack
and automatically deals the listed
damage so
for example wolverines have two attacks
a jaw attack and a claw attack and they
also have an entry that says
rind one action claw what this means is
during the wolverine's turn
if it spins his first action to make a
claw attack that hits
and then spins his second action to make
another claw attack
against the same target and that also
hits
then it can spin its third action to
automatically
deal a claw attack's 1d6 plus 5 damage
to the same target
without having to make another attack
roll and therefore bypassing the
multiple attack penalty
but the key to using rend is it requires
two successful attacks using the same
attack at the same target
during the same round if the wolverine
used
one of his first two actions on a jaw
attack or if it made a claw attack
against two different targets then it
would not be able to use
rend with its third action
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content
and getting to vote on the topics i
cover visit the link shown at the top of
the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more if you would like to support
this channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming