this video is brought to you by roll for
combat
and the fall of plaguestone an official
piezo actual play podcast
join peru cade brixley and celeste as
they band together to save the village
of plaguestone from utter destruction
listen now to the fall of plaguestone at
roll4combat.com
hello and welcome to mental conditions
and pathfinder 2nd edition
in this video we'll be discussing
several of the conditions that impact a
creature's middle status
including confused controlled fascinated
frightened and fleeing
when a creature is suffering from the
confused condition they have difficulty
telling
friend from foe when you are confused
you are flat-footed which imposes
a negative two circumstance penalty to
armor class and you can't treat
anyone as being your ally so for example
you wouldn't be able to receive
any flanking bonuses while confused you
also cannot use the delay or ready
actions nor can you use
any reactions during your turn the gm
assumes control of your character and
uses every action to either make weapon
attacks
or cast can trips against randomly
selected targets
and is worth noting that the gm may also
use actions to facilitate these attacks
such as moving or drawing weapons if you
have no viable targets to attack
then you will spend your actions
attacking yourself when you do this
no rules are needed and instead you
always score a hit but never a critical
hit
if for some reason it is impossible for
you to attack another or yourself
then by raw you spend all of your
actions babbling incoherently
but the gm may decide to perform other
actions
such as the escape action if you've been
tied up
each time you suffer damage you'll roll
a dc-11 flat check
and on a success the confused condition
instantly ends
a few possible sources of the confused
condition include the confusion spell
belladonna poison
and gibbering mouthers
the controlled condition is an even more
advanced version of confused
when you are controlled you completely
lose agency over your character and the
creature responsible for giving you this
condition
spins your actions any way they wish
including the use of delay ready and
reactions
this effectively makes you an npc during
the duration of the controlled condition
typically the effect that imposes the
control condition specifies exactly in
what circumstances the condition will
end
for example if you're suffering
controlled because you failed your will
save against the dominate spell
then you get to attempt a new save at
the end of each of your turns
but if you critically fail to save
against the dominate spell
then you don't get a new save unless the
gm rules that a command you receive
is against your nature such as killing
an ally and if none of those conditions
are met
then the controlled condition goes away
at the end of the dominate spells
duration
which is the next time you make your
daily preparations
a few other sources of controlled
include the position spell
spore blight disease and a specter's
corruption ability
when you're fascinated all of your
attention is focused on
one creature or object virtually
ignoring everything else going on around
you
while suffering this condition you
suffer a negative two status penalty to
perception and all skills
and you cannot use any actions with a
concentrate trait
unless they are directly related to the
subject of your fascination
for example you would be able to use
recall knowledge to learn something
about the subject of your fascination
but
not for other topics nor could you cast
most spells unless
they target the subject of your
fascination that's what fascinated does
but it's probably just as important to
discuss the things it doesn't do
while fascinated you do not face any
restrictions other than the ones already
mentioned
meaning you can choose to ignore the
subject of your fascination you can walk
away from it you can attack it
you can use any action that doesn't have
the concentration trait while targeting
anything you like
also you do not suffer any penalties
other than those
listed you're not flat footed to the
subject of your fascination nor do they
receive any bonuses to attack you
however there are a few situations
especially with monsters
that specifically modify how this works
for example the yellow musk creeper can
spray pollen to fascinate their victims
in this case the fascinated victim must
spend all of their actions moving closer
to the creeper
and standing still so that it can use
its bore into brain ability on them
but that's a specific exception that's
called out in the text
of a creature so generally speaking what
is the fascinating condition for is for
distracting someone
and really i think it would have been
better if they had named it distracted
rather than fascinated as fascinated
leads people to think of being charmed
or enchanted
and fascinated people can do pretty much
whatever they want but have trouble
thinking about anything other than the
subject of their fascination
so they're distracted a good example of
when this condition
might be used would be a bard who casts
enthrall
over an audience so that they don't
notice a rogue sneaking away or
pickpocketing someone
the next condition to discuss is
frightened when you are frightened you
suffer a status penalty equal to the
value of the frightened condition to all
checks in dc's so more or less anytime
you roll a d20 other than flat checks
you will subtract
this number from the roll attacks skill
checks
saves pretty much every d20 roll
and anytime another creature makes a
check against one of your dc's
those dc's are also lowered by the value
of the frightened condition
this includes things like your armor
class reflex dc
perception dc in all skill dc's as well
as the spell dc
targets roll against when you cast a
spell against them
unless otherwise stated the frightened
condition's value lowers by one at the
end of each of your turns until
it completely wears off so if you suffer
the frightened three condition on one
round
after your turn ends it becomes frighten
two
and then after the next turn it becomes
frightened one and then
ends at the end of the next turn also
note that although the condition is
called frightened
in some cases it may be represented as
an overpowering sense of awe
such as when in the presence of an
ancient metallic dragon
in addition to the auras created by
dragons some other sources of the
frightened condition
include the demoralized application of
intimidation
the fear spell and various abilities
used by ghosts and other undead
creatures
now you may have noticed that the
frightened condition in no way prevents
its victim from taking actions against a
creature imposing the condition on them
or
moving closer to whatever is scaring
them those situations have their own
condition
called fleeing when a creature suffers
the fleeing condition
they must spend all of their actions
moving away from the source of the
condition
as efficiently as possible this includes
taking stride actions in the most direct
path away from the scary thing
as well as other actions to facilitate
that such as
opening doors and while fleeing you
cannot use delay already
and while fleeing you are also likely to
be able to make common sense
adjustments to the course you take to
avoid obvious danger
but as usual the gm has the final say on
what would be an appropriate reaction
and path to use when fleeing
fleeing is often imposed as an advanced
form of frightened
for example failing a save against the
fierce spell imposes frightened
but critically failing it inflicts
fleeing and each effect that applies the
fleeing condition
should specify the amount of time that
you are required to run away
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content
and getting to vote on the topics i
cover if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming