this video is brought to you by rooll
for combat an official piso actual play
podcast join Aton hap alhara Riley
Darius and the entire circus of wayward
wonders as they save the starstone Isles
from the dreaded Extinction curse listen
now to three- ring Adventure at rfor
combat.com
hello and welcome to Aquatic combat and
Pathfinder second
edition first off let's talk about
movement in water the effect water has
on a creature's movement will largely be
determined by the GM but the deeper the
water is the more difficult it will be
to move through if the water is deep
enough that you can't move through it as
easily as you can walk on dry land then
you face some kind of penalty there are
no hard rules for this but the guideline
I use in my games is if the water
reaches midcalf then it probably slows
you down and counts as difficult terrain
if the water is knee level then it
counts as greater difficult terrain and
if the water level is higher than your
waist then you probably need to make
swim actions to move through it as long
as the water is calm then you usually do
not need to roll an Athletics check to
swim but the GM May rule otherwise
succeeding a swim check means you move
through 5 ft of water plus another 5T
per 20 ft of your land speed and on a
critical success you move that plus
another 5 ft so for most PCS who have
speed scores between 25 and 35 then they
swim 10 ft on a success or 15 ft on a
critical success on a failure nothing
happens you don't get to move anywhere
but you also don't start drowning and
it's the same on a critical failure
except if you're already holding your
breath then you lose one point of your
remaining Air Supply we'll talk more
about holding your breath your Air
Supply and drowning in just a minute
also note that each type of movement
requires its own action so if you start
your turn 5T from the water and have a
speed score of 25 ft then you have to
spend one action to walk 5 ft to the
water and then another action to begin
swimming you can't use your unused
movement from the first action to begin
swimming and combin walking and swimming
in the same action each movement type
requires its own action and also be
aware that any creature with a swim
speed can completely ignore having to
roll at letics chicks to use the swim
action and they can freely move through
water at their swim speed and if you're
curious how weight and armor factor into
all of this well the game doesn't really
go too deep into specific penalties for
weight being in armor or carrying a
heavy load the rules in water are the
same as on land if you're encumbered
then your speed score is lowered by 10
which may impact how far you can move
with a swim action likewise the
penalties imposed by wearing armor like
check penalties and speed penalties are
the same underwater as they are normally
there are no extra rules applied for
armor for bulk or for incumbrance when
you're in the
water The Aquatic combat rules apply
whenever a player or other creature is
in water deep enough to require a swim
action to move while within an aquatic
environment you gain the following you
are flat footed unless you have a swim
speed you have resistance five to all
acid in fire damage when making melee
attacks you suffer no penalty if the
attack does not pass through water say
for example if you're standing and waste
deep water the GM May rule that aquatic
combat applies this causing you to be
flat-footed and needing to use swim
actions to move but you would not suffer
any penalty to your attacks since the
weapons are not being forced to pass
through water but if your melee attacks
do have to pass through water to strike
their targets then you suffer a Nega -2
circumstance penalty if the attack deals
slashing or bludgeoning damage when
making ranged attacks while you're
underwater or against targets that are
underwater if the ranged attack deals
bludgeoning or slashing damage then that
attack automatically misses if the
ranged attack deals piercing damage then
its range increment is cut in half so if
you're firing a short bow then his range
increment is reduced from 60 ft to 30 ft
meaning there is no penalty for
attacking a Target within 30 ft but
there is a cumulative -2 penalty applied
for every 30 ft beyond that and the
rules are meant to be simple here so it
doesn't matter if you're standing on
Shore 29 ft away from an enemy that's
only 1 foot below water if you or the
target is underwater then the reduction
to range applies and there may be some
other considerations when attacking a
Target this underwater too for example
if the water isn't Crystal Clear then
the GM might grant that Target the
concealed condition forcing you to make
a dc5 flat check to Target them also
while underwater you cannot use any
action or ability that has the fire
trait nor can you cast any spell with
the fire trait and the GM may also
determine that any other action doesn't
work while floating or underwater and
really that's all there is to it or at
least that's all of the hard Guidance
the rule book provides I think they
largely want to leave it up to the GM to
decide how to best handle a lot of the
specifics of underwater combat that said
there are a couple of questions that
always do seem to come up the first is
about fireballs if you're underwater
then you can't cast a fireball spell but
if you're out of the water then you can
attack enemies beneath the surface of
the water with a fireball spell this
works the same as casting Fireball
against enemies on land except that when
in water the targets have resistance
five against fire damage and another
common question is what about casting a
bolt of lightning there are no changes
made to electricity spells when water is
present these spells can be cast
underwater provided you're able to
provide the required Spell components as
usual and suffer no penalties or bonuses
now the GM might allow for other effects
as flavor or as the rule of cool but
there is nothing in the rules that
treats electricity damage any different
in water than on land and one more
question that often comes up is what
happens when a character is knocked out
while they're in the water in this case
the GM decides whether they float to the
surface or sink to the bottom most PCS
carry enough gear to cause them to syn
to the bottom which leads us to the next
topic drowning and Suffocation
rules creatures have an air supply of
five plus their constitution modifier at
the end of every turn that you're unable
to breathe your Air Supply is lowered by
one if you did not attack or cast spells
during the turn and it's lowered by two
if you did attack or cast spells you
also lose an additional one point of Air
Supply every time you're critically hit
by an attack or if you critically fail a
save versus a spell when you run out of
air you fall unconscious and begin
suffocating while suffocating you must
attempt a dc20 fortitude save at the end
of each of your turns on a failure you
suffer 1 d10 damage and on a critical
failure you die not gain the dying
condition but you skip past that whole
mechanic and you die on every round
after the first the DC of this check
increases by five and the Damage applied
for failing the save is increased by an
additional 1 d10 so if you have a plus
seven fortitude bonus then on your first
turn after falling unconscious in the
water you roll 1 to 20+ 7 if the result
of that check is 20 or higher then you
suffer no damage if that check's total
is below 20 then you suffer 1 d10 damage
and note that when suffocating suffering
damage does not remove the unconscious
condition like it normally does and if
you critically fail that check by
Rolling a natural one or you have a
total that's 10 or lower then again you
die regardless of whether you succeed or
fail that fortitude save as long as
you're still alive then on your next
turn you roll the fortitude save again
but the DC is now 25 and on a failure
you suffer 2 d10 damage and every round
after that the DC increases by five more
and the Damage increases by another 1
d10 once you have access to air again
you stop suffocating and lose the
unconscious condition if you're above
zero hit
points before we close I'd like to take
a moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support members of the how played
patreon Community receive special
benefits like exclusive content and
getting to vote on the topics I cover if
you would like to support this Channel
and help it grow the easiest way to do
that is by subscribing and clicking the
Bell icon so you get notified when new
videos release and I can always be
reached through Twitter and Facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming