this video is brought to you by the
battle zoo bestiary a new book with over
100 award-winning monsters
and other resources from piezo lead
designer mark cipher
sign up today at
kickstarter.roll4combat.com and join the
campaign when it launches on
august 31st
hello and welcome to part one of
vehicles in pathfinder second edition by
how it's played
in this video we'll be looking at the
general information needed to manage
vehicles in your game
and in the next video we'll take things
one step further by examining the rules
for vehicles in combat
vehicles and pathfinder are modes of
transportation that are objects instead
of creatures
as such they may function in much the
same way as mounts but have their own
set of rules
and generally speaking these rules only
apply to combat encounters
if a party of players books passage on a
ship across the sea
or are riding in a caravan of carriages
across the countryside
you should feel free to skip over these
rules but if that ship comes under
attack by pirates
or a passing dragon decides that caravan
of wagons looks like its next lunch
then you may need these extra mechanics
to help resolve the scene
so some of these roles may look familiar
to what you're used to
but there are a few differences to be
aware of first
vehicles are assigned a size category
just like creatures
however a vehicle size does not
determine the space it occupies
instead each vehicle will have its
specific dimensions listed in a stat
block
and note that the vehicle size entry is
for the vehicle itself
and does not include any animals that
may be pulling
for example a carriage is a large size
vehicle
and it occupies a 10 foot by 10 foot
area
which is exactly what we're used to with
large sized creatures because that's
a two by two square area on a map but a
cart that is also a large sized vehicle
is 10 feet long and only 5 feet wide
meaning it occupies a 1 by 2 square area
on the map instead
of the 2 by 2 square area that we're
used to for anything listed as being
large
and again that is for the cart itself
and does not include
any animals like a horse that might be
pulling it
a vehicle's movement type is determined
by the vehicle itself
while the distance it moves each round
is determined by its pilot's actions
but the biggest difference with
determining a vehicle's movement
is unlike with creatures vehicles can't
just turn on a dime and therefore
facing rules are enforced for vehicles
at any given time it will be important
to know
which direction the vehicle is facing
which is referred to as its heading
when a vehicle moves it must move
forward in the direction of its heading
and cannot move side to side or
backwards
unless the step block specifically says
otherwise however
several rules state that a vehicle must
travel in a
quote straight line in this case moving
in a quote straight line
is in the direction of the vehicle's
heading but may
move into the space either to the left
or right
of that space but may not change its
heading
so for example if this is our carriage's
heading then moving in a straight line
means it could move here or it could
move here
or it can move here but regardless of
those three
options its heading remains the same it
does not
turn in order for a vehicle to turn on a
battle map
it must first move forward an amount of
distance
equal to its length so using our cart as
an example
it would have to move forward 10 feet
and then once it does that it can change
its heading by
up to 90 degrees in either direction
pretty simple for a carriage
but let's also look at ceiling boots
here it says
they're 75 feet long meaning this boat
would need to move forward
in a direction of its heading for 15
squares
before it could turn up to 90 degrees
and
some vehicles like this one include
special traits like sluggish
that modify the vehicle's turn rate even
further in this case
the ceiling ship would need the before
twice its length to turn
so 30 squares forward instead of 15.
also note that once a vehicle moves its
length forward it can turn
up to 90 degrees meaning it can turn
towards a diagonal heading if it wishes
by raw it still needs to move forward
its entire length to do so
but some gms may choose to only require
the vehicle to move
half its length forward when turning 45
degrees instead of the full 90.
the vehicle's pilot will need to roll
skill checks to control the vehicle and
to steer it
but the exact skill that is used will
vary from vehicle to vehicle
each vehicle's stat block includes a
section for piloting checks
that lists which skills may be used by
the pilot for example the pilot for a
galley
may use sailing lure diplomacy or
intimidation and the available skills
for these piloting checks are largely
informed by the vehicle's means of
propulsion
which are listed in parentheses in the
speed listing
galleys have a swim speed of 30 feet and
a galley's means of propulsion
are road and wind some vehicles like
this one
have more than one means of propulsion
but may never use more than one at the
same time
so a galley can move by means of rowing
or by
wind but not both at the same time
we'll discuss more about the different
means of propulsions and how they work
in the next video when we dive into more
information about
vehicles in combat
every round in encounter mode the
vehicle will move during its pilot's
turn
and the pilot must use their actions to
control it
and vehicles may only take part in one
move action per
round regardless of how many different
people attempt to pilot it during the
round
once a vehicle is in motion it has
momentum and continues to move towards
its current heading
each round if the vehicle moved in the
previous round the pilot must either use
an action to control the vehicle or stop
it
if the pilot does not do this then the
vehicle will become
uncontrolled when a vehicle is
uncontrolled
it moves each round on his most recent
pilot's turn
the distance it moves is 10 feet less
than it moved in the previous round
in a straight line until it crashes or
comes to a stop
so every round that a vehicle is
uncontrolled it progressively moves
slower and slower
at the gym's discretion the rate at
which the uncontrolled vehicle slows
may be increased or even decreased due
to environmental conditions
like difficult terrain wind or the
direction water is flowing
and uncontrolled vehicles may still
interact with some vehicle actions
such as hitting obstacles or other
vehicles or running over a creature
but when doing so the uncontrolled
vehicle uses its current rate of
movement
instead of the vehicle's speed score
another trait we should cover before
getting too deep into how you pilot
vehicles
is the reckless trait when a piloting
action has the
reckless trait the pilot must pass a
piloting check before resolving the
reckless action they want to perform
on a success they can proceed and
attempt the reckless action
but on a failure they cannot attempt the
reckless action
and instead the vehicle moves at his
entire speed score in a straight line
and becomes uncontrolled
as previously mentioned controlling a
vehicle calls for his pilot to roll
piloting checks
the skills and dc's for which are listed
in the vehicle step block
also at the start of an encounter the
pilot can usually roll whatever skill
they use for their piloting checks
for their initiative as well okay so
next
let's look at the different piloting
actions that are available
unless otherwise noted the dc's for
these checks will be the standard dc for
the vehicle's level
and the gm may further modify the dc as
appropriate
for example if the vehicle is moving
through difficult terrain
the dc will increase from standard to
hard and for greater difficult train the
dc becomes incredibly hard
first up is board simply put you spend
one action to get onto
or off of a vehicle if the vehicle is in
motion
then this calls for an acrobatics or
athletics check
against the vehicle's armor class next
is the drive action which is how you
make the vehicle move
each turn the pilot will decide how many
of their actions they wish to invest in
controlling the vehicle
for a one action the pilot rolls their
check and on its success the vehicle
moves up to its speed
and turns normally on a failure the
vehicle moves its entire speed in a
straight line
and can not turn and on a critical
failure
the vehicle moves its entire speed in a
straight line and becomes
uncontrolled if the pilot spins two
actions on drive
then the vehicle moves up to twice the
speed in a straight line
but can not turn note that when you
spend two actions to drive
it gains the reckless trait meaning the
pilot needs to pass a piloting check
before they can resolve this action as
previously discussed
if the pilot spends three actions on
drive then they face an
extra piloting check due to it having
the reckless trait however this time
they face a negative 5 penalty to that
check
but if they succeed then the vehicle
moves up to 3
times his speed in a straight line next
we have the stop action
this costs one of the piles actions and
brings the vehicle to a stop
it doesn't matter how fast it was going
this will bring it to a rest
but remember a vehicle may only be used
for one move action per round
so you can't perform another vehicle
action and stop in the same round
and the last action we're going to
discuss in this video is take
control simply put this takes one action
and a successful potting check
and this is how you designate yourself
as the vehicle's pilot
those are all of the vehicle actions
we'll be discussing here
in the next video we'll examine how
vehicles function in combat
such as running creatures over ramming
collision damage attacks of opportunity
and more
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the house played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release
and i can always be reached through
twitter and facebook too thanks for
watching
take care and happy gaming