this video is brought to you by the
battle zoo bestiary and jewel of the
indigo isles this three-part adventure
path written by piezo veterans patrick
rennie ron lindeen and linda zeus palmer
promises pirates dragons and treasure
hunting on the high seas join the
campaign today at
kickstarter.roll4combat.com
hello and welcome to part two of
vehicles in pathfinder second edition by
how it's played in part one we covered
the basic rules for vehicles how they
work how they move and how to read their
step blocks and now in part 2 we'll be
diving into how vehicles work in combat
combat while aboard a vehicle is not
entirely different from regular
pathfinder combat the key difference is
all attacks made aboard a moving vehicle
suffer an untyped penalty which is
negative 2 if the vehicle has moved
within the last round
keep in mind that combat turns are
declared in linear order but are assumed
to take place simultaneously
so even if the pilot of the vehicle
brings it to a stop on their turn you
will still suffer this attack penalty on
your turn this penalty increases to
negative 4 if the vehicle is
uncontrolled or if the pilot has used an
action with the reckless trait within
the last round even if the pilot rolled
a success on their pilot check for that
reckless action everyone on board that
vehicle will still suffer the negative
four penalty for the next round
and note that this penalty is applied
when making attacks while aboard a
moving vehicle and has nothing to do
with the targets of that attack this
applies if you are attacking someone on
the ground as you pass them someone who
is aboard another vehicle running
alongside you or someone standing on the
deck of the same ship that you are but
of course the gm has the right to apply
this any way they believe is appropriate
for example they may decide not to apply
this penalty for a very large ship that
is sailing through very calm waters
also the gm is encouraged to apply cover
rules
unlike some other d20 systems the snap
blocks here do not dictate how much
cover the pilot or passengers receive
when being attacked from outside the
vehicle so the gm will need to make a
decision about this for themselves the
guideline is if the vehicle has raised
sides but no top a chariot for example
then it provides either a lesser or
standard cover and if the vehicle is
enclosed like the interior of a carriage
then it provides greater cover to the
passengers and also note that vehicles
do trigger reactions just like any
creature does as do the actions of its
pilot and its passengers so a passing
chariot will provoke attacks of
opportunity just as if it was a creature
as will any actions its pilot or
passengers take
whenever a vehicle rams runs over or is
ran to buy another vehicle collision
damage occurs this works the same as any
other kind of damage in most regards
except for when it comes to any
creatures being used to propel the
vehicle whenever a pooled or road
vehicle takes collision damage that same
amount of damage is likely to injure the
creatures that are pulling or ruining it
as well when collision damage occurs
each rowing or pulling creature attempts
a basic reflex save versus the collision
dc of the vehicle that is applying the
damage for example if a carriage suffers
collision damage as a result of
something it does most likely by ramming
into something then each horse pulling
it must make a basic reflex save versus
dc-16 or suffer 2d8 damage if one of
these creatures is incapacitated or
killed the vehicle may slow or lose
control at the gm's discretion
the run over action is one of the main
ways of attacking with a vehicle and
involves driving over or ramming into
enemies
this costs three actions and has the
reckless trait meaning the vehicle's
pilot must succeed at a piloting check
in order to attempt this action we
covered reckless actions in detail back
in part 1 so make sure you go watch that
video if this does not sound familiar if
you succeed then you may move the
vehicle up to double its speed in a
straight line and may inflict damage on
smaller creatures and objects in your
path this is similar to a monster's
trample ability
during this movement you may freely move
the vehicle into the space of any
creatures that are at least two size
categories smaller than the vehicle when
you do so these smaller creatures must
roll basic reflex saves against the
collision dc of the vehicle or suffer
the listed damage
and in addition to running over
creatures this action can also be used
to ram into a target be it a creature or
another vehicle there are a couple key
differences between running over and
ramming into a target first any number
of creatures can be run over but only
one creature or vehicle may be rammed
into each turn
second whereas creatures that are at
least two size categories smaller than
the vehicle may be run over the target
of a ramming attack must be one size
category smaller than the vehicle or
larger
and third by raw running over creatures
does not impede the vehicle's movement
but successfully ramming a target
immediately ends the vehicle's movement
that turn
this doesn't mean that it comes to a
complete stop only that it's movement
ends so carriages that are pulled by
horses have speed scores of 40 and on a
run over action that's double to 80. so
if it could possibly move 80 feet during
a turn that it does the run over action
and it's only moved to 50 feet at the
time that it rams into a target then its
movement ends and it cannot continue
moving the remaining 30 feet that's
provided by the speed score of those
horses pulling it
when a vehicle rams a target that target
gets to attempt a basic reflex save just
like when a smaller creature is run over
if the target is another vehicle then
that vehicle's pilot may roll their
piloting skill as their reflex save
if the target of a ram suffers any
damage then the ramming vehicle and its
pilot each suffer their vehicle's
collision damage there is no save rolled
for the vehicle doing the ramming or for
its pilot they each automatically suffer
the vehicle's listed collision damage
and as previously mentioned when any
damage is applied to a rammed target
then the vehicle's movement immediately
ends
what happens after that is up to the gm
to decide by raw the vehicle's movement
ends but it doesn't say anything about
what happens on the next round the
results of ramming into a person and
ramming into the side of a stone
building are going to be different and
the rules do not specify a result for
every possible situation instead the gm
will need to decide what happens next
does the vehicle keep moving at its
current speed and heading does it glance
into a square to the left or to the
right does it come to a complete stop
all of this will be the gm's call
the gm will also need to decide what
happens to any passengers the rules
state that the ramming vehicle and its
pilot suffer collision damage without
any safes to reduce it and any creatures
pulling or ruining the ramming vehicle
get to make basic reflex saves to reduce
the damage but the rules do not specify
what happens to any other passengers of
the vehicle the rules also don't state
if the pilot and passengers of a vehicle
that you ram into suffer the damage that
their vehicle does or if a vehicle you
ramp into is stopped knocked off course
or slowed down again all of these are
items that the gm will need to make
their own rulings on on a case-by-case
basis
when a vehicle suffers enough damage to
reduce it to its broken threshold which
is usually half of its total hit points
it becomes broken
when this occurs the vehicle suffers an
untyped negative 2 penalty to its armor
class all saves and its collision dc and
the dc of all piloting checks related to
the vehicle increased by 5. also the
broken vehicle's speed score is cut in
half
when a vehicle is reduced to zero hit
points it is destroyed if the vehicle is
in water when this happens then it sinks
if it is flying then it falls and
everyone on board suffers falling damage
and if the vehicle is being pulled or
erode when it is destroyed then all
creatures pulling or rowing it suffer
its collision damage with no save to
reduce it and may also need to be
physically freed from the wreckage as
well
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the how is played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover if you would like to
support this channel and help it grow
the easiest way to do that is by
subscribing and clicking the bell icon
so you get notified when new videos
release and i can always be reached
through twitter and facebook too thanks
for watching take care and happy gaming