this video is brought to you by the
battle zoo bestiary a new book featuring
100 award-winning monsters and the
monster parts system that allows players
to harvest resources from their fallen
foes and craft into custom gear the
battle zoo bestiary is now available at
battlezoo.com
hello and welcome to troops in
pathfinder second edition by how it's
played
[Music]
troops allow a large number of
individuals to function as a single unit
mechanically this has a lot of
advantages rather than having to track a
dozen different creatures the gm only
has to manage one large one and troops
can also allow narrative moments where
the players are overwhelmed by the sheer
number of their foes but if within the
rules they were presented as individuals
they likely would pose literally no
challenge for the heroes but when stated
together as a troop they can be
formidable in this regard troops are not
entirely dissimilar from the swarm
mechanics used when battling large
groups of vermin but there are a few
important distinctions
to illustrate how troops work we'll be
looking at the stat block for a city
guard squadron each individual member of
the city guard is a medium-sized
creature and occupies one square but
when a large group of them gathers
together they may function as a troop
most troops begin gargantuan sized and
occupy 16 squares on the map typically
this is represented as a four by four
square area but it can also be eight by
two or other configuration as long as
all of the squares are connected
there's no harder rule that dictates how
many individuals make up the troop it
may be easiest to think of this as a
group of 16 soldiers forming the troop
but that is not a hard rule
also it's important to note that as a
troop suffers damage it shrinks in size
which makes sense as members of the
troop are whittled away the troop itself
becomes smaller and smaller this is
represented in the rules by including
two hit point thresholds we see here
that a city guard squadron starts with
75 hit points and a parenthetical noting
16 squares
and then we see the two thresholds the
first says 50 and 12 squares meaning
that after the city guard squadron has
suffered 25 points of damage it shrinks
in size to 12 squares and after it
suffers another 25 points of damage it
hits its second threshold and shrinks to
only eight squares
there are some special rules regarding
how troops suffer damage first no
individual single target effect can push
a troop past two thresholds no matter
how much damage it would normally
inflict so for example if the city guard
squadron had 55 hit points and was hit
by a single target attack that managed
to deal 35 points of damage which would
normally push the squadron past both his
first threshold of 50 and its second
threshold of 25 leaving it with only 20
points left
instead that attack would only lower the
troop to 26 hit points one point higher
than the second threshold and note that
this only applies to single target
attacks not to damaging area effects or
other effects that have more than one
target which makes sense decapitating
any one member of a troop is unlikely to
have such a profound effect on the troop
as making it shrink 8 squares in size
every time a troop is reduced to one of
his thresholds the listed value for that
threshold becomes the troops new maximum
hit point value
meaning if the citiguard squadron was
reduced beyond his first threshold of 50
and left with 40 hit points and then
received 20 points of healing it would
only be able to heal back up to 50 hit
points its most recently passed
threshold and any excess healing would
be lost in order to restore its size and
maximum hit points a troop needs to
spend down time to use long-term
treatment on casualties or to recruit
new members to replace those that were
killed
at zero hit points the troop is reduced
to four squares and can no longer
function as a unit at this point the
troop is defeated and its remaining
members either flee surrender or are
effortlessly killed depending on the
troops nature and the disposition of the
players
for any effect that doesn't deal damage
it only applies to the troop if its area
encompasses all of the squares that the
troop occupies if the effect has a
smaller area then it usually has no
effect on the troop i say usually
because there is an important exception
to this if a non-damaging effect can
target at least four creatures or cover
at least four squares that are occupied
by the troop and if this effect would
render the targets unable to act for at
least one round or to flee or have
similar debilitating effect where they
would not be able to do what they would
reasonably want to do on their turn then
the troop is reduced to its next hit
point threshold causing it to lose 4
squares of its size
if an effect would inflict damage and
cause 4 squares of the troop to become
incapacitated then you would apply the
damage first and then lower the troop to
his next threshold thus making it
possible for the troop to be dropped to
threshold by this one effect
so for example say a player casts
command at the troop the spell only
targets one enemy and therefore has no
effect on the troop even if it was to
critically fail a safe making one
soldier temporarily incapacitated by a
spell will not have a significant impact
on the troop as a whole but if the
player heightens the command spell to
5th level it now targets 10 creatures
and any non-damaging spell that targets
at least 4 creatures does have the
potential to damage the troop if the
result of the spell effect causes the
targets to be unable to reasonably act
for a turn so if a player cast command
heightened the fifth level and told the
squadron to flee and the squadron
critically failed their will save then
the troop would be dropped to his next
hit point threshold and lower its size
by four squares to represent the portion
of the squadron that ran away
and note that because troops function as
a single large creature you do not roll
individual will saves against a spell
like this you would only roll once for
the troop
all troops have access to a special
ability called form up this costs one
action and essentially allows the troop
to reconfigure itself and adjust its
formation when a troop uses form up the
gm selects one of his occupied squares
and all of its other squares may move to
any unoccupied space within 15 feet of
that chosen square as long as all of the
troop squares are connected
so a troop shaped like this could spin
one action on form up to arrange itself
like this
or like this
the way a troop moves may vary from
troop to troop but each stat block
should include a section on troop
movement most of them work the same way
so let's look again at the city guard
squadron as an example
here it says that whenever the squad
uses stride it first gets to use form up
for free to condense it into a square
shape
and then it moves as if it was a single
creature of that size this is done for
simplicity instead of having elaborate
rules specifically for the irregular
shape of a troop they just say to
squeeze it all into a square shape and
then use the already established
movement rules for a single creature
that is that size
what this means is that a troop like
this cannot move as a line
but instead would first form up into a
square shape like this
and then move as if it was a single
gargantuan-sized creature
in a troop that has been pushed past its
second threshold that only occupies
eight squares would form up into a three
by three square area and move as if it
was a single huge size creature
otherwise the rules are unchanged it
would stride as usual spending one
action to move 25 feet and if any
portion of the troops area enters a
square with difficult terrain it would
be affected as usual
there really aren't any special rules
for how troops function in combat but
there are a few shared similarities
troops function like any normal monster
with an armor class and saving throws to
defend itself against incoming attacks
and they also have resistances
immunities and weaknesses especially
weaknesses against area and splash
damage
and each troop has its own attacks
listed in their stat block most of these
attacks will be some manner of area
attack as every member of the troop
strikes at once against any enemies
within their range and therefore most
troop attacks target reflex and not
armor class for example city guard
squadrons have two attacks fire crossbow
and lower halberds
fire crossbows takes two actions and
allows the troop to fire their crossbows
into a 10-foot burst area within 120
feet of them
unlike regular crossbow attacks this one
is defended with a reflex instead of
with armor class and note that when the
troop shrinks in size so does the area
of this attack
and for melee combat the city guard
squadron can use lower halberds this
attack targets all enemies within 10
feet of any of the troop spaces and
deals an amount of damage based on the
number of actions spent and again like
with most troop attacks this is resisted
by reflux instead of armor class
those are the general rules for troops i
will say that there are not a lot of
hard rules provided for troops they
don't receive a detailed write-up as one
might expect and instead we only have a
couple of glossary entries to guide us
as such there will likely be situations
you encounter that there are no hard
rules for and you will need to improvise
and make your best rulings as needed
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that is by subscribing and
clicking the bell icon so you get
notified when new videos release and i
can always be reached through twitter
and facebook too thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]