this video is brought to you by battle
zoo ancestry's dragons the book that
lets you play as a dragon written by
pathfinder veteran mark seifer this book
adds over 45 new dragon playable
ancestries to pathfinder second edition
now available at battlezoo.com
hello and welcome to chase mechanics in
pathfinder 2nd edition
the normal rules provided in the core
rules work well for tracking movement
during encounters and across short
distances that can fit on a game map but
for longer more epic scenes the gm may
want to use the chase mechanics found in
the game mastery guide
the chase system focuses on turning
moments where characters are either
chasing racing or being chased into more
complex and interesting scenes than
simply counting how many squares of many
can move on his turn
this system moves away from the focus
being whoever has the highest speed
score wins and towards whoever can best
overcome the obstacles in their way wins
these obstacles can be just about
anything that would prevent a character
from easily progressing a chase in a
city might have obstacles like a fence
blocking off an alleyway a funeral
procession blocking the road or guards
on the lookout and a chase in the
wilderness might have obstacles like
muddy trails a wasp nest or dense
thickets and thorns
each obstacle notes the number of chase
points that need to be earned in order
to overcome them and should also provide
at least two actions that can be used to
earn chase points
these are usually skills but can also be
perception checks saving throws or even
an attack role depending on the
circumstance
typically the number of chase points
needed to overcome an obstacle will be
one per player and the group works as a
team accumulating points for the entire
group rather than individually
so for example if the players are being
chased by guards through a city the gm
might present a crowded market square as
an obstacle if we look at the stat block
for a crowd we see it takes four chase
points to overcome and i believe this is
assuming a standard four player party
and it says that players can use either
acrobatics or athletics against dc 15
or society against dc 13 to navigate
their way past the crowd
although chases do not progress in 6
second rounds like with encounter mode
there is still an initiative order and
characters act in turns
whichever team is being chased goes
first in initiative so if the players
are being chased by guards each of those
players get to take a single turn and
then everyone chasing them takes a turn
note that by default the chase roles in
2nd edition assume that the entire party
of players sticks together and works as
a team to overcome each obstacle one at
a time rather than managing the
challenges individually and having some
players progress faster than others
on each player's turn they describe
within the narrative what they wish to
do to progress past the obstacle and
they get to roll one check
in the case of crowds acrobatics
athletics and society are offered as
suggestions a success earns the team one
chase point
a critical success earns two chase
points and a critical failure cost the
team one chase point
once enough chase points have been
earned the party as a whole makes their
way past the obstacle and progresses to
the next one
there may also be times when certain
actions just automatically earn a
success for example a player might cast
a spell that makes the obstacle
inconsequential maybe they cast a spell
and fly over the crowd in such a case
that player automatically earns one
chase point they don't roll a check and
they cannot fail but they also cannot
earn a critical success
also note that each turn during a chase
may take several minutes depending on
the nature of the obstacle and the
distance being traveled between the
obstacles and that should be taken into
account when managing the duration of
spells also note that players should
always have the freedom to do whatever
they believe is most appropriate given
the situation maybe a player wants to
use intimidation to demand the crowd
move aside and let them through
or a player wants to throw some coins to
the side so people move away from where
they're running or since this is a
marketplace crowd they might use their
lore merchant skill to find a different
shortcut through the stalls
these are all valid options and should
be encouraged even if they're not listed
as available skills in the obstacle stat
block these cases will call for some
improvisation by the gm who will need to
assign an appropriate check to be rolled
and a dc for it in many cases the dc may
be slightly higher than those
represented on the obstacle step block
as they are likely not the most obvious
or simplest solutions
also be aware that obstacles should be
treated as individual adversaries
meaning that chase points are not
carried over from one obstacle to the
next however if an obstacle is defeated
and there are players who have not yet
taken their turns this round play
continues and those players may attempt
to overcome the next challenge the first
step in designing a chase scene is to
determine what type of chase is going to
be
in a chase down the players are trying
to catch someone who is fleeing from
them typically the enemies in a chase
down will start one objective ahead of
the players and will go first in
initiative
if the players can move to the same
obstacle as the enemies before the
enemies complete the final obstacle then
they catch them
the second type of chase is run away
this is a reverse chase down in a
runaway the players are attempting to
flee from chasing enemies the players
lose this chase scene if their pursuers
ever catch up to them and they win the
runaway chase if they complete the final
obstacle or are ever at least three
obstacles ahead of their pursuers before
being caught
the third type of chase is beat the
clock this occurs when the players are
either in a race where neither group is
trying to catch the other or when there
is a time limit such as outrunning a
natural disaster or a collapsing dungeon
typically in a beat the clock scene
there is a time limit noted in a number
of rounds and the players must finish
the final obstacle before that time runs
out a good guideline when building a
beat the clock chase is to design one
obstacle per round of the time limit
and the last type of chase is the
competitive chase as the name implies
this is when the party and their enemies
are both chasing after something whether
it be a third person who is fling from
both groups or they are trying to get to
the finish line of a race first this
works like beat the clock except instead
of a time limit the scene ends when
either party finishes the final obstacle
or catches their target
and since both the players and their
enemies are pursuers they may need to
roll initiative for each group to
determine which of those groups goes
first there are no hard rules for this
so the gm will need to determine what
the modifiers for the initiative checks
will be if any
once you know what type of chase you'll
be running it's time to build the
obstacles a short chase should have
about six obstacles 8 for a medium chase
and long chases call for about 10
obstacles
when choosing obstacles trying to build
a variety that will allow everyone an
opportunity to shine not just experts in
athletics and acrobatics
once you have selected the obstacles for
the scene assign two proposed methods of
overcoming each objective to earn chase
points and again try to use a variety of
options if you've already selected
stealth as one of the options then
assigning thievery as the other option
doesn't really help because characters
who are good at thievery are very likely
the same characters who are good at
stealth on the other hand offering
athletics as an alternative gives a
fighter who's terrible at stealth a way
to help out
also don't assume that every obstacle is
a physical threat especially in an urban
environment you might need diplomacy or
intimidation to convince a crowd to move
out of the way or nature to find the
easiest path through a mess of brambles
you can also use saving throws or
attacks to overcome obstacles as well
maybe there's a shortcut through a
burning building but you have to pass a
fortitude save to make it through or
there is a plank suspended over a stream
and a ranged attack roll will allow you
to throw a dagger to cut the rope and
drop the plank so you can run across
when you set the dc's for an obstacle
you'll typically be using simple dc's
but can also use a proficiency rank
appropriate for the party's level if you
want the obstacle to be more challenging
and is a good guideline for one of the
checks to have an easy or very easy
adjustment to his dc
and again always allow your players to
improvise the two solutions that you
provide with the obstacle are likely the
most obvious solutions but if a player
wants to try something else let them
just set a dc as normal but don't adjust
it to be easy or very easy because if a
player is choosing to do something
different then they likely have a higher
bonus to that check than the checks that
are offered by the obstacle
chases in 2nd edition assume that the
party of players sticks together and
those who are strong in the challenge
help those who are not but there is a
variant option provided where it's every
player for themselves in a solo chase
the players act individually instead of
as a group meaning that they can split
up some players may move through the
obstacles faster than the others or even
split up if the chase is designed with a
branching structure the downside of this
is it increases the likelihood of one
player getting stuck on an obstacle that
they are not well suited for when
running a chase scene using the solo
rules each character only needs to earn
one chase point to overcome any obstacle
and on a critical success they overcome
their current obstacle and gain a plus 2
circumstance bonus against the next
obstacle
when running a chase scene is often
easiest to write the details of each
obstacle on index cards and use them
with miniatures to track the player's
progression
each card should display the two
suggested means of overcoming the
obstacle but always remember that
players should not be limited to these
two suggestions they may be the most
obvious solutions but if the player
wants to try something else let them you
might also find yourself in a situation
where the players get stuck on an
obstacle when this happens a good
suggestion is to let them progress after
their third failed attempt the
explanation could be that they find some
other way around the obstacle or an
external force like a helpful npc
arrives to render them assistance
usually it's best for the final obstacle
of a chase scene to be something
terminal a finish line of sorts if the
players are chasing a bandit maybe the
final obstacle of the scene leads to a
hideout if the pcs ever occupy the same
obstacle as the bandit then they catch
him and the scene transitions into a
combat encounter if the bandit overcomes
the final obstacle before the players
catch him then he rushes into the
hideout and the scene changes into a
dungeon crawl as the players investigate
the hideout and typically if the person
or party that is being pursued ever gets
three obstacles ahead of their pursuers
then the pursuers lose track of them and
they get away
so there you have it as always i'd like
to take a quick moment to thank everyone
who supports this channel by liking the
video subscribing to the channel
subscribing to the patreon leaving
comments sharing the videos with your
friends everything the community does to
support me is greatly appreciated and
with that thanks for watching take care
and happy gaming