[Music]
hello and welcome to the influence
system in Pathfinder 2nd edition
influence is an optional subsystem
included in the game mastery guide that
allows players to gain favor with an NPC
this system is ideal for social
encounter situations where multiple
checks over a given time will be needed
rather than one or two diplomacy or
intimidation checks and this also
provides ways for all players to
contribute to success rather than just
allowing that one player who's an expert
in diplomacy to do all the work while
the rest of the table just sits and
stares and waits for the next scene the
influence system divides a social scene
into a number of rounds which can be of
varying lengths from 15 minutes to an
hour per round
and the number of rounds imposes a time
limit for the encounter for example if
the players are enjoying a six course
meal with a group of visiting diplomats
then the GM might determine that this is
a six round social encounter once that
time limit of six rounds is complete
then the dinner is over and the social
encounter ends the goal of the influence
system is for players to earn as many
influence points as possible before this
time limit is up during each round every
player gets one turn in which they can
either use the influence action to gain
influence points or they can use the
Discover action to learn beneficial
information that could Aid someone
else's influence check
when a player takes the influence action
they role play what they say and do
during the social interaction they gain
favor with the other party at the end of
that role play they make a skill check
this will often be a diplomacy check but
could also be a deception check if
they're lying or even skills that are
not thought of as social checks for
example a Bard might make a performance
check and play the national anthem of a
visiting dignitary to gain their
attention and approval the DC for these
chicks can be found in the NPC's
influence stat block or determined by
the GM as usual for example a landlord
is threatened to evict a theater troop
from a rundown building he owns if a
player uses their accounting lure skill
that's a dc-16 check if they use
crafting this also dc-16 intimidation
and performance are both dc20 diplomacy
is dc22 and deception is dc24 if a
player attempts to use a skill to
influence the NPC that is not listed in
their influence stat block or they use
one of the Liz's skills but in a
different way than is specified then the
game mastery guide recommends applying
the highest listed DC which in this case
would be dc24 and these DCS may be
further modified according to the NPC's
resistances and weaknesses in this
example appeals to sympathy increase the
DC of the check by two and Performing
one of the landlord's favorite songs or
plays reduces the DC for performance
checks by two on a success is the player
earns one influence point for their
party a critical success earns two
points nothing happens on a failure and
on a critical failure the party loses
one influence point
the second action players can use and
influence encounters is discover when a
player takes a discover action they
study the NPC to try and learn their
preferences what do they like and
dislike or what kind of arguments will
help sway them this is a secret check so
the GM rolls a perception check or other
appropriate skill for the player in
secret and compares the total to DC's
that are listed in the NPC's influence
stat block going back to our example
beneficial information about the
landlord may be gained by successful
Mercantile lore perception and Society
skill checks at their listed DCS on a
success the player learns one of the
following which skill that can influence
the NPC has the lowest DC
one of the target's biases one of their
resistances or one of their weaknesses
with a critical success the player
learns two of those bits of information
and they could be two bits of the same
type of information
on a failure nothing happens and on a
critical failure the GM provides false
information such as the NPC is weak to
something that they're actually
resistant to in many regards the
Discover action is very much like a
recall knowledge action
the NPC's influence step block will also
list the conditions for success and what
each total of influence points earns the
players at the end of the scene in the
case of our example with Mr mullweather
the landlord if the players earn four
influence points he will give the
theater troop one week to come up with
the money they owe him before evicting
them if the players earn six points
he'll give them one month and if the
players earn at least eight influence
points then Mr Maul weather grows a
heart reduces their rent and forgives
half of their debt
the game mastery guide does not provide
a lot of hard rules for creating your
own influence encounters but here are a
few key points that may help
influence encounters are assigned to
levels just like combat encounters and
the example of Mr Mall weather that
influence encounter is a third level
challenge so per the DC's by level table
the DC's for The Challenge start with a
base of 18 and then are modified
downward for skills he is susceptible to
like accounting lore and crafting and
modified upward for skills that he is
more alert to like diplomacy and
deception it is recommended that
diplomacy be included in the list of
influence skills for all of the NPCs but
with an increased DC to encourage
players to use discover actions to
uncover other means and not simply rely
on diplomacy as the solution for all
social situations
there is no guidance given for the
number of influence points needed for
success but looking at the example in
the game mastery guide as well as a few
published Adventures that use the system
Point thresholds for rewards tend to be
2 points four points and six points in
most cases regardless of the time limit
and bumped up to four six and eight
points for harder encounters or when the
entire party focuses on one NPC instead
of spreading out to influence several
different NPCs at the same time each NPC
should have at least one resistance and
one weakness that modifies DC's by two
but this modifier can also be set to 5
for extreme cases also NPCs may have a
resistance that causes the players to
lose a point or even in their
discussions if a certain action is taken
or a certain subject is mentioned
so that's it for a quick look at the
influence system from the game mastery
guide for more information about social
encounters see my video on diplomacy and
intimidation a link is provided in the
description and as always I want to take
a brief moment to say thank you to
everyone who supports me whether that's
by clicking the like button subscribing
to the channel subscribing to the
patreon buying a super thanks it all
adds up and I greatly appreciate your
support with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]
thank you