hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents just the basics of perception
in Pathfinder second edition just the
basics is a new series that takes some
of our longer courses and condenses all
of the need-to-know information into
about 10 minutes if you would like to
see the full presentation on perception
with all of the extra detail and
examples you can find it linked in the
description
perception is a measure of what your
character knows about their environment
as well as what other creatures know
about your character although it is
technically not a skill its bonus is
calculated the same way and functions
very much like a skill in most regards
whenever the GM needs to test if you
notice something they will roll a
perception check for you in secret and
compare that chick's total to a DC such
as the stealth DC of a hiding enemy
perception is largely determined by your
senses all senses are categorized as
being either priests licenses imprecise
senses or vague senses priests licenses
allow you to perceive your surroundings
in great detail vision is a precise
sense imprecise senses allow you to
perceive the presence of something but
not with the accuracy in detail of a
priest license for example hearing is an
imprecise sense and vague senses might
at the geums discretion allow you to
perceive the vague presence of something
but not much else
for example smell is a vague sense for
humans the amount of information you can
perceive about a target is measured by
its state of awareness relative to you
all creatures and objects exist in at
least one of four states of awareness
which are unnoticed undetected hidden
and observed when an enemy is unnoticed
you have no idea that it's nearby when
an enemy is undetected you don't know
what space that enemy occupies this
could be because you're not even aware
that the creature is present and
therefore it is both unnoticed and
undetected or you could suspect the
creatures present but not know exactly
where it is in which case that target
would be undetected
for example say you're in a dark cave
and you can hear the sounds of movement
nearby but you can't see what's making
the sounds or know exactly where they
are when dealing with an undetected
threat
you are flat-footed against all of their
attacks and although you're not certain
where the enemy is you can take your
best guess and attack into the space
that you think they're in and hope for
the best
when you do this the GM will make your
attacker roll for you in secret as well
as also rolling a flat check vs. DC 11
unless you're making an area attack on a
failed flat check your attack misses
regardless of how high the attack roll
was but the GM will not tell you why you
miss they won't tell you that it was
because you rolled lower than an armored
class or because you failed at a flat
check they would just tell you whether
or not you hit an enemy in that square
that you're targeting
the next state of awareness is called
hidden when a creature is hidden from
you you know exactly which space they're
in but you can't see them attacking a
hidden creature works just like it does
with attacking undetected targets except
you make the attack roll and the flat
check against DC 11 instead of the GM
rolling those for you in secret hidden
is the highest state of awareness that
you can achieve while using only an
imprecise sense like hearing
and the final state of awareness is
observed when you can see a target it is
observed there are no special bonuses
penalties or conditions imposed by an
observed target however it is possible
for an observed target to also have the
concealed condition if you can see them
but not see them clearly when attacking
a target that is concealed you must make
a flat check exactly as you do when
attacking a hidden target but the DC is
only 5 instead of 11 and unlike with
undetected or hidden creatures you are
not flat-footed against a concealed
enemy also only a precise sense like
vision can be used to observe a target
when a player wishes to improve their
awareness of a target they use the seek
action this costs one action and a
perception check is rowed in secret by
the GM that chicks total is contested by
the stealth DC's of any hidden or
undetected creatures in your field of
view any undetected creature that you
succeed against becomes hidden from you
instead of undetected and any hidden
creature that you succeed against
becomes observed by you essentially
success on a seek action moves the
target one step closer to being observed
and on a critical success the target
moves two steps and becomes observed
this however is limited according to
which since the character is using to
seek and also by lighting conditions if
they were using vision
the last major element that a fixed
perception is lighting there are three
broad categories for a lighting in
Pathfinder bright light dim light and
darkness bright light is the default
norm and is created by sunlight in other
effects like spells and lanterns dim
light is an area that has illumination
provided by a light source that's weaker
than bright light candle lit rooms a
clear night sky with a full moon and
stars and standing 30 feet away from a
lit torch are all examples of dim light
conditions creatures and objects in dim
light can be observed but have the
concealed condition unless the creature
observing them has low light vision or
dark vision and the third category of
lighting is darkness any creatures are
objects within an area of darkness gain
the hidden or undetected conditions
unless the seeker has dark vision or a
precise sense other than vision
creatures without dark vision gained the
blinded condition when perceiving areas
of darkness
and those are just the basics as a
reminder this series of abbreviated
videos is meant to support not replace
the full-length courses if you have any
questions about how any of this works
make sure you view the original
full-length video that is in the
description and as always I'd like to
take a moment to thank all of our
patrons these videos would not be
possible without their continued
generosity and support members of the
basics for gamers patreon community
receive special benefits like getting to
vote on the topics we cover and also get
to see these videos one week before
everyone else visit the links shown in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and
we'll see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder