hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents just the basics of stealth in
Pathfinder second edition just the
basics is a special series that takes
some of my longer courses and condenses
all of the need-to-know information into
about ten minutes if you would like to
see the full presentation on stealth
with all of the extra details in depth
and examples you can find it linked in
the description
when a character wishes to avoid being
noticed they use the stealth skill the
key ability score for stealth is
dexterity and all applications of
stealth can be used untrained typically
when you roll a stealth check it is
contested by your enemy's perception DC
which is ten plus their perception
modifier and on their turn when they
attempt to find you if they roll a
perception check contested by your
stealth DC not the total of any previous
stealth check that you may have rolled
to hide in normal circumstances there
would not be a challenge of roles where
one person rolls their stealth skill and
another person rolls their perception
instead one party makes a role and that
is compared against the other party
static DC
there are three applications of stealth
in the core rules the first of which is
called conceal and object when you wish
to hide something you use conceal an
object this can either be something you
are carrying with you like a dagger up
your sleeve or it could be something
that you hide in the environment like a
secret note planted under the roots of a
tree stump if you are hiding a small
item that you are carrying the GM rolls
your stealth in secret and compares that
to the perception dc's of everyone who
observes you if your check total is
higher than their perception dc's then
they do not notice that you're hiding
anything and note you only roll this
check one time not once per observing
creature if a creature is actively
searching for you for example there are
an alert guard keeping a watchful eye
out then they roll a perception check
against your stealth DC instead of
relying on their perception DC this
works much the same way when hiding an
object in the environment instead of
carrying it with you except you do not
roll a still check instead you spend one
action to hide the object and if anyone
performs a seek action in that area
their perception check will be
challenged by your stealth DC and note
that conceal an object is for hiding
something you already possess if you
want to pick something up without
anybody noticing you you would use the
palm and object application of the
thievery skill
the second application of the stealth
skill is called hide hide is used when
you wish to lower your state of
detection from observed to hidden if
you're not familiar with his terms or
you need a refresher I encourage you to
go view my videos on perception and then
resume this video afterwards when you
take the hide action you roll a stealth
check and compare the total to the
perception disease of anyone who is
observing you as long as you are either
concealed from them or have a source of
cover between you and them if you are
not concealed or do not have a source of
cover then you have nowhere to hide in
the attempt automatically fails if you
do have cover then you add the covers
bonus to your stealth check but only for
those creatures who are observing you
from the other side of that cover while
hiding you immediately become observed
if you use any actions other than sneak
step or another hide action now there
are two exceptions to this and the first
of those is the strike action if you
strike a target while hidden from them
you resolve the attack first and don't
become observed until after the attack
is rolled this means the target is still
flat-footed for the attack and therefore
the attacker can use abilities like
sneak attack with their strike action
but once the attack is resolved the
hiding character obviously becomes
observed in the second of the two
exceptions is the provision in the rules
that states the GM might allow you to
perform an unobtrusive action without
being noticed
possibly requiring another stealth check
for example the seek action if the
hidden character wishes to perform the
seek action I think in a lot of the
cases the GM would agree that seeking
meets the definition of unobtrusive and
not make you instantly become detected
when performing that action and this
provision of possibly requiring a
now they're stealth check to perform the
action could be used by the GM to allow
a player to do things like quietly
opening a door without being seen or
some other interact actions as with
everything else is completely up to the
GM to make those calls also note that
you may not move out of your current
space as part of a hide action hide is
for staying in place and changing your
state of detection from observed to hit
him
but once your detection state is hidden
you can then use sneak to lower your
detection state to undetected and move
away from your location once you declare
that you are sneaking you may move up to
half your speed at the end of your
movement the GM rolls your stealth check
for you in secret and compares the
result to the perception disease of
everyone who you are undetected or
hidden from at the start of your sneak
action if you have cover or greater
cover throughout the entire movement
then the GM adds your cover bonus to the
stealth check at the end of your
movement you instantly become observed
by any creature who you do not have
cover from or the concealed condition
against everyone else has their
perception DC's compared to your stealth
check total and you gain the undetected
state with anyone you wrote a success
against if your check fails against a
creature you have cover or concealment
against then you become hidden to them
they can't see you but you must have
made a sound that gave away your
location if you critically fail then the
creature is able to observe you as long
as they have a line of sight to your
space and just like with the actions
we've already discussed once you are
undetected following a sneak action you
become observed as soon as you take any
action other than hide
step or another sneak unless the GM
rules the action is unobtrusive
and those are just the basics as a
reminder this series of abbreviated
videos is meant to support not replace
the full-length courses if you have any
questions about how any of this works
make sure you view the original
full-length video that is in the
description and as always I'd like to
take a moment to thank all of our
patrons these videos would not be
possible without their continued
generosity and support members are the
basics for gamers patreon community
receive special benefits like getting to
vote on the topics we cover and also get
to see these videos one week before
everyone else visit the links shown in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and
we'll see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder