hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents just the basics of afflictions
in Pathfinder second edition just the
basics is a special series that takes
some of my longer courses and condenses
all of the need-to-know information into
about 10 minutes if you would like to
see the full presentation on afflictions
with all of the extra detail and
examples you can find it linked in the
description
an affliction is any condition that
infects a character over a period of
time and progresses through stages the
most common examples of afflictions are
curses diseases in poisons all
afflictions start with a saving through
which is usually fortitude but could
also be will especially in the case of
curses when you are first exposed to an
affliction you attempt the listed save
if you succeed then the affliction has
no effect but if you fail the save you
become infected or poisoned or cursed or
suffer whatever other fun the affliction
has in store for you some but not all
afflictions have an onset period this is
basically a delay if an infliction list
an onset period of one hour then if you
fail the initial saving through nothing
else happens until an hour passes think
of it as an incubation period like when
you get the flu you don't start feeling
the effects of catching the flu for
about two days after you fail your
real-world fortitude save so the flu has
an onset period of about 48 hours and if
there is no on set period listed then
the affliction takes effect immediately
next let's talk about stages afflictions
are divided up into a number of distinct
stages usually three each stage has an
effect listed followed by an amount of
time in parentheses so when you feel the
initial saving through you then wait
through the duration of the onset period
and once that passes you gain stage 1 of
the affliction you immediately suffer
the effects of that stage and then treat
the amount of time in parentheses as
another onset period so if the
affliction says stage 1 24 poison
damaged and sickened one and in
parentheses next to that is one minute
then as soon as you gain stage 1 you
suffer 1.d4 poison damage you gain the
sickened
one condition and then nothing else
related to the affliction happens for
another minute you do not suffer one day
for poison damage every round for that
one minute nor do you roll any saving
throws during this time but once the
time is up then you do need to roll a
new saving through if you succeed then
you lose the current stage and you gain
one stage lower and if you ever gain
stage zero then you're cured in the
affliction has no further effects if you
fail the save then you lose the current
stage and gain one stage higher also the
initial save and potentially the damage
if there is no onset period both may
occur on the enemy's turn when you're
first exposed to the affliction but all
other saves in damage from afflictions
occur at the end of the suffering
character's turns and is worth
mentioning that critical successes in
critical failures count double when you
critically succeed a saving through you
lose the current stage and gain the
stage two lore and when you critically
fail a savings through you lose the
current stage and gain the stage that is
to hire so if your stage one and
critically fail your savings through you
skip over stage two ignore all of its
effects and gain stage three but note
that you never go to a stage higher than
the afflictions listed maximum if stage
three is the highest the affliction
lists then failing are critically
failing a serious throw wall at stage
three means you lose stage three then
you gain stage three again you repeat
its effects but don't create a
theoretical stage for in the final key
stat that we should talk about is
maximum duration as you may suspect this
is the longest period of time that you
can be infected by an affliction an
important note here is that the maximum
duration does not include the time spent
during the onset period it only covers
the amount of time you're actually
suffering from the affliction if an
affliction has an onset period of 30
and a maximum duration of two hours then
two and a half hours after you fail your
initial savings through the affliction
wears off
there are a few other special
circumstances that we should discuss too
for instance what happens when you're
exposed to an affliction while you're
already suffering from that same
affliction this is one of the rare times
where it's important to know what kind
of affliction you're dealing with if
it's a curse or a disease then multiple
exposures have no effect but if it's a
poison then multiple exposures require a
new savings throw for each exposure and
if you fail you'll lose the current
stage and gain one higher or on a
critical fail you lose the current stage
and gain the stage to higher we should
also talk about the conditions you
receive from afflictions if you are able
to remove that specific condition while
under the effects of the affliction just
be aware that removing the condition has
no effect on the affliction so say an
affliction gives you the second
condition and you remove the second
condition by retching then it only
removes that one condition and has no
effect on the affliction that caused
sickened the affliction continues as
normal and the opposite of that is also
true curing an affliction does not
necessarily cure the conditions that the
affliction caused if you suffer a
condition from an affliction and that
condition has a longer duration than the
maximum duration of the affliction that
caused it then that condition persists
even after the affliction goes away and
the last special circumstance I want to
talk about is virulent afflictions these
are especially nasty afflictions that
operate the same way as normal
afflictions except they require two
consecutive successes to remove the
current stage and gain one stage lower
or one critical success gains one stage
lower instead of two lower
and those are just the basics as a
reminder this series of abbreviated
videos is meant to support not replace
the full-length courses if you have any
questions about how any of this works
make sure you view the original
full-length video that is in the
description and as always I'd like to
take a moment to thank all of our
patrons these videos would not be
possible without their continued
generosity and support members of the
basics for gamers patreon community
receive special benefits like getting to
vote on the topics we cover and also get
to see these videos one week before
everyone else visit the links shown in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and
we'll see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder