hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents
just the basics of thievery in
pathfinder second edition
just the basics is a special series that
takes some of my longer courses
and condenses all of the need to know
information into about 10 minutes
if you would like to see the full
presentation on thievery with all of the
extra detail and examples
you can find it linked in the
description
the first thievery action is called palm
and object
and is used whenever a player wishes to
pick something up without being noticed
for example they try to take an item
from a store without the shopkeeper
catching them
to do this the player rolls a thievery
skill check which is contested
by the perception dc's of everyone
within view of the theft
if the player succeeds then that
creature does not notice them taking the
item
if they fail then the creature notices
and is up to the gm to determine how
they act
and a few other points about palm and
object
first it is intended that the item being
palmed
be of negligible bulk but larger items
might be possible to be palmed with the
gm's permission
and also likely with a suitable increase
in difficulty as well
second the item is picked up no matter
what
the character can't decide that they
don't want to take the item once they
fail the check and realize they've been
noticed
third palm and object is used for
picking up
an item without being noticed but if you
wish to hide an object you are already
carrying
you would use the conceal and object
application of the stealth skill
in fact a gm may require a player to
make both
checks in a lot of circumstances they
would spin an action
to palm an object when they pick up an
item in a store without being noticed
that would be a theory check and would
then spend
another action for conceal an object a
stealth check when they attempt to walk
past the shopkeeper and out the door
and last the item must be unattended
unattended basically means is not in the
possession of another character
you could not use palm and object if you
wanted to pick someone's pockets
for that you would use the second fevery
action
steal the steel action is used to take a
small
object from another character without
being noticed as with palm and object
this is intended to be an
item of negligible bulk also you
automatically
fail if the target you are stealing from
is in combat or on guard
mechanically this works almost the same
as palm and object
the character trying to steal rolls a
thievery check
that is contested by the perception dc
of the target and others within view
and note that the standard steel action
assumes
that the item that's being taken is
loosely worn
or easily accessible and the gm will
apply penalties to the thievery check as
appropriate for example a negative 5
penalty if the item is not
out in the open but is instead inside of
a pocket
or apply a larger penalty if the item is
buried in someone's backpack
or other circumstance
the third thievery action is called
disable a device
as the name implies this action is used
when a character wishes to manipulate a
piece of machinery
in such a way that it no longer
functions as intended
the most common use of disable a device
is
disarming traps most uses of disable a
device
require the use of thieves tools this
requires
trained proficiency and costs two
actions
then the player roll is a thievery check
versus a dc set by the gm
most devices require multiple successes
to disable
on a successful check the player gains
one success
towards disabling that device on a
critical success
they gain two successes towards
disabling the device
plus they leave no trace of their
tampering and can re-arm the device
later if they choose on a failure no
progress is made towards disabling the
device and on a critical failure
they trigger the device
the last thieve reaction works almost
identically to disable a device
but is specifically intended for
disabling locks
just like with disabling a device pick a
lock
requires you to be at least trained in
thievery
and costs two actions per attempt
you must have thieves tools to pick the
lock and
just like devices locks may require
multiple successes to open
the player rolls a thievery check versus
a dc
set by the gm or by the lock in question
on a successful check they gain one
success towards opening the lock
on a critical success they gain two
successes towards
opening the lock and leave no evidence
of their tampering
and on a failure no progress is made
towards opening the lock
and on a critical failure they break
their thieves tools
and one last note it is possible to use
improvised
thieves tools for example maybe a
hairpin but
it is considered as shoddy meaning you
suffer
a negative two to any checks made
with that improvised tool
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basicsforgamers patreon
community receive special benefits
like getting to vote on the topics that
we cover in the future
and also they get to see these videos
one week and ad free before
everybody else visit the link shown on
the left of the screen
and in the description if you'd like to
know more about becoming a patron
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon
so you get notified when new videos
release
and we can always be reached through our
twitter and facebook pages too
thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
pathfinder