hi everybody dave here with a review of
pathfinder 2nd edition's
latest hardback release the lost omens
pathfinder society guide
this book releases today and full
disclosure paizo did provide me an
advanced copy of it for reviewing
but this is not a paid advertisement and
i will be providing my unbiased opinions
so first let's talk about numbers this
is
the fourth book in the lost humans line
it retails for 34.99 and has 127 pages
of content
now that price is three dollars cheaper
than the lost omens world guide
so it is nice to see pizza settling in
on this lower price point rather than
inflating it
however at 127 pages of content
this offering has just a little bit less
between the covers
than the previous lost omen books which
were around 135 pages
you can also purchase the pdf version
from paizo.com
for 24.99 now what do you get for your
25 or 35 dollars
if you've read any of the previous lost
um books then you know what you're in
for
this is a setting book high on flavor
and fuel for your imagination with new
player options sprinkled throughout
and all of it is focused on the
pathfinder society
and is worth mentioning that this book
is about the organization that exists
within the game's narrative
and not the real world organized play
campaign
although most of the content in this
book is applicable to
those games as well the book's content
is divided into four
chapters the first chapter provides an
introduction to the pathfinder society
detailing its history from its humble
beginnings as a social club for
adventurers to the global power that it
is today
it provides an overview of what life is
like in the society
and also puts forth an argument that
pathfinder agents
are more than just common tomb robbers
as part of the introductory chapter to
the book
it also provides introductory guidance
to players
in the form of five new backgrounds
archaeologist
pathfinder recruiter spell seeker
trailblazer
and translator a lot of detail is
provided in this chapter
regarding the pathfinder society's
purpose and where they fit into the
larger campaign world
as well as fun flavor bits such as a
sidebar giving you pathfinder society
slang
the book's second chapter details the
society's different factions
although these factions were briefly
discussed in the lost uma's character
guide
they really go into a deep dive of each
of them here
each faction's write-up includes a
detailed history
section on faction-specific gear and a
biography of the faction's leader
the four most common factions are
covered in this book
including the invoice alliance which is
focused on diplomacy and community
building
the grand archive dedicated to
preserving knowledge in history
the horizon hunters who explore the
unknown
and the vigilant seal which protects the
world from the dangers
that may be unleashed while exploring
the unknown
or unearthing lost truths and
otherworldly secrets
chapter 2 also includes background
information on the society's training
institutions
the scrolls the swords and the school of
spells
this section does not offer any new
archetypes but does provide
all new feats for previously published
archetypes
the pathfinder agent archetype gets 13
new feats
scroll masters receive 9 new feats and a
new focus spell
the spell master archetype also gets 9
new feats
and 2 new focus spells and swordmasters
are provided
with a whopping 16 new feats for their
archetype
chapter 3 of this new book turned out to
be my favorite
it's all about the pathfinder lodges or
regional bases
that dot the inner sea and beyond the
write-up for each lodge is
very similar to the way nations were
presented in the lost women's world
guide
detailing their history locations
services
allies and enemies each section all
provides a biography of each lodge's
venture captain or their leader
and specific information about how that
lodge functions
and who their chief rivals are the most
interesting part of this for me
was just how varied the lodges were and
mostly avoided feeling like generic
fantasy or cookie cutter copies of one
another
the exalted lodge for example operates
within the nation of rasmaron
and this is the kind of thing that i
would want to explore in my own
games what's it like operating a
pathfinder team
within the jurisdiction of rasmir the
living god
how does that nation's strict theocracy
and
dictatorship work in concert with a
pathfinder lodge
and just little details of how life
there works like
how a rasmiri pathfinder's wayfinder
would be different
from another pathfinder's wayfinder or
the grinning pixie this is a sailing
ship
that serves as a completely mobile
pathfinder launch
if you are running a game in the
shackles or
anything that's pirate themed the
grinning pixie is a
great option and there are many more
lodges
each with their own unique twist
location
and purpose throughout this chapter new
gear is also provided to support the
agents operating from those lodges
like magical nose chains worn by agents
of the farseer tower
or special snowshoes worn at the ice
ferry lodge
and the final chapter of the book is the
most player heavy
it includes gear players can purchase
services they can employ such as
fixers or guides to help them get around
unfamiliar locations and new cultures
or hiring researchers who can dig up
valuable information for a campaign
and a host of new player options
provided by academy instructors
one of the key benefits of joining the
pathfinder society
is gaining access to specialized
training and all new feats
not available to outsiders want to learn
how to throw magic cards like x-men's
gambit
stella fan can teach you that art want
to take your monk to their next stage of
perfection
malika sanvara can train you in the
reign of ember's stance
i mean it has an attack called explosive
death drop what more do you want the
book closes out with a section titled
secrets of the pathfinder society that
provides
more gear options for aeon stones and
unique wayfinders as well as new
familiar options which was probably
the last thing i expected in this book
including having a swarm of aeon stones
as you're familiar
dwemer cat familiars or even having
little dull poppets for familiars
to sum up this is a lore and narrative
heavy campaign guide
with some surprising new options for
players too
in the pros column it provides a lot of
history and backstory into the premier
player organization of the pathfinder
setting
gives a glimpse into life as a
pathfinder
provides a lot of imagination fuel in
the form
of vastly different lodges and factions
within the society
it offers more new player options than
expected including dozens of new
pathfinder archetype feats
a few new focus spells new familiars
and plenty of new gear options tailored
to the pathfinder society's needs
and its cons are sometimes i found the
minutia
into the history and background of the
society to be
more than what most players and gm's
would need
at times the detail felt a little bit
exhausting
also every launches section discusses
their enemies and rivals
but there are no real details provided
the biggest piece of missing information
to me
was about the society's foes
protagonists are only as strong and
compelling as their antagonists
so i would have really appreciated a
couple pages about organizations that
oppose the pathfinder society
the aspis consortium in particular in a
similar vein
i also felt there could have been more
attention given to the dark side of the
society
where the line is blurred between
preserving history
and plundering the treasures of other
cultures
that is mentioned in the book i just
felt like there's a lot of room to
expand on that
and provide more drama for a game
i would recommend the pathfinder society
guide to players who have characters
already associated with the pathfinder
society
or are interested in exploring that with
their characters
and also to lore hounds and gm's looking
for fun ways to
weave their story into some new
narrative spaces
surrounding the pathfinder society i
would not recommend the book
to players focused on characters with no
desire at all to affiliate with the
pathfinder society
i would not recommend it to anyone who
really prefers
crunch heavy books as opposed to lore
and setting books
and also to gm's who want detailed
information about adversaries
as there are no enemy stat blocks or
monsters or other similar details in
this
book let me know in the comments if you
have any questions or
if there's anything you'd like to know
about the pathfinder society guide
before you make a purchasing decision
and as always
i would like to thank the patrons who
support me in the making of these videos
if you're interested in giving some
support as well the easiest way to do
that
is by subscribing to the channel so
please take a second and do that if you
haven't already
and also there is a link to my patreon
included in the video's description
if you do pick up the pathfinder society
guide let me know what you think in the
comments
and as always thanks for watching take
care
and happy gaming