hey everybody dave here with something
a little bit different for you today i
uh
got the beginner box or pathfinder
second edition
in the mail just got it now and i
thought it might be fun to do a little
bit of a
an unboxing video to show everybody
what's in there and uh
kind of share the joy of unpacking one
of these with the
with the community out there now i don't
know
if i am going to be able to do a full
proper review of the uh beginner box
um i might be able to do like a uh a
just a preview
of uh you know my my initial thoughts of
the content at a later date
before i can do a full review of it i
would want to be able to actually play
through the adventure in it and really
dive
into it but uh let's go ahead let's uh
let's dive in
and see what is in here
all right so
uh very familiar for anybody who uses
the ponds we've got a set of bases
very glad to see they put a green one in
there that's the uh
the biggest challenge is when all the
pawns look the same and they all have
black bases
uh it's kind of hard to sometimes call
out some but uh
when uh you can just say the green one
does this that makes a lot easier so i
always appreciate when they throw one at
least one that's colored called
stands for the pawns a standard
set of dice here and
um and i i knew we'll see when we get
inside of the actual books
but i like that they use a different
color for each die
uh that way for new players you may not
be able to tell the difference between a
d8 and a d10
you can just say yeah grab the green one
or grab the orange one and that's the
die you're going to use so
a set of dice standard
oh let's see here we've got a
siren scape a postcard
from sirenscape this is another product
i use
so another free plug for sirenscape yeah
so uh
read this first what is pathfinder well
if you're watching this video you
probably already know what pathfinder is
pretty standard there but for folks who
have never played before that could be
a very helpful guidance and there's
going to be some
some flip maps as was it cool
player reference cars now i got a
feeling i might be using these
even if even though i'm not a a beginner
i got a feeling these are going to be
handy regardless so
it's got your action economy uh one two
three actions and your reaction
how many actions to drop prune to
interact to leap
seek stand you know an explanation of
those
the standard uh mechanic of the d20 with
success in failures difficulties
very nice oh okay here we go on the back
are the most
common conditions so so yes i can
guarantee you that this
will be used on my game table with my
experienced players
because it's always handy to be able to
look these up pretty fast
so concealed flat footed frightened grab
persistent damage
prone restrained slowed unconscious and
wounded
and it comes with one two three four
five six so nice
even though it only comes with six
pre-gen care or four pre-gene characters
they're giving us six of these cards so
that we can have uh
you know six people at the table that's
that's very very good
okay so next it looks like we've got our
character sheets
i've got valero's play of fighter if you
want to
fight on the front lines use the best
weapons and armor react quickly to enemy
actions
so these are little portfolio
sort of style uh sheets uh hopefully the
camera is picking that up relatively
well
uh so on the left hand side we've got
all the different dice their shapes and
colors and corresponding to their number
of sides
reminder the actions proficiency on
terrain zero
train two plus level expert four plus
level again even for
experienced players i would think that
uh this would be a nice
sidebar to have for uh for regular
character sheets as well
uh it's like all the standard stats you
would expect
and then on the back of the character
sheet is a biography
about valorous so that's going to help
these new players
get into the mindset to role play their
character
so that was valorous they've also got
one for
ezran the wizard
kyra the cleric and i want to guess it's
gonna be mauricio at the end yeah and
then mauricio
the rogue uh as the fourth one so your
your standard party of fighter rogue
cleric and wizard
no big surprise there
then next we've got the heroes
handbook let's just flip through this
real fast
uh character creation so yeah so we're
starting with our
our abcs we got our ancestry our
background in our class
um an example of play very similar to
what you would see
in a core rule book uh
okay so here we go what ancestries are
we going to have
we've got dwarf elephant human so again
pretty
pretty standard uh dwarf
elf human then backgrounds
uh acolyte deckhand farmhand
warrior you know it seems like they're
not giving you
uh you know everything that you're going
to find in the core rulebook but they
are
giving you a very nice
set to get started you you could
probably make
uh a a completely satisfying
uh new character with just these rules
but it may not give you all the
different options you're going to get
from the core rule book
all right so here we own wizards it
talks about
spell casting their spell book and then
we get into uh wizard spells
uh saving throws basic saving throws how
do those
work and it looks like all the favorites
are here i'm saying acid splash
days detect magic mage hand
ray of frost burning hands i'm sure
magic missiles here
magic missile mage armor uh
looks like all of the the staples of the
genre are included
and then starting equipment
so uh here it looks like if we i don't
know if my camera's
gonna be angled enough to get it but the
bottom of these descriptions
is just a basic set so if you're a
cleric
you're going to start with a chain shirt
or hide armor if you're
if your strength is plus two or more
you're going to get a weapon if you
worship destiny you get a star knife
if you worship siren right you get a
scimitar if you worship taurag you get a
war hammer
and then you get adventurous pack
healers tool shield wooden religious
symbol
and you start with one gold piece so
you don't have to go through all of the
mental gymnastics of buying your starter
equipment this
this reminds me of uh dare i say 5th ed
5th ed
has the system of when you make a new
character uh it just
you make one or two choices but it just
gives you your
your pack to start and i find that to be
helpful at first level because at first
level
your your gear is pretty much just just
just to get the ball
rolling and um and after that
it's going to be stuff that you find
adventuring anyway
so yeah so this is pretty much just
a condensed version of the core rules at
least the
the uh player's side of the core
rules what they need to know
to play the game
ending up with skills
all right yeah so a pretty
pretty good foundation there
looks like next we have a number of
blank character sheets
i'll hold these up so you can get a look
at them
they're not the full portfolio style but
they do have that
sidebar that's very nice for new players
stats on the front equipment spells
adventure log
on the back uh pretty pretty common and
straightforward
and then the game masters guys they got
one book
for what the players need to know and
now here's our book
for what uh the gms need to know
uh oh got a handy map on the inside
cover um hmm okay
um menace under atari
so uh i'll flip through this pretty fast
so we'll try to avoid spoilers but
here's the first
adventure and then we get into
a game masters section
uh so you know how do you game master
what do you do what does that
look like uh planning a session
starting a session uh so yeah this i
mean this is really going beyond
just here's an adventure
and here's four uh sample characters
but uh uh really giving some gm
advice as well uh buying
and selling how much can you sell that
that gear you found for
how do you set difficulty classes
all right building adventures okay so
now this is interesting
so is going beyond simply
uh the adventure that comes in the box
and is going the extra mile
to tell you how to create your own
adventures
and even helping you get the ball
rolling with eight uh
story hooks there you could you could
key off of
uh let's see what else we got
encounter groups okay so help for
designing uh level appropriate
encounters
uh now i wonder if there isn't like a a
mini
bestiary in here as well that you could
pull from
rewards magic equipment that goes all
the way up to sixth level for
consumables and
fifth level for permanent items
uh okay so if you're in an aquatic
environment well
here's what you need to know about
swimming if you're in the arctic
environment here's how you uh
keep your balance walking on ice so uh
i don't recall seeing something like
that broken out in the regular rules but
that's handy
whatever your environment is here's the
things you need to know
uh well that is that's nice
hazards and traps a section there
uh okay so we saw before the list of
magic items there's
uh the details on all of them and here
we go with a a
proper uh bestiary for
all the different monsters and whatnot
and yeah i don't want there to be huge
spoilers so i'm gonna flip through that
pretty fast
that's actually a fairly sizable part of
the book is on monsters
so a pleasant surprise here for the game
masters guide it goes beyond
simply telling you what you need to know
to run
the specific adventure that's included
in the box
and really gives you tools to craft your
own adventures go beyond the scope
of the box and uh that's that's a
pleasant surprise i very much like that
uh that's uh that's that's giving you
more
at least would be giving me more than i
would expect more for my money's worth
okay so there is a double-sided map
that is included in the uh
in the box as well as a
set of pawns as advertised i decided not
to show those because i don't want to
spoil the fun for anybody but the last
thing
in the box here looks like an
advertisement for
pathfinder society organized play and
yeah that's exactly what it is
if you want to know more visit
pathfindersociety.club
for more information on joining the
organized play
and an advertisement for the standard
uh core rule books that you would need
to
to extend your adventures beyond the
box set and an ad for troubles in atari
which has not been released yet but i'm
looking forward to that coming out that
is a
standalone adventure module that i
understand
follows immediately after the beginner's
box
so you can go straight from that to new
adventures
so that's it in a nutshell that is the
the pathfinder
uh beginners box i look forward to
really
diving in and reading it in greater
detail and
hopefully i'll be able to get some some
time with friends to actually
play it and put out my thoughts in a
review
as always i want to thank everybody who
supports me either through clicking the
like button subscribing to the youtube
channel or through
the patreon and as always take care have
fun and happy gaming