this video is brought to you by roll for
combat
and the fall of plaguestone an official
piezo actual play podcast
join peru cade brixley and celeste as
they band together to save the village
of plaguestone from utter destruction
listen now to the fall of plaguestone at
roll4combat.com
hey everybody dave here with another
pathfinder rule reminder for you
and today i'm going to be talking about
the risky surgery feat
risky surgery is a feat available at
first level to anybody who is at least
trained in medicine and what it does is
when you do treat wounds it gives you
the option
of dealing 1d8 slashing damage to your
patient so yes
you're going to first harm your patient
but
if you do that you get a plus 2
circumstance bonus to your medicine
check
and if the result of that chick is a
success
then it automatically gets bumped up to
a critical success
which in the early levels in that train
proficiency
would be 48 healing instead of 2d8
healing
there are a couple of things to keep in
mind about using this
i i saw a number of people online just
oversimplifying this and saying if you
do risky surgery
and you get a success then instead of
worrying about 1d8 damage and 48 healing
just roll 38 healing because plus 48
healing
minus 1d8 damage uh gets you
a net result of 3d8 healing and so just
make life easy and roll that i would
recommend not doing that
and the big reason for that is if you or
your players roll
anything like my players do then it's
entirely possible
that you could deal 8 points of slashing
damage
on the 1d8 damage that you initially do
to the patient
and then roll nothing but ones on the
rest
of the healing so after all of this it
would still be a
net loss of hit points to the patient
and another question that came up was
about battle medicine can you use
risky surgery with battle medicine and
the answer to that is
no you wouldn't be able to because
battle medicine
even though it says that it uses the
same dc
as treat wounds and it heals the same
amount of hit points
as treat wounds it's pretty clear that
it's not
the same as tree wounds and a risky
surgery specifically
says that it applies to uses of treat
wounds so you would not be able to use
risky surgery when you're doing battle
medicine the next question was probably
the biggest one
or the most frequent one that popped up
which was can you use assurance with
risky surgery
and this is a little bit of a contested
topic
um there's two opposing viewpoints and
i'll give you both of them
and then share you my thoughts um the
first uh
the first train of thought is that no
you cannot use
assurance with risky surgery and the
reason is
is because risky surgery uses the
terminology
if you roll a success okay
so it specifically says if you roll a
success
and the assurance fee says you can
forego
rolling in order to get us
a result so if you're foregoing
if you're forgoing a role and the
uh risky surgery feat specifically says
that
when you roll a success this is what
happens then
that school of thought is that you
wouldn't be able to use assurance
with it the other school of thought is
that the terminology is kind of loose
in pathfinder second edition that
rolling a success
is completely synonymous with just
performing any kind of a
check and therefore you would be able to
use
assurance with risky surgery
also if you the second school of thought
would say that if you
are that strict with the wording
of um of the feasts where it says if you
roll a success
then assurance probably wouldn't apply
to pretty much
anything because they all pretty much
say
when you roll this um
so those are the two different opposing
schools of thought on this
issue uh i believe that the intent
is that yes assurance would apply
to using risky medicine or risky surgery
um you would not get the plus two bonus
to that
if you choose to use assurance with
risky surgery you would not get the plus
two circumstance bonus
uh because there are no bonuses or
penalties applied
to uh to the check result when you use
assurance
every gm can make their own
determinations those are the two
different schools of thought on that
issue but yes i believe
that uh the intent here is that
assurance could be used
with uh with risky surgery so
that's the uh the story of risky surgery
in a nutshell
as i mentioned before i'll make sure i
leave links to my other videos i go
over the medicine skill and assurance
and anything else that's relevant to
this topic
if you have any suggestions for future
rule reminders please let me know
in the comments and as always i want to
thank everybody who supports
me whether that's through subscribing to
the patreon
leaving a comment clicking the like
button subscribing to the channel
i really appreciate everything you do to
support me and this channel
with that thanks for watching take care
and happy gaming