this video is brought to you by roll for
combat
an official piezo actual play podcast
visit rollforcombat.com today to listen
to agents of edgewatch
and join basil dougie gomez and loming
as they protect and serve the citizens
of absalom from a mysterious and
diabolical plot
hey everybody today i have for you a
quick preview of the upcoming
lost omens the monkey expanse hardcover
for pathfinder second edition
two quick notes before i get too deep
into this
first i should let you know that i was
provided a pdf copy of this book in
advance by paizo
and second this will be a preview
not a review meaning i will be providing
an
overview of the book's contents but i
will not be sharing any of my own
opinions about the quality or
value of the book here i will be posting
a full review of the book shortly after
its official release on july 7th
also i would like to apologize in
advance for any of the mispronunciations
you'll likely hear during this preview
the monkey expanse is the latest in
pisa's line of
lost omen campaign setting books is 314
pages from cover to cover
and retails for 49.99 us
roughly the first 100 pages are
dedicated to the history of the expanse
and the people who live there it begins
with a broad
description of this territory and
provides some guidance for both players
and characters who may be visiting the
region for the first time
a focus is placed on campaigns being
exciting and not
exotic and also provides a few questions
that players and gm's can ask themselves
and their characters to play the role of
foreigners in this new land
such as how does the expanse raise
questions about the pc's understanding
of where they come from there is a
timeline provided that stretches from
the age of serpents all the way to the
present
as well as fleshed out details for each
age
after the section on history the book
gets into the inhabitants of the expanse
this includes some adjustments to
ancestry rarity
such as cobalt and lizard folks are
common in the expanse
while gnomes and goblins become uncommon
ancestries
and the book dives further into the
human ethnicities of the muwangi expanse
including the bekyar bonawat kaldaru
moxie sargovan vitrik and the zinch who
make up the majority of the expansion's
population
about 70 pages are dedicated to the
various
non-human ancestries found in the
expanse including three elven societies
the alijay akuge and khalid
and two dwarven societies the umbeke
and taralu it also includes write-ups
for the
songo halflings and the demon hunting
matanji orcs
each of these individual groups has
roughly 10 pages of detail provided for
them
very little of which is mechanical
there's one or two new feats and a
couple new items
but the overwhelming majority of this
section is dedicated to each group
society
culture political views religious
beliefs prominent
npcs and the like after that the book
introduces six new playable ancestries
shape-changing spiders called a nadi
constructs imbued with cosmic life known
as
konrasu the familiar gnolls
eight eyed creatures called golomas frog
people known as gripleys
and the human-like shisks who have
quills for hair
each of these new ancestries are given
the standard write-up
with ancestry feats and either four or
five heritages each
the next major section of the book dives
into the religions of the expanse
and includes write-ups for a dozen new
deities each of these includes the usual
information
such as domains favored weapons and
avatar forms
the next 140 pages covers the geography
of the region
35 of which are spent detailing 10
different major territories such as the
monkey jungle and the southern lands
and then the focus moves onto nine
specific settlements
like blood cove a haven for pirates and
merchants
each settlement receives roughly 12 to
14 pages
including stat blocks maps points of
interest prominent npcs and more the
final major section is a bestiary
full of creatures and monsters that
players might encounter
while adventuring in the expanse this
includes a table listing all of the
expanse's monsters already published in
bestiaries one two and three
followed by roughly 20 new creatures
including npc stats for some of the new
ancestries like the inati
as well as new animals beasts spirits
and other monsters as well
so that should give you a pretty good
idea of the contents of this new book
make sure you come back after july 7th
to view a
full review and i'll share my thoughts
opinions and whether or not i would
recommend this book at that time
and as always take care and happy gaming