this video is brought to you by roll for
combat an official piezo actual play
podcast
join atron hap alhara riley darius and
the entire
circus of wayward wonders as they save
the starstone isles from the dreaded
extinction curse
listen now to three ring adventure at
roll4combat.com
hi everybody dave from howitz played
here with a brief review of pathfinder
second edition's
latest hardback release the lost omis
mulwangi expanse campaign setting guide
this review is a companion to my
previously released
preview of this book and this video will
focus on my
thoughts and my opinions about it while
the previous video
provides an overview of the book's
contents so if you would like more
general information about the kind of
material that is found within this book
then i encourage you to go check out
that video too a link to the preview
video
is included in this video's description
okay to get this review started let's
not bury the lead here and get
right to the biggest surprise about this
book it's
huge 314 pages cover to cover
for comparison the largest previous los
uma's book
was the ancestry guide at only 146 pages
so this book is more than twice the size
of any previous lost um's book
and for what it's worth the milwaukee
expanse campaign guide is also bigger
than the game mastery guide
it has about 40 more pages than the
advanced player's guide
despite being offered for the same price
of 49.99 us
to really put things into perspective
the los uma's world guide
that covers the entire continent of
avastin and the northern third of garund
is only 138 pages
this book which only explores one
section of that region
is more than double the size of that in
fact it's 176 pages longer
than the book that covers the entire
primary game world
so this is a surprisingly large book and
if you're the type of person who uses
cost per page as a benchmark for value
then you'll likely be very pleased but
size isn't everything in 300 plus pages
of content
isn't worth much if it isn't good
content so let's talk about what you get
for your 50
or your 35 dollars if you prefer the pdf
version
as mentioned in my preview video for
this book the milwaukee expanse campaign
guide is
absolutely full of valuable information
about the history and the people who
live in this region
the beginning of the book takes extra
links to provide guidance on how to be a
newcomer to this land
with the expectation that a lot of
characters who participate in adventures
within the expanse
likely hail from the more traditionally
western european influenced nations of
aviston
this portion is insightful and focuses
not just
on how their presence will affect the
expanse or whether or not their arrival
will be welcomed
but also explores how they as characters
will be impacted by their time spent in
the expanse
the section on the people of the expanse
provided insight into the different
ethnicities present
and provides a great amount of detail
about the cultures and beliefs of
not just the humans present but the
elves dwarves halflings and orcs as well
but the highlight for many players here
will be the six new ancestries
the anandi who are adventurous spiders
who can shape change into human form
konrasus which are orbs of cosmic
intelligence that create their own
exoskeleton bodies out of wood
knolls eight eyed golomas frog-like
gripleys
and the quilled shisks each of these are
fully fleshed out and provide
all the detail you would expect
including four or five heritages
and the usual array of ancestry feats of
the new options the one i feel most
drawn to are the completely alien
konrasu
but i've also taken a shouting to the
anatti i fully expect
my leisure players to start gravitating
towards this new ancestry
based on this one picture alone the
section on geography provides several
diverse locations for you to set your
adventure in
but it was the detailed write-up of
specific locations and nations that i
found the most valuable
my favorite of which is vitrion a newly
formed and independent nation after
nearly 500 years of colonial rule
the last section of the book provides
stats for several new monsters and
adversaries for players
but it is worth mentioning that some of
these may feel a little too familiar as
versions of them were already made
available in previously released
adventures
such as the annadi beloku and charuca
can all be found in a certain already
published adventure path
overall i think this book provides a lot
of the sending information that you will
need to place your adventures within the
expanse
in the pros column this book is huge it
has
way more content than i expected it has
six new ancestries only two of which
feel like familiar territory those being
gnolls and gripleys
this book really goes beyond the bare
minimum when it comes to setting detail
with a focus
on the cultures of the different people
inhabiting the expanse
and providing a diverse array of
locations as well
and if it wasn't apparent enough already
the art in this book is
absolutely gorgeous this is without a
question at least in my mind the most
beautiful pathfinder 2nd edition book so
far
but notebook is perfect so let's talk
about the cons
for me the biggest drawback of this book
was its lack of
crunch yes there are six new ancestries
and a handful of new monsters
but that's pretty much it as far as
stats and mechanics go
i expected and would have greatly
preferred if paizo had approached this
book in the same way that they did the
lost omens world guide
and mixed in some crunch with all of the
fluff
for example this book provides 12 page
long sections that explore different
parts of the world
in these write-ups it provides
descriptions of life in the city
it's people significant organizations
and so on but
all of it is descriptive text none of it
is mechanical
you won't find anything from this
chapter on anyone's character sheet
whereas in the lost omens world guide
that also
presented 12 page long write-ups of
significant locations
it always provided some mechanical and
gameplay-centric information
along with all of that narrative
description
each of the 12-page long sections in the
world guide
ended with a page of new backgrounds and
a page providing a new character
archetype that was associated with the
location that was discussed in that
chapter
nothing like that is present in the
monkey expanse guide
there are no new backgrounds no new
archetypes no new spells or rituals
there are three new feats that are
provided outside of the ancestry feats
and there are a couple of new items but
not nearly as much as i would hope to
find in a book of this size
i would have greatly preferred that each
chapter be two pages shorter
and give me some of those backgrounds
and spells and archetypes and
other player options as well i would
recommend the milwaukee expanse guide to
any gm looking for inspiration or to
gain an understanding of the history
conflicts and culture of the people who
live within the expanse
and i would recommend this book to
anyone even those who are not interested
in playing pathfinder
who would like to see what a high
fantasy setting can look like
outside of the usual settings that are
heavily influenced by western european
history and cultures
i would not recommend this book to
anyone who is looking for more player
options
outside of the new ancestries there's
not a lot of crunch to be found here
no new archetypes background spells or
the like this is
a setting book and not a player's
companion
so there are my thoughts on the new lost
omens milwaukee expanse book
let me know in the comments if you have
any questions or if there's anything
else you'd like to know about this book
before making
a purchasing decision for yourself
before we close i'd like to take a
moment to thank all of my patrons
these videos would not be possible
without their continued generosity and
support
members of the house played patreon
community receive special benefits like
exclusive content and getting to vote on
the topics i cover
if you would like to support this
channel and help it grow the easiest way
to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release
and i can always be reached through
twitter and facebook too
thanks for watching take care and happy
gaming