this video is brought to you by the
battle zoo bestiary a new book with over
100 award-winning monsters and other
resources from piezo lead designer mark
cipher sign up today at
kickstarter.roll4combat.com and join the
campaign when it launches on august 31st
hey everybody dave here with another
pathfinder rule reminder for you and
today i'm going to be answering a few
questions about the disarm maneuver
disarm is part of the athletic skill it
is an action that takes one action and
when you perform it you attempt to take
a held item away from a targeted
opponent when you do so you roll your
athletic skill against their reflex dc
on a critical success you knock that
item out of their hand and it falls to
the ground in the same square that that
that target enemy is standing if you're
standing adjacent to them and you still
have an action left that turn you can
bend over and pick up that item and
seize it that way on a success you don't
knock it all the way out of their grasp
but you do weaken their hold on it and
this imposes a negative two circumstance
penalty to any attacks they make with
that weapon or any other skill checks
they roll that involve that item
that they might have to have a firm grip
on in order to succeed and it also
grants a plus two circumstance bonus to
your future attempts to disarm that
target of that item again now both that
bonus to your disarm checks and that
penalty to their attacks and other
chicks using that held item those are
until the start of the target's next
turn
now on a failure with that skill check
nothing happens you just fail and on a
critical failure then not only do you
fail to
knock the item out of your opponent's
grasp but in doing so you somehow fall
off balance and you are rendered
flat-footed until the start of your next
turn
now a couple things that we should
probably unpack here
first the bonus and penalty that is uh
received by you and imposed on them when
you succeed but not critically succeed
with a disarm attempt those are
circumstance bonuses and penalties so
they're typed which means they do not
stack another thing to keep in mind is
that by default and by raw the penalty
that's applied to the target after a
successful disarm attempt it is until
the start of their next turn which
usually means uh that that penalty is
only going to apply to any reactions
like an attack of opportunity because at
the start of the next turn it's assumed
they're just for free going to tighten
their grip again on that weapon and uh
not face any further penalties for to
being almost knocked out of their hand
now there is a swashbuckler feat called
disarming flare and what it does is it
extends the duration of those penalties
to the end of his next turn instead of
the start of that target's next turn or
they can sacrifice one of their actions
to make that tighter grip on their
weapon and remove their penalties before
the end of that turn i have seen online
it seems to be pretty popular fairly
popular that uh some gm's house rule to
just make the disarming flare feat
the universal rule for everybody in
their game on this arm attempts this
house rule territory but it seems to be
fairly popular for some of the folks who
believe that the
disarming action of the disarming
maneuver by by raw is a little bit
lacking they want to beef it up a little
bit a question has come up about
disarming a shield uh that is a held
item and this arm says that you can
use it to to remove a held item but
there are other complications that pop
up when using shields and so i want to
walk through a couple of different
options and things that might occur but
it's ultimately going to be up to your
gm and how they view the usage of
shields in their game as to whether or
not each of these things apply so the
first thing to think about is the reflux
dc of that shielded target uh some gm's
out there say that if that shield is
raised then they are going to allow the
bonus of that shield that usually goes
to armor class to be applied to that
target's reflex dc when resisting a
disarm attempt uh there's nothing
involved that says that that's just one
of the things that some gm's do for
trying to disarm shields
igem might also decide that that shield
is strapped so firmly on the target's
arm that it's just immune to to disarm
attempts and it cannot be disarmed
there's a lot of debate about whether
shields are strapped or not the only
shield i'm aware of that specifically
says it is strapped is a buckler but
that doesn't mean that other larger
shields are not
strapped and held long story short
each gm can decide for themselves
whether or not shields are strapped by
default and whether or not that makes
their their wielders immune to disarm
attempts but for the sake of discussion
let's say the gm decides yeah you can
attempt to
disarm this enemy of their shield and
you roll a success what does that mean
well it means you're going to get a plus
two circumstance bonus to future
attempts to disarm that shield before
the start of your target's next turn and
it also means they're going to be
suffering a negative 2 circumstance
penalty to any attacks they make with
the shield like a shield bash and they
will also suffer a negative 2
circumstance penalty to any checks made
with the shield that requires that
target get to have a firm grasp of their
shield
so that raises the question of well do
does this mean that they suffer a
penalty to their armor class because
you've knocked their shield out of their
grasp and uh even if they're not fully
disarmed they're not able to hold it uh
as clear and soundly as they would
normally be able to do
by raw note there's there's no penalty
to their armor class armor class is not
a check
it is a type of dc but it's not a check
so by raw there's no um penalty there
but this is one of those areas where
gm's are allowed to manage circumstances
bonuses and circumstance penalties
however they believe are appropriate so
it is absolutely within agm's all right
to be able to say on that disarm success
they're going to apply the circumstance
penalty to that target's armor class to
represent the fact that the shield's
been knocked a little bit loose and it's
not being held as firmly as is ideal for
protecting oneself and then on a
critical success what happens when
you're trying to disarm a shield
again up to the gm if they believe that
the the shield is strapped on firmly and
immune to disarm attempts then obviously
they don't drop it but the gm could also
rule that uh either they're not strapped
on the arm and therefore they do get
dropped or they can say you know what
you wrote a critical success let's let's
do something fun with that and say that
your disarm attempt cut through the
strap and knocked it loose and it fell
to
the floor to fell to the ground and the
target squared just like a normal
critical success on a disarm attempt but
that's it in a nutshell it is a use of
the athletic skill you're all your
athletic skill check versus your targets
reflex dc on a critical success they
drop the held item and it lands in the
at the ground at their feet in that same
square if you only succeed but not
critically succeed then you get a plus
two circumstance bonus to future
attempts to disarm the target of that
item and they suffer a negative two
penalty to attack with that item or to
use it on any other checks that require
you to have a firm hold of the item
until the start of their next turn and
on a critical failure you not only fail
to disarm the target of that item but
you also render yourself off balance and
you are flat-footed until the start of
your next turn as always if you have any
suggestions for future rule reminders
please let me know in the comments of
this video i'll make sure to leave links
to any other relevant topics that talk
about disarming or other uses of the
athletic skill in the description of
this video and as always i want to take
a quick moment to say thank you to
everybody out there for watching these
videos for commenting for liking them
for subscribing to the channel
subscribing to the patreon thank you so
much for everything you do to support me
and this channel and thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]