hello and welcome to the basics of
crafting in Pathfinder second edition in
this video we're going to discuss the
foundation used for all crafting will be
covering general rules that apply to all
crafting and in the next course we'll
get into specifics for crafting special
items like Scrolls wands rooms and also
crafting weapons and armor using special
materials like cold iron or adamantine
the crafting skill can be used for a
variety of activities such as
identifying alchemical items and
repairing broken gear but for the
purposes of this video we're going to
focus on using the crafting skill to
create items before you can start
crafting there are a few requirements
you need to meet first the item that you
wish to craft must be your experience
level or lower if no item level is
included in the item stats then is
considered to be item level 0 second you
must have the proper proficiency you
must be at least trained and crafting to
craft any items if the item is 9th level
or higher then you need to have master
proficiency in crafting to make it if
the item level is 6 teeth or higher then
you need to have a legendary proficiency
third you might need a special feat to
craft the item the crafting skill by
itself is sufficient to make most common
mundane items like gear and common
weapons and armor but if you wish to
craft specialty items like those we will
discuss in depth with the next course in
the series then you'll need some special
feats if you want to make alchemical
items like elixir is poison Xand bombs
then you need the alchemical crafting
feat if you want to make any magical
items including Scrolls then you need
the magical crafting feat and if you
want to create snares like traps and
alarms then you need the snare crafting
feat the fourth requirement for crafting
is you must have the right tools for the
job
an alchemist slab is needed to craft
alchemical items a writing set is needed
to craft Scrolls and so on artisan tools
are provided as a sort of catch-all term
when purchasing one of these sets you
need to declare what kind of tools they
are for example woodworking tools or a
brewing kit if you want to make beer in
some cases you'll also need a workshop
as determined by your GM for example
you'll need access to a forge if you
want to make a metal shield
there is no harder rule for that in the
book so it's up to common sense and
again the geums discretion the fifth and
possibly biggest requirement is you need
to have a formula for what you are
attempting to make although formula is
the term used in the game this could be
a recipe a blueprint a schematic or any
other form of instructions to follow a
basic crafters book can be purchased for
one silver piece and it has all of the
formulas for crafting common items found
in Chapter six of the core rules so this
one purchase would cover the formula
requirements for swords bows chainmail
holy water
musical instruments a brewing ale and
pretty much everything else that's
considered to be common if you wish to
purchase the formula for a common rarity
item you can do so according to the
table here formulas for items that are
uncommon or rare are only available at
the discretion of the GM and likely will
either be incredibly expensive or
awarded as part of treasurer and last
you need raw materials worth at least
half the listed cost of the item if you
are creating a common item like a
longsword as long as you're in a
settlement you can probably just pay the
price in silver but more exotic items
might require very specific and harder
to get materials that you will need to
source
once you meet the requirements have the
proper tools a formula and the required
materials then you're ready to get to
work in order to create the item you
must invest an amount of time or
resources equal to its listed price and
always start by providing fifty percent
of that total cost upfront you then
spend four days of downtime working
although I didn't see it spelled out in
the second edition the first edition of
Pathfinder is specified that a day of
downtime spec crafting was eight hours
of work so after four days of working
you roll your crafting skill and the GM
compares that total against a secret DC
that they set on a failure your progress
stops but you don't lose any of the
money or resources you've already
invested and can start the process over
again critical failures work the same
way but you lose 10% of the materials
used but if the skill check is a success
you have a few options your first option
is to pay the remaining balance needed
to complete the work you always start by
putting up fifty percent of the items
price so if you roll a success after
four days of work you just need to pay
the remaining 50 percent cost to
instantly complete it this doesn't save
you any money and it takes some time but
might be worth it if the item you're
making is not available for purchase in
your area or if it's important that the
item was made by you for example if
you're crafting a painting or other work
of art your second option is to invest
more time in crafting it every day of
additional work lowers the amount of
resources needed to complete the item by
an amount equal to the earned income
table found on page 236 so for example
if you were a flevit expert proficiency
in crafting every day of down time spent
beyond the initial four would lower the
required resources to complete the item
by three
or pieces and if you are all a critical
success you treat yourself as being one
level higher so if you're again an
eighth level expert enroll a critical
success you would lower the amount of
resources needed by four gold
instead of three for each day of
downtime spent working beyond the
initial four after each day of work you
can decide if you want to pay off the
remaining balance to finish your work
and complete the item or if you want to
spend one more day of work to lower the
remaining balance that's needed note
that there are no additional skill
checks needed after your fourth day of
work once you roll a success there is
just a matter of counting days and
seeing how long you want to work and how
much more money you're willing to pay in
order to finish
now this might have you wondering about
things like arrows do you really need to
spend four days to make an arrow the
good news is no it's not quite that bad
if you wish to craft ammunition or any
item with the consumable trait you can
make those in batches ammunition is
created and batches equal to their
numbers shown on table 6/8
so blowgun darts crossbow bolts and
arrows are all made in batches of ten
and items with the consumable trait are
made in batches of four when you create
by batch every item in that batch must
be identical there's no mixing and
matching so you can't make five arrows
in five crossbow bolts in the same batch
it has to be ten of one or the other
crafting and batches works the same way
as crafting individual items except you
add the price of each item together so
if you're making a batch of four vials
of holy water the price would be twelve
gold and you would need to provide six
gold upfront for the material cost other
than that
crafting batches works the same as we've
already discussed
in this video we examined the basics of
crafting and the next video expands that
discussion to cover magic items and
crafting weapons and armor with precious
materials if you would like to see an
example on how crafting works during
gameplay you can do so by viewing the
next video in this series which is
linked in the description in the
playlist and should also be linked in
the upper right portion of this screen
as well
there are six requirements that must be
met before you can craft an item first
the item level of the object being
crafted may not be higher than your
experience level second you must have
the proper proficiency in the crafting
skill unless otherwise noted trained is
needed for first level items master for
ninth level items in legendary for 16th
level items third you might need a
special feat to craft the item the
crafting skill by itself is enough to
make most mundane items but you'll need
the alchemical crafting feet to make
alchemical items like elixirs and bombs
snare crafting to make traps and alarms
and you will need the magical crafting
feat to make magic items including
potion Scrolls wands and any other
magical item the fourth requirement is
you must have the proper tools for the
job at the geums discretion you might
also need a workshop or laboratory the
fifth requirement is you must have a
formula for the item you are crafting
and the last requirement is you must
have raw materials equal to half the
listed cost of the item
once you meet all six requirements you
can begin crafting this takes four days
of downtime at the end of which you make
a crafting skill check against a DC set
by the GM if successful you can either
pay the remaining 50% cost of the item
to complete it or spend another day of
downtime working on it every day of
downtime spent after the first four
lowers the amount of money needed to
complete the project by an amount found
on page 236 each day you can choose to
pay the balance or keep working if the
remaining balance ever becomes zero then
you finish the project no additional
skill checks are needed after the one
that's made at the end of day 4
consumable items may be crafted in
batches of four unless they have the
ammunition trait in which case they may
be made and batches equal to their
numbers shown on the weapons table found
in the equipment section of the rules
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting the vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder