hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents crafting examples part one for
Pathfinder 2nd edition if you haven't
already watched our knowledge video on
basic crafting rules you're encouraged
to do so before viewing this example a
link to that video may be found in the
description and also in the upper right
of this screen
in this example camera is going to craft
a suit of half plate armor she is third
level with training proficiency in
crafting and a skill bonus of +6 the
first requirement is item level there is
no item level listed for half plate
armor so it defaults to item level 0
camera is third level so she meets this
requirement the second requirement is
proficiency as easier level item trained
proficiency is all that is needed to
craft this third does she need a special
feat to make half plate armor is not
magical alchemical or a snare so she
does not need any feats to make this 4th
does she have the proper tools we'll say
she purchased a set of artisans tools
and labeled them as smithing tools on
her character sheet and the local
blacksmith is letting her use their
Forge so this requirement is covered 5th
that she have a formula for half plate
will say that she purchased a basic
crafters book half plate is a common
item found in Chapter six of the rules
so is formula is included in that basic
crafters book and the last requirement
is materials half plate is listed with a
price of 18 gold pieces so she must
provide nine gold upfront to begin her
work and must provide 18 gold worth of
materials or discounts in order to
complete the armor set she works eight
hours a day for 4 days straight at the
end of which her player rolls a crafting
skill check the GM compares the total to
a DC that they set in secret for this
will say the GM set a DC of 14 gimr rosa
d 20 and as her crafting bonus of +6 if
she rolls a 7 then she fails which means
that her 4 days of work were wasted but
she gets her nine gold pieces worth of
materials back it can try again if she
rolls a natural one then she critically
fails and not only wasted four days of
work but also
10% of the materials in this case we
convert the nine gold to ninety silver
pieces and she loses ten percent of that
or nine silver leaving her with 81
silver pieces worth of material she can
start the process over and try again
provided that she can replace the nine
silver pieces worth of lost materials
but if giver rolls an 8 on her check
than she succeeds
she now has two options the half plate
Armour has a remaining balance of nine
gold that needs to be covered she can
either pay that nine gold and instantly
finish her work or she can spend another
day of work to lower that balance she
decides to invest another day into
crafting the armor to learn how much
this lures the remaining balance by we
need to look at table 4 2 on page 236
Gamera is third level and trained so
every extra day of work lowers the
remaining balance by 5 silver pieces if
she had wrote a critical success that
she would be treated as if she was
fourth level and would lower the balance
by seven silver pieces after an extra
day of work but for this example were
going to say that she succeeded but not
critically succeeded so after day five
the remaining balance lowers from nine
gold pieces to eight gold in five silver
or it might just be easiest to call it
eighty-five silver pieces at this point
her players jaw hits the floor and she
realizes that she'll need to spend
another 17 days in order to finish this
suit of armor she said to her GM there's
no way that can be a right and her GM
tells our sorry but that's how it works
and yes this has been a major point of
contention on the internet but at the
time of this recording there have been
no additional rules provided that would
lower this time requirement beyond
leveling up and gaining a higher level
of proficiency but I would not be at the
least bit surprised if future books
provide new and advanced feats that
would address this regardless gamers GM
tells her that she has three days
remaining of downtime before
her party has to leave town so she
spends the rest of her available time
working on the armor lowers the
remaining balance from 85 silver to 60
and at the end of day 8 she pays the
remaining 60 silver pieces to finish her
suit of half plate armor
if you'd like to see the companion
course they explain to the rules behind
these examples you can find a link to it
in the description and highlighted on
the screen as well if you found this
video helpful please give us a like and
click that bell so you never miss out on
our future videos if you'd like to
support this channel so that we can keep
producing instructional videos you can
do so through our patreon and feel free
to leave in the comments any suggestions
you have for future examples thanks for
watching take care and we'll see you
soon with more basics for your favorite
games