hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of crafting part 2
in the previous course we discussed the
process of crafting most common items
and in this one we're going to take it a
step further and talk about special
situations like crafting magic items in
forging weapons and armor from precious
materials this video will be providing
an overview of the process and if you
would like to see examples of how
crafting works then check out the
companion video that is linked in the
description
crafting magic items works exactly like
crafting everything else but there are a
few points that you will want to pay
close attention to first each type of an
item requires a different formula to
craft if an items listing shows multiple
types then you need a separate formula
to craft each type you cannot craft a
greater coyote cloak with a regular
coyote click formula and you can't craft
a regular coyote cloak if you have a
greater coyote click formula those are
considered to be wholly separate items
each requiring their own formula and
second pay attention to the craft
requirements section in the items
description this area will show you
anything extra needed beyond the norm in
the previous course you learned that
there are six requirements that must be
met before you can start crafting we are
essentially adding a seventh requirement
here which is simply do whatever is
listed under the craft requirements
heading more often than not these
requirements are going to say something
to the effect of supply a listing level
casting of the spell this means that
during the initial four days of crafting
someone must cast the specified spell at
the required level in order for that
item to be crafted so for example if
you're making a major staff of AB
duration then someone will need to cast
alarm at first level and then cast alarm
again heightened to third level and also
cast
magic once at second-level then again at
fourth level and one more time
heightened to 6th level and so on until
all of the spells at all of their listed
levels have been cast you would not need
to cast shield as part of the crafting
process because can trips are not listed
level spells when casting spells to meet
a crafting requirement remember these
key points first the person who is doing
the crafting does not need to be the one
casting the spell there's no requirement
for them beyond having the magical
crafting feat therefore anyone can be
the one who actually cast the spell if
you're making a fireball scroll you do
not need to know how to cast the
fireball spell yourself but instead can
have a friend cast the spell for you as
part of the crafting process second a
spell slot must be used when casting the
spell in other words you can't use a
charge from a staff or a wand to cast
the spell that's needed to craft another
staff or want the energy of the spell
must come from a person third there are
no other effects when casting the spell
when you cast a fireball spell for the
purpose of creating a fireball scroll
you're not going to blow up your house
likewise when casting a wish spell to
make a luck blade you don't also get to
make a wish the energy of the spell is
safely transferred to the item and there
are no other effects and last when
casting a spell as part of a crafting
requirement you will likely need to pay
any associated cost with casting that
spell except if you are making a staff
or a wand so for example you're crafting
a second level scroll of continual flame
it says here that there is a cost of six
gold worth of Ruby dust in order to
catch continual flame if you're making a
second level scroll of continual flame
then you must provide that cost
in addition to the irregular cost of
crafting but staffs and wands are
different if you're making a
second-level
wand of continual flame you do not
provide any of the usual spell cost when
casting the spell as part of crafting
although I haven't seen it spelled out
in the rules I believe the key
distinction here is that when someone
uses a scroll it is consumed and you do
not need to provide spell cost at the
time that the scroll is used but with
stabs and wands which are not
consumables you do need to provide the
cost each time the spell is cast using
the staffer wand and therefore you do
not also need to pay that spell cost
upfront when making the staff or wand
bottom line is you should only be paying
the cost once per actual use of a spell
and while we're on the topic of spells
and magic items it may be worth
mentioning that magic scrolls and wands
cannot be used to cast hand trips focus
spells or rituals they can only be
crafted to cast regular spells you
cannot create a wand to cast your
favorite focus spell or make a scroll to
cast a ritual and also don't make
assumptions about when you need to have
a spell cast as part of crafting if it
doesn't say that you need to then you
don't the skeleton key for example cast
the NOC spell when it is used but does
not require a knock spell to be cast
when crafting a skeleton key likewise
people sometimes assume that potions
that cast spells when you drink them
require the spells to be cast when you
are making and brewing this potion but
it is incredibly rare for that to be the
case barks can potions for example do
not require anyone to cast the bark skin
spell when brewing them in fact the
person who is crafting the bark skin
potion doesn't even need to know how to
cast that spell or have the ability to
cast metals all the information needed
to brew that potion is entirely included
in
Formula beyond these tweaks crafting
items regardless if they are won scrolls
potions wondrous items whatever they all
work exactly as we outlined in the
previous course you need to provide 50%
of the cost of materials upfront and
spend four days working at the end of
which you make a crafting skill check if
successful you can either choose to pay
off the remaining balance or spend
another day working to lower that
balance and since potions and Scrolls
are consumable items they can be made in
batches of four
in addition to magic items we also want
to discuss forging weapons and items
with uncommon materials the items we
discussed in our crafting part 1 video
all assume that you are using mundane
materials like wood or iron but in the
world of Pathfinder there are many more
exotic materials that can be used when
crafting such as cold iron or adamantine
crafting weapons or armor with precious
materials is pretty simple it works just
like a regular crafting but there are a
few special points that we need to
discuss as usual you must provide
materials equal to 50% of the items
price upfront but if you're making
something with precious materials
you can't just pay the cost out of your
pocket in gold or silver coins instead
you have to somehow source the precious
material that's needed as well for
example you want to forge a cold iron
Warhammer when we look at the stats for
cold iron weapons we see a few things
worth noting first precious materials
are categorized as being low grade
standard grade or high grade each with
their own stats like how magic items are
listed with varying types each grade
requires a different formula so if you
have the formula to craft a low grade
cold iron weapon you can't use that same
formula to make a standard grade called
iron weapon we also see it has a listed
level more hammers are level 0 but when
crafting with precious materials you
must meet or exceed the level of the
base item or the material whichever is
higher so you would need to be at least
2nd level to craft a low grade cold iron
Warhammer and 10th level to make a
standard grade hammer but the big
difference comes when we look at price
here price is based on the bulk of the
item that we are making
in this case a warhammer is one bulk so
a low-grade cold iron warhammer has a
price of forty gold plus four per bulk
making the price of this hammer
forty-four gold this is the same price
for any weapon that is only one bulk you
do not add the cost of a normal war
hammer to this also note that you always
need to pay for at least one bulk so if
the item that you are crafting is light
bulk then you treat it as being one bulk
for the purpose of calculating its price
when we start crafting we must provide
materials equal to 50% of the price up
front just like always in this case that
would be 22 gold worth of materials next
we look at the craft requirements line
in the description here it says that of
those 22 gold pieces 22 silver pieces of
that must be cold iron all of the
special material is needed up front we
do not provide 11 silver worth of cold
iron now and another 11 silver worth of
it later so before we can start crafting
we need a hundred and ninety eight
silver pieces worth of regular general
materials and specifically twenty two
silver pieces worth of cold iron this is
all of the code iron that we will need
for this project after four days of work
in a skill check we have the option as
usual of paying the remaining balance of
eleven goal to complete it but none of
that needs to be caught iron it can just
be paid in eleven gold coins crafting
armor from precious materials works the
same way except you need to adjust its
bulk the armor table shows the bulk for
each suit of armor assuming that you are
wearing it when crafting you use the
armors carry the bulk which is one more
than a suit of armor x' worn bulk so you
simply add a 1/2 the bulk that you see
listed in the table
if you were crafting adamantine
chainmail you would calculate is price
using three bulk instead of two
in this video we discussed a few more
advanced applications of crafting namely
crafting magic items in forging weapons
and armor from precious materials if you
would like to see examples of the
crafting process then check out the
companion video that is linked in the
description
crafting magic items works the same as
crafting anything else except there are
a few key points worth remembering first
each different type of an item requires
its own formula second many magic items
have special requirements these are
listed at the bottom of their step
blocks and often say something to the
effect of supply a listing level casting
of the spell this means that every spell
that the item can cast must also be cast
as part of the crafting process and they
must be cast at each of the levels
listed in the items description the
person who is doing the crafting does
not need to be the person who cast the
spells as part of crafting that crafter
does not even need to know how to cast
these spells a spell slot must be used
to cast each of the spells that are cast
as part of the crafting process you
cannot use an item to cast a spell as
part of creating another item and unless
the item that is being crafted is a
staff or wand then you must pay any
associated cost for casting the spell
when it casts a spell as part of the
crafting process for creating either a
wand or staff you do not pay for this
spell cost upfront because you will pay
this cost later when you are casting the
spells with the wand or staff we also
discussed forging weapons and armor with
uncommon materials this works exactly
like normal but again there are a few
points worth mentioning first precious
materials are not categorized as types
like most other items are instead they
are listed by grade low grade standard
grade in high grade when crafting with
precious materials the item level of the
finished item is the higher of the base
items level or the level assigned to
that grade of special material often the
price for items crafted from precious
materials will be based on bulk and the
price will always be at least one bulk
even if the item that is being crafted
is light bulb if the item is armored
remember that the armor table in the
book shows it's worn bulk you must add a
1 to this number to calculate is actual
or carried bulk also the items
description will tell you how much of
the initial 50% material cost must
include the precious material this is
all provided at the start and no more
precious materials are needed after day
4 of crafting
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder