welcome to basics for gamers presents
crafting examples part 2 in Pathfinder
if you haven't already watched our
knowledge videos on crafting you're
encouraged to do so before viewing these
examples a link to those videos may be
found in the description
first off let's make a plus-one weapon
potency rune crafting runes is often
referred to as edging the route and it
can be done directly to a piece of gear
or it can be etched to a blank rune
stone and then can be later moved from
the stone to a weapon or a suit of armor
we'll say were third level and have
expert proficiency in crafting with a
bonus of +9 we'll also assume that we
have the magical crafting feet just like
crafting anything else we need a formula
and since weapon potency runes are
common we should have no problem
purchasing that formula the table on
page 293 shows us that second level
common rarity formulas can be bought for
two gold will assume that we meet all
the other requirements and can get to
work first we must provide basic
materials worth 50% of the rinse price
plus one weapon potency runes cost 35
gold so to make the math easy we convert
that to 350 silver and half of that is a
hundred and seventy-five silver pieces
we pay that price and begin working four
days later we roll a crafting skill
check versus ad see determined by the GM
will assume that we succeed that check
we now have a remaining balance of a
hundred and seventy-five silver pieces
that we can either pay and instantly
finish creating this room or we can
spend another day working if we do that
then at the end of the next day the
remaining balance will lower by five
silver pieces and then we can either pay
a hundred and seventy silver to finish
or keep working for another day and this
continues with everyday work lowering
the balance by five silver until the
balances either reduce to zero or we
decide to pay off the balance and finish
next let's make a greater staff of
conjuration this time we'll say that we
are 12 level with master proficiency in
crafting and a bonus of plus 22 we'll
assume that we meet all the usual
requirements including having a formula
for greater staffs of conjuration this
is a common magical item so as before we
can simply buy the formula for 50 gold
and making the staff is going to work
the same as crafting anything else but
we see under craft requirements it says
supply one casting of all listed levels
of all listed spells so first thing
first we provide half the cost up front
and materials this staff has a price of
nine hundred gold so we must pay four
hundred and fifty gold at the start then
we spend four days working during this
time someone must cast the required
spells into the staff it doesn't have to
be us it can be anyone but every level
of every spell must be cast so over
those four days someone needs to cast
summon construct unseen servant
obscuring mist phantom steed summon
elemental and stinking cloud and also
need to cast summon construct again at
third level summon elemental again at
third level and creation and then also
need to cast phantom steed summon
construct and summon elemental each one
more time at fourth level tanglefoot
does not need to be cast during crafting
because can trips are not leveled spells
spell slots must be used when casting
all of these spells and there are no
other effects of casting the spell their
energy is transferred safely to the
staff with no other benefits and I don't
think any of these spells call for an
additional cost but if they did then we
would not pay that as part of the
crafting process because this is a staff
which is one of the exceptions you only
pay those costs if what you're making is
not a staff or a wand after we've paid
our 450 gold we've cast all of the NIDA
spells and we've spent four days working
then we make a crafting skill check as
normal again CDC set by the GM and if
successful we can either pay the
remaining 450 gold to finish creating
the staff immediately or we can spend
additional days of downtime working just
like normal
last let's make a suit of adamantine
full plate armor same setup as before
and again we're going to assume all of
the requirements have been met this will
work the same as crafting anything else
but there is one big difference to keep
in mind when crafting from purchase
materials and that's the price price
isn't given upfront
instead you need to calculate it for
yourself it says here that the price of
adamantine armor is 1600 gold plus a
hundred and sixty gold per point of bulk
if we check the armor table in the core
rules we see that full plate armor is
listed as for bulk however it is
important to remember that this table
shows the armors worn a bulk and when
crafting we need to know it's carried a
bulk carried bulk is one higher than an
armors worn bulk so the carried bulk of
a suit of full plate armor is five five
times a hundred and sixty is eight
hundred gold pieces plus 1600 makes the
final price for a suit of full plate
adamantine armor two thousand four
hundred gold pieces note that you do not
add the regular cost of the armor the
table says full plate costs thirty gold
but you do not need to add that to the
2400 that we've already calculated
now to begin crafting we need to provide
fifty percent of the price up front in
materials just like always
fifty percent of 2400 is 1200 gold if we
look back at the step block for the
adamantine armor we see it requires that
the initial raw materials must include
200 gold plus 20 per bulk in adamantine
again this suit of armor is five bulk
five times 20 is 100 so that means
before because our crafting we need
three hundred gold pieces worth of
adamantine a
and 900 gold pieces worth of other
materials the 900 gold we can pay
out-of-pocket since it's assumed that we
can find these basic materials just
about anywhere but adamantine is
uncommon we can't just go to a store and
buy it most likely we received a chunk
of adamantine as part of the treasure
from our adventures but once we have the
300 gold worth of adamantine and 900
gold in basic materials we can begin
crafting and from there it works exactly
like crafting anything else we spend 4
days working after which there is a
skill check and if we succeed that check
we can either pay the remaining balance
of 1200 gold pieces or spend more
downtime working to lower that balance
just note that if we decide to pay off
the balance none of that needs to
include adamantine the 300 gold worth of
adamantine provided with the initial
materials is all of the adamantine that
is needed for this project
if you'd like to see the companion
course that explains the rules behind
these examples you can find a link to it
in the description and highlighted on
the screen as well if you found this
video helpful please give us a like and
click that bell so you never miss out on
our future videos if you'd like to
support this channel so that we can keep
producing instructional videos you can
do so through our patreon and feel free
to leave in the comments any suggestions
you have for future examples thanks for
watching take care and we'll see you
soon with more basics for your favorite
games