hello and welcome to basics for gamers
presents the basics of crafting part 3
for a Pathfinder 2nd edition in the
first part of the series we discussed
the basic framework that all crafting
follows and in the previous course we
took a closer look at crafting magical
items and forging weapons and armor from
special materials now in this video
we're going to address a few of the
remaining odds and ends
starting with formulas
we've previously discussed how common
formulas can be purchased and uncommon
formulas may be awarded by the GM as
part of treasurer but there are a couple
other ways that you can use to gain
formulas the first of those being
through invention the inventor feat is
available starting at 7th level for
those who have at least master
proficiency in crafting with this feat a
character can spend downtime to create
their own formulas instead of buying
them the only real requirement worth
mentioning is that the formula must be
for a common rarity item there are no
other hard requirements but I think a GM
would be within the right to say that
you can only create a formula for
something that you can actually craft
for example you would need the magical
crafting feat to create the formula for
a magic potion again that is not a
strict rules as written interpretation
but as a GM I just think that that is
logical also crafting the formula works
just like crafting anything else you pay
half the cost up front for that formula
and then spend 4 days working and then
you make a crafting skill check if
successful you can either pay their
balance or spend another day of downtime
working when the balance is reduced to
zero then you have a new formula the
other way to gain new formulas is
through reverse engineering this works
pretty much the same but in Reverse
instead of creating a new item you're
taking a part and item you already have
to see how it works and then creating a
formula to make that item through the
knives gained by taking it apart first
you spend four days disassembling and
examining that item this effectively
destroys it and leaves you with raw
materials worth 50% of the items listed
price after this you make a crafting
skill check vs. ADC set by the GM and
this DC should be the same DC that you
would roll against to craft that item if
you succeed you can craft the items
formula at the formulas full price
not half as price as is normal
crafting because at this point you have
not invested any money towards the
project yet
the 50% value that you gain from
disassembling the item that is money in
your pocket at this point nothing's been
invested towards creating the formula
and then from there everything just
works as normal you can pay the
remaining balance or spend another day
of downtime working when the balance
reaches zero then you have a formula for
the original item and then if you want
you can use the formula that you just
created in order to recreate the item
that you took apart using the raw
materials that you were given when you
disassembled it these raw materials
again are 50% so conveniently that's the
amount of money that you would have to
put up to begin crafting it anyway
although the book does not state that
only common rarity items can be reverse
engineered crafting a formula like this
is based on the formulas price and at
the time of this recording formula
prices are only available for common
rarity items but if the GM wishes to
place a price on the formula for an
uncommon or rare item then this process
theoretically could be used by players
to gain harder to find formulas
another interesting twist to crafting is
that goblins can take the junk tinker
feat to save a little bit of time or a
little bit of money this feat lets
goblins craft level zero items other
than armor and they make it out of
whatever junk happens to be lying around
when doing so the price of the item
being crafted is reduced to one quarter
of his normal price but if successful
with the result is always shoddy for
example let's say such a goblin wanted
to craft a battle-axe battle-axes
normally cost one gold piece which is
the same as ten silver pieces but in
this case we would treat it as having
1/4 that price or two silver pieces in
five copper so the goblin crafter in
this example would need to provide half
of that upfront which would be one
silver and three copper pieces and after
four days of work would have a remaining
balance of once over three copper this
does accelerate the crafting process but
the downside is if successful it only
produces a shoddy quality battle-ax
shoddy items have half the regular items
hip points and half the usual break
threshold and normally when you use a
shoddy item to make an attack or any
other check with that item you suffer a
negative two penalty to that role by
goblins with the jump tinker feet do not
suffer that negative two penalty when
using any shoddy items that they created
unless it's worth mentioning that the
crafting skill can be used to make more
than just weapons and gear the game
mastery guide points out that the
crafting skill may be used to cut and
polish raw gems into fine jewelry the GM
can provide unfinished gems as part of
treasure an unfinished gem is worth half
of that gems normal value and is then
used as the regular 50% material cost
that's required at the beginning of all
crafting so from there just works as
normal the crafter would spend four days
of work followed by a crafting skill
check and then either paying off the
balance or working until the remaining
balance is reduced to zero at which time
you have a properly cut and finished
gemstone that is worth its full price
instead of the 50% that an unfinished
gem is worth and although we're stepping
a little bit into house rule territory
here I think is reasonable that these
same process could apply to creating
other works of art maybe a player wants
to craft a golden crown as a gift to the
local queen or make an awe-inspiring
holy symbol for their chosen deity the
process in theory would work the same
determine the value of the item provide
half the cost upfront and spend four
days of work and make a crafting skill
check just make sure you also keep in
mind there are minimum proficiency
requirements so you may need to assign
an item level to the work of art being
created not just a price and value to it
and also you may need to enforce other
requirements such as requiring an amount
of gems be included in the initial
materials for creating a fancy crown and
stepping even further into household
territory
you could even apply the same process to
other skills maybe a bard wishes to
write their masterpiece Symphony they
could use in theory the performance
skill in place of crafting but it would
work the same way pay 50% of the value
upfront spend four days working and then
pay the remaining balance or continue
luring that balance with additional day
to work it might seem odd that you have
to pay 500 gold pieces upfront when
writing a symphony that the GM valued at
a thousand gold pieces but that could be
explained away by the need to rent
practice space or for a hiring
professional musicians to play and
rehearse your music as you continue to
listen to it and refine it into a is a
finished symphony again this is deeply
within house rule territory so use with
caution but the point that I want to get
across here is to look outside the box
and try to find ways that you can make
crafting work beyond just building stuff
for adventuring
in this video we close out our series on
crafting by covering a few odds and ends
in addition to purchasing formulas there
are a couple other means of gaining them
the first of those is through inventing
the formula yourself inventor is a feat
those with master proficiency can take
starting at seventh level with it a
character can craft any common rarity
formula using the same process as
crafting anything else and the second
method to gain more formulas is by
reverse engineering this allows a
character to dismantle an object and
study it until they figure out how it
works and then they can write a formula
for it when it character reverse
engineers an item that item is destroyed
but the crafter is left with raw
materials worth 50% of that items listed
price for days are spent working
followed by a crafting check against a
DC set by the GM if successful the
crafter can spend more days working to
pay off the balance just like normal
except the remaining balance after four
days of work starts at the full price of
the formula not half of it and if the
crafting check results in a critical
failure then 10% of the value of the
salvage material is lost goblins can
also craft items a little bit quicker in
relatively cheaper by using the junk
tinker feat this works like normal
crafting except the items price is set
at 1/4 of its listed price and results
in a shoddy item shoddy items have half
the usual hit points and half the usual
break threshold and normally impose a
negative to penalty to any checks made
with that item but goblins do not face
that negative to penalty with shoddy
items that they themselves created in
last crafting can be used to cut and
polish unfinished stones and turn them
into finished gems unfinished gems have
half the value of cut gems and are used
as the initial materials needed for
crafting the finish Jim and although not
strictly permitted by the rules as
written
gm's might want to consider letting
their players use this same framework
for crafting other items like works of
art literature paintings and the like
before we close I'd like to take a
moment to thank all of our patrons these
videos would not be possible without
their continued generosity and support
members of the basics for gamers patreon
community receive special benefits like
getting to vote on the topics that we
cover in the future and also they get to
see these videos one week and ad-free
before everybody else visit the links
shown on the left of the screen and in
the description if you'd like to know
more about becoming a patron if you
would like to support this channel and
help it grow the easiest way to do that
is by subscribing and clicking the bell
icon so you get notified when new videos
release and we can always be reached
through our Twitter and Facebook pages
too thanks for watching take care and we
will see you soon with more basics of
Pathfinder