welcome to complex crafting and
Pathfinder second edition this video
provides an overview of an optional
crafting system that modifies the
original crafting rules that were
covered in Parts one through three of
this series as such it is highly
recommended that you watch part one of
this series before continuing a link to
it is provided in the description
one of the most controversial aspects of
Pathfinder's crafting rules is that it
takes a minimum of four days to craft
anything regardless of its value it
takes a first level blacksmith four days
to create a simple dagger and it also
takes a level 20 blacksmith with
legendary proficiency four days to craft
the same basic dagger the complex
crafting system was released as an
option to address this issue basically
what the system does is it reduces the
amount of time needed to craft items
that are lower level than the crafter
but with an increase to the crafting DC
that must be passed this is a four-step
process step one you must meet all
requirements step two you set up the
project step three roll a crafting skill
check and step four finish the project
by either paying off the remaining value
or by spending additional days of
downtime working on it
the core crafting system is mostly
unchanged with complex crafting and it's
really only in steps two and four that
you'll see any difference
so step one is still the same you must
meet all the same requirements as before
including providing half the items value
in raw materials in step two you set up
the project with the original crafting
rules this took a flat four days but
with complex crafting the amount of
setup time may be anywhere from 4 hours
to six days to determine the amount of
setup time that's needed refer to Table
5 1 from the Pathfinder treasure vault
there are two columns one for consumable
items and another for permanent items if
the item you're crafting has an item
level that's equal to your character
level then you need four days of setup
time if it is a consumable item or six
days of setup time if it's a permanent
item and the amount of setup time that's
required is lowered if the items level
is lower than your character level
once you've determined the setup time
you next need to decide if you're okay
with that amount of time or if you want
to rush things and craft the item faster
the amount of time you can reduce the
setup by is based on your crafting
proficiency level with trained
proficiency you cannot Rush a project
and must use the listed setup time
with expert proficiency you can reduce
the setup Time by one day but suffer a
plus five increase to the crafting DC
with Master proficiency you can reduce
the setup Time by two days with suffer a
plus 10 increase to the crafting DC and
with legendary proficiency you can
reduce the setup Time by three days but
suffer a plus 15 increase to the
crafting DC and setup always requires a
minimum of four hours no matter how much
you lure it by rushing
after the setup time passes you enter
step 3 in need to roll your crafting
skill check this works exactly the same
as it does with the original crafting
rules except the DC might be increased
due to rushing the project
if you succeed on this check then you
move on to step four and can either pay
off the remaining balance and materials
or you can spend additional days working
on the project each extra day spent
reduces the remaining balance by the
appropriate amount found on the income
earned table again this is the same as
with the original crafting system so see
part one of this video series if you
need a refresher on how that works
what is different with complex crafting
though is you can choose not only to
rush the setup process but you can also
choose to rush the finishing process
here as well
if you are at least expert in crafting
you can Rush the finishing process
reducing the value of the materials you
must expend to complete the item by
twice the amount found on the income
earned Table after each day of downtime
working so for example if you're six
level with expert crafting proficiency
each additional day of downtime spent
working on the project will reduce the
remaining balance by two gold pieces but
if you decide to rush then each extra
day of work will reduce the remaining
balance by four gold pieces this of
course does not come without added risk
at the end of the crafting process after
the remaining balance has been reduced
to zero and the item would normally be
complete you must roll a flat check
the DC for this check is 10 plus the
items level minus your crafting
proficiency bonus note that this is only
your proficiency bonus not your total
crafting skill modifier so this will be
your level plus four if you have expert
proficiency your level plus six with
Master proficiency or your level plus
eight with legendary proficiency and
because this is a flat check nothing is
added to the roll it is just a straight
D20 against the DC for example if you're
six level with expert proficiency and
you're crafting a fourth level item the
DC for this check will be 10 plus 4 for
the item level minus 10 for having
expert proficiency and that gives you a
final DC of four if this flat check is a
success or critical success then the
item is crafted without any issues if
the check is a failure then the item is
completed but gain a quark and quarks
can be found on page 86 of the game
mastery guide and if the check is a
critical failure then the item is either
ruined or may become cursed at the GM's
discretion
complex crafting also introduces one new
crafting skill feat called quick setup
as the name implies this feed allows a
character to reduce the amount of needed
setup time even further for items that
are at least six levels lower than the
character's level
it also allows a character to reduce the
setup time for consumable items to only
two hours which makes it possible to
craft such items during the adventuring
day instead of solely during downtime
however please note that this feat is
listed as rare so it should not be
commonly available and the book provides
an additional warning that reads this
rapid form of crafting could cause your
players to end up with higher treasure
values or more items than an adventure
expects them to have so be careful about
allowing this fee in campaigns that
already provide significant amounts of
downtime
so that should give you an overview of
the new complex crafting rules found in
the Pathfinder treasure Vault stay tuned
for a follow-up to this video where I
will be providing an example that walks
you through the entire crafting process
of crafting a magic item using this
system and again if any of this is
confusing make sure you check out the
first video of this series as this new
complex crafting system keeps the
original process largely intact a link
to that video and all my others that
touch on Crafting are included in the
description and I'd like to take a quick
moment to thank everyone out there who
supports me with us by leaving a comment
clicking the like button subscribing to
the channel subscribing to the patreon
buying a super thanks it all adds up and
I greatly appreciate everything the
community does to support me and this
channel so with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]