this video is brought to you by roll for
combat and the fall of plaguestone an
official piezo actual play podcast
join peru cade brixley and celeste as
they band together to save the village
of plaguestone from utter destruction
listen now to the fall of plaguestone at
roll4combat.com
hey everybody today i have for you a
first look and preview of guns and gears
for pathfinder 2nd edition two quick
notes before i get too deep into this
first i should let you know that i was
provided a pdf copy of this book by
paizo and second i don't want this video
to be confused with a full review so let
me see up front i've only just now
received the book and i have not yet had
an opportunity to see any of his
contents played out on the game table so
what follows will be a first look at his
contents and my initial first
impressions
guns and gears is 242 pages from cover
to cover and retails for 49.99 in the us
the pdf version may also be purchased
online for only 14.99
the book begins with an introduction
that addresses some of the common
concerns about introducing firearms and
technology into a fantasy setting there
will be those who embrace this sort of
thing but there will be others who
prefer their fantasy worlds to stick to
swords and sorcery without adding rifles
and robots to the mix and that's okay
it's also okay to add just a little of
the book's contents to an existing game
instead of all or none of it the
introduction explains that guns and
gears is broken up into three distinct
sections each of which can be considered
to be its own small mini book the first
of these mini books covers the gears
portion the second covers the guns
portion and the final mini book is a
gazetteer that discusses where within
the official setting of gallerium you're
likely to find these elements organizing
the book in a modular way should help
gms to pick and choose how much of the
book they want to allow in their games
some games may only want to add
clockwork inventors to the games without
also allowing firearms others may like
the idea of noble pistol-slinging
paladins like roland from the dark tower
but don't necessarily want to open their
game up to robots in higher science the
introduction goes on to tackle another
often voiced concern which is what's the
point of having a sword when you can
have a machine gun the book says that
all the firearms are treated as examples
of early black powder weapons and
promises that they are balanced with the
other weapons of the game but again i
have not had the opportunity to put that
to the test yet
the book's first chapter tackles gears
characters here we find the first of two
new classes introduced in the book the
inventor the inventor feels very much
inspired by edgar and other machinists
from final fantasy each inventor has
their own unique device that they
created and only they know how to use
these are referred to as innovations and
guns and gears provides three options
for players armor construct or weapon
innovations
each of these options have their own
special features and can be sort of
overclocked for additional benefits at
the risk of exploding as the inventor
levels up they have breakthroughs and
discover new and exciting ways of using
their personal innovation this chapter
also introduces a new rare ancestry the
automaton not to be confused with
androids automatons are centuries-old
constructs imbued with the mind and soul
of an ancient gisken soldier or scholar
these are not mass-produced robots but
instead are as unique and individual as
any other living creature and as living
creatures they do not have the usual
construct immunities and are affected by
anything that affects a living being
including positive healing
and automatons do not need to eat drink
or sleep but do need two hours of rest
each day during which they remain awake
and aware of their surroundings many of
the automatons feats deal with enhancing
their bodies like claws magical
camouflage i-beams and the like this
chapter also provides a wealth of new
gear inspired backgrounds and also rare
backgrounds like the ones we saw in
secrets of magic i won't list all of
them but you can see them on the screen
here just keep in mind that the rare
backgrounds are not intended for all
games and so you're going to want to get
permission from your gm before you
pursue any of those
the gears portion of the book also
provides several new archetypes the
first is overwatch these are battlefield
tacticians who use gear that enhances
their vision so they can keep watch over
and direct their allies during battle
next are sterling dynamos who are
attached to special clockwork
prosthetics
next are trapsmiths and they're pretty
much what you would expect they're
experts at crafting and setting snares
trick drivers are experts at piloting
vehicles and vehicle mechanics not only
repair but enhance vehicles to new
heights
chapter 2 of the book is all about new
gear themed equipment the new items
presented here range from the fantastic
to just plain wacky some of the gear
here even feels like it was pulled
straight out of an old james bond movie
such as the dart umbrella this chapter
also introduces a new kind of consumable
technological device called gadgets
much like elixirs and mutagen's art
alchemists you don't have to be an
inventor to use gadgets although they
are especially well suited to do so an
example might be blast boots that allows
their user to jump without having to
stride first
after the gadgets the book covers siege
weapons which honestly i was surprised
to see here i figured siege weapons
would fit in better with a book about
mass combat rules and cover everything
that goes into sieges but guns and gears
does provide a basic foundation for
rules and several common examples
including ballistas battering rams
catapults and trebuchets
guns and gears also introduces enhanced
mobility devices for physically disabled
characters this includes several new
wheelchair options including frog chairs
they'll let the user not just roll for
movement but also jump over pits and
other obstacles as well
and then chapter 3 kicks off the second
mini-book of guns and gears and is all
about guns character options the most
notable new addition here is the
gunslinger class unsurprisingly
gunslingers are arranged combat experts
but do not strictly wield firearms in
fact some quote gunslingers never touch
a gun and instead are experts with
crossbows
gunslingers each choose a particular
fighting style to specialize in called
waze guns and gears offers four ways to
choose from way of the drifter mixes
ranged and melee combat skills think of
pirates who fight with a colors in one
hand in a black powder pistol in the
other
way of the pistolero focuses on fighting
with pistols while the way of the sniper
focuses on longer range combat with
rifles
and last way of the vanguard is for
heavy weapon experts who use explosives
to clear a path for their allies
beyond the new class this chapter also
presents even more new backgrounds on
common backgrounds and rare backgrounds
several of which seemed less tied to
guns and firearms so much as to a
western theme such as the saloon
entertainer
the guns chapter also introduces new
archetypes beast gunner bullet dancers
who are sort of gun wielding monks
demolitionist firework technician pistol
phenom sniping duo which is a sniper who
uses a partner to serve as a spotter
spellshot a class archetype for
gunslingers that adds magic to their
firearm use
and unexpected sharpshooters who turn
clumsy good luck into precise shots
next chapter 4 is all about new guns
related equipment just like with the
previous section about gears equipment
this chapter is roughly 40 pages full of
new options after a discussion of
firearms and their place in a fantasy
setting the chapter provides stats for
each gun and an explanation of misfires
that can occur if the gun is not
properly cleaned once per day
generally speaking the steps for
firearms are not inherently more
powerful than existing ranged weapons
but where they really shine is with
critical hits many firearms have the
fatal trait allowing them to do extra
damage on their crits
after discussing conventional firearms
the book dives into the more fantastical
guns of golerian beast guns for example
these weapons use magic instead of black
powder and are forged from the harvested
remains of monsters for example the
petrification cannon this is a
double-barreled musket crafted from the
remains of a basilisk so that it also is
capable of casting flesh to stone
this chapter also introduces cobwed
firearms which are special guns crafted
by goblins that are prone to misfires
and the book also provides rules for
combination weapons that meld two
weapons together this basically allows
you to use one of final fantasy 8's gun
blades
the gun section of the book continues by
adding more siege weapons as well
specifically those that use black powder
like cannons and mortars
the fifth and final chapter of the book
is 40 or so pages of lore it dives into
where the tech comes from why it is used
there and to some degree why this
technology has not spread and become
commonplace elsewhere in the world the
chapter explores several locations
giving each of them about five pages
worth of space to flesh out their
history and their relationship with this
technology
this includes the dwarven fortress of
dogen hold and the industrial city of
alkenstar each of which has embraced
technology as a means of survival within
the mana wastes
similar attention is paid to absalom as
the so-called center of the world houses
technological wonders such as the
clockwork cathedral
and breeze most prominent temple in the
city the gallery of innovation
the next featured location is arcadia
home of beast guns and sky metals
i may be wrong but i think this may be
the most detailed information we've
received about arcadia in second edition
so far the next section covered is the
ancient jessica imperium a long lost and
almost forgotten empire that once ruled
through mighty golem armies although
jessica itself was defeated long ago by
the assyrian armies remnants of its lost
technology occasionally resurfaced today
next a section devoted to the shackles
dies into the role of black powder in
piracy and naval battles
and a write-up of tion shaw and vudra
gets into the invention of black powder
from simple fireworks to explosives and
rockets and how they are embraced in
these faraway lands
and the final section of the book is
dedicated to usolav and their recent
discovery of stasian technology that
uses electricity to produce amazing
effects this very much seems to be
inspired by tesla coils and movies like
the prestige
as mentioned at the start it's difficult
to do a proper review without first
seeing all of these new rules and new
systems played out on the table but my
initial first impressions are largely
positive i very much appreciate the
modular approach this book takes to
dividing up the material between gears
chapters and guns chapters so gm's have
an easier time picking and choosing what
is appropriate for their games
i suspect the biggest draw for this book
will be the two new classes inventor has
very quickly become one of the classes i
most want to play and gunslinger it
seems fine but i'm not quite as excited
about playing that as inventor
reading it didn't really strike me with
the same wow factor that inventor did
but that said i do like that they
incorporated crossbows into the class so
that it can be used in campaigns that
don't allow firearms i don't really have
any major complaints about the book but
will say that the inclusion of siege
weapons strikes me as a little bit odd
they fit the theme of the book just fine
but it almost feels like i'm only
getting half of the rules that i would
want to have when running a siege i
would have preferred that siege weapons
be saved for a more robust rule set that
covers all the different stages and all
the things that go into a siege this
book gives us weapons to attack with but
what about siege defenses um this isn't
really a complaint it's just an
observation i guess anyway that should
give you a pretty good idea about this
book's contents please let me know in
the comments if you have any questions
about this book and as always take care
and happy gaming