hey everyone in today's video I'm going
to walk you through crafting a magic
item using the new complex crafting
rules from top to bottom if you haven't
already done so make sure you've watched
my crafting part 1 video as well as my
video on complex crafting as they
explain the rules that I will be
illustrating here links to those videos
are provided in the description
Bruno the dwarf is seventh level and
discovered the formula for a spell guard
Shield while adventuring once her party
returns to Town the GM gives them two
weeks of downtime which she decides to
spend forging the spell guard Shield the
complex crafting system is a four-step
process step one you must meet all
requirements step two you set up the
project step 3 roll a crafting skill
check in Step 4 finish the project by
either paying off the remaining value or
spending additional days of downtime
working on it so let's walk through this
step by step in Step 1 Bruno must meet
all six requirements to craft the item
the first requirement is that the item's
level may not be higher than the
character's level the spell guard Shield
is a sixth level item and Bruno is a
seventh level character so we're good
here the second requirement is the
crafter must have the required crafting
proficiency rank as a sixth level item
crafting a spell guard Shield requires
trained proficiency Runa has Master
crafting proficiency so she easily meets
this requirement
the third requirement is as a magical
item a character must have the magical
crafting feat to craft a spell guard
shield and Bruno does have this feat the
fourth requirement is you must have the
proper tools for the job Runa is well
regarded in this community and the local
blacksmith is allowing her to use their
workshop
the fifth requirement is you need to
have the items formula and Bruno
discovered this formula as part of her
last adventurous treasure and the sixth
requirement is you must provide fifty
percent of the item's value in materials
spell guard Shield has a price of 250
gold pieces so Bruno must provide 125
gold worth of raw materials there are no
special material requirements here so
Bruno's GM allows her to Simply pay 125
gold and she meets this requirement too
with all requirements met we can move to
step two set up the project Bruno is
seventh level and the shield she wishes
to craft is sixth level per table five
one in the Treasure Vault crafting a
permanent item that is one level lower
than you calls for five days of setup
she's only expecting to have two weeks
to complete the project so Bruno decides
to rush the setup and save a little bit
of time
since she has mastered proficiency she
can reduce the setup Time by up to two
days but doing so would increase the DC
of the check by 10. she decides to only
Rush by one day which reduces the setup
time to four days but with an increase
to the DC of the chick that she must
pass in step three by five
after these four days pass Bruno moves
into step three and must roll her
crafting skill check to set the DC for
the check the GM first uses table 10-5
from the core rulebook
Milgard Shields are sixth level items so
per table ten five this is a dc22 skill
check
next the GM would modify this DC by
Rarity but since spellguard Shields are
common Rarity this DC is not modified
further due to Rarity but for the sake
of illustration if the shield was
uncommon Rarity the DC would be
increased by two and if it was rare the
DC would be increased by five
last we add the penalty for rushing the
setup which brings the final DC for this
check to 27.
Bruno has a crafting skill bonus of plus
16 so she has a 50 50 chance of passing
this chick all she needs is an 11 or
higher on the die so we'll say she rolls
a 13 for a total of 29 which is a
success if she had failed the check she
would have to start the process over
again and if she had critically failed
she would have to start over and would
also have ruined 10 of her materials
with this successful skill check we move
into step 4 finishing the project spell
guard Shields have a listed price of 250
gold and Bruno has already provided half
of that in materials which leaves a
remaining balance of 125 GP
per the income earned table as a seventh
level character with Master Proficiency
in crafting each additional day of work
will lower this remaining balance by two
and a half gold which is about 50 days
of work
if she decides to rush the finishing
process each day of work will be worth a
double and reduce the remaining balance
by 5 gold which means it'll only take 25
days instead of 50 days to complete the
project
the GM said that she has two weeks of
downtime and she's already spent four on
the setup so Bruno decides to rush and
get as much out of her remaining 10 days
of downtime as possible
at the end of these 10 days she has
reduced the Project's budget by 50 gold
leaving a remaining balance of 75 gold
pieces
since time has run out Bruno decides to
pay the remaining 75 to complete the
project within the narrative she and her
GM decide that the extra money was spent
on a couple assistants as well as a
local wizard who helped with the
necessary enchantments to craft the
Magic Shield
and now there's only one thing left to
do since Bruno decided to rush the
finishing of the project she must roll a
flat check to see if the shield has any
defects the DC for this check is 10 plus
the items level minus Bruno's crafting
proficiency bonus as a seventh level
character with Master proficiency and
crafting that proficiency bonus is 13.
so in this case the DC of the flat check
is 10 plus 6 for the item level minus 13
for the proficiency bonus which gives us
a final DC of three
this is a straight D20 roll with no
modifiers so as long as she rolls a
three or higher The Shield works
properly if she rolls a 2 which is a
failure The Shield develops a special
Quirk and if she rolls a one which is a
critical failure the GM needs to decide
if the shield is ruined or cursed
although not specified in the rules it
might be best for the GM to roll this in
secret just in case the result is a
cursed item
for fun we'll see that she rolls a 2 on
the D20 and that means that the item has
a special cork
s can be found on page 86 of the game
mastery guide the GM rolls a D100 and
gets a 36 which makes the spell guard
Shield bloodthirsty it Quivers in
Bruno's grip whenever is near blood
so there you have it crafting a magic
item from start to finish using the new
complex crafting rules if you have any
questions please leave them in the
comments below I'll leave links to any
of my related videos about crafting in
the description and I'd like to take a
quick moment to thank everyone out there
who supports this channel whether that
be by clicking the like button
subscribing to the channel subscribing
to the patreon buying a super thanks it
all adds up and I greatly appreciate
everything you do to support this
Channel and with that thanks for
watching take care and happy gaming
thank you
foreign