[Music]
hello and welcome to stamina in
Pathfinder 2nd edition
stamina is a variant rule found in the
game mastery guide as such it is not
assumed to be used in most games but is
an alternative method of tracking player
Health that many GMS play self-included
prefer instead of the standard hit point
rules that are found in the core
rulebook and the standard hit point
system hit points are a one large lump
sum that represent a character's ability
to avoid suffering a fatal injury the
loss of hit points can represent several
things that loss could represent a
character tiring themselves out as they
repeatedly Dodge in Perry Blues it could
represent the effects of drinking a
poison or it could represent being
stabbed by a sword this is largely up to
the GM and the way they narrate combat
but the main issue that seems to occur
is if one player loses hit points from
becoming fatigued and another player
loses hit points from being run through
by a sword then shouldn't the first
player have an ease your time recovering
these lost hit points then the second
and that's one of the things that the
stamina system addresses it takes
characters hit points and divides them
into two separate resources stamina
points and hit points
stamina points represent the character
avoiding physical damage but becoming
increasingly more tired as they do so
and as such stamina points are very easy
to recover needing only a few minutes
for the character to sit and catch their
breath while hit points represent
physical damage to the character when a
player suffers hit point damage their
character has been physically hit
they've been bruised they've been
slashed or burned or stabbed and as such
healing lost hit points is significantly
more difficult than recovering lost
stamina points
combat using the stamina system works
mostly the same as with the standard hit
point rules the main difference is how
stamina points and hit points are
deducted unless the GM determines
otherwise when a character suffers
damage they apply that damage to their
temporary hit points first if they have
any and once their temporary hit points
are reduced to zero damage is then
applied to their stamina points and once
their stamina points are reduced to zero
damage is then applied to their hit
points and once those are reduced to
zero the character Falls unconscious as
normal
that is the usual process but the GM may
decide that the nature of an injury
could only be applied to hit points and
therefore skip over stamina points
entirely and apply the damage directly
to hit points for example full damage
might be difficult to describe as only
tiring a character and the GM may decide
to apply that damage to hit points or to
split it between hip points of stamina
however I caution to do this only in
very rare cases when you absolutely
cannot explain the damage as anything
other than physical trauma for example
some people may say that being stomped
by an elephant could only be applied to
hit points but if you describe it as
jumping out of the path of the Elephant
at the last minute that would be a valid
description for losing stamina points
instead of hit points would in doubt
stick to the regular process of
deducting from temporary hip wounds
first then stamina points and last hit
points
to calculate a character's stamina
points and hit points you use table 4-21
at the bottom of page 200 in the game
mastery guide at first level characters
gain a number of stamina points as
listed in the second column of the table
and they gain a number of hit points
equal to their ancestry hit points plus
an amount listed in the third column and
for every level after first they
increase their stamina and hit points by
the amounts indicated in the table let's
use a halfling rogue with a constitution
score of 12 as an example at first level
they would calculate their stamina
points as 4 per the table plus one for
their constitutional modifier for a
total of five stamina points and they'd
calculate their hit points as six for
their halfling ancestry plus four per
table 421 for a total of 10 hit points
at second level their stamina points
would increase by five more and their
hit points would increase by four more
because ancestry hit points only apply
for first level essentially characters
in the stamina system have the same
amount of points they're just divided
into these two pools in addition to
stamina points and hit points when using
the system players will also have one
more resource to track which is called
resolve every player has a number of
resolve points equal to their key
ability modifier so using our example of
the halfling Rogue if they have a
dexterity of 16 and that is their key
ability then they would have three
resolved points and note that all spent
resolve points are returned after a full
night's rest there are two main ways
that resolve points are spent first an
unconscious player may spend one resolve
point to stabilize and if they do so
they gain one hit point and return to
Consciousness at the start of their next
turn note that if you choose to use the
stamina system you may want to remove
the ability of hero points to stabilize
characters also the second way resolve
points are used is to regain lost
stamina
as mentioned before lost stamina points
and lost hit points are each healed in
different ways we'll start with the
stamina points the first thing to know
about regaining stamina is stamina
cannot be healed by traditional means
anything in the game that is currently
used to heal hit points does not also
heal stamina so the heal spell treat
wounds healing potions and the like have
no effect on stamina instead there are
two main ways of regaining stamina
points the take a breather action and
the rally action
take a breather costs one resolve point
and takes 10 minutes after which you
regain all lost stamina points since
stamina represents the character tiring
they're relatively easy to get back
after a fight you just need to rest for
10 minutes and catch your breath and you
completely heal all stamina up to your
maximum stamina value and since this
costs one resolve Point players have a
limit to how often they may use this
action the second way to recover stamina
is through the rally action to use rally
you must be trained in diplomacy
intimidation or performance you spend
one minute encouraging an ally after
which you roll a dc-15 skill check using
one of the listed skills diplomacy
intimidation or performance
on a success you can continue
encouraging them for nine more minutes
10 minutes total if you do so then the
target can then spend one resolve point
and regain their stamina up to their Max
stamina value this is functionally the
same as take a breather so why would you
do this the answer is because on a
critical success the Ally can
immediately spend one resolve point to
regain their stamina up to their maximum
stamina value after only one minute
instead of 10 minutes
if you don't think you're going to have
10 minutes for take a breather this
could be a solution to regain all of
your stamina back on the downside if you
critically fail the chick the Ally
suffers 1d8 mental damage to their
stamina points and this kind of loss is
only applied to stamina and can never
affect hit points
and the third way to regain stamina is
through rest after a full night of rest
the character regains all of their
stamina and all of their resolve points
they also still heal an amount of hit
points as normal for a night of rest
a few things to consider about the
stamina system first only players in
very significant NPCs should need to
make adjustments to use this system
there is no need to give stamina and
resolve points to monsters and other
enemies
when a character is reduced to zero hit
points they fall unconscious like normal
even if they somehow still have stamina
points
since this is an optional variant rule
system not every single detail in the
other rule books are written with
stamina in mind therefore the GM will
need to make their own decisions for how
certain issues interact with stamina for
example massive damage was not written
with stamina in mind so it will be up to
the GM to decide how massive damage
interacts with the stamina system
they'll need to decide if massive damage
occurs when one blow doubles the
character's maximum hit points or if it
occurs when one blow deals double the
character's maximum hit points and
maximum stamina points combined for what
it's worth in my games I use the latter
remember the traditional means of
healing only heal hit points for example
if an ally has no stamina and 15 out of
20 hit points remaining and you heal
them for seven points of damage they
will have their maximum of 20 hit points
but still no stamina points excess
healing does not heal lost stamina you
have to use other means like take a
breather or rally for that and the vice
versa is also true healing excess
stamina points will not carry over and
heal hit points affects either heal hip
points or stamina and never both
and last be aware that there are both
pros and cons to using this system a
major Pro is the system makes healing up
between encounters easier without
spending time at the table rolling
numerous chicks for treat wounds but on
the con side this system makes it more
difficult to heal up in the middle of an
encounter since both take a breather and
rally can only be used during times of
rest players will find healing in the
middle of a fight even more challenging
there are however two new Feats that can
help mitigate this a little the first is
called encouraging words and is sort of
like battle medicine for stamina it's a
second level feat and with it you can
spend one action to inspire an ally
within 30 feet you roll a diplomacy
check versus dc15 and honest success the
target regains 1d8 stamina points on a
critical success they regain 2d8 stamina
points and on a failure nothing happens
and on a critical failure they suffer
1d8 mental damage that can only be
applied to stamina
no matter what the result of the check
is the target of encouraging words
cannot benefit from it again until they
either use the takey Breather action or
they get a night's rest
note that this is slightly different
than how battle medicine works when you
use battle medicine the target becomes
immune to your battle medicine for the
rest of the day whereas with encouraging
words the target becomes temporarily
immune to anyone's future use of
encouraging words until they get a full
night's rest or use the take a breather
action and just like with treat wounds
or battle medicine if you are at least
expert Proficiency in diplomacy you can
choose to increase the DC of the check
for more healing a dc-20 check heals an
extra five stamina points a DC 30 chick
heals an extra 15 stamina points and a
DC40 check heals an extra 25 stamina
points
and the second feat that allows the
character to heal stamina during an
encounter is steal your resolve this is
a third level feat and with it a player
may spend one action and one resolve
point to regain an amount of stand-up
points equal to half their maximum
stamina this is half as effective as
take a breather but may be used in the
middle of combat for one action
so there's a look at the optional
stamina system for Pathfinder second
edition if you have any questions please
leave them in the comments I'll leave
the links in the description of any of
my other videos related to health and
hit points and as always I want to take
a quick moment to thank everyone out
there who supports me whether that's by
liking this video subscribing to the
channel subscribing to the patreon
buying a super thanks I greatly
appreciate everything you folks do to
support me and with that thanks for
watching take care and happy gaming
foreign
[Music]