welcome to battle breakdown by how it's
played the series that examines famous
scenes from movies and television
through the lens of a role-playing game
and illustrates how those events might
play out at the game table in this
edition we'll be looking at an encounter
from 1973 godzilla vs megalon as if it
was an encounter in pathfinder 2nd
edition the participants in this
encounter include godzilla who obviously
needs no introduction
jet jaguar a giant robot with a
nightmare inducing jack nicholson smile
and they'll be battling a giant chicken
with blade arms named geigen and a giant
cockroach with drill arms named megalon
we'll begin this breakdown during the
film's climactic battle godzilla's
robotic ally jet jaguar has been
attacked by the evil duo of megalon and
geigen and godzilla now arrives on the
scene
the fight begins with megalon striding
adjacent to godzilla and missing with an
unarmed strike which allows godzilla to
perform his kaiju jiu-jitsu
counter-shove this cost him one reaction
to shove an opponent who misses a melee
attack and note that godzilla's king of
monster's ability allows him to apply
improved knockdown with any successful
melee attack or athletic skill check
that is opposed by a 42 dc
as you'll see in this video everyone
godzilla touches falls to the ground so
either godzilla is really good at
knocking monsters down or is really hard
to walk in a giant rubber suit in the
next round megalon stands from prone and
then moves into a flanking position with
geigen flanking imposes the flat-footed
condition on godzilla which lowers his
armor class by two
but before geigin can take advantage of
this godzilla has his turn and executes
a quick reversal
this ability allows godzilla to spin a
reaction to attack two targets that are
flanking him unlike the player feet
version of this ability godzilla's
version does not have the press or
flourish traits because he's godzilla
when we resume the fight godzilla opts
for a new strategy rips a tree from the
ground and uses it to bludgeon megalong
it costs him one incorrect action to
pull the tree from the ground and a
second to strike with it this tree
counts as an improvised weapon which
imposes a negative two penalty to his
attack role he hits dealing minimal
damage but still knocking megalon prune
and then tosses the tree away because
improvised weapons are garbage
godzilla then checks on his enemies
conditions to ensure they're unconscious
he gives megalon a gentle nudge with his
foot this is likely a sense of motive
check using perception of the gm rolls
in secret
satisfied that megalon is out cold
godzilla goes on to check gigan unknown
to him geigen is only pretending to be
unconscious so when it was geigen's turn
and he declared this the gm rolled
geigen's deception skill versus
godzilla's perception dc and geigen
succeeded
and now on godzilla's turn since he is
actively using since motive the gm rolls
his perception versus gigan's deception
dc in secret godzilla fails the check
and believes his enemy is truly helpless
now on geigen's turn he declares a
haikiba action springs his trap and
attacks godzilla since godzilla has been
fooled by geigan's deception the gm
decides it's appropriate to apply the
flat-footed condition on godzilla for
this attack which lowers his ac by two
and geigin's attack hits
in the next round after godzilla
recovers he moves to grapple geigen he
spends one action on grapple enrolls his
athletic skill versus gigan's 42 dc
he succeeds which applies the grabbed
condition to gigan and then with his
next two actions he executes his kaiju
jiu jitsu hip toss ability this requires
two actions can only be used on targets
that are grabbed by godzilla and allows
him to move the target into another
adjacent space and impose the prone
condition essentially it's a combination
of trip and shove except he can move the
target to any adjacent space instead of
only away from him and this kaiju jiu
jitsu ability ends with godzilla
mounting his victim and pinning him to
the ground this imposes the restrained
condition on gigan and renders him
flat-footed as well
godzilla continues with kaiju jiu-jitsu
flurry of blows an ability that can only
be used against restrained targets and
allows him to unleash a combination of
thunderous fist attacks
now we'll skip ahead to a little later
in the scene geigen has recovered and is
attacking a helpless jet jaguar
as godzilla moves to save his ally the
giant chicken monster places a bladed
arm against the robot's neck and uses
the ready action he states the
conditional trigger as if godzilla moves
closer i will execute jet jaguar
since jet jaguar is unconscious this
attack would apply to his dying
condition and likely kill him
also the gm may allow gigan to spend
another action as an intimidation check
against godzilla's will dc to demoralize
him however godzilla does not fall for
this ruse and instead unleashes his
atomic breath on gigan this is a ranged
attack and geigen would normally receive
lesser cover for having a creature in
the path of the attack but the gm bumps
this up to standard cover given the
circumstances the attack hits deals its
damage and as usual applies the
knockdown effect from godzilla's king of
monster's special ability when we return
to the battle geigen has been defeated
and now jet jaguar and godzilla are
pondering what to do with megalon
megalon is unconscious but godzilla is a
bit of a bloodthirsty dick and decides
to further humiliate his fallen foe
he runs back throws up a pair of victory
fingers and jet jaguar takes his cue to
lift megalon from the ground and hold
him megalon is already suffering the
unconscious condition so he's
flat-footed but jet jaguar also grapples
him just to be sure godzilla then spins
two actions to perform his super omega
tail slide drop kick attack
this allows him to leap up to his speed
and deliver an unarmed melee attack to
an enemy who is adjacent to the final
square of the leap
the attack hits and since his opponent
is unconscious the damage of the attack
is irrelevant and instead megalon gains
the dying one condition
godzilla then spins an action to
backpedal and deliver a second super
omega tailslide dropkick to megalon
once more this hits and increases
megalon to dying too
not yet satisfied with his cold-blooded
lust for violence godzilla grapples
megalon and uses his kaiju jiu-jitsu
slam ability this allows him to add an
extra die of damage to grabbed enemies
which is completely irrelevant since his
target is already unconscious after the
first slam megalon is dying three
uh then dying four
[Applause]
[Music]
but he's definitely dead now
dude seriously he's dead
um okay after godzilla is tired of
bludgeoning a giant corpse he spends his
remaining actions on stride to waddle
off into the sunset a true hero
okay that's godzilla and jet jaguar vs
megalon and gigan as a follow up to this
video i will leave links to my full rule
explanation videos about the grab action
damage and other relevant topics in the
description and please leave your
suggestions for future battle breakdowns
in the comments and as always i want to
thank all of my patrons and everyone
else who supports me by subscribing
commenting and liking these videos until
next time take care and happy april 1st
[Music]
bye