[Music]
hello and welcome to crafting in
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part one I already have a complete
series of videos about crafting for
those of you who are using the Legacy
Second Edition rules and a link to those
videos is provided in this video's
description in this video we're going to
discuss the foundation used for all
crafting we'll be covering all of the
general requirements and Rule
and in the next course we'll get into
specifics for crafting special items
like Scrolls wands runes and also
crafting weapons and armor using special
materials like cold iron or
adamantine the crafting skill can be
used for a variety of activities such as
identifying alchemical items and
repairing broken gear but for the
purposes of this video we're going to
focus on using the crafting skill to
create items before you can start
crafting there are a few requirements
that you will need to meet first the
item that you wish to craft must be your
experience level or lower if no item
level is included in the item stats then
it's considered to be item level zero
second you must have the proper
proficiency you must be at least trained
in crafting in order to craft any items
if the items level is ninth or higher
then you need to have Master Proficiency
in crafting to make it and if the items
level is 16th or higher then you need to
have legendary
proficiency third you might need a
special feet to craft the item the
crafting skill by itself is sufficient
to make most common mundane items like
gear and common non-magical weapons and
armor but if you wish to craft specialty
items like those we will discuss in
depth in the next video in this series
then you'll need some special Feats if
you want to make alchemical items like
elixir poisons and bombs then you need
the alchemical crafting feat if you want
to make any magical items including
Scrolls then you need the magical
crafting feed and if you want to create
snares like traps and alarms then you
need the snare crafting feet the fourth
requirement for crafting is you must
have the right tools for the job an
alchemist lab is needed to craft
alchemical items a writing set is needed
to craft Scrolls and so on Artisan
toolkits are provided as a sort of catch
all term when purchasing one of these
sets you need to declare what kind of
tools they are for example woodworking
tools if you're working on carpentry or
a brewing kit if you want to make beer
in some cases you'll also need a
workshop as determined by your GM for
example you'll need access to a forge if
you want to make a metal shield there's
no hard rule for this in the book so
it's up to Common Sense and again the
GM's discretion the fifth requirement
only applies if what you are making is
not common Rarity and that is you must
have something to work off of in other
words you can't make an uncommon or rare
item just off the top of your head you
either need a sample of that item that
you are going to make a copy of or you
need the items formula although formula
is the term used in the game this could
be a recipe a blueprint a schematic or
any other form of instructions to follow
note again that you do not need a work
sample or formula to craft common items
and you are not required to have the
items formula for uncommon and rare
items if you have a sample of the item
you are making a copy of but all of that
said it is always a best practice to
have the items formula because working
from a formula will cut the amount of
time required to craft the item in half
obtaining formulas for common Rarity
items is pretty easy a basic crafter's
book can be purchased for one silver
piece and it has all of the formulas for
crafting common items found in chapter
six of the player core book so this one
purchase provides all of the formulas
for swords bows chain mail musical
instruments Brewing ale and pretty much
everything else that's considered to be
common
and if you wish to purchase the formula
for a common Rarity item that is found
in a different book you can do so
according to the table here formulas for
items that are uncommon or rare are only
available at the GM's discretion and
likely will either be incredibly
expensive or awarded as part of
treasure honestly given that acquiring
the formulas for common items is so easy
you should probably just consider that
having the formula for the item that
you're crafting is a requirement
unless you have a sample that you're
working from and last you need raw
materials worth at least half of the
listed cost of the item if you are
creating a common item like a long sword
as long as you're in a settlement you
can probably just pay the price in
silver but more exotic items might
require very specific and harder to find
materials that you will need to
Source once you meet the requirements
have the proper tools a formula or work
sample and the required materials then
you're ready to get to work in order to
create the item you must invest an
amount of time or resources equal to its
listed price and always start by
providing 50% of that total cost upfront
you then spend two days of downtime
working or only one day of downtime
working if you are using a formula so
after one or two days of working
depending on if you have the formula you
then roll your crafting skill and the GM
Compares that total against a secret DC
that they set on a failure your progress
stops but you don't lose any of the
money or resources you've already
invested and can start the process over
again critical failures work the same
way except you lose 10% of the materials
that were used but if the skill check is
a success you have a few options your
first option is to pay the remaining
balance needed and complete the work you
always start by putting up 50% of the
items price so if you roll a success
after one day of work with a formula you
just need to pay the remaining 50% cost
to instantly complete it this does not
save you any money and it takes some
time but might be worth it if the item
you're making is not available for
purchase in your area or if it's
important that that the item was made
specifically by you for example if
you're crafting a painting or other work
of art your second option after rolling
a success is to invest more time in
crafting it every day of additional work
lowers the amount of resources needed to
complete the item by an amount equal to
the table found on page
229 so for example if you were eighth
level with expert Proficiency in
crafting every additional day of
downtime spent beyond what is required
would lower the needed resources to
complete the item by three gold pieces
and if you roll a critical success you
treat yourself as being one level higher
so if you're again an eighth level
expert and roll a critical success you
would lower the amount of resources
needed by four gold instead of three for
each extra day of downtime spent working
on the item after each day of work you
can decide if you you want to pay off
the remaining balance to finish your
work and complete the item or if you
want to spend one more day of work to
lower the remaining balance that's
needed note that no additional skill
checks are needed for the extra days
spent crafting once you roll a success
is just a matter of counting days and
seeing how long you want to work and how
much more money you're willing to pay in
order to
finish now this might have you wondering
about things like error
do you really need to spend an entire
day to make a single Arrow the good news
is no you don't it's not quite that bad
if you wish to craft ammunition or any
item with the consumable trait you can
make those in batches non-magical
ammunition is created in batches equal
to their numberers shown on page 281 so
blow gun darts crossbow bolts and arrows
are all made in batches of 10 and all
other items with the consumable trait
including magical ammunition are made in
batches of four when you create by batch
every item in that batch must be
identical there's no mixing and matching
so you can't make Five Arrows In five
crossbow bolts in the same batch it has
to be 10 of one or 10 of the other
crafting in batches works the same way
as crafting individual items except you
add the price of each item together so
if you're making a batch of four vials
of holy water the price would be 12 gold
and you would need to provide six gold
up front for the material cost other
than that crafting in batches works the
same as what we have already
discussed in this video We examined the
basics of crafting and the next video
expands that discussion to cover magic
items and crafting weapons and armor
with precious materials I will also be
uploading a full example of crafting in
the remaster Edition from start to
finish so keep an eye out for that if
you have any questions please leave them
in the comments and I'd like to take a
quick moment to thank everyone who
supports me in this channel by clicking
that like button subscribing to the
channel or subscribing to the patreon
thanks for watching take care and happy
[Music]
gaming