[Music]
hello and welcome to crafting examples
for Pathfinder second edition remastered
if you haven't already watched our video
on basic crafting rules you should
probably do so before viewing this
example a link to that video may be
found in the description also this video
follows the rules provided in the re
mastered version of Pathfinder second
edition if your game is using the
original Legacy Second Edition rules
then please see a link in the
description that will take you to my
series on Legacy
crafting in this example gamra is going
to craft a suit of half plate armor she
has third level with trained proficiency
and crafting and a skill bonus of plus
six the first requirement is item level
there is no item level listed for half
plate armor so it defaults to item level
zero gima is third level so she meets
this requirement the second requirement
is proficiency as a zero level item
trained proficiency is all that is
needed to craft this third does she need
a special feat to make half-plate armor
it's not magical alchemical or a snare
so she does not need any Feats to make
this fourth does she have the proper
tools we'll say she purchased an artisan
toolkit and labeled it as smithing tools
on her character sheet and the local
blacksmith is letting her use their
Forge so this requirement is covered
fifth does she have a formula for half
plate armor technically she doesn't need
a formula to make half plate since it is
common Rarity but we'll say that she
purchased a basic crafter's book and
therefore does have the formula since
that book includes all of the level zero
common items that are found in chapter 6
of of the player core book which does
include Half plate armor and the last
requirement is materials half plate is
listed with a price of 18 gold pieces so
she must provide nine gold up front to
begin her work and must provide 18 gold
worth of materials or discounts in order
to complete the armor set she spends one
day of downtime working on the armor at
the end of which her player rolles a
crafting skill check
note that she is able to roll this check
after only one day of work because she
has the formula if she was not crafting
with the formula she would need to spend
two days of downtime working before
rolling this check she rolls her
crafting skill and the GM compares the
total to a DC that they set in secret
for this we'll say the GM set a DC of 14
gima rolls ad20 and adds her crafting
bonus of plus 6
if she rolls a seven on the die then she
fails which means that her day of work
was wasted but she still gets her nine
gold pieces worth of materials back and
can try again tomorrow if she rolls a
natural one then she critically fails
and not only wasted her day of work but
also loses 10% of the materials in this
case we convert the nine gold pieces to
90 silver pieces and she loses 10% of
that or nine silver leaving her with 81
silver pieces worth of material she can
start the process over and try again
provided that she can replace the nine
silver pieces worth of lost
materials but if gimmer rolls an eight
or higher on the die then she succeeds
she now has two options the half plate
armor has a remaining balance of nine
gold pieces that needs to be covered she
can either pay that N9 gold and
instantly finish her work or she can
spend another day of work to lower that
balance she decides to invest another
day into crafting the armor to learn how
much this lowers the remaining balance
buy we need to look at the income earned
table on page 229 of player Core 1 gima
is third level and trained so every
extra day of work lowers the remaining
balance by five silver pieces if she had
rolled a critical success then she would
be treated as if she was fourth level
and would lower the balance by seven
silver pieces after each extra day of
work but for this example we're going to
say that she succeeded but not
critically succeeded so after the second
day of work the remaining balance lowers
from nine gold pieces to eight gold and
five silver or it might just be easier
to call it 85 silver pieces at this rate
it will take take her more than 2 weeks
of additional work to finish the suit of
armor but she only expects to have three
more days of down time before her party
leaves town to continue their Adventures
so she decides to spend the rest of her
available time working on the armor
which lowers the remaining balance from
85 silver to 70 and at the end of the
fifth day of work she pays the remaining
70 silver pieces to finish her suit of
half plate armor she and her GM are
provided as much flexibility as they
like to explain this within the
narrative it's unlikely that on the
evening and the fifth day gima simply
threw seven gold coins at the half
finished suit of armor and it magically
completed instead she and her GM decide
to explain the final expense as money
she paid to a trio of local Apprentice
blacksmith who assisted her throughout
the process so she could complete the
entire suit of armor in only 5 days
if you would like to see the companion
course that explains the rules behind
this example you can find a link to it
in the description if you have any
questions please leave them in the
comments and I'd like to take a quick
moment to thank everyone who supports me
in this channel by clicking the like
button subscribing to the channel or
subscribing to the patreon thanks for
watching take care and happy
[Music]
gaming