[Music]
hello and welcome to crafting in
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part two in the previous video we
discussed the process of crafting most
common items and in this one we're going
to take it a step further and talk about
special situations like crafting magic
items and forging weapons and armor from
precious materials the rules for
transferring and upgrading runes will be
addressed in a future video that's all
about
runes also note that this video is for
the remastered edition of Pathfinder if
your game is using the original Legacy
Second Edition rules please see the link
in the description for my series that
covers those rules and one last Quick
disclaimer the examples used in this
video all assume you have a formula for
the item being crafted so if you're
crafting by making a copy of an item
instead of using a formula simply simply
add one extra day of setup meaning it
will take two days of work before you
roll your skill check see the previous
video in this series if you need more
information on how and why that is
crafting magic items works exactly like
crafting everything else but there are a
few points that you will want to pay
special attention to First although an
item stat block might include different
types of that item in most cases each
type of a given item will have its own
formula for example the stamp block for
an animal staff includes three different
types regular greater and major you
cannot use the formula for a greater
animal staff to craft a major animal
staff those are considered to be two
wholly separate items each using their
own formula however there is one key
exception to this which is any item
where the key difference between types
is item level for example the stat block
for spacious pouch shows four different
types and the key difference between
them is item level therefore the same
formula can be used to craft any of the
four different types of spacious pouches
but note that this only applies to items
where item level is the main difference
between types and each type of the item
is the same Rarity for example having
the formula to craft one type of Aon
Stone
cannot be used to craft other types of
Aon Stones because each type of Aon
stone is wildly different from the
others when in doubt the GM will decide
if the formula you have can be used for
other types of the same item second pay
attention to the craft requirements
section in the items description this
area will show you anything extra needed
beyond the norm in the previous video
you learned that there are six
requirements that must be met before you
can start crafting
we are essentially adding a seventh
requirement here which is simply do
whatever is listed under the craft
requirements heading often these
requirements are going to say something
to the effect of Supply a casting of a
specific spell at a given rank this
means that during the first day of
crafting someone must cast the specified
spell at the required rank in order for
that item to be crafted so for example
if you're crafting a major animal staff
then someone will need to cast runic
body and summon animal at first Rank and
then cast animal messenger speak with
animals and summon animal again all at
second Rank and then cast animal form
and summon animal again both at third
Rank and summon animal yet again at
Fourth Rank and finally animal form Moon
frenzy and summon animal all at fifth
rank you would not need to cast know the
way as part of the crafting process
because that is a cantrip and cantrips
are not listed rank spells when casting
spells to meet a crafting requirement
remember these key points first the
person who is doing the crafting does
not need to be the one casting the spell
there's no requirement for them beyond
having the magical crafting feat
therefore anyone can be the one who
actually cast the spell if you're making
a fire Fireball scroll you do not need
to know how to cast The Fireball spell
yourself but instead can have a friend
cast the spell for you as part of the
crafting
process second note that the rules
specify that a spell slot must be used
when casting the spell to craft a scroll
or wand in other words you can't use a
charge from a scroll or a wand to cast
the spell that's needed to craft another
scroll or wand the energy of the spell
spell must come from a person in the
form of a spell slot third there are no
other effects when casting the spell
when you cast a fireball spell for the
purpose of creating a fireball scroll
you're not going to blow up your house
instead the energy of the spell is
safely transferred to the item and there
are no other
effects and last when casting a spell as
part of a crafting requirement you will
likely need to pay any associ cost with
casting that spell except if you are
making a staff or a wand so for example
if you're crafting a rank two lock
scroll it says here that there is a cost
of six gold worth of precious materials
in order to cast lock at second rank if
you're making a rank two lock scroll
then you must provide that cost in
addition to the regular cost of crafting
but staves and Wands are different if
you're making a rank two to WAND of lock
you do not provide any of the usual
spell cost when casting the spell as
part of the crafting process although I
haven't seen it spelled out in the rules
I believe the key distinction here is
that when someone uses a scroll that
scroll is consumed and you don't need to
provide spell cons at the time that the
scroll is used but with staves and Wands
which are not consumables you do need to
provide the cost each time the spell
cast using the staff or wand and
therefore you don't also need to pay the
spell cost up front when making the
staff or want the bottom line here is
that you should only be paying the cost
for the spell once per actual use of the
spell and while we're on the topic of
spells and magic items it may be worth
mentioning that magic Scrolls and ons
cannot be used to cast cantrips Focus
spells or rituals they can only be
crafted to cast regular spells you
cannot create a one to cast your
favorite Focus spell or make a scroll to
cast a ritual and also don't make
assumptions about when you need to have
a spell cast as part of crafting if it
doesn't say that you need to then you
don't the skeleton key for example casts
the breach spell when it's used but does
not require a brief spell to be cast
when crafting a skeleton key likewise
people sometimes assume that potions
that cast spells when you drink them
require those spells to be cast when
you're making and burrowing those
potions but it is incredibly rare for
that to actually be the case
invisibility potions for example do not
require anyone to cast the invisibility
spell when Brewing them in fact the
person who is crafting the invisibility
potion doesn't even need to know how to
cast that spell or have the ability to
cast spells all the information needed
to brew that potion is enti Al included
in its formula Beyond these few tweaks
crafting items regardless of if they are
ones squirrels potions wondrous items or
whatever they all work exactly as was
outlined in the previous video you need
to provide 50% of the cost of the
materials up front and spend one day
working with the formula at the end of
which you make a crafting skill check if
successful you can either choose to pay
off the remaining balance or spend
another day working to lower that
balance and since potions and squirrels
are consumable items they can be made in
batches of
four in addition to magic items we also
want to discuss forging weapons and
items with uncommon materials the items
we discussed in our crafting part one
video assume that you are using mundane
materials like wood or iron but in the
world of Pathfinder there are many more
exotic materials that can be used when
craftting such as silver or Adam mantin
crafting weapons or armor with special
materials is pretty simple it works just
like regular crafting but there are a
few special points that we need to
discuss as usual you must provide
materials equal to 50% of the items
price up front but if you're making
something with precious materials you
can't just pay the cost of that out of
your pocket in gold coins instead you
have to somehow Source the precious
material that's needed as well for
example you want to craft a cold Iron
Warhammer when we look up the stats for
cold iron weapons we see a few things
worth noting first precious materials
are categorized as being low grade
standard grade or high grade each with
their own stats like how magic items are
listed with varying types if you're
curious what the difference is between
the grades of of a material each grade
dictates the highest level item that may
be crafted from it as well as the
highest level of Rune that may be etched
upon it low grade materials can be used
to craft items up to eighth level and
hold runes up to eighth level standard
grade materials can be used to craft
items and hold runes up to 15th level
and highgrade materials can be used to
craft items and hold Runes of any level
material grades will also affect the
hardness hit points and break thresholds
of the item made from them we also see
it has an item level warhammers are
Level zero but when crafting from
precious materials you must meet or
exceed the level of the base item or the
material whichever is higher so you
would need to be at least second level
to craft a lowgrade cold Iron Warhammer
and 10th level to make a standard grade
hammer
but the big difference comes when we
look at Price here price is based on the
bulk of the item that we are making in
this case a Warhammer is one bulk so a
lowgrade cold Iron Warhammer has a price
of 40 gold plus four per bulk making the
price of this Hammer 44 gold pieces this
is the same price for any weapon that is
only one bulk you do not add the cost of
a normal Warhammer to this also note
that you always need to pay for at least
one bulk so if the item that you are
crafting is light bulk then you treat it
as being one bulk for the purpose of
calculating its price when we start
crafting we must provide materials equal
to 50% of the price up front just like
always in this case that would be 22
gold worth of
materials next we look at the craft
requirements line in in the description
here it says that of those 22 gold coins
22 Silver pieces of that must be in cold
iron all of this special material is
needed up front we do not provide 11
silver worth of cold iron now and
another 11 silver worth of it later so
before we can start crafting we need 198
silver pieces worth of regular General
materials and specifically 22 silver
pieces worth of cold iron this is all of
the cold iron that we will need for this
project after one day of work in a skill
check we have the option as usual of
paying the remaining balance of 11 Gold
to complete it but none of that needs to
be in cold iron it can be paid as usual
with 11 gold pieces we now have a cold
Iron Warhammer crafted with lowgrade
cold iron and we can etch runes upon it
up to eighth level we we will need to
upgrade to a standard grade cold Iron
Warhammer if we want to use runes that
are ninth level or higher crafting armor
from precious materials works the same
way except you need to adjust its bulk
the armor table shows the bulk for each
suit of armor assuming that you are
wearing it but when crafting you use the
Armor's carried bulk which is one more
than a suit of Armor's worn bulk to
calculate this you simply add one to the
bulk that you see listed in the table if
you were crafting at a mantain chain
mail you would calculate its price using
three bulk instead of
two in this video we discussed a few
more advanced applications of crafting
namely crafting magic items and forging
weapons and armor from precious
materials as a reminder we will be
discussing how to craft etch and
transfer runes in a future video that's
dedicated specifically to the topic of
runes if you have any questions please
leave them in the comments and as always
I'd like to take a moment to thank
everyone who supports me in this channel
by liking the videos leaving comments
and subscribing to the channel or
patreon with that thanks for watching
take care and happy
[Music]
gaming