[Music]
hey everybody Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule REM reminder for you and
today we're going to be talking about
crafting tattoos I recently put out a
video a a second part of a series this
is looking at the remastered crafting
rules and that second video was all
about crafting magic items but one
specific type of magic item that was
missing from that video and that folks
the comments uh pointed out was crafting
magical tattoos so I just wanted to make
a a another video to very briefly go
over what those rules are now before I
get into this I should say that uh the
reason why uh magical tattoos were not
included in that previous video even
though they are a type of magical item
is because the new remaster books make
no mention of tattoos in them and I was
following those books so what I'm
sharing today is the version of of the
tattoo crafting rules as they exist in
the Legacy Edition and we can all pretty
much assume at least for now that this
is the way that they work uh in the
remaster version as well unless at some
point they do go back and make a
specific change to to state otherwise so
magical tattoos are again they're type
of type of magic item they are are
mechanically speaking magic items but
they have the tattoo TR trait and that
tattoo trait does handle things a little
differently than some other magic items
you can basically think of them as uh
worn magic items that are just
impossible or extremely difficult to uh
to remove or disarm from you they're
like permanent worn items and as such
they do need to be invested however the
mechanism for investing them is a little
different um mechanically speaking what
they do is they look lower the maximum
number of items you can invest by one
and that distinction is important
because the user then does not choose
whether or not they want to invest a
tattoo or basically turn them on or off
once the tattooing is complete the
tattoo has been crafted on a person they
are active and they lower the amount of
items you can invest by one as opposed
to Counting as uh their own regular
invested items but other than that
they're going to function very similar
to other magic items but crafting is
different so the crafting rules for
Magical tattoos can be found on page 164
of the secrets of magic book and there
you'll find a section that reads as
follows to craft a magical tattoo you
must be able to craft magic items and
have a specialty in tattooing you can
attain these requirements by taking the
tattoo artist skill feet below or you
can take both the magical crafting and
Specialty crafting skill Feats choosing
Artistry as your
specialty so even though tattoos are
magic items they don't fall under the
general umbrella of other magic items
where you only need the magical crafting
feed in order to craft tattoos
you need either the magical crafting
feat and the specialty feat where you
specialize in
Artistry or you can take only the tattoo
artist feet and basically what that
means is you have the ability to craft
create ink a magical tattoo but no other
magic items so basically for one feet
you can specialize in uh in magical
tattoos and you'll get a uh at minimum a
plus one bonus to crafting those tattoos
but it does not give you the ability to
craft any other magic items or the other
path is you take the magical crafting
feat which will let you create and craft
you magic swords magic runes magic hats
magic flying carpets magic bags magic
Scrolls all that stuff and then have to
also take the specialty crafting feet in
in in addition to that in order to craft
uh magical tattoos now why magic tattoos
are treated differently than everything
else and all the other magical items I
don't know um if you have insight to
this or you you have an idea please let
me know in the comments it does seem odd
to me that uh the magical crafting feat
is a blanket feat that will let you do
all those things I previously mentioned
Scrolls ones swords armor uh gemstones
magic bags just you can create
everything with that except tattoos
tattoos are special we're going to
separate those out and make you take a
uh a second feed if you want to do those
now I understand in the real
world the Artistry involved in in
drawing and ining a tattoo is radically
different than blacksmithing a suit of
armor um but mechanically within
Pathfinder second edition they've
largely said we we don't want to get
involved in a million different Feats
for a million different uh a million
different ways to craft we're just going
to have one crafting skill we going to
have one you know basically three
crafting Feats uh you if they're
breaking out magic items and a chemical
crafting and
snares um it just seems weird to me that
tattooing wouldn't just be under the
umbrella of um of other magic items for
the sake of Simplicity in this more
simplified rule system but uh that's the
way it works if you want to craft a
magical tattoo uh is going to work the
same as crafting any other magic item
you're going to either need the formula
for the type of magical tattoo you're
going to be inking or you're going to
need to be working off a copy of it if
you have the formula uh in the remaster
edition if you have the formula that's
going to reduce the time required to
only one day uh minimum um may go longer
as usual after that first day you're
going to buy out the balance you put 50%
of the cost uh on day one and then at
the end of day one you can either pay
off the other 50% or work for another
additional day or further lowering the
balance required by the am the amount
found on the um on an income table if
any of that sounds weird or unfamiliar
check out my other videos about crafting
that go over the U the general crafting
rules but uh that's it for for today if
you have any questions about crafting
magical tattoos please leave them in the
comments below and as always I want to
take a moment to say thank you to
everybody out there who supports me in
this channel whether that's by clicking
the like button subscribing to the
channel subscribing to the patreon
leaving your comments and questions and
suggestions I appreciate everything you
folks do to support me so thanks for
watching take care and happy
[Music]
G