hello and welcome to runes in Pathfinder
second edition remastered part one in
this video we're going to cover what
runes are and how they work and in part
two we'll examine other related topics
like how to upgrade a rune how to remove
a rune from its item or transfer a rune
from one item to another as a reminder
this video is for the remaster Edition
so if your game is using the original
Legacy edition of Pathfinder Edition
please see the link in the description
for a video that covers those
rules most magic weapons armor and
shields gain their special properties
through runes runes represent ancient
secrets in magical science that bestow
power to the items that they're engraved
upon and they take two forms fundamental
runes and property runes fundamental
runes provide the most basic and common
magical effects for our weapons these
runes increase attack bonus in damage
for armor these runes provide a bonus to
armor class and saves and for Shields
these runes provide an increase to the
shields hardness hit points and break
threshold any weapon or armor can have
one and only one of each kind of
fundamental Rune the second type of
runes are property runes these Grant
many other effects beyond the basic
enhancements provided by fundamental
runes for example making a suit of armor
resistant to acid damage or setting a
long sours blade on
fire let's take a closer look at
fundamental runes first there are two
kinds of fundamental runes for armor and
those are armor potency runes and
resilient runes armor potency runes
Grant an item bonus to Armor class and
the number of the bonus also indicates
the maximum number of property runes
that the item can have so a suit of Plus
one leather armor means it is a suit of
leather armor and gets a plus one item
bonus to armor class in addition the
potency Rune makes the armor magical and
it will register dis spells like detect
magic in rora the plus one potency Rune
also means this leather armor may have
one property Rune etched on it as well
the second fundamental rune for armor is
the resilient Rune resilient runes Grant
a bonus to all saving throws in common
three varieties resilient greater
resilient and major resilient each of
those runes increase the bonus of Saves
by one so resilient runes are plus one
to all saves greater resilient runes are
plus two and major resilient runes are
plus three remember when you see the
name of a suit of armor the plus value
in the name refers to its armor potency
Rune and is also the bonus it receives
to Armor class the plus number has
nothing to do with the resilient Rune
and its bonus to saves instead the armor
will have the word resilient for plus
one to saves the name will say greater
resilient for a plus two to saves or
major resilient for a plus three to all
saves fundamental runes for weapons
function in much the same way the First
Fundamental rune for weapons is weapon
potency when a potency rune is added to
a weapon it is shown as a plus number in
the weapon's name so a plus two battle
axe has a plus two weapon potency Rune
etched on it and that plus number is
both the item bonus added to attack
roles as well as the number of property
runes the weapon can have and remember
that plus value is only added to attack
roles it does not Grant a bonus to
damage instead to increase the weapon's
damage you'll want to etch the second
kind of weapon fundamental Rune which is
called striking striking runes can
increase the number of damage dice
rolled with a weapon a striking Rune
increases the weapon's damage to two
dice a greater striking Rune increases
base damage to three Dice and a major
striking Rune increases base damage to
four dice so if you add a striking Rune
to a long sword it will deal 2 to8
damage on a hit instead of 1d8 and
remember this is an increase to the
weapon base damage dice so anytime the
weapon dice are modified the extra
damage from striking is also modified as
well for example the twoand trait
changes the weapon's base damage dice so
a plus one striking Bastard Sword does 2
d8 damage when used with one hand and 2
D12 damage when used in both hands not 1
D12 plus
1d8 and the the damage due to striking
is also increased if the effect
specifically says it is for example the
deadly trait states that its damage is
increased if the weapon has a greater or
major striking Rune therefore the number
of deadly dice are increased but not if
the weapon has just a regular striking
Rune but striking runes do not increase
the damage dice of damaging effects that
are in addition to the base physical
weapon damage for example Bon damage
from a sneak attack would not be
increased because of a striking Rune or
fire damage caused by a flaming weapon
that also would not be increased due to
a striking Rune Shields only have one
type of Rune which is called a
reinforcing Rune reinforcing runes
increase the shields hardness hit points
and break threshold also note that
reinforcing runes come in six types each
with increasing bonuses and level
requirements they are minor lesser
moderate greater major and
supreme as mentioned before there are
two kinds of runes fundamental runes are
the core runes that provide basic
enhancements and the second type of
runes are property runes simply put
property runes let the armor or weapon
do all kinds of other cool stuff beyond
the basic things that come from
fundamental runes want to give your
sword the voral quality or where armor
that can turn you invisible then you
need to add property runes when you look
at a property Rune step block you will
see some effects are passive and always
occur when the item is in use for
example armor Ed with a shatter Rune
grants its benefit whenever the armor is
worn and invested but other runes like
the shifting Rune require you to
activate the item in this case it takes
a single action to use the shifting Rune
special properties there are way too
many property runes to go over all of
them here but it's pretty simple you
would just treat those property runes in
a very similar way as you would any
other magical item the key difference
being that runes cannot be used on their
own they must be attached to another
item it's also important to remember
that there are limits to how many runes
a single item can have etched on it each
weapon or suit of armor can have one
potency Rune in and either one resilient
Rune if it's armor or one striking Rune
if it is a weapon and then can have as
many property runes as the bonus that's
provided by its potency Rune so for
example a plus one long sword has a plus
one weapon potency Rune etched on it a
plus one striking long sword has a plus
one weapon potency Rune and a striking
Rune and a plus one striking flaming
long sword has a plus one weapon potency
Rune a striking Rune and a flaming Rune
this long sword cannot gain a second
property Rune until it first increases
its potency Rune to plus two and since
the Striking Rune is a fundamental Rune
it does not count against the number of
property runes the sword can have and
note that an item cannot have more than
one of the same type of fundamental Rune
so you couldn't have two plus one
potency runes and instead dead would
start with a single plus one potency
Rune and then upgrade it to plus two but
note that a weapon or armor can have
multiple etchings of the same kind of
property runes on them however the
benefits do not stack if a weapon or
armor has two or more of the same type
of property Rune you only count
whichever one provides the highest
benefit that should give you a basic
idea of how runes work in Pathfinder
second edition remastered in the next
video of this series we will expand this
conversation by covering topics such as
how to upgrade a rune how to remove a
rune from an item and how to transfer a
rune from one item to another and as
always I'd like to take a quick moment
to thank everybody who supports me in
this channel whether that be by clicking
the like button subscribing to the
channel or subscribing to the patreon I
greatly appreciate everything you do to
support me and with that thanks for
watching take care and happy
gaming
[Music]