hey everybody Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you and
today I'm going to talk a little bit
about Pathfinder Allure I'm not going to
be creating a lore video for you but
instead I'm going to direct you to some
wonderful folks who are making lore
videos and the reason I'm doing this is
because as you probably already know
Piezo announced that in a few months
they're going to start rolling out a new
series of core rulebooks for the
remaster editions and as part of that
there's going to be a whole lot of
changes to the rules as we have them and
so with me running a YouTube channel
that's dedicated to Pathfinder rules it
doesn't really make sense for me to be
putting out videos today that may be
invalidated in a few months when the
remaster uh sets come out the first
books of that come out is actually going
to be about six months or so before they
all come out but at any rate a lot of
people out there have been kind enough
to share their suggestions with me for
things I could do with this channel in
the meantime while I'm waiting for all
the new rules with the remasters uh to
come out and a surprising number of
people have been recommending that I get
into lore videos if I start making lore
videos and this is what really has
surprised me is the number of people who
have specifically said Dave make lore
videos because nobody is making more
videos there's nobody out there making
more videos so we need somebody to fill
that Gap and I'm here to tell you and
that that is incredibly not true there's
a lot of people out there who are making
very very very good high quality lore
videos for the Pathfinder setting so
that's what I'm doing with this video
today I want to connect those of you out
there who suggest that I get into lore
videos because quote nobody is making
them and connect you to the people who
are so that's what I'm doing I'm wanting
to share with you five YouTube channels
that are producing great Valyrian
Pathfinder setting lore videos for you
so the first of those is going to be a
relatively newcomer to the scene called
the lore tour and the Lord tour as of
right now has about 20 little more than
20 videos they have a series that takes
a dive into the different districts of
Absalom they have videos that are
focused on specific creatures like
ghosts and Sea Hags and they also have
videos that take a look at different
parts of geography in particular they
recently put out a video on Atari that I
liked so much that I forwarded it out to
a group of players who will be joining
me in July to start a campaign set in
Atari and they all gave me positive
feedback on that video as well so I want
to make sure everybody checks out the
lore tour as one of the places you can
go to for lore videos but it's not alone
next up we have the Tower of tomes the
Tower of tomes has a 60-ish videos all
about lore they cover monsters
ancestries different deities but with
system apart from a lot of the other
people out there making lore videos is
they have a great series of one minute
long shorts that dives into the
different types of fiends found in
galerion next up we have sir vertigo sir
vertigo has over 50 lore videos and
these videos cover a wide array of
topics including prominent NPCs that I
don't see being represented on the other
channels and also they provide videos on
some of the less commonly covered areas
of galerium like the stolen lands and
alken star and the last of the channels
that are currently producing lore videos
that I want to cover is myth keeper
recently they have a lot of videos that
really focus on locations lots of videos
on the different nations of galerian as
well as the different planes of the
cosmology of the Pathfinder setting but
they also have videos covering religion
and different ancestries as well and the
last Channel providing lore videos I
want to share with you is kind of an
honorable mention they're called Venture
captains and they're no longer active
but they produced uh 20 or so videos
about lore back in the Pathfinder first
edition days and uh not only are they
great because the lore videos that they
created are still valid today a lot of
the history hasn't changed but I want to
highlight them because this is the
channel that inspired me to become a a
YouTube content creator as well I sold
their videos about Pathfinder lore and
said maybe it'd be fun to make videos
about Pathfinder rules so without
Venture captains I wouldn't be here so
those are five different channels four
of them are still actively producing
lore videos for the Pathfinder setting
so go check these folks out make sure
you click the Subscribe buttons make
sure you click the like buttons If you
like the videos and feel free to come
back to this video into this comment
section and share your thoughts positive
or negative whatever you think about
these five different groups I'm sharing
today so that's it for today if you have
any suggestions for future rule reminder
videos please let me know as always I
want to take just a quick moment to say
thank you to everybody out there who
supports me whether that's by clicking
the like button on the video subscribing
to the channel subscribing to the
patreon I really appreciate everything
the community does to support me and
with that thanks for watching take care
and happy gaming
thank you