[Music]
hey everybody Dave here and today I've
got a little bit of a sneak peek preview
at the new and upcoming player core
remaster and GM core remaster books for
Pathfinder second edition if you've been
following this channel for a while
you've probably seen my previews before
the way I usually do them is by sharing
pages from the book by sharing the table
of content by doing a broad overview of
page counts and that sort of thing as
well as giving a little bit of an
overview of the highlights for these
remaster books I'm going to do it a
little bit different because the
majority of the concept is going to be
very familiar if you have the core rule
book if you have the game mastery guide
for Pathfinder second edition then you
largely already know what is in the
books and how they function and instead
for this video what I thought I would do
is solicit questions from the community
about whatever aspects of these two new
books are are most curious to them in
providing answers to those questions and
that's exactly what I did I I posted on
both my patreon as well as to Reddit and
a lot of folks out there were kind
enough to offer their their questions
and the things that their most
interested in learning about the new
books and I'm going to go over a number
of those with you today now I do want to
do a couple of disclaimers first of all
I should let you know that I was
provided copies of these books by piso
and also I'm not going to be able to go
over literally every one of the
questions that was posed to me um some
of them um were just not applicable for
example there were a lot of questions
that were specific to either the
champion or monk classes and those
surprisingly are not included in player
Core 1 instead we will have to wait
until player Core 2 to uh get the new
writeups for those classes and also some
of the questions that were asked were um
things that frankly I'm going to have to
do a lot of analysis to really formulate
an opinion on um and some other items
were were just simply things that I
couldn't get a definite uh yes no answer
when I look them up and so again I'm I
might take a little more time to do a
little more digging uh with the
materials have been provided before
answering those questions but don't
worry there's still a lot for us to
cover today so with that all in mind
let's go ahead and jump into the first
question that was asked and it's all
about recall knowledge we we have heard
that recall knowledge is going to change
and now finally in player core one we we
have the U the new Rite up for for
recall
knowledge essentially what the change is
is they're adapting a common house rule
that I already used in my games and I
know a lot of other people did as well
where instead of taking the original
rules which said that you gave the most
commonly um the most commonly known fact
about an item or a monster that's being
identified or something like that with
recall knowledge um instead we are
turning it now in the new system you
your player is going ask you one
specific question they're not going to
say I want to do recall knowledge on
this windigo they might say I'm going to
do recall knowledge and I would like to
know if the the Windy go is weak to fire
so it's going to be one question they
ask and then the gy is going to make a a
secret um skill check for that person's
um recall knowledge check and if it is a
success then they're going to answer
that question if it is a failure nothing
happens if it's a critical failure the
GM is going to give them a false bit of
information and if it's a critical
success then the GM's going to answer
that question and either expound on it
with more related adjacent information
or might um might uh just allow them to
ask a second question as well so in a
nutshell that's how recall knowledge is
working now uh no more do we have to
worry about the mystery of figuring out
what would be the most commonly known uh
trait or aspect of whatever recall
knowledge is being applied to and
instead uh the onus is on the player to
ask us a specific question that they
want answered so the second question was
all about uh states of awareness in
Stealth have there been any uh
meaningful material changes to those and
from an overview and reading of those
pieces in the player core I do not see
any meaningful material changes um that
are applied to any of the uh states of
awareness or to stealth moving on is
kind of a big one and I'm going to have
to kind of divide it into a number of
different parts and these are all about
the new damage types so how to how do
vitality and void work how do holy and
Unholy damage work and how does Spirit
damage work so first up vitality and
void damage as far as I can tell they
are pretty much just onetoone
correspondence to the positive and
negative damage types that we already
had uh Vitality damage will only harm
Undead and uh the opposite is true void
damage will only harm the
living um then holy and Unholy so holy
and Unholy damage types and the holy and
Unholy traits are largely replacing the
mechanical side of alignments so if you
haven't heard the big news in the
Pathfinder second edition remaster
alignments are a thing of the past and
so there's still a mechanical need
especially for divine characters to be
able to apply some sort of additional
effect when they're fighting um fiends
and evil doers and so forth but we can't
say evil doer anymore cuz evil is not a
mechanical concept
anymore so first thing you need to know
is there is this thing called being
Sanctified and
sanctification when you are a uh when
you choose to play a cleric and this is
really in player core one the only area
with this comes into effect we'll have
to wait for player Core 2 to see how uh
sanctification applies to uh Champions
and potentially other other uh classes
but um if you are a cleric you must
choose a god you worship and that God is
going to have some manner of
sanctification listing in their little
write up in the uh in the rule book and
so that is either going to say if that
the clerics that follow that God must be
Sanctified as holy or must be Sanctified
as Unholy or it could say that the
cleric is required to choose one of
those two or it may say that the cleric
can choose one of those two if a cleric
follows a God where the sanctification
listing says that they can choose either
holy or or Unholy that means that they
can also choose none of the the above
and not be Sanctified but uh in general
uh good aligned so to speak uh deities
are going to require their their
followers uh or their clerics to be
specific to be holy uh evil deities are
probably going to ask that their um
their clerics be Unholy and neutral in
other French cases it could be you get
to choose if you want to be holy or
Unholy or you get to choose either of
those or say none of the above but
provided you are Sanctified then you
gain the holy trait or you gain the
Unholy trait now this also applies to uh
casting spells and other damaging
effects so holy affects anything with
the Unholy
trait so this is typically going to be
fiends of every variety demons Devils so
forth if it is a fiend it will probably
have the Unholy trait and most Undead
will also most likely have the Unholy
trait so if you're dealing holy damage
it's going to apply to uh most likely to
fiends to undid but also to anything
that has the Unholy trait which would
include a cleric of a pre previously
defined evil
deity and the opposite of that is also
going to be true uh Unholy damage is
going to affect anything with the Holy
trait which are typically going to be
celestials like angels as well as any
creatures with the Holy trait such as
the cleric to a good aligned deity also
there are a number of different spells
and other effects that say if the target
has either the holy or Unholy trait is
going to do this extra effect as well
now the third type of damage is Spirit
damage so Spirit damage um as the name
implies it uh damages the spirit of a
creature so this is not inherently
living or Undead um because a ghost is a
spirit it most likely has a spirit and
could be affected by Spirit damage but
this damage is not affecting the
physical body is affecting the soul so
one example that the book points out is
that if a creature is possessed by
another being and you deal Spirit damage
to them then it's not the physical
possessed person who is hurt is going to
be the person doing the possessing who
is home harm because it's their Spirit
who is in control of that possessed body
and uh constructs are going to be immune
to this kind of damage because they
don't have Spirits typically so the next
question that kind of is is building
onto that is about holy and Unholy runes
do we have magical runes for those new
damage types and yes we do holy runes
deal an extra 1 D4 Spirit damage to a
weapon attack that has a holy Rune or 2
D4 against enemies with the Unholy trait
also once per day after critically
succeeding on a strike against an Unholy
Target the wheeler can spend their
reaction to heal themselves double the
target's level Unholy creatures are
going to be infeed too whenever carrying
or wielding a weapon that has a holy r
Rune etched upon it and Unholy runes are
going to function pretty much exactly
the same way except they don't heal on
those Critical Hits once per day instead
they're going to apply bleed damage once
per day to a holy Target that they
critically succeed their strikes
against so next question is there a way
to get the holy and Unholy traits other
than being a clarc I did not see any
other ways in the uh player core book uh
to apply sanctification and gain the
holy and Unholy
traits um outside of being a cleric by
class or taking the cleric multiclass uh
dedication feat which requires you to
undergo sanctification in the exact same
way as as a regular cleric um you still
have to choose a God and apply either
holy or Unholy
or none of the above if you get that
option uh I was a little surprised by
that I was expecting there to be some
other some other method within the the
game to gain those um those traits uh
for example the Nephilim which is sort
of the catch all ancestry for Outsiders
or people who have an outsider Heritage
in their bloodline so teelings and ASMR
and so on and so forth in the new book
are all gathered together Under The
Heading of Nephilim and um even though
it writes about like you know uh uh if
you have an infernal ancestry or what
would used to have been called a teeling
uh people look at you and see horns and
hoofs and they might assume you have the
Unholy trait but I didn't see anything
in that write up that gave a path to
earning either the holy or Unholy trait
all right so moving on I got a question
about uh Consecration and the consecrate
ritual so the consecration trait is
unchanged as far as I can tell from uh
the Legacy Pathfinder Second Edition
rules but the consecrate ritual has been
adjusted to account for Holy and Unholy
traits and it now has a a part of it
that reads as follows if your deity's
Divine sanctification allows you to
choose holy or Unholy you can choose to
make the consecrated site holy or Unholy
as well if the deities sanctification
must be holy or Unholy you must make the
site match that
sanctification and it adds strikes made
by worshippers of your deity within the
area gain the sight's sanctification
trait if any so if you perform the
consecrate ritual and uh you are
following a holy God and you have been
Sanctified as being holy then that uh
area of the consecration is going to
have the Holy trait applied to that area
and any followers of your God in that
area or regardless if they're clerics or
not or if they have uh the holy trait or
not all those followers within that area
they follow your God will have the Holy
trait applied to their strikes and their
attack against enemies within that area
so uh next question is about Focus
points and the focus pool are Focus
pools still capped at three yes there is
still a hard cap of a maximum of three
Focus points but you can use the refocus
activity every 10 minutes without
limitation so in the original Pathfinder
Second Edition rules you could refocus
for 10 minutes but you could only do
that if you had spent at least one Focus
Point since the last time you uh
refocused and so that would prevent
someone from taking 30 minute taking a
30- minute break after a fight and
getting all three of their points back
and having them all available for the
next fight that rule was uh more than a
little confusing to to a number of
people so they've simplified it in the
remaster Edition and uh now that
language is removed from refocus it no
longer has that limitation so now if you
do have 30 minutes you can spend uh all
30 minutes and refocus three times in a
row and get all three of your focus
points back but uh three points is still
the listed maximum for Focus points uh
the next couple questions are all
dealing with the layout of the book um
is it more user friendly is it easier to
navigate gate around does it look nice
uh so first of all yeah I think it looks
very nice second of all um it is a
little easier to navigate around but I
don't think the changes are are so uh
material and wide sweeping that I would
go so far as to say that it's
fundamentally an easier layout and book
for for new players if you want a layout
that's going to be friendly for new
people then perhaps the beginner box is
still the place to to look for that but
some of the things that they've done uh
with the layout and presentation of the
remaster books first of all they are
using green as a dominant color so it's
easy to recognize what is uh a remaster
book versus one of the original Legacy
Rule books they are also applying some
more use of bold there are some sidebars
in the new book that have bolded words
to Stand Out whereas in the original
version those same sidebars did not and
uh the index has been improved uh in my
point of view because for example the
player core one not only includes all
the index items that you would expect to
find in a player core rule book but if
there was something that was included in
the core rule book in the original
release that has now been moved to GM
core then the player core book has an
index entry for those items and it says
hey that's not in this book anymore
you're going to want to go check out the
GM core and it will give you the page
number to the GM core which is super
handy a good example of this is runes
runes are no longer found in the player
book runes are now listed solely in the
GM book but because players might be
looking for that information the index
in the player core book does direct them
to the appropriate page in the GM core
rules which I think was um a great
addition and well thought
out next question is about Shield runes
we heard that there were changes coming
to Shields um but what about Shield
runes how are these going to function
okay so Shields now have their own
potency runes that are called reinfor
forcing runes reinforcing runes increase
the hardness the hit points and the
break threshold all three of them for
any Shield that is Eed with a
reinforcing Rune unlike potency runes
for uh for weapons and for armor Shield
potency runes these reinforcing runes
come in six varieties instead of three
the first it becomes available at fourth
level and then a new one every three
levels after
so the six types of reinforcing runes
are minor lesser moderate greater major
and supreme now those are the um potency
runes for
Shields however at this time I don't
believe there are any potency runes for
Shields I didn't see any of those listed
uh that could be something that they
plan to add later I don't know but for
example there's no like flaming shield
runes and and so forth there are still
plenty of just standard magical Shields
that apply
different different aspects similar to
what we would achieve through potency
runes or through U through property
runes excuse me um but as of right now
in this first release No property runes
for Shields only potency runes they are
called reinforcing runes they increase
hardness hit points and break
threshold so next question was uh are
there any changes to crafting and yes
and um there are changes that I am
pretty excited about that I like um
these changes are going to alleviate
some of the most common um concerns
about crafting but if there's one thing
I've learned running this channel is
that there's a lot of people out there
who just
fundamentally hate the crafting rules in
Pathfinder second addition for those
folks this may not uh may not fix all
year problems but here's what they've
done to crafting first of all they have
reduced the base time to craft from 4
days to only two days so now you have to
it still works the same way you still
have to have half of the value of the
item you want to craft and raw materials
you spend two days instead of four days
uh setting up and beginning work and uh
exhaust those uh
that value that half value of uh the
price of the item you're crafting and
then make a skill check and then after
that you can choose to either pay the
remaining cost out of your pocket and
finish immediately or continue working
additional days and for every additional
day spent crafting you reduce the uh the
remaining budget by the amount found on
the earn income table that process is
is all the same the difference is
instead of having to work four days
before you can finish you only have to
work two also another big thing that
changed is if what you are crafting is
common Rarity then you do not need a
formula for it so you no longer have to
have a formula to craft something if it
is common Rarity now if you want to
craft something that is not common
Rarity then you either must have the
formula for that item or you must have
an already crafted uh sample of that
item if I want to uh craft a magic
weapon and that magic weapon is uncommon
Rarity I either need a formula for that
weapon or I need to have that weapon in
front of me for me to examine and figure
out and basically
replicate now
here's the thing though you no longer
have to have a formula for common Rarity
and you don't have to have a formula for
uncommon and more rare as long as you
have a sample to work off of but if you
do have the formula for what you're
trying to craft then the amount of time
needed to to craft it is further reduced
from two days to only one day so if you
were to apply this logic to the original
crafting rules and you have the formula
for whatever you're trying to craft then
it goes from being a minimum four days
to a minimum one day of work uh so I
think that's going to make a lot of
people happy out there even if it
doesn't fix all of the concerns that
exist uh with crafting moving on the
next question is about disarm did they
fix disarm rules um and I can't
objectively say if it is fixed or not
but they did improveed this did get a
buff and what they've done is they've
removed the limitation that's listed in
the write up for disarm that says until
the start of that creature's turn so in
the original disarm rules if you
succeeded but not critically succeeded
on a uh disarm attempt then you JW the
item loose in your opponent's hand and
that gives you a plus two to Future
attempts to knock it out which would
require a critical success and it
imposes a negative -2 penalty to that
person uh wanting to use it but in the
original rules those penalties
immediately went away at the start of
that creature's next turn which
basically meant imposing
the2 to their attacks with the weapon
you're trying to disarm completely
useless except if maybe they were going
to uh get an opportunity attack
um uh which is no longer called an
attack of opportunity in this system uh
but uh I'm sure you get the idea that's
very limited use the new version of his
arm just removes that language and
instead the penalty that's app applied
to using an item that has been knocked
Loose by a disarm attempt persists until
that person spins an action to to
interact with the weapon or whatever
you're trying to remove from their grasp
and fix their grip so uh that so when it
comes to that that character that
enemy's turn they're going to have to
make the decision do I want to attack
with this and suffer a negative -2 to
the attack or do I want to sacrifice one
of my three actions to regrip the weapon
properly um and remove those penalties
so probably is not the uh the fix
solution that some people want it's not
going back to the housian days of
Pathfinder first edition but this is
definitely a buff to disarm attempts so
next up we have the Ruffian Rogue and
the Ruffian Rogue is something that uh
they had hinted that there were changes
coming for so now they're here so let's
talk about them this is going to deal
with what weapons a Ruffian Rogue can
use to make sneake attacks in the
original Legacy first release of
Pathfinder second edition uh that was
limited to simple weapons they could use
Simple weapons to make their sneak
attacks and that's been changed uh and
it now reads as the following you can
deal sneak attack damage with any weapon
not just the weapons listed in the sneak
attack class feature this benefit does
not apply to a simple weapon with a
damage die greater than d8 or a marshall
or Advanced weapon with a damage die
greater than D6 apply any abilities that
alter the damage die first critical hits
you make with these weapons gain the
weapon critical specialization benefit
if the target is off guard to you um
offu by the way is the new term for flat
footed so uh this was great they're
they're uh greatly expanding the weapons
that a Ruffian Rogue can use to make
snake attacks with however there is a
damag die cap again for simple weapons
that cap is d8 and for Marshall or
Advanced weapons that cap is at
D6 so next is uh a question that um by
now if you're on Reddit or following uh
a number of my peers in the world of
YouTube you've probably heard an awful
lot about and that is wounded and dying
did they clarify exactly when the
wounded value is added to your your
dying condition value and this goes back
to inconsistencies in the original text
and also the beginnner bunks had areas
where they they said that uh the wounded
condition only applies to your or only
increases your dying value at the moment
you become unconscious and there's other
places that say that you add the
wounded's value to your dying value
every single time you either fail a
recovery check while you're unconscious
with the dying condition or whenever you
suffer additional damage while you have
the dying condition the good news is
this has been clarified
uh the bad news is that I I absolutely
cannot fathom why they decided to go
this way uh but for whatever is worth
the new official rules clearly specify
that for Recovery checks the dying
condition increases by one plus your
wounded value on a failure or two plus
the wounded value on a critical failure
and also your wounded value is added to
your dying value every time you suffer
additional damage while you have the
dying
condition so if you are wounded one and
get knocked down into zero hit points
you immediately go to dying two if you
fail your first recovery check that is
going to increase by one for the failure
and go from two to three but you're also
going to apply your wounded condition
value again taking U24 and um Pathfinder
second edition has been the most most
lethal D20 based RPG I've ever run I
have had more player deaths in this
system than any others so making it more
deadly more dangerous more difficult to
play I have no clue why piso decided to
go this
way um if you if if your goal is to to
uh scare away new players this is an
excellent way to do that this is a great
way to make sure people do not adopt and
play your
game uh so that said uh my house rule
number one is I'm not doing that I'm
only applying the wounded value to the
dying condition when a person gains the
dying condition and not after every
single failed recovery Checker when they
suffer additional damage uh the game is
simply just lethal enough the way it is
and if I'm introducing new players to my
game uh I want to be a little more
lenient with them making mistakes um and
again I I am baffled frankly baffled by
their decision to go this way but that's
what the the new rule is and our next
question is about the warrior Muse bard
uh this question says that they
mentioned that they were doing something
to make it feel better but we haven't
heard anything since okay so uh the
warrior Muse Bard I did a a cursory look
at it and I believe the changes are have
been applied to the Marshall performance
feat which all Warrior Muse bars receive
the old version said you become trained
with all Marshall weapons if you gain
the B weapon expertise class feature
your proficiency rank with Marshall
weapons increases to expert now the new
version of Marshall performance for the
warrior Muse BS has been completely
Rewritten and it now says when you have
a courageous Anthem composition canri
active Al so it's worth mentioning that
courageous Anthem is the new name for
inspire courage so this is sort of like
saying in the old version whenever you
have Inspire courage active but now it's
called courageous Anthem so when you
have that cantrip active and you damage
an enemy with a strike the Spell's
duration is extended by one round you
can extend an individual casting only
once this
way so I believe what they're basically
saying here is as long as you can
reliably strike and deal damage to your
enemies then you will only need to spend
one action to cast a courageous Anthem
or Inspire courage once every two rounds
instead of having to spend an action on
it every single round but again you have
to be able to successfully strike and
deal damage to an enemy in order to get
that benefit uh it goes on to say if you
gain the rallying Anthem or song of
strength composition cantrips you can
apply this benefit to those cantrips as
well and uh this is another time where
the U the names have changed a little
bit rallying Anthem is what used to be
known as Inspire defense it's now called
rallying Anthem but um if you are a
warrior Muse bar
then you get that same benefit for
courageous anthem for rallying Anthem
and for song of strength as if you have
one of those cast and it's active and
you strike and deal damage to an enemy
then it extends the duration of that
casting by one round but you can only do
that one time per casting so again I
believe the benefit here is that uh as
long as you can reliably hit and deal
damage you will only sacrifice one
action every two turns on those can
trips instead of once every single turn
all right so those were a handful of
questions that were asked on Reddit and
on patreon and uh if you have any
questions about them please feel free to
leave those in the comments if you have
any questions that uh were not touched
on in this video I do plan to do more
videos about this please leave those in
the comments as well and as always I
want to take a quick moment to say thank
you to everybody out there who supports
me whether that's by leaving those
questions and comments and suggestions
or clicking the like button subscribing
to this Channel or subscribing to the
patreon I really appreciate everything
you folks do to support me and with that
thanks for watching take care and happy
[Music]
gaming