[Music]
hey everybody Dave here and I just
wanted to get out a very quick update in
regard to the brand new remaster
editions that released officially today
um and especially in regards to one
piece of information that was delivered
in my previous video about the remaster
editions where I answered uh questions
from the community about it um today
along with the release of those two new
books they also released and updated on
their website list of verada for both
player core and GM core as well as some
remaster updates to other existing books
like the advanced players guide and if
you saw my video on the uh questions
that were being answered about the
remaster editions you know that my my
number one concern um the number one
change that I was really kind of upset
about was that they had made uh the
death and dying rules much much much
more
lethal uh for those who are not familiar
in the original release of uh Second
Edition there was some conflicting
language uh both in the player or the
core rule book as well as the uh
beginners box set where in some places
it said that you only add your wounded
value to your dying value uh at the time
that you're knocked unconscious in other
places
said that you added your wounded
condition to your dying value basically
every time you fall unconscious plus
every time you fail a recovery check
plus every time you take additional
damage while unconscious which
essentially meant that if you had a
wounded value of one and you fail even
one recovery check you you die
um and that's probably not great uh I
had expressed a lot of concerns about
what this was going to mean to new
players ERS who come in and are trying
to learn the system and find out that
they're having a tbk right off the bat
it's a real good way to to ruin a new
players fun but here's I guess the good
news in the newly released ARA to the
new player core book they include this
passage Pages
411 the text for the wounded condition
was changed for consistency but became
consistent with the wrong piece of textt
which I think is an interesting an
interesting way to phrase it in an
interesting mistake uh and I'm not sure
how this slips past QA but uh so be it
that's what it says it goes on to say
this would lead to much deadlier
encounters I believe so the following
changes should ensure that death and
dying works the way we intended in the
recovery checks degrees of success
remove all instances of that
parenthetical that says plus your
wounded condition of any that's both in
the failure and critical failure entries
under taking damage remove the final
sentence that reads if you have the
wounded condition remember to add the
value of your wounded condition to your
dying value this reminder should only
apply to when you gain the dying
condition after getting knocked out so I
believe with this official AA it does
put it back in line with what I
originally thought the rule was what my
videos that deal with death dying in the
wooden condition say and that is you
only apply the value of your wounded
condition to your dying condition at the
time you become unconscious and not
again when you fail or critically fail a
recovery check or take additional damage
so uh that's it for tonight I just
wanted to get out a very quick video to
let everybody know that because this is
a a topic that has generated a lot of
conversation
uh both on the comment section of my
previous remaster video as well as all
over the forums and reddits and every
and every place else and of course thank
you to everybody who supports me whether
that's by clicking the like button
subscribing to the channel subscribing
to the patreon buying a super thanks I
appreciate everything you folks do to
support me thanks for watching take care
and happy
[Music]
game