[Music]
hello and welcome to forced movement in
Pathfinder second edition remastered
although this video does provide the
roles specifically from the remaster
Edition they should be easy to apply to
the Legacy Edition as well forced
movement occurs whenever a character is
moved not by the player controlling them
but by another creature or effect for
example when one character shoves
another or is hurled by a powerful gust
of wind a few common sources of force
movement include the shove and
reposition actions shove is an
application of the athletic skill costs
one action and requires you to have at
least one hand free you roll your
athletic skill versus your Target's 4
to2 DC in on his success your target
moves back 5T and on a critical success
your target moves back 10 ft in either
case you can sh choose to follow after
them as might occur when bull rushing
someone on a failure nothing happens and
on a critical failure you fall prone and
note that shove does have the attack
trait so it both contributes to and is
affected by the multiple attack penalty
so for example Omi is fighting a horned
devil and wishes to push him away he
would roll his athletic skill of plus 13
and compare that total against the devil
's fortitude DC to calculate the devil's
fortitude DC we take their fortitude
save bonus of plus 15 and add 10 for a
total 42 DC of
25 omi rolls a 14 on the DME plus their
Athletics bonus of plus 13 for a total
of
27 this is a success and the devil is
pushed back 5T or one square and note
that if Ami made a strike with their
first first action and then attempted
this shove with their second action they
would have failed because this check
would be subject to A5 multiple attack
penalty luring it to only
22 the second common source of forced
movement is the reposition action this
is also an application of the athletic
skill but is used to move an enemy into
a space that is not away from you this
works almost the same way as shoving
someone except you don't need a free
hand if you already already have that
Target grabbed or restrained the target
must remain within your reach throughout
the entire movement and if you
critically fail your target gets to move
you as if they had performed a
reposition action so for example say Ami
and Quinn the Rogue are fighting the
same devil Omi may decide he wants to
grab hold of the devil and move him one
space to the right to apply flanking so
that Quinn can get all of the benefits
of the devil being off guard on his turn
this wouldn't be a shove action because
the devil is not being moved away from
AI he's currently 5T away and will still
be 5 ft away at the end of the
reposition therefore he's not being
moved away Ami would roll his athletic
skill versus the devil's fortitude DC
just as before but the major difference
here is if he critically fails the devil
can instead move him into another
space special rules of apply when forced
movement occurs in the game first the
speed and distance the creature is moved
is determined by the effect that causes
the forced movement for example the text
for the hydraulic push spell says on a
success the target is pushed by 5T and
on a critical success the target is
pushed back 10t this is an example of
forced movement and the distance the
target is moved away from the Caster is
listed in the description and has
nothing to do with the target's own
speed score next be aware that Force
movement does not trigger reactions that
are normally triggered by a movement for
example say you're a fighter and you're
wielding a club with critical
specialization you roll a critical hit
against a bug bear and knock him back 10
ft at this point you might also want to
spend your reaction to perform a
reactive strike which was previously
called an attack of opportunity because
an enemy that was previously with in
your reach just moved out of its Square
however you would not be able to do so
in this case for two reasons first
because this is a forced movement which
does not trigger reactions due to
movement and second because the text for
reactive strike specifically states that
the target must spend their own action
to move which does not occur due to a
forced
movement the path that the target of
forced movement takes is determined by
the creature or effect that caused the
forced movement second addition does not
enforce a lot of hard rules for
determining this and mostly leaves it in
the hands of the GM to make a final
decision on if the path makes sense or
not most causes of forced movement state
that the target is either knocked back
or pulled towards in these cases
knocking back should be a fairly
straight line away and pulling towards
should be a fairly straight line toward
towards the source of the effect and
also note that difficult terrain and
other hindrances to movement do apply to
forced movement just as they do to
normal movement and if the path of
forced movement would move a creature
into a space that cannot occupy for
example because there is a wall or other
object there they would stop moving in
the last valid square that they can
occupy this can sometimes raise the
question of what happens when you shove
one enemy in into another the rules say
that no two creatures can occupy the
same space therefore when you try to
shove one creature into another the
shoved creature would stop moving in the
last valid space of the path and not
enter into or interact with the other
creature or space Also the rules for
moving through an Allied creature space
would not apply here because the rule
for forced movement says movement ends
if the space cannot be occupied and one
creature cannot occupy another creature
space however the GM makes the final
decision as to what happens when one
creature is shoved into another and in a
lot of cases I would rule differently in
my game than what the official rule says
and declare that the second creature
needs to make a save to avoid me kn
prone simply because that sounds more
fun to me than just having the shoved
creature stop in the last valid space
but from a rules perspective be aware
that the shoved creature would likely
stop stop before interacting with the
second creature the rules also provide
guidance for what happens when forced
movement moves a creature into a
dangerous space like shoving a creature
into a pit or into a wall of fire the
rules state that when a creature is
pushed or pulled they may be moved into
a dangerous space but not when they are
repositioned in some other manner so if
you were to shove an enemy off a ledge
they would immediately start falling and
be allowed to spin their reaction on
grab an edge and if he shoved an enemy
into a wall of fire they would suffer
immediate damage for Crossing into it
and more damage at the start of their
turn assuming they are still occupying
that space and some abilities allow a
creature to pick up and carry another
with it this is also forced movement but
unlike with pushing or pulling someone
you cannot move a carried creature
through a hazardous space that that you
too do not also pass through for example
some types of animated constructs have
the ability to pick up and carry a
target with them if they did so both the
construct and the carried creature would
be considered as occupying the same
space for the duration of that movement
the construct couldn't walk one path
while holding the carried creature in an
adjacent space so that they are harmed
by an environmental hazard that the
construct is able to avoid
likewise forced movement that does not
involve a push or a pull could not be
used to move an enemy into a danger
space for example you cannot use
reposition to move an enemy over the
ledge of a cliff but remember in all
cases the GM has the final say as to
what is or is not possible with forced
movement that should do it for our
discussion on forc movement in
Pathfinder if you have any questions or
insights please leave them in the
comments and I would like to take a
brief moment to thank everyone who
supports this channel whether that be by
leaving comments clicking the like
button subscribing to the channel
subscribing to the patreon or buying a
super thanks I greatly appreciate all
you do to support me with that thanks
for watching take care and happy
[Music]
gaming