hello and welcome to runes for
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part two in the previous video we
discussed the foundation for runes and
Pathfinder primarily the relationship
between fundamental runes and property
runes and in this video we're going to
expand on that by covering a few of the
other additional rules including how to
etch or create a magic rune how to
upgrade runes and how to transfer runes
from one item to another this video does
does rely heavily on the crafting rules
so if you've not already viewed my
videos on Crafting it's highly
recommended that you do so before
continuing here links to these videos
are provided in the description the term
etching a rune is just a formal way of
saying creating a rune and adding it to
an item this follows the same system as
crafting anything else the only real
difference is you're not making an
entirely new item you're just adding to
an already existing item if you want to
etch a plus one weapon potency Rune on a
long sword you would first need to be at
least expert Proficiency in the crafting
skill and have the magical crafting feat
you also need the long sword you plan to
etch the Rune on and you need to either
have the formula for weapon potency
runes or you need to have another item
with that Rune on it already that you
can copy and you would need to have at
least half the rune's price available in
raw materials in this case that would be
half half of 35 gold which is 17 gold
and five silver from there assuming you
have the formula you spend one day of
work as usual with crafting and after
that you will make a skill check and if
that's successful you can pay the
balance to finish the project or invest
more time in lowering the balance again
check out my videos about crafting for
more detail on how all of that
works some runes typically fundamental
runes allow you to upgrade low lower
level versions into higher level
versions if a rune is eligible to be
upgraded it will say so in its
description here the description for the
armor potency Rune spells it all out for
you the process is simple it works just
like etching a rune except the price is
discounted by the price of the existing
Rune that is being replaced so if you
want to upgrade a suit of plus one chain
mail to plus two chain mail you would
treat it the same as crafting a plus two
armor potency Rune from scratch you need
to have either the formula for armor
potency runes or have another item with
the armor potency Rune on it that you're
going to copy you must be at least 11th
level and have Master Proficiency in
crafting you need the magical crafting
feat and you must provide 50% of the
run's price up front in raw materials
the difference with upgrading though is
the normal price for this Rune is 1,60
gold but when upgrading you discount it
by the original runes price P of 160
gold making the upgrade price 900 gold
pieces you pay 50% of that up front or
450 gold spend one day of downtime
working assuming you're using the
formula and then make a crafting skill
check as usual then assuming you succeed
the check you can either pay off the
remaining balance of 450 gold or spend
more days of downtime lowering that
balance further note that the table on
page 224 of the GM or rule book outlines
a typical progression for upgrading
armor and weapons and follows the
pattern of upgrading the potency Rune
then the resilient rune for armor or
striking rune for weapons then upgrading
the potency Rune again and repeating
this is a typical progression but it is
not absolutely required for example you
can upgrade the Striking Rune of a
weapon before upgrading its potency Rune
you can even have a striking Rune on a
weapon that has no potency Rune but
given the availability of these runes
and the way their prices are staggered
it makes most sense to follow the
progression that's provided in these
charts you can also use the crafting
skill to move a rune from one item to
another or swamp a rune on one item with
a rune that's on another item doing so
takes one day of downtime and costs 10%
of the runes price if you're swapping
runes between two items then you only
use the price of the highest level Rune
to determine the cost you don't have to
pay 10% of the price of each of the
runes being swapped only the higher
level one also you don't need a formula
to transfer a rune but otherwise this is
identical to crafting or etching a rune
you must have the magical crafting feat
and pay half the cost which is 5% of the
run's price up front then make your
crafting check and if that's successful
you can choose to pay the other half or
continue working as normal with crafting
ing there are a couple of other rules
that you might want to be aware of first
if swapping runes they must both be
fundamental runes or both must be
property runes and the final item or
items must be legal for example you
can't transfer a wounding rune from a
dagger onto a mace because this Rune
requires it to be attached to a slashing
or piercing weapon and maces are boning
weapons one tweak to be aware of is when
transferring potent runes it's possible
you might end up with an item that has
property runes on it that can no longer
function because they require a potency
Rune that is no longer present this
doesn't prevent you from transferring
the potency Rune but affected property
runes go dormant until they're either
transferred to an item that does have
the necessary potency Rune or until you
etge the appropriate potency Rune onto
the item that is bearing those dormant
runes at which time they reactivate and
can function again
I also want to mention run Stones
runestones cost three gold pieces each
and they essentially provide a way of
transporting a rune without requiring it
to be etched onto a weapon Shield or
suit of armor these are provided so that
GMS can distribute runes to players so
that those players can decide how best
to use the runes rather than giving them
runes already etched onto equipment they
may not want to use or may not even be
able to use R Stones work like any other
item for the purposes of crafting or
transferring a rune you can etch a rune
onto a runstone or you can transfer a
rune off of an item and onto a run Stone
the big difference is that runestones
are consumed and destroyed as soon as
its Rune is removed off of them and
transferred to another item and that
transfer has no cost associated with it
under normal circumstances when you
transfer a rune off an item you have to
pay 10% of its price but if that item is
a run Stone there is no cost associated
with transferring that Rune from that
runestone and onto another
item so that's it for the fundamentals
of runes for those of you who would like
a summary of what has changed with the
remaster Edition the key mechanical
differences lie with the crafting rules
the minimum time required to craft or
upgrade a rune has decreased from 4 days
to 1 day and it is now possible to craft
an item without having its formula
as long as you have a sample of that
item and are making a copy of it however
having the formula allows you to craft
the item faster in addition to that
there are several other points that have
been clarified since the original
release of second edition those are you
do not have to upgrade potency before
other fundamental runes like resilient
and striking you don't have to upgrade
runes step by step for example you can
upgrade a plus one weapon potency Rune
directly to a plus three Rune and and
you do not need a formula to transfer a
rune but you do need to have the magical
crafting feat to transfer
runes if you have any questions please
leave them in the comments below and as
always I'd like to take a brief moment
to thank everyone who supports this
channel whether that be by clicking the
like button subscribing to the channel
or subscribing to the patreon I greatly
appreciate everything you do to support
me with that thanks for watching take
care and happy
gaming
[Music]