hello and welcome to identifying
monsters in Pathfinder second edition
remastered in this video we're going to
discuss the mechanics involved when a
player wants to see what their character
knows about a given enemy are they weak
to fire will cold iron hurt them did
they come from one of the Outer Planes
things like that and it's worth
mentioning that although this video is
targeted towards identifying Monsters
the process that's explained here
applies to any Recon check so the same
process could be used to see what a
character knows about a coat of arms
about an old tree or really anything and
as a reminder this video is again for
the remaster Edition so if your game is
using the original Legacy edition of
Pathfinder second edition then please
see the link in the description for a
video that covers those
rules when players encounter a creature
they don't recognize or more
appropriately when their characters
encounter such a monster as separating
player Knowledge from character
knowledge is going to be very important
to this discussion they may attempt
skill checks to see what information
their character knows about the creature
this is a recall knowledge check
requires one action and can be attempted
untrained when doing so the player will
ask the GM one questions such as can it
be reasoned with what environments does
it live in
what's its most notable offensive
ability is it highly vulnerable or
resistant to anything or are any of his
defenses weak ideally the question
should be phrased using in universal
language but it's usually acceptable for
players to use Game language too for
example most GMS would allow their
players to ask what is its worst saving
throw and then the GM rolls the skill
check in secret so the player does not
know how well or how poorly they did or
in other words they don't know how
reliable the result is going to be on a
success the GM answers the question
truthfully but without providing any
numbers for example if after observing a
trolls regeneration ability the player
uses their recall knowledge action and
asks is there any way to negate this
regeneration the GM would roll the check
in secret and on a success answer you
know the trolls generation ability can
be temporarily deactivated by dealing
electricity or fire damage also note
that the GM May limit the knowledge
given according to the proficiency level
of the character making the check for
example an untrained character may not
know very obscure information about a
Target no matter how high they roll
there are no concrete rules for
determining what information is granted
at each proficiency level and this will
require the GM to make a judgment call
regarding what is appropriate
information for each proficiency level
on a critical success the GM answers the
question that was asked truthfully and
either provides additional information
related to that question or allows the
player to ask a second question which
they will also answer truthfully the
book doesn't provide a lot of guidance
for this but in my game if a player asks
is it weak to anything enrolls a success
I would provide what I consider to be
the greatest weakness or the most
well-known weakness in the case of this
troll I would tell them that it is weak
to Fire and if they rote a critical
success I would tell them all of the
creatures weaknesses in this case I
would tell them it's weak to Fire and
electricity but I wouldn't provide any
numbers I wouldn't tell them that the
weaknesses are electricity 10 and fire
10 and on a failed recall knowledge
check the player learns nothing and on a
critical failure they learn incorrect or
misleading information maybe they
mistake the troll for a marsh Giant and
therefore don't know that it has
regeneration abilities this is why it's
important to roll the check in secret so
the players don't know if the
information is correct and there may be
sometimes you need to remind players
that player knowledge and character
knowledge should be separate so if a
player knows that the information you
give them is false you may need to
remind them that their character
believes that it is correct and they
should play that character
appropriately but before you can roll
those recall knowledge checks you need
to know which skill to use by default
the skills you use to identify a
creature are based on its traits the
table on page 55 of the GM chord book
spells it all out for you Arcana is used
to identify beasts constructs dragons
and Elementals crafting is used to
identify constructs nature is used to
identify animals beasts Elementals Fay
fungi and plants occultism is used to
identify aberations astral beings dreams
creatures with the Ethereal trait ooes
spirits and time creatures religion is
used to identify Celestial beings fiends
monitors such as psychopomps Shades and
Undead and Society is used to identify
and know details about the various
humanoid ancestries that inhabit Garian
like humans elves dwarves and so on and
note that we're talking about the
humanoid trait here not the creatures
shape a zombie may have two arms two
legs and a head but they're not
considered to be quote humanoids in game
terms so for example if players
encounter a mantore they could use
either the Arcana or nature skills to
identify it since manacor have the Beast
trait in addition players can also use
an appropriate lore skill to identify
creatures so as another example if
you're trying to identify a vampire you
could use either religion or lore Undead
or even more specific lore skills like
lore vampire at the GMS discretion
players might also be able to use other
related skills hags for example are
humanoids and therefore you would
normally use Society to identify them
but hags are also well known for their
occult spell use so a GM might allow
occultism in place of society it's also
possible to gain knowledge about a
creature using even more skills this
will be entirely up to the GM but if the
character has an ability or skill that
they're trying to assess in the Target
creature then they might be able to use
a skill to see if the target creature
has the same ability or to what degree
for example if a character is trained in
athletics and wants to know if they can
outrun a monster they might be able to
roll Athletics instead of a knowledge
skill but they would use their
intelligence modifier for the bonus
instead of strength for that check and a
quick per tip if you look up the
creature using an online resource like
PFE easy tools it will tell you exactly
which skill to roll and as DC for
example using recall knowledge with a
force troll is a dc20 society
check once you know what skill needs to
be en rolled the next next question is
what DC needs to be beat to score
success this is fairly easy simply
compare the level of the creature to the
DC's by level table found on page 53 of
the GM core book and then modify by the
creatures
Rarity common creatures use the listed
DC increase the DC by two for uncommon
creatures by five for rare creatures and
by 10 for unique creatur creatures and
then lower the DC if a lore skill is
being used instead of one of the general
knowledge skills this reduction is
either two points lower or five points
lower at the GM's discretion for example
nths are common 10th level aberration so
identifying one would call for a dc27
occultism check Cyclops are uncommon
fifth level humanoids so it would take a
dc22 society check to identify one of
them and if using the lore cyclop skill
instead of society the DC may be lowered
to
17 things get a little more tricky when
talking about unique creatures rules as
written unique creatures have a DC that
is 10 higher than what's listed for
their level on the table but I think
this is one of those areas where the GM
really needs to Leverage their own
insights if the creature has the unique
tag because they are an individual
member of a species like warble Bumble
Brasher is then by raw the DC to
identify her is 25 15 for being first
level plus 10 more for having the unique
trait although not spelled out in the
rules I believe the intention here is
for it to be a dc15 society check to
know that looking at a goblin and a dc25
check to recognize her as a specific
Goblin named warble Bumble Brasher and
the GM May lower the DC to know that
warble is a goblin due to the standard
Goblin being a level negative one
creature again this is all up to the GM
to make a judgment call the GM also
needs to ask themselves if warble is a
goblin of great Renown in the community
then wouldn't it be easier to identify
her if that's the case the DC may be
lower to know her name but would likely
still be
dc25 to know that she's deadly accurate
when throwing her heavy books as ranged
weapons again the GM will need to use
some common sense and their own
interpretations when managing the DCS to
identify unique
creatures that's the gist of how to
identify a monster you use recall
knowledge with an appropriate skill
versus a DC that's based on the
creature's level and Rarity if
successful the GM answers one question
about it and if you critically succeed
you either learn extra information
related to the question that you asked
or the GM offers to answer another
question but what if that's not enough
what if you need to learn even more
information about the creature you can
continue to spend one action and make
one skill check but with two
restrictions first as soon as a
character fails a recall knowledge check
they cannot make any further checks on
that subject at that point the GM has
revealed all the information the
character knows about the creature and
second the DC increases by one
difficulty level with every additional
check so for example if you succeed your
first skill check against a regular DC
the GM answers one question about the
monster if you spend another action this
becomes a harded check increases the DC
by two and if successful the GM answers
another question about it and if that's
still not enough information you can
make a third check at plus five if you
fail that check you're done but if you
succeed then you can make one last check
at incredibly hard difficulty with A+ 10
DC this is the last check you can make
regardless of success or failure after
you attempt an incredibly hard check the
GM will have revealed all the
information you know about the creature
and note that if the character is using
a lore skill then they start at either
easy or very easy on this chart this is
where that Nega -2 and5 reduction to DCR
previously mentioned comes from which
means you have more potential checks
that can be made with lore skills as it
will take a person starting at very easy
six recall knowledge actions to max out
their knowledge of a creature versus
four attempts when using a general
knowledge skill and a standard
DC and since this is for the remaster
edition let's briefly review the changes
from the Legacy Edition the biggest
change in this remastered version is the
player asks a specific question and gets
a specific answer in the Legacy edition
if they rolled a success then the GM
needed to decide what the most commonly
known fact about the monster was and
share that and on repeated attempts the
GM would need to decide what the next
most well-known fact about the monster
was and so on this process could be
frustrating for GMS because it forced
them to sort of rank all of the Monster
stats from best known to least known
without any guidance and it could also
be frustrating for players because they
could receive information that they
didn't want or need in the new version
The Players ask specific questions and
that helps ensure they'll be rewarded
with applicable
information so there you have it the
rules for identifying monsters in other
applications of recall knowledge and
Pathfinder second edition remastered if
you have any questions please leave them
in the comments and I want to take a
quick moment to thank everyone who
supports me and this channel whether
that be by leaving your comments
clicking the like button subscribing to
the channel buying a super thanks or
subscribing to the patreon I really
appreciate all you do to support me with
that thanks for watching take care and
happy gaming
[Music]