hey everybody Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you and
today we're going to be talking about
gambling in Pathfinder this was a
question that recently came up of how do
you make gambling work in a tabletop RPG
are there rules in place to ensure that
the players don't just completely break
everything by winning billions and
billions of of gold coins and how would
you manage players who want to either uh
play into the character trait of being a
gambler like a a Lando calisan Fantasy
character type or how would you handle
characters who want to do like a a um an
Oceans 11 style heist with uh casino
games so we're going to talk about a
couple of those pieces um primarily
we're going to be talking about uh the
gambling activity itself and you can
probably take these pointers and ideas
and craft them into a larger story if
that's what you
want so there are a couple different
ways to manage a player gambling in your
game and each of them kind of have their
own uh strengths and weaknesses and
we'll talk through um each of these in
turn the first is just going to be your
regular earn income activity this is a
downtime activity where on on days where
there's no adventuring going on you can
give your players the opportunity to do
a downtime activity and for some people
that could mean I'm going to go craft
for some people that could mean I'm
going to go work in the Local Tavern and
for some players that could be uh I want
to go to the local casino and see if I
can make some
money and gambling as an earn income
Activity Works exactly the same way as
any other earn income activity the only
difference is going to be in the
narrative however you describe it
occurring but it's going to be uh an
entire day or roughly 8ish hours of
activity in the casino and it comes down
to one di roll and that di roll will
determine how much of a profit is
generated by that character in their
gambling activities for that day of
downtime they will need to use an
appropriate lore skill to do this most
likely either Casino lore or game lore
and um if you want detailed information
of how that works I'll make sure I link
in the comments section or the
description of this video uh my previous
videos on the earn income activity that
really goes through the nuts and bolts
of how earn income Works uh I will
mention that uh there is a spell that
was released I think in secrets of magic
called nudge the odds and the nudge the
odds spell allows a person to get a plus
one bonus to their games lore roles for
one hour and it turns any critical
failures into regular failures so uh the
base version cannot be used with um with
earn income because it only has a 1hour
duration but if you increase it to fifth
level I believe it becomes an all day
activity and you specifically can use it
as part of your downtime activities now
on the downside of using this spell is
one facial feature determined by the GM
is turned golden for the duration of the
spell so uh this is a pretty clear tell
that uh you are using some sort of magic
to enhance your abilities uh whether or
not the people in the casino can
recognize it will will determine will
come down to a recall knowledge check on
their end uh but just be aware that
there uh there is the danger of getting
busted pretty easily using uh the um uh
nudge the odds
spell so um that is the first op earn
income a benefits super simple it comes
down to one die roll uh it's earn income
activity it uh inherently does not
require a lot of time at the game table
you can knock it out at the same time
everybody else is doing their crafting
or their uh their retraining or whatever
their downtime activities are um the the
downside of it is it comes down to one
di roll so if you have a player that's
really wanting to invest or if you're
trying to craft a meaningful narrative
that revolves around gambling and and
games of chance then it's probably not
going to be uh super fulfilling for them
but that kind of leads us to our second
option which is uh book three of the
Agents of edge Watch Adventure path
called All or Nothing uh has in its back
matter or in its Adventure toolbox I
think they call it a number of different
uh
realworld gambling games chance
converted into the Pathfinder setting
that you can play out at the game table
uh now the plus side is that these are
much more immersive experiences than uh
just an earn income role um the downside
is is your players are going to be
playing this for real using their own
Noggin and their own abilities uh not
their characters so one thing in common
with these uh I think is three from All
or Nothing I'll be sharing in a second
is none of them interact with character
sheets so none of them interact with
games Lords of skill interact with
Casino lore uh would be uh impacted or
interact with uh the nudge the odd spell
you are you are playing these games for
real so to speak at your game table um
but with the characters money and their
ability to profit from it
also I'll mention that all three of
these games are available on Archives of
nethys um and I will include links to
those writeups in the description of
this video um in case you don't have the
um old or nothing Adventure so the first
is a game called Gollum and golum is
sort of like the Pathfinders version of
Poker uh the idea is that you have a
number of players sitting around the
table and there's a dealer and those
players are trying to build the best
poker hand out of their cards um now
I'll I'll say that um the writeup
doesn't tell you the rules of Poker I
think it just references poker and says
like you know to determine who has the
winning hand is the same rules as poker
so you might need to go to Wikipedia or
some other resource online to find out
you know when a full house beats a
straight flush and all those kind of
rules but it's going to use those
familiar rules uh the game is played in
rounds uh anti is usually capped at five
gold um Everybody matches the current
bet or the anti and then they can either
raise or fold just kind of like in poker
where you go in rounds betting continues
until all players have matched the
current bet or they have folded and then
each player May discard up to two of
their cards and draw two new cards so
everybody still in the game if they've
if they've matched the uh the current
bet for that round they can discard zero
one or two of their cards and then draw
in new ones uh those cards are going to
be placed face down on the table so none
of the other players can see what was
discarded and those cards now all belong
to the Golem essentially the dealer at
the table is going to take all those
cards and keep them and they are the
Golem and those cars now belong to the
Golem uh if everybody folds except for
one player that player wins the pot
minus 5% that goes to the house uh in
Golem the house always gets 5% of the
pot uh no matter what the outcomes
are if at least two players match that
bet at the end of the round then the
dealer frees the Golem and then the
Golem is going to flip over all of their
cards and make the best possible poker
hand that they can out of all of the
cards that were discarded by the players
who are in that round and if the if one
of the players um has the best hand to
Beast the other players and the Golem
then that player uh wins the pot minus
5% that always goes to the house and if
no player beats the Golem then uh you
start over again you're going to to
double the size of the current ante and
start over again and you keep playing
until every round if nobody beats the
goem we start again and double it and
double it double it and um at the or
it's going to end when one player
eventually beats the Golem and they get
whatever is in that pot minus the 5%
that goes to the house so that's Golem
which is kind of basically like poker
the second game um from All or Nothing
is called Bounder which I believe is
kind of like craps I should probably
confess that I'm not a gambler so I I
may be I may be wrong uh let me know in
the comments if I'm goofing it up I
think this is supposed to be like
craps this is played with uh a bunch of
gamblers standing around a table
throwing Dice and each of them goes in
turns uh there is a shooter and that's
whose ever turn it is and then there is
a dealer so Shooters are going to roll
2D2 and the dealer is going to roll 3d6
and the the goal is if you're the
shooter you want to bound the total of
the dealers
3d6 and bounding means one of your D20
numbers is lower than the Dealer's 3d6
total and your other D20 is higher than
the 3d6 total from the dealer so you're
on either side on either bounds you're
bounding the um the dealers 3d6 total so
the way this is going to work in turn is
whoever is the shooter is going to roll
one D20 only one of their two dice
rolled first and whatever that total is
is called the point at that point the
shooter can choose to double their stake
double their bet based on their first
D20 result so if if they throw that
first die and it's a a one a two a 19 or
a 20 then they know they're going to
have at least one di on one side of the
3d6 because one 12 19 and 20 are not
possible totals for 3d6 so there they're
going to say yeah automatically I'm
going to double my my my stake um and
they can also D choose a double it I
mean if if they roll a five they might
choose to double it because still odds
are good but so on and so forth they get
the opportunity to double it if if they
if they roll a nine on that one20 they
probably don't want to risk doubling
their uh their stake um at that point
all the other gamblers who are not the
shooter on the table can choose whether
or not they want to bet on the final
result so they can throw in a stake and
say I think uh the shooter is going to
win based on this first role on this
point I think they're going to win
they're going to bound the dealers roles
so I'm going to throw 10 gold into the
pot or
whatever at that point the dealer is
going to roll their
3d6 now it says it varies from gambling
location to location but some casinos
before the dealer rolls their 3d6 will
allow all the gamblers at the table to
place bets on what the the 3d6 total is
going to be or actually not the total
but you can make a side bet and say I
think the dealer is going to roll all
odd numbers or I think they're going to
roll all even numbers or I think they're
going to roll three of a kind and um if
you bet that they're going to roll all
odd or all even you get uh you get
basically double back you get the same
amount as what you staked and in profit
and if you bet that there are going to
roll three of a kind you uh get tripled
now uh let me I'm going to give me one
second check here because I have on my
form here the odds yeah the odds of the
dealer rolling all evens or odds on 3d6
is less than a 133% chance and the odds
of rolling three of a kind is less than
3% so these sound like pretty bad bets
to me but um but that is something that
is an option when playing
Bounder so then um the dealer rolls
there 3d6 you see the total and uh from
there if if the total is equal to the
first 1 D20 that the that the shooter
rolled then the shooter automatically
loses and everybody loses their stake on
that um in order to win boundary you
have to have one lower than and one
higher than any die that equals the
total of the dealer automatically lose
loses and then the shooter is going to
roll their other D20 and see if they win
if they end up with having one of their
D20 results being lower than the dealers
3d6 total and one Higher they're going
to uh get a they're going to win an
amount equal to their stake and if uh if
if any other scenario happens either
they tie or both numbers are lower but
the numbers are higher then they lose
their their
stake uh this the odds of this it says
is about 40% the shooter should win
about 40% of the time and after one
person plays as the shooter then you
just go like clockwise around the table
and the next Gambler gets their chance
to be the shooter and it just repeats
and repeats for as long as people want
to play and have
fun so that brings us to our third um
casino game our game of chance from um
the all or nothing book for agents of
edge watch and that's a game called
Century which I believe is like
Kino um and this is kind of just like a
lottery so basically what happens is the
house is going to be randomly generating
20 numbers and those numbers are going
to be between one and 100 and you can
choose to uh bet between two and 10
times so you can you can choose choose
two numbers between one and 100 or you
can choose 10 numbers between one and
100 or anywhere between there and for
every number that you pick that is that
is drawn or rolled by the house then
you're going to win uh an amount of
money and uh if you don't then you lose
your money so it it is basically just a
lottery system as far as I can tell uh
there is a handy chart that's in the
book that shows you
the amount of money that is W uh if you
correctly guess the numbers so for
example we can see on this chart if you
uh predicted two numbers and you got one
of those right you're going to win times
one which basically just means you're
breaking even they're going to give you
back the money that you bet uh if you if
you made seven predictions or you know
you chose like seven lottery numbers if
that's an easier way to think of it and
a four of those came correct you're
going to get to double your your money
back if you made 10 predictions and you
got six of those 10 rights you're going
to get 20 uh times your your stake back
so it's it's purely a lottery you're
basically guessing numbers and and then
the GM who's playing the the house will
roll 1D 10020 times and that's how we
generate our numbers and if you
correctly predict a certain number of
those um of those 1D 100 rolls then you
are potentially going to get a payout um
if you made 10 predictions and got four
of them right you're going to get
nothing if you do 10 predictions you got
to get at least half of those right out
of the out of one to 100 um so
unsurprisingly the odds are always going
to be in The house's
favor so that is basically how Kino
works so we have our first option is
earn income super simple super easy um
it interacts with your character's
skills but it's not super immersive
second option take one of those three
games out of all or nothing they are
very immersive but they're also timec
consuming and they don't interact at all
with your character sheet it's entirely
based on what you as a human being as a
player choose to do the last option is
kind of a happy middle ground between
the two but it's definitely going to
take some work on your end as a GM and
that is just to use the victory point
system out of the game mastery guide or
out of GM core um build your own um game
using the rules for the victory point
system where your players can do skill
checks in a gaming environment with the
potential of earning victory points and
then set a a certain amount of payout at
the end of the games based on how many
victory points they earn uh I'm not
going to dive deeper than that at this
time um I may make a a true Deep dive
video about victory points in the future
but um that is a third option that's
kind of a happy middle ground between
all of these options so that's it for
today if you have any questions about uh
these gambling rules in Pathfinder
please let me know in the comments below
also this is the kind of thing that I
imagine GMS and games have been doing
for a while now so if you have your own
tips your own games the way that you've
used games lore or Casino lore in the
past to generate uh income or to
generate a a gaming feel in your session
let me know in the comments as well
share that with all of our viewers out
there and as always I want to take a
quick moment to say thank you to
everybody out there who supports me
whether that's by clicking the like
button subscribing to the channel
subscribing to the patreon buying a
super thanks I really appreciate
everything you folks do to support me
and with that thanks for watching take
care and happy gaming