[Music]
hello and welcome to sanctification in
Pathfinder second edition remastered by
how it's played sanctification is a new
system added to the game as part of the
remaster project and does not apply if
your group is using the Pathfinder
second edition Legacy rules simply put
the original release of second edition
used The Familiar alignment system found
in most D20 fantasy RPGs but alignment
was removed as part of the remaster and
sanctification takes its
place some deities but certainly not all
participate in the ongoing holy war
between celestials and fiends and use
their divine power to imbue their
followers with abilities that
potentially make them more deadly to
members of the other side of the
conflict but also possibly more
vulnerable this process is called
sanctification
it applies either the holy or Unholy
trait to the sponsored character and
only those who have a mechanical feature
that specifically calls for them to
become Sanctified may be Sanctified this
will most likely be through the deity
class feature that belongs to both the
champion and cleric classes members of
these classes must choose a deity that
they worship and selecting that deity
informs the player of their
sanctification options for example the
stats for iom say Divine sanctification
must choose holy meaning all characters
Sanctified by iom must be holy and have
the Holy trait and if we look at eroa it
says Divine sanctification must choose
Unholy meaning all characters Sanctified
by eroa will have the Unholy trait those
are two examples that have strict
sanctification requirements but but many
deities allow their devotees some
flexibility for example the block for
desna says Divine
sanctification can choose holy meaning
those characters who have a class
feature that grants sanctification and
follow desna get a choice they can
either choose to be Sanctified holy and
therefore have the Holy trait or they
can choose not to be Sanctified at all
but they cannot choose to be Sanctified
Unholy should they choose not to be
Sanctified at all then they will have
neither the holy nor Unholy traits and
abidar entry says Divine sanctification
can choose holy or Unholy so his clerics
can choose to gain the holy trait the
Unholy trait or can choose not to be
Sanctified and received neither and one
last example is Goa whose entry says
Divine sanctification none and never
sanctifies their clerics the key to
Remember When choosing sanctification is
if your deity's entry has the word can
in it then you have the option of
choosing either what is listed or you
can choose not to be Sanctified at all
and therefore not have either the holy
or Unholy trait but if your DD's entry
says must then you have to be Sanctified
according to the listing and cannot
choose to not be Sanctified and remember
that a character must have a feature
that grants sanctification in order to
be holy or Unholy for example a sorcerer
who worships ium and cast spells from
the Divine tradition is not Sanctified
and does not have the Holy trait at
least not by default this sorcerer could
gain sanctification by taking a feature
that mechanically provides
sanctification such as multiclassing
with cleric but once a character cleric
Champion or otherwise gains such a
mechanical feature they must choose a
deity to follow in each deity stat block
describes what sanctification options
are available to their
worshippers so what does it mean to be
Sanctified and gain the holy or Unholy
trait in and of themselves these traits
do very little but what matters is how
they interact with other mechanics and
effects First Holy and Unholy are
frequently used as prerequisites to gain
access to something
for example the Eternal blessing feat
can only be selected by a character who
has the holy trait second all Sanctified
actions you perform gain your
sanctification trait for example the
Divine Lance spell has the Sanctified
trait making it a Sanctified spell what
this means is that it is neither
inherently holy nor Unholy but if the
person casting it has the holy or Unholy
trait then the divine l Spell gains that
corresponding trait meaning it will
trigger weaknesses of that same type
only spells with the Sanctified trait
gain your holy or Unholy trait not all
spells or similar effects meaning when a
cleric of saren Ray who is Sanctified as
holy casts Divine Lance it gains the
holy trait and triggers any weaknesses
to Holy the target has but if that same
cleric casts Fireball that will not
become a holy Fireball and Trigger those
weaknesses because Fireball does not
have the holy or Sanctified traits and
the same is true when casting the heel
spell heel does not have the holy or
Sanctified traits therefore the damage
it deals to Undead does not trigger
weaknesses to Holy nor does it harm
living creatures that are weak to Holy
however there is a feat clerics can take
at first level called Divine castigation
that grants heal the holy trait and
allows it to damage anyone with the
Unholy trait this is Spirit damage and
it would apply to any creature with the
Unholy trait and if that creature is
also weak to Holy it would trigger that
weakness as
well let's look at a more specific
example Kirra is a cleric of sarra and
is Sanctified as holy therefore she has
the holy trck
she attacks a goblin warrior with Divine
Lance because Divine Lance has the
Sanctified trait it adopts her holy
trait making it a holy Divine Lance so
to speak if she hits the goblin with her
holy Divine Lance it will suffer 2 D4
Spirit damage just like most anything
else the goblin is not weak to Holy and
there is nothing else here that
interacts with the Holy trait so Kyra
being holy makes no difference in this
example her Divine Lance functions the
same as any other Divine casters when
attacking this
Goblin next let's consider what happens
when Kyra casts Divine Lance at a bar
guest we see here that bargus have the
Unholy trait and weakness five to Holy
therefore if Kyra hits it with her
Divine Lance she will trigger its
weakness and deal an extra five damage
for a total of 2 D4 + 5 Spirit
damage and now let's look at what
happens when Kyra casts Divine Lance at
a grave Knight we can see here that
grave Knights do have the Unholy trait
so what happens when Kyra hits it with
one of her holy Divine lances well
nothing special it simply deals its
normal 2 D4 Spirit damage why because
there is nothing in the Great Knight
stat block that interacts with holy
effects simply being Unholy isn't enough
the creature needs to have a weakness to
Holy which grave Knights do not have or
they need some other mechanic that
specifically mentions how it interacts
with holy effects but what if Kyra had
cast Holy Light at the grave Knight here
it specifically says that if the target
has the Unholy trait It suffers an
additional 5d6 Spirit damage and Grave
Knights do have the Unholy trait so in
this case they would suffer 5d6 fire
damage plus an additional 5d6 spirit
damage so to sum up Simply Having the
Holy or Unholy trait does not make you
weak to the opposite effects you must
specifically have a weakness to Holy or
Unholy likewise Having the Holy trait
does not make you automat atically
suffer additional damage from Unholy
sources all of an Unholy Champion
strikes have the Unholy trait but they
won't do any extra damage to Kyra
because she does not specifically have a
weakness to
Unholy the holy and Unholy traits also
modify how certain items can be used if
a creature who is weak to Holy or Unholy
attempts to use an item with that trait
they suffer an amount of damage equal to
their weakness for example there is
nothing that prevents a devil that has
weakness five to Holy from picking up
and using a defeated enemy's holy long
sword but if they do they will suffer
Five Points of damage every time they
attack with it they will also be in
feeble to per the text of the Holy Rune
while carrying it assuming they have the
Unholy trait in addition to being weak
to Holy and similar to using Sanctified
weapons we should also discuss who can
cast Sanctified spells and the short
answer is anyone who can cast spells of
that tradition can cast the spell you
can cast a spell that has the holy trait
even if you are not holy and even if you
are Unholy and vice versa a person who
is Sanctified as holy can cast spells
that have the Unholy trait but there is
one major problem if they do casting
such a spell might be an anema to their
religion behaviors that are anathema are
against your personal code or an
institution you are bound to like a
religion to deities these acts are
heresy and indirect violation of their
beliefs to gain some insight into what a
deity labels as anathema check out their
writeup for example in the Church of
abdar it is forbidden to engage in
banditry or piracy to steal or undermine
a law of abiding Court into eroa it is
anathema to deny your appetites destroy
Undead or to sacrifice your life
committing such acts have serious
consequences the exact punishments of
committing acts that are anathema to
your faith are largely up to the GM to
determine but some guidance is provided
in the deity class feature for clerics
and champions here it says if you
perform enough acts that are anema to
your deity you lose the magical
abilities that come from your connection
to your deity and these abilities can be
regained only if you repent by
conducting an atone ritual the book also
says casting spells with the Unholy
trait is almost always anathema to
deities who don't allow Unholy
sanctification and casting holy spells
is likewise anathema to those who don't
allow holy sanctification casting spells
that are anathema to the tenants or
goals of your faith could interfere with
your connection to your deity for
example casting a spell to create Undead
would be anatha to fasma the goddess of
death so can you cast Unholy spells if
you are Sanctified holy yes but you run
the risk of being punished by your deity
exactly when that happens into what
extent is LIF up to your GM to decide
but it'd probably be wise not to even
test those
Waters so what has changed with the
remaster well basically everything with
the elimination of the alignment system
everything in this video is New
Territory so instead of listing the
differences here as I usually do I'm
instead going to go over a few points to
remember about
conversions if you are running a
remaster Edition game and want to use
content from the Legacy Edition there
are a couple of things worth noting
first alignment damage is no longer
supported instead wherever in the Legacy
Edition you see effects that deal good
damage or evil damage you should instead
change that to Spirit damage also
resistances and weaknesses to alignment
damage should be updated if a legacy
monster has resistance or weakness to
good damage change that to Holy and if
they have a resistance or weakness to
evil damage change that to Unholy it
would probably be reasonable to also
give them the appropriate sanctification
trait as well so there you have it
sanctification and Pathfinder second
edition remastered if you have any
questions please leave them in the
comments below and as always I'd like to
take a moment to thank everyone who
supports me whether that be by clicking
the like button leaving a comment
subscribing to the channel subscribing
to the patreon or buying a super thanks
I greatly appreciate all you do to
support me in this Channel with that
thanks for watching take care and happy
Gam
[Music]