hello and welcome to how monks played in
this video we'll look at the rules and
mechanics that are pivotal to playing a
monk in Pathfinder second edition
remastered and just as a bit of
expectation setting here at the start I
should mention what this video is not
this video does not contain build advice
or an overview of all of the abilities
that are gained when leveling up as
several of them like proficiency
increases are not unique to monks the
Feats and abilities discussed will focus
on the lower levels since this video is
intended for newer players and note that
this video is not a review of the
perceived quality Effectiveness or value
of the class but what this video will
provide you with are all of the
foundational mechanics that make playing
a monk different from playing any other
class let's start by looking at a few of
the abilities and mechanics that are
shared among all monks first up is
unarmed attacks as martial artist a
monk's unarmed attack are more deadly
than normal unarmed attacks are made
with a part of the body instead of a
manufactured weapon this could be your
fist heel knee elbow or forehead and
they all count as unarmed strikes in
addition unarmed strikes could include
things like claws biting or swiping with
a tail some ancestries even offer ranged
unarmed attacks such as the Les's
ability to launch seed pods in general
all unarmed attacks are treated as using
a fist per the table on page 277 of
player Core 1 even if within the
narrative you describe the attack as a
kick or headbutt they deal one4 bling
damage belong to the brawling group and
have the agile finesse non-lethal and
unarmed traits of note here is the
non-lethal trait by default unarmed
attacks cannot kill a Target unless the
attacker wishes to make their attacks
lethal which imposes a negative to
circumstance penalty to attack rolls
special unarmed attacks such as those
provided by certain ancestries modify
these rules as listed in each entry for
example razor tooth goblins gain a bite
attack the attack bonus for this is
calculated the same as any other unarmed
attack but it deals 1d6 piercing damage
and only has the Finesse in unarmed
traits meaning this bite attack lacks
the agile and non-lethal traits that
normal unarmed attacks have and it's
important to note that since this bite
is still an unarmed attack any bonuses
or penalties that apply to unarmed
attacks apply to biting the same as they
would to punching so those are the
normal rules for unarmed attacks but
what makes monks special is their
powerful fist ability when monks make
unarmed attacks they do not suffer the
-2 penalty for making lethal attacks and
the Damage die for basic unarm armed
attacks increases from 1 D4 to
1d6 as a monk levels up their unarmed
attacks become increasingly more
powerful too at third level monks gain
the Mystic strikes ability that allows
their unarmed attacks to overcome
resistances to non-magical attacks at
fifth level the expert strength ability
grants critical specialization for
unarmed attacks in the brawling group
meaning when a monk makes an unarmed
strike and scores a critical hit the
target must succeed at a fortitude save
or be slowed one at seventh level monks
gain a weapon specialization that
increases the damage of their unarmed
strikes and this bonus is further
increased at 15th level at Ninth level
monks gain the metal strikes ability
that treats their unarmed attacks as if
they were made of cold iron or silver
meaning these attacks trigger weaknesses
to those Metals in certain creatures
like demons devils and Fay and monks
gain adamantine strikes that treats
their unarmed attacks as if they were
made of adamantine meaning they overcome
resistances such as the gargoyle's
resistance to all physical damage except
adamantine and it may be worth noting
that normal adamantine weapons reduce
the hardness of objects they strike by
half as long as the object's hardness is
not more than the weapon's hardness but
unarmed attacks do not have a hardness
so monks do not receive this bonus from
the Adam maintain strikes ability
however they can take the shattering
strike feet at 16th level to gain
this so that's the general information
you'll need to know about unarmed
strikes next let's look at the monks
trademark ability Flurry of Blows this
allows monks to make two unarmed strikes
at the cost of only one action the
multiple attack penalty applies to these
strikes normally meaning there is no
penalty for the first strike assuming
the monk has not already made an attack
this round but the multiple attack
penalty will apply for the second strike
with Flur of blows these strikes can
Target any enemies within range so they
can apply to two different creatures but
if the monk decides to use both strikes
on the same enemy and they both hit you
combine the damages of both strikes
together for the purposes of resistances
and weaknesses and also note that FL of
Blu has the flourish trait meaning it
can only be used once per turn let's
take a look at a few examples and our
first example San the monk is using
floral blows to punch a goblin twice
this costus his first action of the turn
the first strike is made with no
multiple attack penalty and the second
is made with a -4 multiple attack
penalty -4 instead of neg5 because fist
attacks have the agile trait if he
wanted to continue making unarmed
attacks with his second and third
actions this turn those attacks would be
made with a ne8 penalty now let's say
this Goblin San is fighting is a monk to
and has the razor tooth Heritage on its
turn the goblin uses Flurry of Blows
spins one action and attacks San twice
the first strike is an unarmed fist
attack and the second is a bite attack
the first strike is made with no
multiple attack penalty but the second
is made with a -5 penalty instead of -4
because their bite attack does not have
the agile trait so they would have been
better off leading with their bite in
our third example San is fighting two
ugal or faceless stalkers he could
decide to use Flor a blows to attack the
same ugal twice or each of them once
let's say he decides to divide his
attacks he would make a strike against
the First ugal with no penalty and then
strike the second ugal with a -4
multiple attack penalty we'll say both
are hits so next he rolls his damage for
each strike separately he deals six
points of damage to the first one and
eight points of damage to the second but
since ugal have resistance five to
blending damage this resistance is
applied to both strikes separately
meaning San deals only one point of
damage to the first enemy and three
points of damage to the second but if he
had decided to only attack one of them
and succeeded on both strikes then the
damage would have been combined for the
purposes of overcoming
resistances in that case you would add
the six damage from the first strike to
the eight damage of the second strike
for a total of 14 and then track the
five resistance to boning only once and
that Target would suffer a total of nine
points of damage instead of only three
and next let's take that same example
but instead of ugal that are resistant
to bling damage San is fighting a pair
of necr fidus who are weak to
bludgeoning damage if he chooses to
attack one of them with both of his
strikes the damage of both attacks will
be added together for a total of 14 and
then the necroid his weakness to
blending damage will be triggered once
for a total of 19 damage but if he
chooses to divide the attacks and strike
each of the enemies once the first will
suffer six damage plus five more for the
weakness totaling 11 damage and the
second will suffer eight damage plus
five more for the weakness for a total
of 13
damage one of the concerns often raised
about Flur of blows is it doesn't seem
any different from just making two
attacks since the multiple attack
penalty still applies but the true
benefit of fluid blows is that it only
takes one action which leaves one or two
actions each turn that can be applied to
other things like movement and Mobility
is another area where monks really shine
starting at third level monks enjoy an
increase to their speed score whenever
they're not wearing armor this starts as
a plus 10 bonus to speed and increases
by a additional 5 ft at 7th 11th 15th
and 19th level for a final bonus of plus
30 ft so a typical strategy for monks
especially at low levels might be to
spend their first action to move into
melee distance use Flor of blows to
attack twice and then their third action
to move away after third level the monk
likely has a higher speed score than
most enemies meaning those enemies will
have to spend two of their actions to
move into melee against the monk leaving
them with only one action left to strike
and if the enemy has a ranged weapon the
mon can use their extra speed to move
into cover that otherwise might be too
far to reach with one action yes if the
enemy has reactive strike or other
abilities that trigger on enemy movement
this would trigger it but remember
unlike some other popular D20 based RPGs
in Pathfinder not everyone has the
ability to perform reactive strikes or
what you might call Opportunity attacks
but if you want to feel extra safe you
can take the guarded movement feet at
fourth level that grants a plus4 bonus
to Armor class against reactions that
trigger on your Movement Like reactive
strikes so those are the abilities that
are Universal to all monks but unlike
some other classes monks do not have a
form of broad grouping of abilities to
choose from like how a cleric chooses
their Doctrine a druid chooses their
order or a rogue chooses their racket in
other games you might call these
subclasses but whatever you want to call
them monks do not have those instead all
monks have the previously mentioned
features and then each player can
customize their monk by choosing Feats
and a lot of these feet options are
going to fall into one of three
categories which are stances monastic
weapons and key spells first let's take
a look at stances monks can learn
several different combat stances Each of
which have their own benefits but they
all work the same way unless otherwise
stated it costs one action to enter a
stance and once you in that stance it
persists turn after turn until you are
either knocked out you violate any of
its prerequisites the encounter ends or
or you use the dismiss action which
costs one action you can also switch
between stances by spending an action
but you can only enter a new stance once
per round let's take a look at a couple
stances available at first level Dragon
stance and Mountain stance as long as a
monk is not wearing armor they may spend
one action to enter dragon stance while
in The Stance they can choose to make
unarmed attacks as normal or they can
make special dragon tail attacks that
deal 1 d10 damage and have the back
swing trait meaning when you miss with a
dragon tail attack you gain a plus one
circumstance bonus made with your next
dragon tail attack before the end of the
turn also while in The Stance you ignore
the first square of difficult terrain
for comparison let's also look at
Mountain stance it also costs one action
to enter The Stance and can only be used
while wearing armor and while touching
the ground while in this stance the only
strikes a monk can make are falling
Stone unarmed attacks which have the
forceful non-lethal and unarmed traits
the forceful trait means the more times
you use the attack in the same round the
more damage it does starting with the
second attack gaining a damage bonus
equal to the number of damag dice being
rolled and that bonus is doubled for the
the third attack and more note that you
do not need to hit with these attacks to
gain the benefits of the forceful trait
you only need to
attack also while in this stance monks
enjoy a plus4 item bonus to Armor class
and a plus two circumstance bonus
against being repositioned shoved or
tripped and this Armor class bonus does
stack with the armor class bonus
provided by explores clothing bands of
force and Mystic armor spell on the
downside while in this stance the Monk's
speed score is reduced by five and they
don't receive any dexterity bonus to
their Armor class meaning if the Monk's
dexterity modifier is already four or
higher this stance will not increase
their Armor class however the dexterity
cap can be increased by one with the
mountain stronghold feet available at
six level and further increased to two
with the mountain Quake feet at 14th
level let's illustrate how these stances
work with an example San is fighting an
enemy soldier and this is the first
round of combat so he's not already in a
stance he uses his first action to enter
dragon stance and then uses Floria blows
with his second action he makes a dragon
tail attack as the first strike with no
multiple attack penalty and what he does
with his second attack is going to
depend on if that first first attack
hits or not if that attack hits he might
want to make a normal unarmed attack
with the second strike since it will be
made at a ne4 penalty whereas another
dragon tail strike would be made at a
neg5 penalty because it lacks the agile
trait but if he misses with the first
dragon tail attack he definitely want to
make another dragon tail attack with the
second strike of Flor of blows since the
plus one gained from the back swing
trait would yield a final ne4 penalty
just like with normal unarmed attacks
with regard to his third action San has
some options including making another
attack at the maximum multiple attack
penalty moving away making a Recon
knowledge check and more but one thing
he absolutely cannot do with his third
action is activate Mountain stance in
preparation of the soldier attacking him
back stances are limited so that players
may only enter a new stance once per
round so since San used his first action
on this round to enter dragon stance he
can't spend his third action to enter
Mountain stance and increase his AC and
it may also be worth noting that you may
only enter a stance while in encounter
mode you couldn't for example enter The
Stance while in Exploration mode in
anticipation of an encounter you would
have to wait until after initiative is
rolled and on your first turn in that
combat encounter before you enter any
stances those are the basics of how
stances work but there is one more
stance worth mentioning here monastic
Archer stance allows a monk to use a bow
with Flurry of
Blows as with the other stances we've
looked at it takes one action to enter a
monastic Archer stance and while in The
Stance the only strikes a monk can make
are with bows they cannot make their
usual unarmed melee attacks or swing
their bow like a melee weapon but they
can fire their bow twice with Flurry of
Blows and use their bow for any monk
ability or feat that normally calls for
an unarmed attack unless it specifies a
specific strike this may only be done
when attacking within half of the first
range increment so what this means is
any ability that has the monk trait and
includes the text make an unarmed strike
can be delivered at range with a bow
while in this stance this includes
things like one- inch punch knockback
strike disrupt key and shattering strike
as well as key spells such as inner
upheaval and while we're on the topic of
weapons we should discuss the monastic
Weaponry feet this isn't a stance but is
an optional first level feat that
expands the types of weapons a monk can
use by default monks are only proficient
with simple weapons and unarmed attacks
the monastic Weaponry feat grants
trained proficiency with simple and
Marshall monk weapons and proficiency
with these weapons increases whenever
the Monk's unarmed attack proficiency
increases in addition any agile or
finesse weapons you have access to from
a familiarity feat also gain the monk
trait and you can use these weapons to
deliver monk abilities just like with
monastic Archer stance the only main
difference being you don't have to be in
a stance to benefit from the monastic
Weaponry feat you could for example
deliver a 1-in punch with a fighting fan
or perform a knockback strike with a bow
staff in addition to stances and
monastic Weaponry the third optional
path for monks is key spells key spells
is a first level monk Fe
that allows the monk to harness their
inner Life Force to produce magical
effects in the form of focus spells when
you take this feat you first need to
decide if your key spells will be divine
or occult and you gain trained
proficiency with those spell attacks and
spell DCS wisdom is used as the ability
modifier when calculating these you also
gain one Focus point that can be spent
and replenished as normal for Focus
points
and as part of this feat you get to
choose one first rank key spell such as
inner upheaval this spell costs one
action and one Focus point to cast the
spell and let you make one unarmed
attack or FL of blows with a plus one
status bonus to attack rolls and an
additional 1d6 to damage rolls that is
of a damage type of you're choosing
between force Spirit vitality and void
and just like with all Focus spells key
spells automatically heighten to half
your level rounded up this feat can be
taken multiple times to gain access to
multiple first rank key Spells at sixth
level monks can take the advanced key
spells feet that grants access to third
rank key spells master key Spells at
16th level grants access to eighth rank
key spells and Grandmaster key spells
grants access to ninth rank key spells
in addition
several Feats like Harmon self Grant
access to specific key spells and others
like clinging Shadows initiate Grant key
spells that provide new stances as
well and there are a few other Feats of
note but as mentioned before this video
is for newer players so we'll only be
focusing on the lower levels first
flurry of Maneuvers available at fourth
level allows you to substitute one or
both of the Flur of blow those attacks
with grapples repositions shoves or
trips but remember all of these
Maneuvers have the attack trait meaning
they receive and apply the multiple
attack penalty just like with normal
strikes so if you use the second strike
of Flur of blows for one of these
Maneuvers it will be rolled with a ne5
penalty as normal one staple of fantasy
martial arts is swatting arrows out of
the air this is accomplished with the
deflect projectile feet that allows a
mon to spend their reaction to gain a
plus4 bonus to armor class against a
physical ranged attack note that the
trigger here is when you are the target
of the attack meaning this reaction must
be declared before dice are rolled and
success or failure is announced monks
don't get reactive strikes like some
other Marshall classes but they can take
the stand still feet to gain a similar
reaction it works in much the same way
as reactive strike except it doesn't
trigger on manipulate actions or
arranged attacks and instead of
disrupting manipulate attacks like
casting a spell stand still disrupts
movement meaning if an enemy tries to
use the stri action to run away you can
spend your reaction to make a melee
strike and if that strike is a critical
hit the stride is disrupted and the
enemy remains standing adjacent to you
and another feat we'll mention is 1in
punch which allows you to gain
additional damage dice at the cost of
spending two or three actions for the
strike two actions adds one die and
three actions adds two and this number
of additional dice increases at 10th and
18th
level those are the general basics for
the mechanics at play with monks but we
should also discuss gear especially
since by default monks avoid wearing
armor and have limited access to weapons
one common question that comes up is how
does a monk keep Pace with other classes
when they have no armor and no weapons
to attach runes to and the simple answer
is that they do have ways to use runes
just like these other classes the first
piece of gear that most monks will want
is a set of Explorer clothing Explorer
clothing is technically not armor but
can be with armor runes that don't
specify an armor category for example a
monk can etch a suit of Explorer
clothing with a plus one armor potency
Rune a resilient Rune and a size
changing Rune making it plus one
resilient size changing Explorer's
clothing just like it was regular armor
but the monk wearing it is still
considered to be unarmored so they can
use stances and other abilities that
require you to be unarmed armored but
remember the one restriction that
explores clothing is not considered to
be any kind of armor for example it does
not belong to the light armor group and
therefore you cannot place any runes on
it that require a light armor or medium
or heavy armor for that matter for
example you cannot place a shadow Rune
on Explorer's clothing and the second
piece of gear worth mentioning is hand
wraps of Mighty blows these do for the
monks offense what explorer clothing
does for defense so as you might expect
hand wraps of Mighty blows work
basically the same way allowing you to
etch weapon fundamental and property
runes to them to enhance your unarmed
attacks this allows a monk's attack and
damage with unarmed attacks to progress
along with other weapon wielding
characters but there are two points to
keep in mind first these hand WS modify
all unarmed attacks not just punches for
fist attacks they also modify kicks bite
attacks tail swipes and any other attack
that has the unarmed trait and yes this
does include a lesi cactus spines and
their arranged SE pod attacks as well
for example an orc with the Tusk feet
and wearing plus one striking holy hand
wraps of Mighty blows receives a plus
one item bonus to attack rolls and extra
damage damage die and an additional 1 D4
Spirit damage or 2 D4 to Unholy targets
with all unarmed attacks including again
punches kicks and yes their Tusk attacks
and the second thing to keep in mind
with runes and hand wraps is you can
etch them with property runes that
normally are restricted to certain
damaged types other than bludgeoning but
they only function when making unarmed
attacks that deal that damage type
for example Keen runes require the
weapon they're attached to to deal
piercing or slashing damage but normal
unarmed attacks deal beding damage if
this was a hammer you wouldn't be able
to place a keen run on it but hand wraps
work differently you can etch a keen
Rune on them or any similar Rune but
they only provide their bonus when
dealing that kind of damage for example
when a monk enters tiger stance and
slashing damage with their unarmed
attacks so there you have it a look at
the foundational mechanics you'll want
to know before playing a month if you
have any questions please leave them in
the comments and I would like to take a
quick moment to thank everyone who
supports me whether if that's by
clicking the like button subscribing to
the channel subscribing to the patreon
or buying a super thanks I greatly
appreciate everything you do to support
me and with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]