Hello and welcome to Alchemy and
Pathfinder second edition remastered. In
this video, I'll be discussing
alchemical items such as bombs, poisons,
and elixirs, including mutagens in a
general sense, and anything specifically
associated with the alchemist class,
such as quick alchemy and versatile
vials, will be saved for another class
specific video all about alchemists.
Alchemy can be thought of as sort of the
science of the Pathfinder universe. Its
practice is based on principles such as
chemistry, biology, and botany, but with
a fantasy twist. As such, alchemical
items may resemble magic items and
function in much the same way. But it's
important to remember that alchemy is
not magic. An elixir of life may
function very closely to a healing
potion. And drinking liquid from a vial
that instantly heals our wounds might
feel like magic to our modern
sensibilities, but alchemical elixirs
are not magical. They do not register
dispels like detect magic, nor can their
effects be counteracted by dispel magic.
And another important note regarding
alchemical items is you do not need to
be a member of the alchemist class to
use or even create alchemical items.
Anyone can drink an alchemical elixir or
light an alchemical sunrod, not just
alchemists. The alchemical crafting feat
is required to create alchemical items.
This process works much the same way as
crafting anything else, except when you
critically fail a crafting check to
create an alchemical item, something bad
happens in addition to you losing your
spent resources as normal. The exact
result is up to the GM, but will usually
mean that the bomb you're creating
explodes in your face or you
accidentally expose yourself to
poisonous chemicals. For more
information about the crafting process,
check out my videos on crafting. You can
find links to those in the description.
Also, it's worth noting that there is no
alchemy skill. Instead, the crafting
skill is associated with alchemical
items in much the same way that arcana,
nature, religion, and occultism relate
to their magical traditions. meaning you
use the crafting skill to identify or
recall knowledge about alchemical items.
And last, most alchemical items include
the consumable trait, meaning they can
only be used once and then are lost.
This includes alchemical poisons and
oils as well. One dose means one use.
Let's take a closer look at each type of
alchemical item, starting with
alchemical bombs. Alchemical bombs are
basically Pathfinder grenades, but they
don't always deal damage, and they can
take many shapes and forms. Sometimes
they are ball-shaped grenades, but they
could also be glass flasks or even small
bags of goo. Regardless of shape, all
bombs are distinguished from other
alchemical items by the bomb trait and
have the same basic stats when used in
combat. Unless otherwise noted in their
descriptions, all alchemical bombs are
marshall ranged weapons. Bombs also have
a range increment of 20 feet or four
squares. And note that although bombs
are usually thrown at targets like a
grenade, they do not have the thrown
trait. Therefore, you do not add your
strength bonus to damage when throwing
an alchemical bomb. And an important
note to remember is since bombs have the
consumable trait, they cannot have runes
etched on them, nor can they benefit
from other effects that apply the
benefits of a rune. For example, a bomb
cannot benefit from the runic weapon
spell. Let's look at alchemist fire as
an example. This is a glass vial of
volatile liquids that you throw at a
target. The glass shatters on impact,
causing the liquid inside to burst into
fire. It has the alchemical trait,
meaning it's not magical. It has the
bomb trait, meaning it uses the
alchemical bomb stats found on page 281
of player core 1 as a foundation that's
further modified by the alchemist's fire
stat block. And most bombs that deal
damage have the splash trait. So, let's
take a moment to talk about that. If an
attack with a splash weapon succeeds or
critically succeeds, then all creatures
within 5 ft of the target, including
that target, take the listed splash
damage. And on a failure, the target of
the attack still suffers the splash
damage, but no one else does. Note that
splash damage is automatic. If the
attack roll is a hit, then everyone
within 5 ft of the target suffers the
damage. No extra attack rolls are
needed, nor does anyone get to make a
reflex save to lessen or avoid the
splash damage. And also be aware that
splash damage is never doubled due to a
critical success. So in the case of
alchemist fire, if you throw this at a
target and score a hit, the target
suffers 1d8 fire damage plus one
persistent fire damage and one fire
splash damage. Also, all creatures
standing in adjacent squares to the
target suffer one fire splash damage.
There is no saving throw to avoid this.
They just take the damage. On a critical
hit, the target suffers 2d8 fire damage
plus two persistent fire damage and one
fire splash damage because again, splash
damage is not multiplied due to a
critical success. And also, all
creatures adjacent to the target are
going to suffer one fire splash damage
as well. Note that splash damage is
added to the base damage when resolving
resistances and weaknesses. Meaning, if
the target of an alchemist fire attack
is weak to fire damage, that weakness
will only be triggered once, not once
for the base fire damage and then again
for the splash fire damage. If the
result of the attack roll is a failure,
then only the target suffers one fire
splash damage. And on a critical
failure, nothing happens. I usually
treat this as the bomb is just a dud and
doesn't go off. But in the right
situations, I might rule that it says
fire to something behind the target
instead. Using a bomb has the same
action requirements as anything else. So
it's one action to draw and one action
to throw. Not really any different than
drawing and throwing a dagger. Although
the quick bomber feet available to
Alchemists does reduce this to only one
action.
The second type of alchemical item is
alchemical poison. Poisons are basically
portable afflictions. So rather than
covering all of these rules here, I
instead recommend you view my video all
about afflictions, which I will include
a link to in the description. For this
discussion though, it is worth covering
the methods of exposure that are
available to alchemical poisons. Each
poison will have at least one of the
following traits: contact, ingested,
inhaled, or injury. Contact poisons
require direct contact with a creature's
skin in order to take effect. These
poisons are typically not used during
combat encounters as they cannot be
applied to weapons for delivery and
often have onset periods of at least 1
minute. Also, when it comes to
alchemical contact poisons, they only
affect the first creature to touch them.
So if you apply a dose in such a way
that more than one creature might make
contact with it, the poison is only
effective against the first. Ingested
poisons must be eaten to affect their
target. Typically, this means the poison
is placed in food or drink and may
require additional deception and stealth
checks to be successful. Next, we have
inhaled poisons. When these are applied,
they create a 10-ft cube lasting for 1
minute and affecting every creature that
enters the area. Raw specifically says
entering the area, but I believe
creatures who start their turn within
the space would be affected, too. If a
creature is aware of the poison gas,
they can spend one action per turn to
hold their breath and gain a plus two
circumstance bonus to their saving
throws. and a strong wind may remove
this area of effect prior to the end of
its one minute duration. Last are injury
poisons. These are applied to weapons or
ammunition that deal piercing or
slashing damage and then function on the
first strike made with said weapon. If
that attack hits, then the target will
need to make a saving throw. If it hit
but did not deal any damage, for
example, due to resistances, then the
poison does not take effect except in
the case of ammunition like arrows. If
the attack misses, then the poison
remains active on the weapon and you can
try again. And on a critical failure,
the poison does not affect the target
and is lost. So basically, once you
apply an injury poison to a piercing or
slashing weapon, the poison remains
active on it until you roll anything
other than a failure on an attack. Each
poison description will also detail how
many free hands and actions are required
to use the poison. For example,
Belladonna is an ingested poison that
requires one hand and one action to
place in someone's food or drink. But
black adder venom is an injury poison
that requires two actions and two hands
to apply the poison to a weapon.
Those are the basics of alchemical
poisons. Again, for a full explanation
of how they work, including what each
stage means and how they function, check
out my video on afflictions that's
linked in the description.
And the last type of alchemical item to
cover is the elixir. Elixirs are
essentially magic potions except again
they're not actually magical. They're
one use consumable items that you drink
and they apply their effect. That's
pretty straightforward, but there is one
special type of elixir worth discussing.
Mutagens. If regular alchemy is
considered to be the science of
Pathfinder, then mutagens are the realm
of mad scientists like Dr. Jackekal and
Mr. Hyde. Mutagens are alchemical
elixirs, so they are consumable items
you have to drink in order to gain their
effects. But they differ from regular
elixirs in that they always have both a
beneficial effect and a drawback. For
example, the juggernaut mutagen grants a
bonus to fortitude saves and temporary
hit points, but also applies a penalty
to will saves, perception checks, and
initiative roles. And all mutagens are
polymorph effects. The rules for
polymorph state that no creature may be
under the effects of more than one
polymorph effect at the same time. If
they're subject to a polymorph effect
and then targeted by a new polymorph
effect, the new polymorph effect
attempts to counteract the first. If it
succeeds, then the first polymorph
effect ends and the new one begins. What
this basically means is you can't drink
two mutagens and gain the effects of
both. And furthermore, you can't choose
to end the effects of the first one in
favor of the second one. Instead, the
second would need to make a counteract
check against the first one.
Essentially, the two mutagens are
fighting it out in your system to see
which one is going to win and be
effective. When making these counteract
checks, each mutagen has a counteract
level equal to half their item level
rounded up, a counteract DC equal to a
standard DC for its item level, and a
counteract modifier equal to a standard
DC for its item level minus 10. Now,
this may sound complicated, and
honestly, it is, but this situation only
occurs when you try drinking a second
mutagen before the first one wears off.
As long as you don't do that, then you
don't need to worry about counteracting
anything. The entire process and rules
for how this counteracting works is
beyond the scope of this video. But if
you do want more details about how
counteracting works, I'll leave links to
my full video on counteracting and my
video on polymorph spells in the
description. And note that although
these mutagens are not magical, any
attacks gained through drinking them are
considered to be magical. For example,
the claws gained from a bestial mutagen
are treated as being magical when
attacking enemies that are resistant to
non-magical attacks. But since they are
not really magical, they still don't
register to spells like detect magic.
So, there you have it, a quick look at
alchemy and alchemical items. If you
have any questions, please leave them in
the comments below. And as always, I'd
like to take a quick moment to say thank
you to everybody out there who supports
me. Whether that's by clicking the like
button, subscribing to the channel,
subscribing to the Patreon, buying a
super thanks. Everything you folks do to
support me is greatly appreciated. And
with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[Music]