hey everybody Dave here and today I want
to talk about a few of the things that
people migrating from 5e over to
Pathfinder second edition uh
specifically Pathfinder second edition
remastered may want to know when they
come to that table for the first time
I've noticed a a bit of a an influx of
uh people coming over to the game from
5e lately and in my own game I believe
every single one of my players also
plays in a different 5e game so
sometimes they come to the table and get
a little confused on what rules are and
how things work and for people coming
over from 5e uh I know a familiar
experience is you have a friend who's
running a Pathfinder game and they say
hey come over and play with us some
night and that 5V player says well you
know I really don't want to have to
learn a new system so their friend says
don't worry about it if you know how to
play 5 you know how to play Pathfinder
is the same thing and then that person
shows up at the Pathfinder game only to
realize that it's the same except for
this this this this this and so on so
that's what this video is going to try
to uh to tackle uh I am going to go over
a number of the um the tripping points
that uh I've seen at my table for 5e
players coming into Pathfinder and this
is a pretty long list so uh first things
is not going to be all inclusive of all
the changes I'm not going to go into
specific differences between classes
this is all going to be General and a
lot of rules have exceptions which I
won't be going into each and every
exception either but this should give
you a really good idea of the key things
that you might want to know when making
that that conversion from from dndd 5e
over to Pathfinder second edition
remastered and uh if you're new to
Pathfinder you're probably new to this
channel so I guess first of all just let
me say oh welcome on behalf of the
Pathfinder Community welcome to uh to
our our side of the tabletop RPG space
and welcome to this channel uh I create
uh rules instruction videos and one of
the reasons why I'm not going to go into
all the detail of the things I'm going
to be talking about today is because
odds are I probably have a more detailed
video that goes into these things and so
if you're not clear on something that I
I say or share in this video uh check
out the comment section I'll have a a
pinned to the top of it a list of other
videos that you can click on to get more
information so with that uh all set up
let's go ahead and dive in and the first
thing I think 5V players need to know
about Pathfinder second edition is the
trait system and you are going to want
to know your traits so in 5 I believe uh
for for for a gear for your weapons
there's a table and I think they're
called properties in DND D 5e same idea
in Pathfinder each weapon's going to
have h a set column on the big table
that shows their traits we call them
traits but the reason why I bring this
up is in Pathfinder this goes well
beyond just your gear traits are used in
every action every feat every spell
every saving throw you're going to roll
every
poison everything uses traits and these
traits are great because they save a lot
of uh print space on in the books
because if you know how a trait works
you don't have to repeat the text for
that for that piece in every single
thing it applies to but uh a lot of
these traits really kind of um really
kind of modify the way things work in
the game uh so if you're especially if
you're a spellcaster make sure you look
up what the traits for that spell
actually mean and do before you cast
that spell uh if you are going to cast a
spell and it has the incapacity trait
make sure you look up incapacitate and
know how that's going to uh uh alter or
change the expected effects of that
spell and U the places you can go to to
look up these TR traits very little bit
uh officially you can go into the
indexes of the books and look up those
traits to find the information if you're
playing at a table that has uh you know
any kind of digital setup use your phone
use an iPad whatever uh you can go to
the archive of nethys which is the
official Pathfinder uh online rules
repository and search for the traits
there uh another place you can go to is
PFE easy PFE easy tools is a is a
similar um web-based uh you know index
of all the different rules and whatnot
and that's another place you can go to
to to quickly search for these
traits um another thing I want to talk
about is going to be how success and
failure Works in Pathfinder second
edition so in Pathfinder there are four
degrees of success which are going to be
very familiar to D and players you know
your critical success your regular
success your regular failure and your
critical failure uh but what may be
different is those four degrees of
success apply to pretty much
everything uh pretty much every skill
you you use is going to have these four
degrees of success so yes you can
critically succeed on your skills and
critically fail at your skills as well
anytime you roll a saving throw there
are going to be those same four degrees
of success so you can critically succeed
and critically and critically fail on
your saving throws
and uh one of the main reasons why you
should understand that is because the
way you determine if your action is a
critical success or a critical failure
is a little bit different and Pathfinder
than it is in dndd 5e uh so you may be
accustomed to every time you roll a
natural 20 on the die critical hit
critical success every time you roll
natural one critical failure uh uh
critical Miss however you want to put
that
but in um in Pathfinder there is one
more very important way that you can
score a critical success or a critical
failure and that is by hitting a DC that
is 10 higher or 10 lower than the
regular DC so for example if you're
trying to hit a DC 15 you roll a natural
19 but your modified total is a 25
that's 10 more than the target DC so
that's a critical hit or a critical
success if you're doing a Skiller and
whatnot and the same is true for
failures if you if you're if you don't
roll a natural one maybe roll a natural
two or natural three and your final
total is 10 below what the target number
is you get a critical failure so this is
this is great not just in the sense of
it gives you more ways to critically
succeed and critical fail but it also
makes every plus one uh or minus one on
any role much more significant because
you're not just increasing your odds of
success you're increasing your odds of
critical succeeding and you're
decreasing your odds of having a
critical failure so um that makes every
little bonus you can get a little more
important and opponent also something to
be aware of here is that just because
you roll a natural 20one does not
guarantee a critical success or a
critical hit and vice versa just because
you're rooll a natural one does not
necessarily mean a a critical
failure what happens when you roll a
natural 20 is you you add your bonus to
it and you compare that bonus that final
total to the target number and then you
increase it by one degree of success so
say you're trying to hit a target number
of 25 you're roll a natural 20 and
you've got a plus n to your to as a
bonus that you're applying to this 20 +
9 is 29 so 29 versus a target number of
25 that would be a normal success
normally but because you roll a natural
20 you increase it one step to a to a
critical success but if the target
number was say 30 and you roll a natural
20 and you add your plus n bonus to a 29
that would normally be a failure but
because you wrote a natural 20 it
increases at one step from failure to a
regular success not a critical success
so this does add a little more
complexity to um to I guess the math of
your critical successes and critical
failures to be completely transparent
and honest as long as you're in the
ballpark for what you're attempting to
do if you're fighting similarly Lev
uh enemies this is not going to be an
issue a natural 20 should typically be
at least a regular success and not a
failure for whatever you're doing so
it's it's very infrequent that this
comes up but it can possibly come up
especially if you are in a situation
where you're engaging with people who
are enemies that are way overleveled or
way underleveled um or if you're
attempting to use a skill that you have
training in or minimal training in to do
something very difficult this could come
up as well but just know um by the rules
is written a 20 is not always a critical
success and a one is not always a
critical
failure uh another thing to talk about
is how we calculate critical
damage so when you when you do roll that
critical success a critical
hit the way you calculate your damage in
Pathfinder is you roll your damage and
you multiply that final damage by
two and right now I'm sure there are 5
players out there saying what are you
talking about Dave that's that's no
different than than d and d d andd you
get your double damage on a critical hit
but it is a little different because in
Pathfinder what you do is you just
pretend you didn't roll a critical
success just pretend you didn't roll a
critical success roll it like it was a
regular success and then double it uh so
what that means is your those static
bonuses your strength bonus that gets
double too you're if you're a rogue and
you're sneak attacking somebody that
sneak attack damage gets double
to if you just pretend you didn't roll a
critical success you roll the damage add
everything together uh sneake attack
damage Precision damage uh if you have a
flaming sword the the the Flaming one6
extra flaming damage you add that your
static bonuses everything you add
together and then you multiply it by two
as opposed to the way I believe 5e Works
where you don't get to double that uh
strength bonus that static damage you
don't get to double some other things
and Pathfinder like I said pretend you
did not roll a critical success roll it
as normal and multiply it by two now at
the beginning of this video I said that
I wasn't going to go into every
exception but this is an area that I
will go into uh a little bit of an
exception and that exception is if
there's any effector modifier that
specifically only occurs on a critical
hit if you're if you're if you are are
casting a spell it it might give you
special text for what happens on a
critical success or a critical hit and
you're going to follow that rule as
opposed to the more general rule of you
just rule it like normal and multiply by
two uh also there are certain weapon
traits uh like I mentioned before know
your
traits there are two traits to know and
those are deadly and fatal the deadly
and fatal traits that belong to weapons
modify how they function when they
deliver Critical Hits so if you're using
a weapon that has one of those two
traits you're going to want to make sure
that you read those traits and
understand how they modify this the good
news is is going to in both those cases
is going to increase the damage but if
you don't have a weapon that has the one
of these traits like deadly or fatal uh
the general rule thumb is going to work
in most cases pretend you did not roll a
critical hit just roll it normal add
everything together multiply it by
two so um while we're still talking
about uh our our checks and our our four
degrees of success and whatnot we should
probably talk a little bit about DCS or
difficulty classes one of the things
that often comes up in my games from 5
players coming over to the table is I
might ask them for a a specific DC and I
might ask a player what is your
perception DC and that player looks all
over their sheet and they say I I I I
don't see perception DC listed
anywhere whenever uh a GM asks you what
a a DC is find the
corresponding uh skill or saving throw
or whatever and just add 10 so if you
have a plus eight bonus to perception
and your GMS you what's your perception
DC you just add 10 to it a plus eight
bonus becomes a perception DC of 18 if
you have a plus 12 bonus to stealth your
stealth DC is 22 if you have a plus six
um reflex saving throw bonus then your
reflex DC is going to be 16 anytime your
GM asks you what a DC is find the
corresponding ability and just add 10 to
it it's that easy also talking about uh
our DCS and our skills uh you might be
interested to know that there are no
opposed roles in Pathfinder with one
possible little asteris which I'll talk
about a little bit later so what this
means is you might be accustomed to if
you're a rogue and you're you're you're
trying to sneak past a guard you would
roll your your stealth skill the the DM
would roll the perception check for that
uh for that guard and then whoever has
the highest
wins that's not the way it works in
Pathfinder and Pathfinder whoever is
performing the action roles the dice and
you compare it to the static DC of of
the other party so if you're a player
you're a rogue you're trying to sneak
past a guard you would roll 1 D20 add
your stealth score that's your that's
what you're you're rolling for you're
sneaking past this guard that is
compared to that
guard's perception DC kind of like
passive perception although we don't use
that term in this game and it's probably
best that you not even think of it that
way but whatever their perception bonus
is you add 10 to it that's the Target
number that the Rogue needs to beat in
order to sneak past
them on that on that uh guard's turn if
they want to spend one of their actions
to actively search the area for any
Intruders then they would roll 1 D20 and
add their perception bonus because
they're the active uh character in that
point in time and that would be compared
to the stealth DC of the sneaking player
they would not roll their Ste stealth
score again nor would they use the total
of the stealth score that they rolled
the previous round is going to be our
are DCs are what um all the active roles
are compared to no opposed
roles another thing to uh consider is
going to be how saving throws work uh
well first of all saving throws are this
is old school goes back to like third
and maybe even fourth edition D and D
this only three saving throws uh reflex
fortitude and will as opposed to being
one for all six of the different ability
scores that's not going to be too hard
for you to wrap your heads around I
imagine but you're going to see text
that says roll a quote basic saving
through uh and this is most common in
spells and this is like traits this is
an area where they're using a little bit
of a shorthand to prevent having to
retype the exact same information a 100
times for a 100 different
spells but what you need to know when
you see uh a basic saving throw is all
that means is you roll your saving throw
and if you get a critical success you
suffer no damage if you roll a regular
success you suffer half damage if you
roll a regular failure you suffer the
full damage and on a critical failure
you suffer double damage
so you're only going to see the words
basic saving throw applied to effects
that deal damage and that's all it means
is it will say roll a basic if you look
at a fireball it's going to tell you to
roll a basic reflex saving throw versus
an amount of damage and they're not
going to spin page space telling you
that on a critical success you suffer no
damage on a regular success you suffer
half damage Dage on a regular failure
you suffer normal damage and on a
critical failure you suffer double
damage they're just going to make that
stat block real small and concise know
that when you see that word basic that's
what it means also don't assume that a
damaging effect follows those rules if
it says to make a a reflex save and does
not say basic then you do not apply that
staggered process you would just apply
whatever the effect listed the U
description of that spell or other
ability would
be all right so now let's move on to the
action economy uh this is one of the
major features of Pathfinder second
edition uh I think most people um view
this more favorably than in 5e but
basically you are given three actions on
your turn and one reaction that you can
spend during someone else's turn
including during an enemy's turn but but
your three actions during your turn can
be used for basically
anything uh you so that means if you
want to attack somebody that's going to
be one of your actions if you want to
move at your speed score that's going to
be another action uh if you want to take
any other actions then there's likely
going to be a number of Errors at the
top of that actions description and
those errors tell you how many actions
you have to spend to do the thing so for
example most spells are going to have
two little arrows at the top which means
it costs two actions to cast that spell
and so this gives you a lot of
flexibility in how you can you can
operate on every
turn um but there are some particular
things I want to make sure I cover here
uh first is multiple
attacks so yes you got three XS a turn
if you start your turn standing adjacent
to your enemy you can spend all three of
your actions to make three attacks but
there is was known as the multiple
attack penalty which just uh means every
attack after the first is going to
suffer a penalty so your first attack
every turn whether it's your first
action of that turn or your last can be
made with no penalty at all your second
attack in a turn is going to suffer a
ne5 multiple attack penalty and your
third and possibly fourth and and future
attacks at turn will all be made at at
-10 so yes you can attack three times
per turn just make sure that that second
attack you're suffering a neg five and
the third attack you're suffering a -10
uh the key exception to this is again
know your traits some weapons uh have
the agile trait so these are typically
light weapons like a dagger and the
agile trait reduces that multiple attack
penalty from the second attack being5 to
only being4 and your third attack in all
future attacks from being -10 to
being8 generally speaking uh it's not a
great idea statistically speaking to
attack three times that -10 or even
negative 8 penalty is pretty harsh so
you might want to think about other
things to do with that third
action uh the most frequent things would
be raising your Shield important thing
to know and under second addition just
having a shield strapped to your arm
does not give you a bonus to your armor
class you must spin an action to raise
that shield in order to receive that
bonus so if you attack twice you don't
want to suffer a negative 10 to that
third attack I'm going to spend that
third action to raise my shield you can
also use that third action to uh perform
recall knowledge see what you know about
this enemy do you know any of its
weaknesses that you might be able to
exploit that actually might be something
that you do with your first action so
that you might be able to exploit that
weakness with your second action which
would be your attack another thing you
might want to do with that third action
is to move away from your enemy so we
should talk a little bit about how
attacks of opportunity or what I believe
in fifth Ed is called opportunity
attacks in Pathfinder second edition
remastered these are now called reactive
strikes um but it's basically the idea
if your enemy moves away from you you
get a sucker punch him you get a free
attack on him so the first thing to know
about opportunity attacks or what we
call reactive strikes is that not
everybody has them in fact they are
fairly rare especially in the early
levels uh Fighters get them by default
all fighters will have them uh other
Marshall classes can typically choose
them with one of their feet as they
level up and some monsters that um that
you might expect to have that kind of
Marshall prowess have them but not
everybody has them and this is a
wonderful thing because what this does
is it really opens up that entire map
for you to use in a fight uh my
experience with uh 5e in earlier games
like
3E has been that you get into melee
combat and people get
rooted they just stand still and and
just blow leging each other until
somebody dies because nobody wants to
move away and risk triggering that
opportunity teack or reactive
strike but in Pathfinder they're fairly
rare so that means you shouldn't be
afraid to move away from most enemies if
you're fighting somebody who seems like
they are a fighter by class you can
pretty much expect they're going to have
opportunity attacks for reactive strikes
everybody else you might want to test it
out try a gamble whatever but this
really opens up the entire map for you
to move around and not feel rooted in
place also be aware that in 5e I believe
uh opportunity attacks are triggered
when you move away from your opponent um
so in 5V you can circle around your
opponent as long as you remain within
their threatened area the reach of their
weapon that's not the way it works in
Pathfinder um by raw if you leave a
square that is threatened by an opponent
and that opponent has reactive strike
that can trigger it also be aware that
other classes have other things that can
trigger like an opportunity attack when
you move away from them uh that function
a little differently uh I believe a
barbarians have an ability that let them
follow you so when you try to move away
from them that triggers their reaction
that they can have a free stride that
they just stay Pace with you so you
can't escape them uh and monks have an
ability called Stand still that when you
try to leave your space and get away
from them they get a free attack to try
to trip you and knock you down uh so
just be aware that there other there are
other reactions that can't Trigg but
generally speaking what you need to know
not everybody can do opportunity
attacks uh another thing to know uh
about movement and this is a little bit
of a point of contion that a lot of my 5
players don't like but I think um they
warm up too once they kind of understand
how this action economy works and that
is in Pathfinder you cannot split your
movement so you may be used to if you
can move 30 feet in a turn you can move
15 feet attack somebody move 15 more
feet in Pathfinder it takes one action
for you to stride up to your speed and
then would be a second action to attack
and then if you wanted to uh move again
you would have to spend your third
attack even if you didn't use all of
your speed on your first
attack and um a lot of 5V players don't
don't like this uh generally speaking um
I think it's a bit of a wash because in
Pathfinder we have three actions that we
can spin on
anything and so in D and D you're used
to moving 15 ft attacking and moving 15
more feet in D and D you can still do or
in I'm sorry in Pathfinder you can still
do that you can still move attack and
move in your turn it's just you spend
your first action to move your second
action to attack and your third action
to move again uh and I understand that
bonus actions and some other things may
modify how that works and that's same in
in in Pathfinder uh we don't have bonus
actions but we do have other Feats and
things that might modify this but long
story short what you need to know you
cannot split your actions so there is
one very big exception to this in the GM
core rulebook it does empower the game
master to make sort of Common Sense uh
adaptations to this so say you're
standing 5 feet away from um from a wall
you want to
climb by raw you spend your first action
to move 5et your second action to climb
that wall and then your third action
either to keep climbing or do something
at the top or whatever the GM uh core
rule book does say that game Masters
don't get too silly with this if you
want to you can include the five feet of
that movement in your
climbing uh and not make it cause two
actions and not not make someone with a
speed score of 35 feet have to spin an
action to only step five feet so um but
generally speaking you cannot split your
movement GMS know that you are empowered
to play with that however makes sense in
your
games uh let's see what next is on the
list oh I talked a little bit um earlier
about how spells typically cost two
actions but I do want to talk about some
spells that cost uh either three actions
or one action typically anytime you
summon a creature you're summon animal
spells summon Dragon summon plant all
your summon abilities those are going to
cost three actions uh and typically be
your entire turn to summon that extra
creature onto the field other spells
most notably the heal spell you can cast
it with only one action and when you do
it that way you have a range of touch
with your healing spell so you can
either heal yourself or someone adjacent
to you for only one action for two
actions it becomes a ranged healing
spell and heals a little more and if you
cast that spell with three actions it
becomes an emanation and you heal
everybody around you in that
emanation um and that's all for one
spell slot uh this doesn't alter how
your spell slots are spent it only
Alters the number of actions you have to
use to cast the spell and the effects
the more actions you spend the more
benefits you get um but that only
applies to spells like heal that
specifically call that
out talking about spellcasting um this
is an area another area that um 5
players often uh find a little
confusing Pathfinder second edition uses
old school vanan spellcasting rules for
their prepared spellcasters all our
spell spellcasters fall into the
category of either being prepared
spellcast
or spontaneous
spellcasters so this mostly is going to
apply or entirely apply to our um our
prepared spellcasters so typically we're
talking about our Wizards and our
clerics and a few others but those are
the the two major
ones as a prepared spellcaster in the
morning as part of your daily
preparations you pick every spell slot
and you assign a specific spell to that
slot so when you prepare in the
beginning of the day you you set in
stone I have these spells and for this
specific spell slot I can only cast this
spell at this level and so on and so on
and so on and so you don't have as much
flexibility whereas like in 5e you
prepare a number of spells of from your
spell book but you have flexibility in
casting those spells throughout your day
that's not the way it works in
Pathfinder if you're a prepared
spellcaster at the beginning of the day
you more or less edgeing Stone how
you're going to spend each spell slot
and what the coresponding spell will be
there are uh exceptions to that uh there
are ways Wizards can can swap a spell or
or modify how that works I'm not getting
into all those exceptions the key thing
to know prepare spellcasters at the
beginning of the day you prepare your
spells and you're locked in to those
specific spells
uh so that means um if you don't prepare
to cast uh a to cast fly multiple times
you can't cast it multiple times you're
you're locked
in a lot of people coming over from 5 do
not like this they want the freedom they
had in 5 and the great news is is there
is an archetype called flexible
preparation you can find it in the book
secrets of magic you can also find it on
archives of nth this or easy tools or
any of those other online uh
platforms and I think this is an
optional archetype so you'll have to get
permission from your GMS to use it but
if you are a prepared spellcaster and
you take the flexible preparation
archetype it more or less makes those
classes function exactly the way you're
used to them functioning in fifth
edition uh the downside is you have one
fewer spell per level you cast per day
but the benefit is you have a whole lot
more uh um uh freedom of choice and how
you spend your spell slots and keeping
on with our discussion of spells uh
let's talk about concentration spells in
5e you are used to only being able to
cast one concentration spell at a time
uh and you may go through the Pathfinder
rle book The Player's core book look
through the Spells and you notice like I
told you remember those tag those traits
those tags at the top of these things
and you'll see different spells that
have the concentrate trait or tag
assigned to them and your natural
assumption is that means I can only if I
have multiple spells that have the
concentrate trait I can only keep one of
these running at a time that is not what
that means in
Pathfinder in fact for for uh the moment
Let's ignore the concentrate trait all
together those spells that you're used
to where you can keep them persisting
turn after turn after turn as long as
you're able to concentrate on them in
Pathfinder we call those sustain spells
so if you see a spell that has a
duration listed as
sustain what that means is every turn
after the first you have to spend one
action to sustain that spell you spend
an action and it extends the duration of
that spell for one round so on your next
turn if you want to keep that spells
effect going you have to spend one
action to sustain it again and so on and
so on and so on until you either decide
not to sustain it anymore or until
you're noted unconscious or whatever and
can't act to sustain
it the key thing to know here is that
there is no limit to that no limit in
sense of of you can only concentrate on
one spell at a time you have three
actions per turn if you wanted to you
could sustain three sustained Spells at
a time uh it would be difficult to get
three sustained spells
cast um but mathematically it's possible
that you could have three sustained
spells active and spin your three
actions to sustain them every turn to
keep all three of them going you
wouldn't be able to do anything else
that turn
so when you're used to having that
limitation of one concentration spell
going just know that in Pathfinder we
call those sustain spells and you'll
look for the duration of sustain and
just know one action to keep those going
turn after
turn so what does that mean when we see
the concentrate trait or tag applied to
these if we don't have to concentrate to
keep them going what does that
concentrate tag or trait mean
in and of itself that that trait doesn't
mean
anything what that is there is for other
effects to interact with the ability so
for example if you're a barbarian and
you're raging you cannot use any action
that has the concentrate trait because
you're so fuel of rage and anger you
can't concentrate so if you were a a
barbarian who could cast spells you
cannot cast any spell with the
concentrate trait while you are raging
that's one
example uh so just like I said I'm not
going to go into all the specifics in
this video just know that when you see
that concentrate tradeit it does not
mean that you can only keep one of the
Spells active at that time it just means
there's other abilities that might
impose limitations on how they can
function with concentrate abilities if
you want to know the rules for keeping
spells active persistently from turn
after turn that's sustain is what you're
going to look
for uh another thing to talk about is
going to be
initiative uh you are probably
accustomed to initiative bonuses being
based on dexterity and Pathfinder um
well first of on Pathfinder you can use
pretty much any skill for your
initiative it comes down to what you
were doing at the time the GM calls for
initiative so if you were um keeping an
eyee out on a tree line your Druid
you're using the nature skill you might
notice uh a fluck of birds come out of
the bushes before goblins jump out to
attack you if you were scanning that the
area you might be able to convince your
GM to let you use your nature skill as
your initiative score because in
Pathfinder it's not based on on
dexterity it's not based on how fast you
can draw your weapon is based on
perception it's based on how soon you
can can realize you're in
danger and so rule of thumb if there's
something you were doing at the time
initiative is called you might be able
to use that skill um as your initiative
score another example is you're a rogue
you're going to initiate con combat by
jumping on a chandelier doing a back
flip off of it well you know what if
that's what you're doing to initiate
combat AGM can I roll my acrobatic skill
as my initiative role uh if they're a
cool GM they'll probably say Yes um also
uh there are times in Social encounters
where you can use social skills to uh
initiate combat if you are in a social
situation and you decide you're just
going to throw a punch out of nowhere
and punch somebody you might use your
deception skill as your initiative
because they're not going to see that
punch coming so long story short and um
and Pathfinder any skill can be used as
your initiative role provided that you
were basically doing that thing at the
time initiative was called for and your
GM agrees uh that that's
allowable uh your default initiative is
going to be your perception score w20
plus your perception bonus is the
default usual initiative role because
again it's not based on how fast you can
pull your sword out it's based on how
quickly you can realize your in
danger uh something to know about action
economy that is related to initiative is
in Pathfinder there are two ways you can
modify your place in the initiative
order and that's through the delay
through delaying and through readying um
in D and D5 you're used to being able to
ready an action that's nothing new
except that in Pathfinder it takes two
actions to ready so on your turn you'll
say I'm going to spend these two actions
and I'm going to ready this action to
perform later during somebody else's
turn but the key difference about
initiative and Pathfinder is
delay uh you're never going to be
penalize for Rolling too well on
initiative you might win initiative but
say you know know what I'd rather have
my tanks get out in front of me before I
act but they rolled lower in the
initiative and Pathfinder you can
basically voluntarily lower your
initiative score as low as you like so
you can drop down to an initiative score
below your your allies let them go first
and then take your turn so this is
somewhat similar to what you're used to
in 5 where you might be first in the
initiative order and use your your ready
action to say I'm going to wait until my
more tanky allies move first and then as
my readed action I'm going to follow
after them or do something like that the
key difference here is in 5e a readed
action is One Singular action you you
prepare to do that one action uh later
in initiative as a result of something
else whereas in Pathfinder when you
delay you you do change your place in
the initial order and when that comes
around you get all three of your actions
you get to take your full term then and
your place in the initiative order
remains in that place going forward so
the next thing I want to talk about is
uh a thing called secret checks that
exist in Pathfinder second edition so as
the name applies a secret check is a
skill or something else that is rolled
on the players behalf by the GM in
secret behind behind their screen and uh
so the GM rolls it for the players and
does not necessarily tell them uh it
certainly does not tell them the
numerical result it may not even tell
them if they succeeded or failed so this
is for those situations where a
character within the narrative would not
have that knowledge a typical example is
any kind of a stealth check or a
perception check those are rolled in
Secret by the
GM so um if you're a person and you're
exploring a dungeon and you come to a
new room and you say I'm going to before
I step in this room I want to check it
out I'm going to roll perception to look
around the room and see if I spot any
danger uh if that's not a secret roll if
you roll a 20 on the dying AER bonus and
the GM tells you well you don't spot any
danger you as a player know for certain
there is no danger Butz I rolled a
natural 20 and I didn't spot anything
and by the same virtue if you roll a
natural one and the GM says well you
don't findun anything well you go well I
didn't see anything but you know hey Tim
you know why don't you check out the
room too and see if you get a better
role in reality in reality when we're
doing perception checks boring something
you know that would apply a penalty to
that check like concealment or flash of
light that blinds us or something like
that we don't know if we succeeded or
failed on these checks we don't know in
reality Did We R A one or a 20 or a 10
or whatever all we know is do we see
something or do we not so that's where
the secret checks come in the GM rolls
it in secret adds your perception bonus
to the role and just tells you if you
saw something or if you didn't see
something but you as a player you don't
know how well you rolled on that die you
don't know if you critically succeeded
or critically failed you just know I see
something or I do not see something and
then you have to act on that information
alone secret tcks also come up in
knowledge checks if you're wanting to do
a knowledge check uh on you find an
enemy monster you want to do a knowledge
check do I know what kind of monster
this is do I want know what its
weaknesses are what have you GM rolls
that in secret you don't know if if you
don't know how well or how poorly you
did in most cases unless the GM wants to
tell you that um and the main reason for
this is because if you critically fail
this check then the gam is going to give
you false information if you critically
fail a knowledge check then you remember
things incorrectly or you mistake one
monster for another if you roll a
natural on the table then as a player
you know the information you're getting
is
bogus um so just be aware that secret
checks exist and and uh Pathfinder uh
and these will be called out any ability
that has again these traits know your
traits as the secret trait means the GM
rolls it for you on your behalf in
secret uh sense motive uh there's new
sense motive skill in Pathfinder uh
Second Edition and there's no
investigation skill either both sense
motive and investigation are rolled into
perception so if you would like to
investigate an area uh or do what you
are accustomed to being investigate then
that's just going to be a perception
check if you want to perform sense
motive as you are accustomed to in uh
Dungeons and Dragons fifth edition
that's just going to be a straight
perception check in Pathfinder second
edition another thing that we should
talk about is
resting so uh the concept of short and
long rest doesn't exactly exist in
Pathfinder the way you're accustomed to
them
existing and the big Point here is you
do not get all of your hit points back
on a long rest so I believe in D andd
fth Edition long rest you rest for eight
hours you heal back to full Pathfinder
second edition is not that forgiving
which uh I think to most Pathfinder
player sensibilities that's a good thing
um because to a lot of people frankly
spending your day getting bruised and
beaten and possibly cut by a weapon or
set on fire by a fireball or a dragon's
breath to have all that damage just
completely go away after uh a good night
of sleep um can rub a little bit against
immersion for some people in the
Pathfinder world but uh long story short
what you need to know is you don't
instantly heal everything back after a
long rest a ni rest instead you're going
to heal a number of hit points that are
equal to your Constitution modifier
times your level with a minimum
Constitution modifier of one so if you
have a constitution modifier of two and
your third level a nice rest is going to
heal six hit points if you want to heal
anything beyond that you're going to
need to uh either have healing spells
cast on you use Certain Magical items or
do what sort of replaces the hit nice
healing on a short rest which is the
medicine skill so instead of having a
short rest where you roll your hit dice
you expend your hit dice to heal a
little bit uh you can have someone who's
trained in the medicine skill use an
ability called treat wounds to try to
bandage you up and heal you to a certain
degree uh also something to know about
is going to be flanking in um in uh
Pathfinder second edition flanking is
not an optional rule it is baked into
the game uh flanking always occurs when
you and an ally are on opposite sides or
opposite corners of your enemy uh and
this can be pushed back a little bit if
you have a reach weapon um so if
especially if you're a rogue always be
looking for flanking because uh flanking
is going to impose the offguard uh
condition on your enemies and that's
what triggers a lot of what you might
think of as flanking
bonuses um another things to to be aware
of in Pathfinder second edition is the
system of advantage and disadvantage
doesn't entirely exist it kind of exists
just is not as
frequent so you're used to things being
uh simplified to where if you have
Advantage you roll two dice you take the
higher if you have disadvantage you take
roll two dice you take the lower instead
in Pathfinder second edition we have
static bonuses and penalties that meet
all of those uh times when you would
normally roll advantage or disadvantage
uh if the GM believes that there are
certain circumstances in which you would
have Advantage instead of you rolling
twice your GM would likely tell you well
I'm going to give you a plus two
circumstance bonus to this role now the
concept of rolling twice and taking the
higher or taking the lower does exist in
Pathfinder second edition these are
called Fortune effects uh and I'm not
going to go too deep into this because
it's relatively rare that they come up
if you're playing a halfling you might
be able to get halfling luck that would
allow you to do something similar to
what you think of as as advantage and
disadvantage just long story short just
understand as you understand advantage
and disadvantage in dungeons Dragon
fifth edition does not exist in
Pathfinder second edition instead there
are static modifiers that or and
penalties that are applied to things and
if you believe believe that you should
have advantage on an action because of
your character's backstory your history
the weather lighting conditions whatever
it is your GM is probably going to still
give you a a bonus to those moments it's
just not going to be Advantage it's just
going to be like hey add two to your
role I'm going to give you a plus two
circumstance bonus and the last thing I
want to leave all of you with is the
number one question that I get asked by
5e players which is where's DND beyond
for Pathfinder what's the DN D Beyond of
Pathfinder and there's and sadly there
is nothing that is quite as nice as D
and D Beyond
I I was I was about to say I love D and
D Beyond I used to love D and D Beyond I
loved it D and D Beyond back when you
could do allart allart purchases and say
like I just want to buy this one feet I
don't want to buy the whole book I
believe now they force you to buy the
whole book which Hasbro is lame which is
probably why you're here in the first
place
But to answer the question there is
really no great one toone comparison of
D and D Beyond Pathfinder the closest
thing is going to be a a website called
demiplane where you can find Pathfinder
Nexus that works very similar to D and
Beyond in fact I believe it's it's the
company that's creating it uh I might
have this a little bit wrong but I
believe I've been told that that a lot
of their staff worked on D and
Beyond but is this same general idea you
buy digital versions of the books and
there's a character builder and you can
search for that for that stuff but you
have to buy the books digitally to use
that platform on a um Demi plane or
Pathfinder
Nexus uh if you're looking for a really
solid character builder I recommend path
Builder uh path Builder uh 90% or maybe
even 98% of it is free to
use um and if you if there is a feature
that you want to have uh all you got to
do is pay a onetime fee and you unlock
everything forever in
perpetuity uh and I think that was only
a
$5 flat charge when I did I don't know
if his prices have gone up what have you
but path Builder is available um on any
on the internet on you know through
Chrome or whatever your browser of
choices is also available on um Android
devices and uh I saw an announcement
this very morning that he is working
finally at getting path Builder ported
over to um to Apple devices on iOS as
well they're not there yet but if you
look for a good character builder path
Builder is the recommendation if you
want full feature like D&D Beyond check
out Demi plane uh Pathfinder Nexus is
part of De plane and if you want an
online tool just to look up a rule uh I
find PF easy tools to be the um the
easiest for me to find what I'm looking
for but it's sometime not as complete as
archives of nethys which is the official
repository on so those two would be uh
online resources for you to
use so that's it uh I try to make this
as brief as possible although I know
this is going to be one of my longer
videos of key things you should know as
a 5e player coming into Pathfinder
second edition remastered if you have
any questions please leave those in the
comments if you're a 5 player and I
goofed on anything let me know cuz I
actually haven't DMD 5 in a while I do
have a playlist of rule videos for path
ler fifth edition or for I'm sorry for
Dungeons and Dragons fifth edition that
you you might find interesting still
I'll include those in the comments but I
may have tripped up on a particular two
let me know um I would appreciate it and
as a veteran Pathfinder players if you
have tips for all of our new friends is
coming in from from Dungeons and Dragons
fifth edition let them know in the
comments as well uh you know let's let's
be welcoming neighbors and invite them
all into our happy little community so
uh with that I'm going to close out as
always I want to take a moment to thank
everybody who supports me in this
channel whether that's by clicking the
like button subscribing to the channel
subscribing to the patreon buying a
super thanks I really appreciate
everything this community does to
support me and with that thanks for
watching take care and happy gaming
[Music]