hello and welcome to Shields and
Pathfinder second edition
remastered Shields and Pathfinder
function a little different than what
you may be used to from other D20
Fantasy games as you might expect
Pathfinder Shields require an arm to use
and Grant a circumstance bonus to Armor
class but what's different are a couple
tweaks to the old Formula First Shields
do not always grant their bonus to Armor
class instead a character must use the
raise a shield action to gain that
benefit this costs one action and grants
The Shield's circumstance bonus to armor
class until the start of their next turn
if you want to keep this bonus going
longer then you need to keep spending
one of your actions every turn and note
that this is a general action so it is
available to everyone there is no Shield
proficiency requirement anyone can pick
up a shield and use the raise a shield
action to gain its bonus to Armor
class the second point we need to
discuss is The Shield block feat this
feat is provided automatically to
several Marshall classes such as
Champions Druids exemplars and Fighters
War priest clerics also gain this feat
for free but not other clerics and as a
general feat anyone of any class can
pick up Shield block as one of their
General feat selections and I would
would recommend anyone who plans to make
using a shield a regular part of their
game play to do so if you're willing to
invest in action every round to use your
Shield you might as well get the most
benefit out of doing so what this feat
does is it allows you to spend your
reaction each round to mitigate the
damage received from a successful enemy
attack this can only be done while you
have a shield raised so you would spend
one action on your turn to raise the
shield and then later in the round
during during an enemy's turn if they
hit you with an attack that deals
physical damage you can spend your
reaction that round to block it so since
this costs a reaction you typically will
only be able to block one attack per
round with your Shield but there is an
exception to this that we will talk
about a little bit later and remember
that blocking an attack with your Shield
does not mean that you suffer no damage
it just reduces the amount of damage you
receive each Shield has a listed
hardness rating as well as hit points
and break threshold abbreviated as
BT hardness is damage reduction when you
block an enemy's attack with your Shield
you calculate their damage as normal and
then subtract The Shield's hardness
value from that and if there is any
remaining damage after hardness is
removed that amount of damage is applied
to both you and your Shield remember
this excess damage is not divided
between you and the shield it is applied
equally to both you and the shield for
example let's say valorous the fighter
is battling a goblin on his turn valeros
spins one action to raise his wooden
Shield doing so increases his armor
class by two then on the Goblin's turn
it makes an attack roll and scores a hit
even with Valero's buffed up Armor class
the goblin rolls damage and gets a total
of five is's player now decides to spend
their reaction on Shield block and this
is important to remember you do not have
to declare that you are using Shield
block until after the damage has been
rolled wooden Shields have a hardness
value of three so we would subtract that
from the damage of five leaving two
points of damage that would be applied
to both valeros and his shield so
valeros loses two hit points and his
wooden Shield is reduced from 12 hit
points to 10
if the goblin spent its second action to
attack again valerus would still have
the plus two bonus to armor class but
would not be able to use Shield block
again because doing so Conant reaction
and he has no more reactions to spend
this
round we've discussed how Shields can be
used to mitigate or absorb damage with
the shield block feet so now let's look
at what happens when your Shield takes
too much damage and runs out of hit
points as previously mentioned each
Shield is listed on the table with a
break threshold when a shield or really
any object has its hit points lowered to
this threshold number it becomes broken
broken items no longer function as they
are meant to which means a broken shield
no longer grants a bonus to Armor class
and in fact cannot even be used with
raise a shield nor can it be used to
block further damage it's worth noting
that the entry for the broken condition
does contain exceptions to this for
broken armor but mechanically speaking a
shield is not armor and therefore does
not interact with this exception when a
Shield's hit points are equal to or
lower than his broken threshold it
effectively ceases to be a shield and if
a shield or or any item has its hit
points reduced all the way to zero is
destroyed so if a shield is destroyed at
zero hit points and a broken shield
can't be used anyway then why even have
a broken condition wouldn't it make more
sense just to say The Shield is
destroyed at its broken threshold says
it can't be used
anymore well the reason for this
distinction between broken and destroyed
is a broken shield can still be repaired
and used again whereas a destroyed
Shield is beyond the point of
repair unsurprisingly to repair a shield
you use the repair applic ation of the
crafting skill you do not need to be
trained in the crafting skill to attempt
a repair but it definitely helps to use
repair you'll need a repair toolkit and
spend 10 minutes of work hammering out
dents and mending tears at the end of
this time you'll roll a crafting skill
check versus a DC set by the GM this is
usually a level based DC per the table
on page 53 of the GM core rule book
based on The Shield's level not the
players on a sus The Shield regains a
number of hit points equal to five plus
five more for each level of proficiency
so if you're not trained at all in
crafting you restore five hit points if
you have trained proficiency you restore
10 hit points and so on if this raises
The Shield's hit points higher than his
break threshold it loses the broken
condition and once more functions like a
normal shield on a critical success you
restore double the usual amount on a
normal failure nothing happens you spend
10 minutes but you don't gain any ground
and must spend another 10 minutes and
try again and on a critical failure you
mess up so bad that you deal 2d6 damage
to the shield fortunately The Shield's
usual hardness value reduces this damage
as normal but if this damage reduces The
Shield to zero hit points it is
destroyed and cannot be repaired
again there are four basic types of
shields each with their own features
these are bucklers wooden Shields steel
Shields and Tower Shields wooden and
steel Shields function as we've already
covered the key difference being steel
Shields are sturdier and have higher
hardness scores and more hit points
bucklers are lighter Shields that are
strapped to the arm but do not require a
hand to use instead said the hand that
would normally hold a larger Shield can
be used to hold any light object that is
not a weapon so a person using a buckler
could still use that arm to drink a
potion to use athletic actions like grab
and shove or take other interact actions
that don't involve weapons and they
would still be able to use the raise of
Shield action Tower Shields are very
large in function as portable cover
carrying one imposes a negative 5
penalty to speed but the wielder may use
the tower shield with the take cover
action while their Shield is raised to
increase their circumstance bonus Armor
class from plus two to plus 4
essentially this allows you to use take
cover even when you're in an open field
with no other viable sources of cover
nearby those are the standard shield
types but it is worth noting that there
are also magical Shields with unique
properties as well as runes that can be
Ed onto Shields to enhance them in the
same way that runes can enhance armor
and weapons there's currently only one
Rune that can be placed on Shields and
that's the reinforcing Rune these runes
increase the hardness hit points and
break threshold of any Shield they're
edged onto up to a specified maximum
Shields can also be made from precious
materials for example making a shield
out of adamantine increases the base
stance of that shield and a can then be
further enhanced by a reinforcing Rune
as long as doing so doesn't increase its
hardness in hit points past the maximum
limits specified by the Rune and other
Shields forged from precious materials
like cold iron and silver are treated as
Weapons of that material when the
shields are used to bash an enemy so
let's take a moment to go over Shield
bashing when making a shield bash attack
The Shield is treated as a marshall
melee weapon per the weapons table on
page 278 of player Core 1 it deals one4
bling damage and belongs to the shield
group meaning if you have access to the
critical specialization effect for
Shields you can push your target back 5T
after scoring a critical hit with a
shield bash and this damage can be
further increased to D6 by attaching a
shield boss and changed to piercing
damage with Shield spikes and unlike the
shield itself Shield bosses and shield
spikes can be enhanced with weapon runes
Shields can also be enhanced by
attaching a shield augmentation you
can't use a shield augmentation if you
already have a shield boss or Shield
spikes attached but if you choose to add
an augmentation over one of those it
allows you to add special traits to the
shield you can choose to add one trait
being either back swing or forceful or
or you can choose two of the following
disarm non-lethal shove thrown 10 ft
trip or versatile slashing so this can
give you a few more options for how to
use your Shield but if you really want
to cosplay Captain America with it you
might want to invest in the throwing
Shield adjustment that increases its
range to 20 ft is damaged to a D6 and
allows you to remove the shield so it
can be thrown with a free action however
this augmentation also makes the shield
lighter which reduces its hardness
rating by
one next let's talk about Shield Feats
I'm not going to go over all of them but
a few of note include reactive Shield
which lets you spend your reaction to
raise your Shield instead of an action
reflexive Shield lets you use Shield
block against attacks that call for a
reflex save including those that don't
deal physical damage like a fireball
spell
quick Shield block grants an extra
action each turn that can only be used
for shield blocks this allows you to
make two Shield blocks each turn or make
a shield Block in the same round as you
use reactive shield and ever stand
stance and ever stand strike require you
to be a knight of last wall to gain
access but the stance increases the
damage die of The Shield by one step
when using it as a weapon and also
increases its hardness by two when using
the shield block provided you are
wielding the shield with both of your
hands and ever stand a strike allows you
to automatically raise your Shield after
a successful Shield
strike so that's it for today a few
things you should know if you plan to
use a shield and Pathfinder second
edition if you have any questions please
leave them in the comments below and as
always I want to take a brief moment to
thank everyone who supports me in this
channel whether that be by leaving a
comment click the like button buying a
super thanks subscribing to the patreon
or subscribing to the channel I greatly
appreciate everything you do to support
me and with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]