hello and welcome to reactive strikes in
Pathfinder second
edition the reactive strike is a feature
for Fighters at first level and may be
gained through Feats for most other
Marshall classes despite differences in
availability they all function the same
way this ability allows characters to
use their reaction to make a melee
strike against an opponent who has
dropped their guard there are a few
requirements to trigger this reaction
first the enemy must be within your
reach meaning they must be close enough
that you could strike them with your
melee weapon or with an unarmed melee
attack and second one of the following
must occur the enemy uses a manipulate
action the enemy makes a ranged attack
the enemy uses a move action or the
enemy moves out of its Square during a
move action that it is using if both
those criteria are met being that the
enemy is within range of your melee
attack and performs one of the four
triggering actions then you may spend
your reaction to make a melee strike
against them the strike is always made
at your highest bonus without any
multiple attack penalty even if
technically it may be your fourth attack
that round that's what reactive strike
is but let's take a closer look at each
of these
elements first the enemy must be within
reach of your melee attack and this
would be what whatever melee attack you
have prepared at that moment meaning
it's either a weapon you're already
holding or it's an unarmed attack any
square that you can make a melee attack
into is sometimes referred to as your
threatened area or that you are
threatening those spaces now for clarity
that's a first edition term that you
will not find in the second edition Rule
books officially but I think those terms
help illustrate this requirement if
anyway the enemy must be standing in a
threatened space for you to use reactive
strike against them generally speaking
your threatened area will be the eight
squares immediately surrounding you
however some weapons have the reach
trait that allows them to attack enemies
more than one square away for example
Hal birds have the reach trait which
means they can attack enemies that are
10 ft away and per the notation on page
426 of player Core 1
this means they can attack enemies that
are two squares away including
diagonally so if you're wielding a
Warhammer you threaten these spaces if
you're wielding a long spear you
threaten these spaces if you're a hill
giant you threaten these spaces and if
you're a hill giant wielding a long
spear you threaten these spaces as long
as your enemy is is occupying at least
one of these spaces they meet the first
criteria for reactive
strike assuming at least part of the
target is occupying a threatened space
the next question is does the Target
meet one of the four triggering actions
the first of which is using a manipulate
action any action that has the
manipulate trait is considered to be a
manipulate action the manipulate trait
not any action that requires the user to
physically interact with an object or to
make
gestures probably the most common place
you'll find this is with interact
actions interact has the manipulate
trait meaning anything that calls for an
interact action is also a manipulate
action a few common examples include
reloading weapons drawing a weapon or a
potion fetching an item from Storage
giving an item two or taking an item
from another character and opening a
door another example would be activating
items for example applying Black Adder
Venom to a dagger requires two actions
with the manipulate trait which would
trigger reactive strikes also most
spells have the manipulate trait too we
should also note that one action that
may feel like a manipulate action
because it involves moving an item is is
strike the strike action used to make
attacks with weapons does not have the
manipulate trait therefore melee attacks
do not trigger reactive
strikes so the strike action itself does
not trigger reactive strikes but the
second listed trigger is making a ranged
attack which is easy enough if someone
attempts to make a ranged attack with a
longbow while they're standing in one of
your threatened spaces that could allow
you to spend your reaction to make a
reactive strike against them and this
applies to any ranged attack shooting a
bow throwing a dagger or checking an
acid flask at someone all count as
ranged attacks and enemies making ranged
attacks don't just trigger a reactive
strike from their target for example if
they were F Point Blank at an adjacent
enemy but they would trigger from
everyone that they are within melee of
assuming those enemies have the ability
to make reactive strikes ranged spell
attacks also count for this but there's
a good chance that those spells are
already covered by being manipulate
actions as we've already
discussed the third possible trigger for
reactive strikes is using a move action
if you use an action that has the move
trait while standing in an enemy's
threatened area you might trigger an
attack from them a few examples of this
would include falling prone standing up
from prone or mounting a horse declaring
any of these or other actions that have
the move trait May trigger reactive
strikes and the fourth possible trigger
is the enemy moves out of its Square
during a move action that it is using
and this may sound the same as the
previous trigger of using a move action
but the difference is the previous
trigger refers to declaring a move
action while standing in a threatened
space and this fourth requirement covers
situations where a creature might
declare the move action while outside of
the enemy's threatened space and then
move through that threatened area
typically this will occur with stride
actions but may also happen with other
forms of locomotion like swimming flying
or climbing move actions trigger
reactions not just when they are used
but again every time that creature
attemps to leave a square so if you use
stride starting outside of a threaten
space you do not trigger any reactive
strikes then and if you move into a
threatened space you do not trigger
anything either because the movement
trigger occurs when leaving squares but
if you then leave that threatened space
you may trigger reactive strikes but
note that you may never trigger more
than one reaction per creature with a
single move action no matter how many
threaten spaces you exit even if that
creature somehow has more than one
reaction to spend also be aware that the
step action exists to allow creatures to
move without triggering reactions step
cost one action and you can only move 5
feet instead of your full speed but you
do not trigger reactive strikes when
doing so and last note that the name for
this trigger is the enemy moves out of a
square during a move action that it is
using emphasis on that part during a
move action that it is using in other
words if the target moves out of one of
your threatened spaces but doesn't use
one of their own actions to do so then
that movement does not trigger reactive
strikes basically if they're forced out
of their space by someone else's action
like a shove attack then you do not get
to use reactive strikes on
them when reactive strike is triggered
the attacking character may spend their
reaction that turn to make a melee
strike against the provoking creature as
mentioned before this attack is made
using the attacking character's highest
bonus and is not affected by or
contribute to the multiple attack
penalty this strike is resolved as
normal except if the result is a
critical hit and the reactive strike was
triggered by and manipulate action if
that is the case then the action is
disrupted when an action is disrupted
all resources and costs associated with
that triggering action are still spent
but the effect of that action does not
occur for example if you're a fighter
and an enemy cast a spell with the
manipulate trait while standing in one
of your threatened spaces you could
spend your reaction that turn to make a
reactive strike if the result of that
attack is a critical hit then not only
do you deal double damage as normal for
a critical hit but you also disrupt that
spell from being cast the enemy in this
case still loses both actions they had
invested in casting the spell as well as
the spell slot and any other resources
that were invested in the casting as
usual the only difference is the spell
effect does not occur in some cases it
may be important to know exactly when
the reactive strike occurs for example
if a successful reactive strike results
in killing an opponent you may need to
know which Square the body occupies if
the reactive strike is triggered by an
enemy moving out of a threatened space
the reactive strike occurs immediately
effectively before they leave that space
if it occurred after they leave the
space then they would likely be out of
range of your attack so if an adjacent
enemy uses the stride action to move out
of their space you do not wait for that
action to completely resolve and may
attack them immediately but if the
reactive strike is triggered by using a
move action without leaving their space
then the enemy gets to fully resolve
that action before the reactive strike
occurs for example if an enemy stands
from prone they completely stand up
before resolving your reactive strike
this is important when determining if
the enemy suffers the offguard condition
from being prone or
not that covers my introduction to
reactive strikes but do leave any
questions you have in the comments below
and before we close out I do want to say
thanks to Scuba Steve from my patreon
who was a big help in researching this
topic and I also want to thank everyone
who supports me whether that be by
clicking the like button leaving a
comment subscribing to the patreon or
buying a super thanks I really
appreciate everything you do to support
me and with that thanks for watching
take care and happy gaming
[Music]