hey everybody Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you and
today's question is about players
writing upon other players with the
release of how of the wild we now have
large size ancestries that players can
play so this specific scenario involves
what if we have two players one of them
is a human that's mediumsized and the
other is a minur which is large size
what are the rules for the human player
to ride upon their large siiz minur
friend into
combat and so let's take a look at these
rules the rules are provided in Hall of
the wild the same book that gives us the
new large size ancestries and it's on
page nine and the first thing that uh
this rule says is a PC can write on
another PC as long as the second PC is
at least two size categories larger than
them so this is a little different than
the rules we've seen before and and
before Hall of the wild when you looked
at any information uh for example the
mount action uh it would specifically
say that you used it to get upon a
creature that was one size category
larger than you so that right there is
going to invalidate the scenario of a
medium-size human riding on a large siiz
Minotaur because that's only a on siiz
category difference uh instead what we
would have to have is a small size
character wanting to ride upon the minur
so uh that would be a halfling for
example or a goblin anything the small
size leesy whatever writing upon the um
the minur uh I actually think the the
the new moon uh Heritage uh seren are
like Smalls siiz minotaurs so you could
even have some bizarre situation of a
small-sized minur riding upon a large
siiz minur shoulder players don't get up
to Wacky stuff with uh with with these
rules and that's one possibility but uh
anyway uh I think the reason that the
previous uh rules always refer to two-
size categories larger is because they
were specifically talking about
creatures that were intended to be
mounts these are typically long
creatures instead of tall creatures and
typically quadrupeds so even though the
roles didn't you know specify that you
had to be long instead of tall and you
had to have four limbs to walking Pond
instead of two
uh that was what the Assumption was so
we're talking horses or riding
dogs uh you Wars for goblins stuff like
that but now that is actually PCS who
are typically going to be by pedal we
have a new set of rules so that's the
first part uh you have to be two size
categories larger for that to serve as
um a creature to be ridden upon here it
also says this requires a tremendous
amount of coordination to ensure the
smaller PC doesn't get in the way or the
two PCS don't jostle each other into
losing actions as a result for most
parties this tactic is less favorable
than the smaller PC just using their
amount and yeah and as I go through this
it's I think it's going become more and
more clear that um there's not a lot of
mechanical benefit to uh to having one
PC ride upon another uh especially in
combat so why would they do this answer
is simple because it's fun because it's
cool because it's narratively
interesting uh those are the reasons why
players are going to want to engage in
these rules not because in most cases uh
there might be one little Fringe area
we'll talk about in a bit but in in
certainly in most cases there's not
going to be a uh a distinct mechanical
benefit to doing this um I think right
off the bat the most the most clear
downside to this is you're now occupa
occupying the same space on the board
which means uh if someone wants to hit
you with an AOE they only have to hit
one of your your squares instead of
being able to set the cone or the burst
or whatever so it's hitting two
different squares so that right off the
bat is a downside at doing this but uh
let's go ahead and see what else it says
here if a PC who is at least two sizes
smaller rides along with with another PC
or similar non minion intelligent
creature roll both their initiatives and
use the lower of the two results the two
PCS act in either order on the same
initiative count so what the raw is
saying here is uh it doesn't matter what
order you roll your initiatives in
between the person writing and the
characters being written upon they both
roll their initiatives as normal but you
take the lower of the two in every round
those two characters can take their
actions in either order but my reading
of the rule would be that uh whichever
one goes first they resolve all of their
actions they they resolve their entire
turn and then the other character
resolves all of their actions in their
turn separately not intermingling those
actions together and it continues on to
say while traveling in this way the PCS
gain two actions at the start of their
turns instead of three since the larger
PC spends one action keeping the smaller
one balanced on their back and the
smaller PC spends one action maintaining
their grip there's not a whole lot of of
benefit to do this mechanically the
benefit in doing this is is going to be
uh narrative because it's fun because
it's cool because it might be awesome to
be a halfling pursed on your buddy's
shoulder your minur buddy shoulder and
you're holding a hor with one hand and
you're whacking people with a mace as he
runs past them with the other uh
mechanically not going to give you a lot
of benefit but it's that it's that it's
that narrative moment that you might
appreciate and the last bit of text says
some ancestry specialize in being able
to carry smaller riders or have Feats to
enable this such as Centaur so that's
the guidance we have in raw for writing
PCS you must have uh two size C atories
different and both those people are
going to be reduced to only having two
actions per turn uh as basically they're
each losing one action in favor of
either not accidentally throwing a
person off or or holding on for deer
life and staying on that minur shoulder
or what have you um and initiative is
going to be at the lowest of their two
roles but every round round as I read it
they can swap so like maybe one round is
most advantageous for the writer to go
first and then the the character being
ridden to go next or in the next round
they could swap that order and go the
other way so let's talk about those
special situations like the centur so
centur if we look at their ancestry they
have a special feature called Mount and
it says your ecoin body is well suited
for caring trusted allies a piece PC can
ride you if they are one size category
smaller than you rather than needing to
be two size category smaller so if the
PC that is being written upon is like a
centur and has the mount feature as part
of their ancestory then you only have to
be one siiz category different so a
medium-sized human could ride a centur
that large size whereas they could not
if it was a minur in that case the minor
would just be carrying
the mediumsized creature like anything
else and there's an additional optional
feat that uh that the centur players can
pick up at level five and it's called
accommodating Mount you've trained to
serve as a mount if only for your most
trusted allies when another PC writes
you as a mount your expert coordination
allows them to gain three actions at the
start of their turn rather than the two
they would normally for writing another
PC you still gain only two actions at
the start of your turn in so three as
you spend one action keeping them
balanced on your back in ensuring
they're firmly mounted so um so if you
do want to lighten the load a little bit
of the rule that says you only are going
to start each turn with two actions
instead of the normal three then the
Centaur player could get accommodating
amount to to offset that a little bit by
giving the person rotting upon them
their fourth reactions
so there are a number of other things
that we might want to look at uh
questions that come up um in regard to
this and I will
say there's going to have to be a little
bit of GM interpretation for a lot of
this GM is going to have to think about
the rules as written and the rules as
intended or interpreted and uh what's
going to be most uh most narratively
satisfying and most importantly fun for
your players as you figure out how to
use each of these rules but the first is
going to be the question about bulk so
if uh if one player is writing upon
another player uh do we need to enforce
bulk rules I would assume so and so uh
if you want to know what the bulk of a
character is that's going to be found in
player core one there's a table on page
269 that gives you sort of a rough
average bulk for a creature by uh size
category and then you would just take
the additional B that that character is
carrying add those two numbers together
and that would be the bulk of what the
uh the creature being ridden upon is now
having to
accommodate another question would be
about mounted Feats so especially if
maybe like you're you're a Cavalier you
might have a lot of Feats that they that
give you special abilities and features
while you are
mounted so how does this apply to riding
another piece c um the section on
running PC doesn't really go into this
so again this is going to be a place
where hgms going to have to make their
own rulings um I think a lot of the
mounted Feats uh are definitely are
probably going to apply when you are
riding upon a creature that has the
mount feature like a
centaur um and may not apply to when
you're writing another creature or
another PC uh you'll notice the section
on writing PC uh doesn't use the term
Mount anywhere doesn't say that you use
the mount action to get onto or off of
the creature that you're riding upon it
doesn't refer to the creature you're
riding upon as a quote Mount um so uh a
lot of the Feats that give you bonuses
to being mounted uh I think GMS are well
within their right to say like I don't
think it's going to defend the situation
where you're writing on perched on the
shoulder of a
minur uh versus the um versus a on the
back of a centaur but again do what's
going to be uh narratively satisfying
and fun for your players as long as it
doesn't break the game uh another thing
to keep in mind is a lot of these Mount
Feats or no not a lot but some of them
certainly imply that the person who is
writing is also controlling the creature
they're riding upon and that's not going
to be the case when you're riding upon
another PC that the PC that's being
written upon is going to maintain their
full agency and do what they want to
move where they want to go so those
Feats for mounted combat may not apply
here
either so what about things like in
mounted combat it talks about cover well
this is an area that I think probably
would apply to when you're riding up a
PC even though they don't have the mount
trait it may not officially be called a
mount uh just because it makes sense to
me
uh those cover rules are that the rider
receives a a basically receives lesser
cover from the creature they're riding
upon that's going to be a plus one AC
but it also says that they are going to
suffer a negative2 to their reflex saves
uh simply because they're not in control
entirely of being able to dodge out of
the way of things at the mercy of what
they're what they're riding
upon kind of a Akin to that especially
with reflex an area of a
attacks uh do do you as a rider occupy
all the same spaces as the creature
you're riding upon the section on
writing PCS doesn't go into this uh but
the section on mounted combat does
specifically say that uh if you're
mounted on a creature that's larger than
you then you occupy your tree is
occupying all the same scores as they
are I would assume this is the same for
when you are riding a PC
uh instead of having to choose which of
the four specific squares a large
creature occupies for your Square you
would be treated as occupying all of all
four of those squares at the same time
another quick question is about reach um
in mounted combat it says you got to
have 15 feet of reach to attack two
squares away instead of 10 feet of reach
to attack two squares away if you're are
ridning upon a mount that is size large
uh wouldn't apply if you're like a small
siiz character riding on a uh
mediumsized U you know uh riding dog or
work or something like
that I would assume that's going to
apply here um so even though that this
is again we're not entire I'm not
entirely certain if you know where we
draw the line between writing a PC and
them being a mount other than centaurs
having the mount trait I think rules
like this will still
apply how about using a jousting weapon
uh jousting weapons uh are used on
mounts and what it is is you can either
use the the jousting weapon for example
a lance with two hands and do its
regular damage in the case of a lance
that would be a d8 weapon
die or you can joust with it which means
you can hold it in one hand and have
your other hand fore to hold a shield um
and it does uh in the case of a lance it
does a D6 damage wielded one hand
instead of instead of U 1d8 for two
hands I would assume that you would have
to do that uh when you're riding on
another creature using the example of a
halfling on a menur uh they can't wield
a two-handed weapon they'd have to have
one hand on on minotaur's Horns or
whatever to hold themselves study and
then they would Jou with the other now
the the tricky area here is jeling
weapons
say that if you move at least 10 feet on
the action immediately before you make a
a a strike with your Lance then you're
going to get a bonus of damage equal to
the number of weapon dice so in in using
a regular Lance uh that's that'd be 1 D6
damage jousting you would get a plus one
that damage if the if the mount that
you're runting upon moves at least 10
feet on the action immediately before
you make strike so that's the piece that
by raw gets really fuzzy here
because the rules for jousting and for
mounts uh assume that you as the rider
you're controlling the mount and so on
your turn you're controlling where the
mount goes and how the and how that
action economy spent is spent but with
the rules for writing a PC
one creature completely takes all their
actions and completely resolves their
turn and then the next creature does or
the next player
does so that makes it a little more
difficult to say that um if if the if
the creature being ridden upon takes
their actions
first uh does this mean that they have
to spend their last action on stride and
the first action of the next character's
turn must be a strike in order to get
that bonus uh in my uh Asad Dev series
uh I I I talked to or ask a Pathfinder
designer series a question similar to
this came up and they said that whenever
you see this text that says on the
action before they're referring to your
actions and it's not you're not
splitting between rounds you're not
splitting between players is intended
like you spend your first action do to
do a thing and then your second
so that kind of by raw makes the
jousting trait uh just not really
functional uh so as as with my other
recommendations I say you know do what
makes sense and what makes fun uh and I
would say as long as during the uh turn
of the person being ridden during that
turn if they move 10 ft at least uh then
I would allow the character writing to
make that strike and get the bonus I've
actually not had this this situation
come up in my own games yet but I I
think I would probably give them the
freedom to intermingle their three
actions and use them however makes sense
that can get fuzzy when you're getting
to things like uh if they're suffering
persistent damage when does that
persistent damage kick in stuff like
that but uh it that just seems to make
more sense to me and be easier for the
players to understand if you say uh okay
you know player one that's being that's
playing the Centaur you spend your first
action stride okay now go ahead uh human
on his back uh spin your ACT first
action to make your strike just makes it
easier my rules uh so I would allow that
and also the question would you allow
jousting to be um to be something that a
character writing upon another player
that is not a mount
like a centaur would you allow that uh
for me this is falling in that category
of uh this sounds fun so why not uh if a
halfling wants to have a a lance in one
hand and holding the minotaur's horn and
the other and the minur is going to make
a charge attack against an enemy uh why
not let the halfling you know thrust
with their Lance and get their jousting
benefit in doing so so uh get you know
luring or or or just getting a plus one
bonus to that damage making it 1 D6 plus
one 186 damage it's not going to break
the game and it sounds fun so let your
players do stuff like that um okay so
that's it for today's rule reminder
about what are the rules for when a
smaller size player wants to ride upon a
larger size Ally uh in combat if you
have any questions about this please
leave them in the comments below if you
have suggestions for future rule
reminders also leave those in the
comments below and as always I want to
take a quick moment to say thank you to
everybody out there who supports me
whether that be by clicking the like
button leaving your comments subscribing
to the channel subscribing to the
patreon buying a super thanks all of
that adds up and I really appreciate all
the support you folks give me and with
that thanks for watching take care and
happy gaming
[Music]