Hello and welcome to Troops and
Pathfinder second edition remastered. If
your group is using the legacy edition
rules, please see my original troops
video that is linked in the
description. Troops allow a large number
of individuals to function as a single
unit. Mechanically, this has a lot of
advantages. Rather than having to track
two dozen or more different creatures,
the GM only has to manage one single
large creature. And troops also allow
narrative moments where the players are
overwhelmed by the sheer number of their
foes. If presented as individuals, they
likely would pose little to no challenge
for the heroes. But when they're stated
together as a troop, they can be
formidable. In this regard, troops are
not entirely dissimilar from the swarm
mechanics used when battling large
groups of vermin, but there are a few
important distinctions.
To illustrate how troops work, we'll be
looking at the stat block for a city
guard squadron. Each individual member
of the city guard is a medium-sized
creature and occupies one square. But
when a large group of them gathered
together, they may function as a troop.
A fresh undamaged troop occupies 16
squares like a gargantuan sized
creature, but not a single 16 square
area. Instead, these 16 squares are
divided into four 2x two square
segments. If the troop is made up of
individual medium or smallsiz units like
the city guards, it may be best to
represent the troop with 16 tokens or
miniatures. And if the troop is made up
of largesiz units like mounted cavalry,
you can represent each segment using a
single largesized token or miniature.
But within the narrative, it's important
to remember the troop is not literally
16 city guards. It's often many more.
Each square is crowded with bodies, and
the map, miniatures, and troop roles
exist to simplify the mechanics of the
encounter in a somewhat abstract way.
Each segment can be positioned on the
map independently from the others except
each segment must share a border that's
at least 5 ft in length with another
segment so that they are all chained
together. And it's not enough for the
segments to be diagonal from one
another. They must share a border with
each other. For example, this is a legal
shape for a troop. and so is this or
this. But this is not a legal shape, nor
is
this. Also, it's important to note that
as a troop suffers damage, it shrinks in
size, which makes sense. As members of
the troop are whittleled away, the troop
itself becomes smaller and smaller. This
is represented in the rules by including
two hit point thresholds.
We see here that a city guard squadron
starts with 75 hit points and a
parenthetical noting four
segments. And then we see the two
thresholds. The first threshold says 50
and three segments, meaning that after
the cityguard squadron as a whole has
suffered 25 points of damage, one of its
four segments is removed from the map.
And after it suffers another 25 points
of damage, it hits its second hit point
threshold and loses another
segment. There are some special rules
regarding how troops suffer damage. The
troop as a whole has a single pool of
hit points that is shared among all of
its segments. Meaning damage is
abstracted so that if one segment is
targeted for an attack and hit, its
damage is applied to the entire troop
and not specifically the one segment
that was targeted. Each time a troop's
hit points is pushed past one of its
thresholds, a segment is removed. By
raw, the player who deals that damage
that pushes the troop past a threshold
typically gets to decide which segment
is removed. But I find it much easier
for the GM to be the one who makes that
call because sometimes the abstracted
nature of troop combat can be confusing
for some players. For example, if
Valeros attacks the troop here with a
melee attack and deals enough damage to
push it past its first threshold,
Valeros's player might logically declare
that this segment be the one that's
removed. However, it can't be removed
because doing so would leave the troop
in an illegal formation on the map.
Remember, each segment must share a
border with another segment. So, the
segment that's removed must be one of
these, and that can feel
counterintuitive for players. So, James
will need to describe what happens
within the narrative. As Valerus chops
down the foes in front of him, more
soldiers rush in to take their place,
which has the result of shrinking the
troop, starting with the segments that
are furthest out and sharing only one
border. Also, every time a troop is
reduced to one of his thresholds, the
listed value for that threshold becomes
the troop's new maximum hit point value.
Meaning if the cityguard squadron was
reduced beyond its first threshold of 50
and left with 40 hit points and then
received 20 points of healing, it would
only be able to heal back up to 50 hit
points is most recently passed threshold
and any excess healing would be lost. In
order to restore lost segments and its
original maximum hit points, a troop
needs to spend downtime to use long-term
treatment on casualties or recruit new
members to replace those that were
lost. At zero hit points, the troop can
no longer function as a unit. At this
point, the troop is defeated and its
remaining members either flee,
surrender, or are killed off depending
on the troop's nature and the
disposition of the players.
We should also take a look at how troops
deal with non-damaging effects. Troops
are usually immune to any non-damaging
effect that only targets a single
creature, like a charm spell or using
the intimidate skill to
demoralize. However, non-damaging
abilities that target at least five
creatures can affect an entire segment.
Abilities that target 10 creatures can
affect two segments. And abilities that
target 20 or more creatures can affect
an entire troop. And for non-damaging
abilities that target all creatures
within a certain area, each segment that
is completely within that area is
affected and rolls their saves and other
checks individually. If a non-damaging
effect would prevent a segment from
acting, causing them to flee or
otherwise make them unable to function
as part of the troop for one round or
more, that segment is removed
entirely. When this happens, the troops
hit points are reduced to its next
threshold to account for the lost
segment. And note that if a single
ability has both damaging and
non-damaging effects, apply the damage
first and then the non-damaging effects.
So, for example, say a player casts
command on the troop. The command spell
normally only targets one enemy and
therefore has no effect on the troop,
even if the troop was to critically fail
their save. Making one soldier
temporarily incapacitated by a spell
like this will not have a significant
impact on the troop as a whole. But if
the player heightens that spell to fifth
rank, it now targets 10 creatures, which
means it has the ability to affect two
segments. Each segment rolls their will
saves against the spell independently.
We'll say the first segment fails their
will save and the second segment
critically fails their will save. This
causes the troop to shrink by one
segment. So why would the troop lose
only one segment here and not two when
it failed both of its saves? Because in
order for a non-damaging effect to
remove a segment, it must prevent that
segment from acting for at least one
round. Failing a will save against
command causes the target to lose one
action, not an entire turn. But
critically failing causes the target to
lose all three actions, which is most
likely an entire
round. Given the unusual size and shape
of troops, they have special rules to
manage their movement, too. Troops spend
actions to move like normal creatures
do. For example, a cityguard squadron
can spend one action to stride 25 ft.
But when troops move, you select one of
their segments to be the leading segment
and move it as you would normally move a
single largesized creature. And then all
of the other segments follow behind that
segment. When the leading segment
finishes its move, the remaining
segments can be placed in any
orientation that is legal and does not
require them to move a greater distance
than the leading
segment. Trips can also spend a single
action to adjust their formation. When
performing this, you simply select one
segment that stays in place and then
move the other segments into any
formation you wish as long as it is
legal. meaning each segment shares an
edge as normal. This is all the official
guidance that's given. So, GS may need
to make their own calls as to what
happens when troops try to move through
or reorient themselves in unusual
situations or unusual
environments. There really aren't any
special rules for how a troop functions
in combat, but there are a few shared
similarities. Troops function like any
normal monster with an armor class and
saving throws to defend against incoming
attacks. And they also may have
resistances, immunities, and weaknesses,
especially against area and splash
damage. And each have their own listed
attacks in their stat blocks. Most of
these will be some manner of area attack
as every member of the troop strikes at
once against any enemies within their
range and therefore most troop attacks
target reflex and not armor class. For
example, city guard squadrons have two
attacks, lower halbirds and shoot
crossbows. Lower halbirds cost one to
three actions, but can only be performed
once per round. This attack targets all
enemies within 10 ft of any of the
troops spaces and deals an amount of
damage based on the number of actions
spent. Unlike normal single halbird
attacks, this attack is resisted by a
reflex saving throw instead of armor
class and shoot crossbows takes two
actions and allows the troop to fire
their crossbows into a 10 ft burst area
within 120 ft of them. Unlike regular
crossbow attacks, this one is defended
with reflex instead of armor class. And
note that when a troop shrinks in size,
so does the area for this attack.
So, those are the general rules for
troops. I will say that there are not a
lot of hard rules for troops. They don't
receive as detailed a write up as one
might expect, and instead, we only have
a couple of glossery entries to guide
us. As such, there will likely be
situations you encounter that there is
no hard rule for, and we'll need to
improvise and make your best ruling as
needed. In general, my advice for these
moments is to keep it as simple as
possible and where mechanics are
involved. Treat the troops as one
creature and not focus too heavily on
the narrative presenting the troops as a
bunch of individuals. If you have any
questions, please leave them in the
comments below. And as always, I'd like
to take a moment to thank everyone out
there who supports me and this channel.
Whether that be by clicking the like
button, leaving a comment, subscribing
to the channel, or subscribing to the
Patreon. I greatly appreciate everything
you do to support me. And with that,
thanks for watching. Take care and happy
gaming.
[Music]