Hey everybody, Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you. And
today I'm just doing a little followup
to my previous video on troops. Last
week I put out one of my, you know,
regular how was played videos on the
remastered rules for troops and it
generated a lot of interesting
conversation and a lot of good
questions. And I did realize there's
maybe a point or two that in hindsight I
wish I had included in that video or or
made more clear in that video. So, I
figured I'd just do a rule reminder as a
follow-up to address a few of these
issues. Since this is following up on
that video, I do strongly encourage you
to go watch that video first, the how
it's played video about the remastered
version of troops and then continue on
with this video here. I will leave a
link to that video in the comment
section for you to click on. And um a
lot of the questions that came up seem
to stem from a a misunderstanding of how
do you target the troops and the
segments of the troops with whatever
effect, ability, spell, attack or
whatever you want to inflict upon that
troop. And so I want to try to clarify
that uh as best I can. So the first
thing you need to do is anytime uh you
are are going to attack or in any way
affect a troop, you need to think is
this a damaging effect or is this a
non-damaging effect and kind of even
think of it as as two separate tracks in
your mind because the rules of how you
target with damaging effects is
different than how you would apply the
rules for non-damaging effects. So, for
example, uh you're making a melee
strike. You're sending adjacent to the
troop. You have a sword. You're going to
spend one action to do
strike. All you have to do since this is
a damaging effect, the result of it will
be damage, is target any single square
of the troop as a whole. Doesn't matter
what segment you're attacking. You just
got to be within range of your attack as
normal to any square of the troop. And
if you hit, then that damage is going to
be applied to the troop as a whole.
There's one one bucket of hit points for
the entire troop. That's a really simple
uh example that I I I don't think is
going to confuse anybody. But then comes
the up questions of well what if I cast
a fireball spell and the fireball's area
of effect is so large that it can fit
two or more incomplete segments in that
blast. So uh if I'm hitting three
segments of the of the troop, does each
segment roll its own individual reflex
save? And if they all fail those saves,
do I then apply the fireball effect
three times? And the answer is no. When
you are dealing with a damaging effect,
fireball deals damage as a damaging
effect. then you only have to target one
square of the troop and you only treat
the defenses of the troop one time and
you only apply the damage one time for
the um for the entire troop. So
basically in most situations when you're
talking about doing a damaging effect,
you're not going to worry about segments
at all. uh only for the purposes of
determining range and cover and things
like that. But by raw, if just one
square of the troop is in the range of a
fireball, then the fireball is going to
have its total normal effect. And if the
entire troop is within the range of the
fireball, again, it's only going to
attack once. There's only going to be
one reflex save for the entire troop and
the damage and potential weaknesses to
uh area effects, all that is applied one
time. Now, I know that for a lot of
people that's counterintuitive and for a
lot of people it's like, hey, look, it
doesn't make any sense to apply the
whole damage to just, you know, just
cause one little corner, one square on
the end. Uh, and we'll talk about
situations like that in a second, but
rules as written, that's how a damaging
effect would work. So, now let's talk
about non-damaging
effects. So, non-damaging effects are
going to potentially apply to specific
segments and not to the troop as a whole
necessarily.
When you are targeting with a
non-damaging effect, you um well, the
first thing is any non-damaging effect
that only targets a single creature has
no effect at all on the troop as a on
troops period. So, if you have a
non-damaging effect, it only targets one
person. So, for example, a charm spell
that's not heightened, it only targets
one person, is not going to have any
effect at all on the troop.
In order for you to use a non-damaging
effect against a troop, it has to be
able to either target five or more
targets, five or more creatures or you
have to be able to fit all four squares
of a segment in the in the area effect
of that. So, if you had like an aura
effect, then you know, you were um
casting Bane and you had sustained it
enough that it
expanded, all of an entire segment would
have to be within that area for that to
have an effect upon it. Now, things get
a little bit weird when you start
thinking about exactly what those
effects are and how they impact things.
So, I I guess the the next thing to to
talk about is going to be the the actual
text from the rule book. And I wish I'd
included this in the uh earlier video.
Uh I talked about how this is going to
be a system where a lot of the decisions
are going to be up to the GMs. Like,
you're just going to have to make
judgment calls. You're going to have to
look at the situation and say, "I think
this makes sense or it doesn't make
sense." and just decide how you're going
to apply any of these effects. Uh
because the there's so many different
variations of so many different
conditions and so many different effects
and so many different situations of how
a troop may be oriented and how a map
may be shaped and environmental
conditions that the book really doesn't
get into uh any kind of uh by
raw coals on conditions and specific
effects. Uh instead again they give you
rules for targeting and they leave it up
to you to figure out what happens. But
this um this text says the rules for
troops especially troop defenses cover
many circumstances where it's important
that troops are not all one entity.
However, the rules can't cover every
possibility and it's best to use common
sense. And uh this is the the piece that
I wish I had included in my previous
video. If a player uses an ability you
don't think works on a troop, discuss
with that player and refund actions
spent based on mistaken
assumptions. So the rules are really
just saying, you know, like, hey,
everybody, players and GMs alike are
going to have to understand that this is
going to be up to GM interpretation to a
greater degree than what is. So try not
to, you know, say, "Oh, you took your
your hand off the chest piece. You you
said you were going to do X and too bad.
It has no effect and your turn was
wasted." Well, that's not fun for
players, that's probably not fun for the
GM either.
So the recommendation, which I think is
a good recommendation, is if the players
want to do something, they say they take
their actions to do something, and then
you process it and you decide, you know
what, that's not going to have an effect
on the troop, give them back their
actions. Let them try again. Make sure
everybody's on the same
page. So, um, a couple of different, um,
things that were put into the comments
that might be worth looking at. Uh, can
a troop be flanked? Well, okay. So,
let's think about this. Flanking, if
you're imposing flanking, if that is, is
that going to be a damaging effect or a
non-damaging effect? Well, flanking is a
non-damaging effect. Now, it could lead
to damage by making it easier for an
attack, but flanking is a non-damaging
effect. So unless you have a ability, a
spell or something that would apply
flanking or the offg guard condition to
an area or to five or more targets, then
we fall back on that rule that says that
non-damaging effects only target one
creature. The troops are immune to
those. So it has no effect at all. So in
most cases, no. Flanking is not going to
apply to a troop. Uh what about using
your athletic skill to grab somebody?
There's nothing in the rules that says
that a troop cannot be grabbed or that
is immune to the grabbed condition.
That's true, but again, what are you
using to impose grabbed, which is a
non-damaging effect on this troop? Is it
a like the athletic skill is a single
target where you're just literally
grabbing somebody? Well, uh, first of
all, common sense would say that
wouldn't impede an entire troop. But
second of all, even in the rules, single
target non-damaging effect would have no
effect at all on the troop. So, uh, no,
you can't use grab to to uh, you know,
use athletics to grab a a target. Same
thing with, you know, tripping someone
to knock them prone. But if you had some
sort of ability or spell, a quick effect
or something that would impose the prone
condition on an entire
segment, then that could work. And then
the question would be, well, what does
that do to that segment? So, anytime a
segment a an entire segment faces a
non-damaging condition or a non-damaging
effect, if that effect would prevent the
um the troop from acting uh for an
entire turn,
then you assume that is enough for that
segment to be killed. They've been
debilitated enough that they would be
wiped out by their opposing force. and
you you lower the hit points to the next
threshold. You remove one segment from
the map, which may or may not be that
specific segment depending on the
orientation. But so that's easy if
you're talking about effects that are
going to uh you know slow a target to
three actions so that they don't act on
their next turn. If it's going to
completely immobilize them for a turn so
they can't, you know, freely move and
act for an entire turn, that all makes
sense. But what about these effects that
impose
penalties but don't impede the segment
from acting? There's nothing in the book
that says that effects like that don't
work at all and there's nothing in the
effects in the text that says they work
as normal. Uh, so I would say the the
raw interpretation would be they act as
normal, but you are as a GM going to
have to figure out exactly what does
that mean for a troop. So, for example,
let's say you cast the fear spell, you
heighten it uh to a high enough rank
that it would affect an entire segment,
they failed their save, and now they're
they're facing frightened one or
frightened two um from that. Now, if you
if they critically fail on something
like that and they have to flee, then I
would say that they're not acting as
normal for an entire turn next turn and
fall back on that ruling. But if it's
just frighten one or frighten two, they
can still take all three of their
actions, but we're only talking about
one segment. So, what does this mean for
the game?
My ruling in a situation like that would
be any attacks made by the troop against
an enemy that can only be targeted by
that segment. If if if a PC is on the
map in such an orientation that only uh
that they're only in range of the troop
through that segment is affected by
fear, then I would subtract uh the
appropriate amount of fear one or two
from their attack roles uh against that
one specific player, but it wouldn't
have any effect at all on other players
who are in range of other segments that
are not affected by fear.
Same thing if uh if a PC is attacking
the troop, even though like I said
before, all you got to do is target one
square. Well, if that square happens to
belong to a segment that is affected by
fear, I would lower their reflex save
their armor class by the appropriate
amount for that attack. Uh but not
obviously for other attacks that are
targeting the troop through other
segments, if that makes any sense at
all. But
again, this is going to have to be
something that every
GM just reviews the situation and makes
their own calls. But the major thing
that I wanted to kind of get across that
I think people were getting confused in
my comments was
about damaging
effects are targeting the troop. So, it
doesn't matter how much of the troop is
in the area of the attack, it's only
going to be one attack roll against
their armor class. There's only going to
be one reflex save against your spell
DC. Uh, no matter if it's one square or
16 squares that are within range of that
effect being targeted. It is the
non-damaging effects where you have to
evaluate it on a segmentby segment basis
and each segment is going to manage
their saving throws and their defenses
individually.
Um, and so again, you as the GM, you're
going to have to make judgment calls on
what then happens. If they're not able
to function as normal for an entire
round, they're wiped out. anything short
of that, you're going to have to make a
judgment call as to how it affects. Now,
the other thing that I wanted to um to
share in the first video, and I just
forgot, I apologize, is there is a
passage in NPC core. Uh I forget the
page number, but I'll put it on the
screen somewhere for you, but there is a
special ability that is available to
troops called change formation. The I
believe the text says that this is not
um given by default to all troops of all
kinds. But if you have a military
focused troop like a failins, then they
might have other additional things they
can do with this change formation. So I
wanted to review these items with you.
So change formation uh costs two actions
and it says the troop reconfigures to
assume one of the formations below they
know. Using this action again ends any
previous formation and the troop can
also use this action to revert to its
default formation ending any benefits
and drawbacks. So it's going to take two
actions for the troop to change their
formation. And each of these formations
includes uh a benefit and a drawback. So
loose, when you do loose, members of the
troops fan out to cover more ground. The
benefit of this is that any weaknesses
that the troop has to area and splash
damage are no longer enforced, but the
enemy's saving throws against their uh
their damaging effects are one degree of
success better. So they they fan out.
They cannot be uh they do not suffer the
additional damages and weaknesses of of
of area effect and splash damage. But
because they're not tightly focused and
able to coordinate their attacks and
focus fire like they previously could,
then uh the players who are going to be
making reflex saves most likely against
damaging effects from them treat that as
one success higher.
marching column. The formation traverses
long distances more rapidly. The benefit
is the troop gains a plus 10 foot
circumstance bonus to all of its speeds.
The drawback is they suffer a negative
two penalty to reflex saves. Uh turtle
shell uh the troop interlocks their
shields only available to groups and
troops that have shields. And when they
do this, they gain a plus two
circumstance bonus to armor class
against ranged attacks and reflex saves.
but the troop moves slower at a -10 ft
penalty to all the speeds. I can see the
this turtle shell probably being the
most common of these formations I would
probably use in my games. It makes a lot
of sense. It's very thematic and it's
frankly kind of cool. Uh then you have
the wedge formation. The troop aligns
itself behind a powerful commander. The
troop chooses an adjacent allied
creature without the troop trait to fall
in behind. Each time the chosen creature
strides, the troop follows as a free
action, striding to keep the chosen
creature adjacent. Drawback, the troop
loses some of their autonomy, their
slowed one, and cannot voluntarily move
away from their leader. So again,
another very thematic thing. You have
the leader, the commander of the army,
and they've got a formation of their
troops following behind them. And this
makes sense to me. they're losing
essentially one action on the troop's
turn be to be able to freely move with
their commander. Um, so pretty cool. So
again, uh, these are four special
effects that can be applied to some
troops if the GM decides that they are a
military focused troop and are available
through the change formation ability. So
that is it. I I hope I have cleared up
some of the the thoughts and potential
miscon misconceptions about troops in
this video. Uh I apologize if I've just
made things more confusing, but if you
do have questions, please leave them in
the comments below. And as always, I
want to take a quick moment to say thank
you to all of you folks out there who
support me and this channel by clicking
the like button, subscribing to the
channel, subscribing to the Patreon,
buying a super thanks. I really
appreciate everything you folks do to
support me. And with that, thanks for
watching. Take care and happy gaming.
[Music]