Hey everybody, Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you. And in
this one, I'm just going to address a
couple of similar questions that were
posted to video comments in the last
week or so. Both of which deal with uh
how do you determine if an item is
available for sale in a given community?
How do you determine if a player can can
purchase a certain thing that they want?
And um you know, how does this all work?
what are the mechanics involved and
players wishing to purchase some new
magic items with their hardearned gold.
And um I'm just going to say up front
that there's not a whole lot of really
really really
concrete guidance. A lot of this is left
up to the GM to make decisions and
interpretations for what makes sense for
for their game and the kind of tone they
want to strike and where in their world
uh this particular proposed purchase is
going to take place and so on. But there
is some guidance in the GM core book and
uh really comes down to two major
considerations and a handful of minor
considerations. So the major
considerations are going to be
settlement level and rarity. So the
general rule of thumb is if a player
wishes to purchase an item that is of an
item level equal to or lower than the
settlement level of the place that
they're wanting to purchase this uh and
it is common rarity, then there's a
pretty good chance they're going to be
able to source and purchase that item.
Um, it's not entirely fair to say that
it's a guarantee because there are a
couple of things we'll talk about in uh
in just a minute, but the the sort of
first layer or first criteria you should
be thinking about is what is the item
level compared to the settlement level
and what is its rarity? If it is of an
item level equal to or lesser than the
settlement level and it is common
rarity, good chance they're going to be
able to find it somewhere in that
settlement and purchase it.
Now, uh the reason why I say that uh
it's not a guarantee that it's going to
be available there is because there is
um a piece of guidance that's provided
in GM Core and was previously in the
game mastery guide that I think a lot of
people overlook and that is that there
is a cap placed on the highest level
items, the number of highest level items
available in any given settlement.
So, it's not like if you walk into a
sixth level city that literally every
single common rarity magic item of sixth
level or lower is sitting on store
shelves waiting for you to buy them.
What it does, what the the guidance is,
is that you take a look at the uh the
party treasure table that is on page 59
of GM Core and you take one level lower
than the settlement's level and that
tells you how many of the highest level
items are available in that settlement.
Uh so if you are in a sixth level city,
you look at the the column for permanent
uh magic items and consumable items and
you look at fifth level cuz that's one
less than the settlement level and it
says uh sixth level two and fifth level
two for permanent
items. That means not every sixth level
common rarity magic item and fifth level
common rarity magic item is going to be
available for sale in this community.
means two sixth level items are going to
be available and two fifth level items
are. And then at at level four and
below, those are considered so
insignificant that uh it should be easy
to find and source one of those items in
the
settlement. But you are placing limits
on the highest level items, the number
of highest level items available in each
uh
settlement. Now, generally, even though
they refer to this
table, most of the time it's it's going
to work out as being any settlement has
at most two items of it of a settlement
level, two items of its level minus one
for permanent items. And for
consumables, there's another layer that
goes down three levels or two levels
below the settlement level and is capped
at two consumable items of that level as
well. Uh, so that might make it easier
than referring to this table all the
time. Now, there are some other things
to consider. Uh, what if the item that
you're wanting to find is not common
rarity? Uh, the book doesn't
provide hard
uh hard mechanics for finding items that
are not common. Uh, again, this is going
to be up to the GM, but the guidance
that they that they do give you is that
common rarity items are typically gated
behind something. They might be gated
behind uh a certain ancestry that is
fond of making these items. They could
be gated behind belonging to a specific
faction. They could be gated behind a
particular nationality. They could be
gated behind a lore skill. Maybe only
people who are um expert level lore in a
particular magical tradition would even
know that such a thing exists and uh
would would have a an ability to to find
and source uh those particular items.
But when you think about the um the
access requirements to these uncommon
items is is might be a good guideline to
not just think about um does the
player's character meet an access
requirement or does the settlement
itself meet that requirement. So, um, if
you have an elven character and they are
proficient with elven marshall weapons
and they want to go by a plus one
striking, uh, elven curved
blade, if they're in a a predominantly
human settlement, this might be
considered or probably would be
considered an uncommon item, but they
might be able to uh to rely on their
familiarity to start conversation ations
to find uh an an elven bartender who was
a retired adventurer and talk to them
and say, "Hey, can I buy that blade off
you?" Something like that. Um it's just
not going to be uncommon items are just
not going to be freely available
typically to everybody in the settlement
unless the settlement itself meets the
criteria for the access. So, if this was
an an predominantly elven community, uh,
then elven curve blades are probably
available at every blacksmith. So, when
you think about these access
requirements, um, or access guidelines
for uncommon items, be sure to look at
it from both perspectives, the
individual and but also the community
itself. What makes sense that they would
have access
to? There is new rule that says you in
order to source an uncommon item, you
have to pass a gather information skill
check or a lure score skill check of a
DC equal to the item level of the item
and so on and so
forth. If a GMs will want to run a game
that way, perfectly welcome, well within
your rights. Uh and I and I have seen
online some people say that they do
similar
things but just understand that is not a
official rule that is you know coded
into the DNA of Pathfinder second
edition the way systems like that are
coded into other uh other role playing
games. Now when we talk about uh rare or
even unique items then the criteria to
source and find and purchase these
things get even steeper. Uh so common
items if it's you know you're you're if
it's common rarity and you're at the
sediment level or lower for the item
level then you have a pretty good chance
of finding it. uncommon. You're going to
have to have some sort of special
access, jump through some minor hoops,
and but when we get into rare, these are
going to be items that ideally should be
tied into the narrative of the game. Uh,
very very infrequently, I almost said
very rarely, but I guess very
infrequently, should a person just be
able to go into a settlement and just
buy a a a rare item, unless there's
special circumstances. Uh, if a player
wants just says that they're looking for
a particular rare item, either tie that
into the narrative, tie that in the
story, give them a quest that they have
to complete to get access to that item.
something like that. Um, it shouldn't
getting a rare item should be a major
event. It shouldn't be a purely
transactional event the way that
purchasing common items and even some
uncommon items would be. Now, some of
the other little considerations you
might want to think about is the
player's level. If the player's
character level is higher than the
settlement level, then they might have a
degree of fame, reputation, influence in
that community that could that could be
used to give a narrative explanation as
to why people in that community are more
likely to part with things uh in and and
and sell them something of a higher
level than they normally would, which
could be justification for why a tenth
level characters able to source a
seventh level magic item in a sixth
level settlement, something of that
sort. And also keep in mind that when
the book talks about these
rules, they're referring to a very
standard sort of generic general
community settlement.
And it's up to you as the GM to apply
modifications to what's available there
according to like what's their trade,
what are their major imports and
exports, where are they located, things
of that nature. So, as a GM, you very
much should be willing to bend some of
these rules a little bit uh in favor of
what you envision would make sense for
each of those communities.
As far as official guidance that I've
seen in the book, that pretty much
covers all the official guidance, but
there's probably a few other linkering
questions that uh might be worthwhile
just taking a look at. Just keep in mind
from here on out, we're not talking
about official game rules or official
guidance to the rules. This is mostly uh
my opinion, my take, and perhaps some
things I've seen discussed online as
well that's worked for for other people.
So, the number one question after
hearing that you're capped at only two
magic items of the settlement level and
two magic items of the settlement level
minus one is how do you determine what
those items
are? So, uh again, no official guidance
for this. Uh but could just be the GM
could, you know, GM could just say, you
know what, I think this item and this
item makes sense. that's what they're
going to be. It could be items that are
thematically tied to the settlement. Uh,
this is a traditionally dwarven
settlement. So, I'm going to make sure
that uh that the the two settlement
level equal items are items that have
the dwarven trait cuz they're more
likely to be there. Uh, you can also
just, you know, make it easy. Uh, these
are often very transactional moments.
And like I said, as long as it's not
like a rare item, it probably isn't
something that's that's that's really
tightly integrated into the story. This
is is just so so transactional. Just
have the players decide. You It could be
the first two items that the players ask
for, those just happen to be the items.
Or it could be have your players make
their wish list. And then when they have
their wish list, you look at it and you
say, "Okay, you you've selected four
sixlevel items and this is a sixle
settlement. They're only going to have
two of these. Now, which of these two do
you want?" Uh, and and put it into their
hands. Now, I agree not entirely
realistic and may great a little bit on
immersions just to say, "Hey, whatever,
you know, the two items that you wanted,
they happen to be here." But again, I
personally in my games find these
moments to be very transactional in
nature. I think the number one um
barrier to to prevent players from, you
know, just getting whatever they want
whenever they want is the cost of the
items. And frankly, a lot of times they
can't afford whatever would be an equal
level of that settlement unless they're
higher level characters visiting a lower
level settlement. Um, so if it's common
already, I I'm I'm usually cool with
just letting them buy whatever and not
worry about the caps as long as they got
the money for it. But um, again, those
caps are the official
guidance. Another thing that you could
do to determine what those uh those
limited items are in a community is to
use some kind of random loot generator.
Uh, there's several online. I I do not
know them well enough to really endorse
any of them and say that I use them
because I don't know like, you know, how
vast their loot tables are and how they
uh how rarity influences their results
and so on and so forth. So, I'm not
going to name any, but if you go into
Google and you just type Pathfinder
second edition uh loot tables random
loot generator, something like that,
you'll you'll you'll
find. So, another question that might
come up that's not addressing the rules
is when do the the these two limited
items per level of the Sodomus level and
the level beneath it, when do those get
refreshed? So, my players go in and they
they they buy all four of those limited
items in a settlement. When can they
come back and, you know, have the the
store shelves refilled, so to speak, and
buy more? Uh, no guidance to that. Uh I
think uh easy recommendations would be
after a major story milestone, they
would have uh more items available for
sale within the settlement uh or after a
significant amount of downtime the next
time the players have a week of
downtime, then that might be an
opportunity to sort of refresh what is
available and let them do some more some
more higher level shopping in that
community. Uh, another question uh that
comes up is like where are these things
sold? And like like one of the the
comments that kind of generated um this
video was some one of the comments was
very tongue and cheek but was like do
you just walk into Runes or Us to buy a
rune?
And the answer to that is
maybe probably not literally runes
areas, but um higher level settlements,
I mean like Golarian and the Pathfinder
setting is is a is a high fantasy
setting. It's a it's a high magic
fantasy setting and uh in higher level
settlements here larger cities and
metropolises there certainly are uh
businesses that deals probably solely in
the purchase and sell and trade of
magical items. Uh now is it is it going
to have literally runes or us? Probably
not, but it could be uh melik runes and
magical curiosities something like that.
uh where you would go in and you would
purchase your magic runes. Uh smaller
settlements probably don't have enough
magic trade business to to necessitate
an entire, you know, magic shop, but
there's other ways to source magic items
in even the smaller villages and so
forth. Uh you know, you you might have
to talk to the local wizard and see what
what uh they've got in their possession.
could find again uh former adventurers
who have retired to the community and
have you know pieces of gear that
they're willing to part with. It could
be you know blacksmiths, armormiths, you
know any kind of trades person or guild
would uh be a good place to go to uh
source anything that they would be able
to craft.
And
so there there certainly is an an area
within the narrative where you would go
to so-called magic shops. And there's
other settings where either because of
the size of the settlement or because of
the culture or nationality wouldn't do
that.
Um, it's also worth to keep in mind that
when they talk about what's available,
they're talking about what's available
across the entire settlement, not what's
available at any one given store. So,
it's not like you walk into one store
and they've got every common rarity
magic item of level one to level four
and then two level fives and two level
sixes. It's in that entire city. those
items can be found spread out wherever
makes the most logical
sense. Now, for me, in my games, for
whatever it's worth, I tend to use
churches as um as a
major a major resource for the the
buying and selling and trade of magic
items, especially the churches of Abidor
and Nephis. Uh these are places that are
going to have you know an interest in in
buying magic items which in general you
you sell player sell at 50%. Um and
there's also a general cap that you
shouldn't be selling items of a higher
settlement level than the settlements
level because there's not people in that
settlement who you know a seventh level
settlement doesn't have the funds to buy
15th level magical items from players.
But anyway,
um I use churches. Uh I I think Abbidar
is always interested in trade and making
money and also they've got, you know,
especially in their cities, they got
vaults. So you would think things that
are as valuable as magical items aren't
just sitting on store shelves anyway.
They're in a vault somewhere. And Nethos
has an interest in magic. Um, so I use
churches often to to manage the uh the
buying and selling a trade of magical
items. Again, that's just me what I do
with my games. There's nothing official
in the um in the rules about that. Um,
another question, I guess I kind of
touched on this a little bit already,
which was, are there any mechanics
involved in in finding a seller? So, if
you want to purchase that uncommon
rarity item or you want to try to source
something that is one level higher than
the settlements level and you're a
higher level character, um, what are the
rules to do that? There's really not a
lot of hard rules to do this. Um, it's
going to be up to the GM to decide, you
know, how crunchy and how mechanical
they want to get. Uh, gather
information. Skill checks could be used.
lower skill checks could be used, modify
those according to
rarity. But if you do that, I would
advise that you you as the GM need to
decide, is this something that actually
exists in this settlement? And if they
pass the skill checks, then they're able
to track down the person who has that
item. um and not turn this into if you
pass the skill
check, that item magically is going to
be available for sale in the community.
Uh I know it can be a downer to pass a
skill check and then say despite your
best efforts, you're not able to source
that here. Uh but you don't want to get
into a situation where a player that has
really high skill bonus and or really
good luck with the dice is able to
source just like anything. I would view
this like a perception check. you roll
really high on a perception check and if
there's some and if there's a goblin
hiding in the corner, you spot them. But
if there's not a goblin hiding in the
corner, it doesn't matter how high you
roll on a perception check, you don't
see anything there, right? Same thing
with using gather information and lord
checks to track down and source. Decide,
does this actually exist in the
community? And if so, use those skills
to perceive it, to find it, uh, and not
to determine whether or not a a rare
magical item is is available. So, that
covers all of the basic general
information with regards to uh,
purchasing magical items in a
settlement. To to sum up, use rarity,
use settlement level, compare to the
item level. with the item level is
common rarity and of a level equal to or
lower than the settlement, there's a
good chance it's going to be there. And
the book advises placing a cap on two
permanent magical items of the
settlements level and two magical items
that is one level beneath the
settlements level. Uh, and then uncommon
items could be available if you have
access to them by meeting some other
requirement or if the GM wishes. and
rare magical items, you really want to
have a a narrative significance. So, tie
those into the story, assign a quest to
find them, something of that sort. If
you have any questions about the
purchasing of magical items in
Pathfinder second edition, or if you
have uh any insight on any rules that I
may have missed, please leave those in
the comments below. And as always, I
want to take a moment to say thank you
to everybody out there who supports me.
Whether that be by clicking the like
button, subscribing to the channel,
subscribing to the Patreon, buying a
super thanks. I really appreciate
everything you folks do to support me.
With that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[Music]