Hey everybody, Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you. And
today we're going to be looking at
non-lethal damage. So non-lethal damage
is an option in the rules that allow you
to make attacks with the intent to
disable your opponent as opposed to kill
them. Because this is a high fantasy
actionoriented
adventure role playing game, the default
rules in the game uh assume lethal
damage. It assumes that you are trying
to kill the goblin or dragon or manticor
or whatever that uh your party is
facing. But it does provide non-lethal
damage options for those who want to
subdue their targets. So, you might want
to use non-lethal damage when you want
to capture somebody and question them if
you're a bounty hunter and you're going
to get paid more to bring your target
back alive than dead or you're in any
kind of situation where you don't want
things to escalate. So, instead of of
killing the town's people, you subdue
them with non-lethal damage or maybe for
those times when uh one of your party
members gets controlled or goes mad and
uh you got to you got to put them down
without killing them. These are all
situations where you might want to use
non-lethal damage instead of the regular
lethal damage uh rules. So, what does
this mean when you use non-lethal
damage? Well, in the the the the vast
range of combat, it doesn't mean a lot.
It really only comes down to the last
hit that reduces your target to zero hit
points. If that is dealt using lethal
damage, then in most cases, they die. Or
if they're a significant uh NPC or a
player character, they fall unconscious
and they gain the dying condition.
That's lethal damage. the normal damage
rules. If that final hit that reduces
them to zero hit points is made with
non-lethal damage, then instead they
just fall unconscious.
Uh this does not impose the dying
condition. You don't have to make
recovery checks. This does not interact
in any way with the wounded condition.
You don't gain the wounded condition or
elevate it when you leave an unconscious
state. If that last hit is dealt with
non-lethal damage, then no dying
condition, no wounded condition, no
recovery checks, essentially they fall
unconscious, they gain the unconscious
condition, they have zero hit points,
and they're effectively stable. Again,
none of these recovery checks. There's
no hard rule for how long they stay in
that unconscious state, but if they
receive any healing and they go above
zero hit points, they would become
conscious again. And in absence of that,
it it like I said, it doesn't give you a
hard guideline. It just says like about
a minute or so. Uh basically that's you
know that's Pathfinder language for when
this combat encounter is over they'll
regain consciousness normally. As always
GMs evaluate the situation however makes
sense to you. So some situations might
cause you to to prolong that unconscious
state because again there's not a hard
rule. That's just the guidance in the
book. One minute. So how do you deal
non-lethal damage? Some weapons, some
melee weapons have the non-lethal trait.
And if a weapon has the non-lethal
trait, like a fist attack, most unarmed
attacks that aren't things like biting
and claws, uh the sap, a whip, these all
have the non-lethal trait. Non-lethal
trait weapons always deal non-lethal
damage unless you do something special.
So monks can deal lethal damage with
their unarmed attacks, but in absence of
any other ability, rule, special
circumstance, non-lethal weapons,
weapons with the non-lethal trait deal
exclusively
non-lethal damage.
Um, so,
uh, for some people it might make sense
that they carry one lethal weapon and
one non-lethal weapon. If you're someone
who's playing like a bounty hunter and
you think you're going to be uh dealing
a lot of non-lethal damage, you might
want to invest in like a shifting rune
for your weapon, so you can convert it
between uh similar weapons that either
deal lethal damage or non-lethal damage.
The bounty hunter archetype also has a
feat called tools of the trade that
would allow you to do an additional 1d4
precision damage with certain specific
weapons that have the non-lethal trait.
So that might be something you're
looking for if you want to do this
non-lethal damage. And the same is going
to be true for spells. A a very very few
spells have the non-lethal trait, but
there are a few primarily days and
phantom pain. Both of those spells have
the non-lethal trait and deal non-lethal
damage. Uh, and so that would work just
like making a non-lethal damage attack
with a non-lethal weapon. If if the
damage imposed by days or phantom pain
reduces a target to zero hit points,
they would fall unconscious and not get
the dying condition. And although it's
not strictly spelled out, I don't
believe I at least I haven't seen it
strictly spelled out, I believe the
possible persistent damage that is
provided by phantom paint would also be
non-lethal.
Uh, so those are the primary ways of
dealing non-lethal damage with a weapon
with a non-lethal trait that's designed
to do non-lethal damage. Your sap, your
fist, a whip, or with spells that have
the non-lethal trait, days, phantom
pain, and there might be a few others
that I'm not aware of.
Now, that doesn't mean that you can't
also make a non-lethal attack with a
traditional standard lethal weapon.
Any regular weapon, be it a mace, an
axe, a long sword, whatever, a long bow,
can deal non-lethal damage if you are
willing to take a -2 circumstance
penalty to that attack.
So, this could be you've got your sword
and so slashing with your your blade.
You're going to take a pommel and you're
going to smack someone in the forehead
with the pommel in hopes of knocking
them unconscious. That might be one way
that you do a non-lethal damage attack
while using a long sword. Uh the damage
itself is not changed. It would do the
same damage as normal. it would have a
negative two circumstance penalty to the
attack because you're using your weapon
in a way that it was not designed to be
used. Sort of like making an improvised
attack, an improvised weapon attack. But
if it hits, it does the exact same
damage. It just has the non-lethal
trait. And if that's the hit that lowers
the target to zero hit points, it would
not kill them. It would knock them
unconscious. Axe, turn it sideways, use
the flat of the blade, smack somebody in
the head, and so on.
Um, it's worth mentioning that there are
a couple of feats that grant a better
access to making non-lethal attacks with
regular weapons. Uh, I know
investigators can take the take down
expert feat that lets them make or lets
them deal non-lethal damage with pretty
much all of their weapon attacks without
suffering that negative two penalty. And
uh gladiators uh the gladiator archetype
can take the stage fighting feat that
does basically the same thing. List them
make non-lethal damage attacks with
regular weapons without suffering the -2
penalty. Also, it may be worth
mentioning that the opposite is kind of
true. You can take a non-lethal weapon
and deal lethal damage with it by
suffering a negative two penalty. So, if
you've got a sap and you want to deal
lethal damage with it, you can do so.
You suffer a negative two penalty, but
you uh but you deal lethal damage and
you could potentially kill somebody with
that strike. I would say like, you know,
you're you're taking the negative2
penalty because you're specifically
trying to hit them in the throat with
it. Something like that would be the
narrative explanation for why that that
works. Now, there is no such provision.
uh there is no such broad provision for
spells. So even though you can take a a
long sword and suffer a negative -2
penalty to deal non-lethal damage with
it, you cannot just take a negative -2
penalty to a spell that makes a spell
attack and turn it into non-lethal
damage. But uh there are some things you
can do which we'll talk about in just a
moment. So I also want to talk a little
bit about immunity to non-lethal damage.
Some creatures, especially things like
golems, have immunity to non-lethal
damage. And the example in the book is
is basically it doesn't matter how hard
you're punching a tank with your bare
fist, you're not going to deal, you
know, you're not going to incapacitate
it, right? And that's basically the
immunity that uh creatures like
constructs that specifically have
immunity to non-lethal damage. um
the the benefit that they have. You're
you're you're never going to kill an
iron golem by punching it with
non-lethal damage. If you want to uh
destroy the constructs with lethal
damage, you would have to suffer the
negative -2 penalty to turn your
non-lethal attacks lethal or use regular
lethal weapons and lethal means. Now, uh
there are a number of different
questions. Um, some of these came from
uh one of my patrons. So, as always,
thank you everybody out there who
supports me through my Patreon. And uh I
think one or two of them I also noticed
just from research on the net. But let's
take a look at some of these uh
questions that come up. Can a spell
without the non-lethal trait be made
non-lethal? Again, no. Not there's not
like a blanket rule like there is with
with weapons being used to do non lethal
damage, but there is a wizard feat
called the non-lethal spell feat that uh
it takes one action, you cast it, and if
the following action is to cast a spell
that does not have the the death or void
traits, then that uh spell gains the
non-lethal trait and deals non-lethal
damage.
So, um, this could turn your force
barrage, the oldfashioned magic missile,
maybe they're now stunbolts. You've
customized the spell as you're casting
it by spinning an extra action. Uh, you
know, some people say, "Well, wait a
second. What about fireball? How do you
turn a fireball non-lethal?" Well, maybe
the fireball becomes a concussive blast
with a bright bright light. It no longer
does lethal damage, but it's basically a
giant modern-day flashbang, you know,
that that police might use to clear a
room uh and stun people in it before
they come in. Uh you're you're you're
adjusting and changing the the magic
involved, the weave and the magic and
the spell wire, casting of that extra
direction to make it non-lethal. This
this may be a situation where you have
to lean a little bit on roleplaying the
result, see what the result of the spell
is, and then tailor the narrative to fit
that. But mechanically,
uh, you know, like would the fireball
still do fire damage? By raw,
mechanically, yes. It's still doing fire
damage. It's just doing non-lethal fire
damage. Now, what mental gymnastics has
to go along in the narrative to make
sense of that is going to be up to the
GM and the players to figure out. Uh me,
I probably would no longer call it fire
damage. You know, I would, like I said,
I would say it's a concussive blast with
a bright light or whatever. That would
still do the same thing. The only the
only problem would be if uh you're using
that fireball to deal non-lethal damage
against a target that is weak to fire.
Uh in those cases, they would still take
the their weakness would still be
triggered. They would still take that
extra damage. Um but and it is still
fire damage. It's just non-lethal.
So, I I'm I'm the first to say that
there's there may be some some give and
take between, you know, the players and
the GM to figure figure out what makes
most sense in the narrative to make this
work. But rules is written. What the
rules say is that it just gains the
non-lethal trait. And all that
non-lethal trait means is if you reduce
the target to zero, then they fall
unconscious instead of dying. everything
else is the same. Still fire damage,
still triggers fire weaknesses or
whatever. Um, it just would not kill
somebody. But I agree, you may have to
do a little bit of a little bit of work
to figure out how to make that work in
the narrative. Um, likewise, there's the
question about like the disintegrate
spell. So, what happens here? Um,
can you use the uh wizard's uh
non-lethal spell feat to cast a
non-lethal disintegrate spell? Yeah, you
can. So, what happens when that reduces
a person to to zero hit points? Does it
turn them to dust like it says in the
description of the spell, or do they
just fall unconscious?
Personally, as a GM, I would I would
lean on whatever the cer's intent is. If
a player spends the effort to make their
disintegrate spell non-lethal,
I I I would just have it knock the
person out. You know, it is clear that
that is what they're trying to
accomplish. Let's not penalize them for
rolling too well. Um if if if they're
taking the time to spend the extra
action on that feed to make it
non-lethal, just let it knock them out.
But as always, uh, GMs are always going
to have the final call and the final
rule, and they may rule differently. Uh,
I also want to mention that, uh, in the
Agents of Edge adventure path, there is
a blanket rule that basically says that
the assumption in this campaign is that
players are doing non-lethal damage as
opposed to the regular assumption that
they're doing lethal damage. So, in that
adventure path, because the players are
supposed to be city guards who have had
extra training on how to subdue and
capture their targets,
all of their damage, even spell damage,
even poison damage, all damage period,
is non-lethal.
And again, that's another place where
you might have to do some work and some
give and take to to figure out exactly
how within the narrative that works. But
that's the rule. Uh that is not a feat
that people outside of that campaign can
just take. But GMs just know like
there's a precedent that exists for just
having a blanket statement that says I
allow you to deal non-lethal damage
without any penalties, without anything
else. And that is found in the agents of
edge watch adventure path specifically.
It's in the players guide. Um, also, uh,
kind of adjacent to regular
spellcasting, uh, kineticists at fourth
level can take a feat called safe
elements that gives them the pacifying
infusions action that works very much
the same way as the wizard's non-lethal
spell feat. They spend that action and
then that turns their next impulse into
a non-lethal damaging ability.
So, another question that comes up is,
what if 99% of the damage is lethal? So,
we've been we've been stabbing this this
this target with swords and then someone
walks up with their bare knuckle fist
and punches them and that does
non-lethal damage and that's the final
hit that reduces them to zero. Um, does
it make sense for them to fall
unconscious when prior to that we've
been stabbing them repeatedly?
So, a lot of that's going to come down
to, you know, again, how you manage the
the narration, how you describe these
things in the narrative. Uh, a couple
things to be aware of. Pathfinder second
edition has tried to streamline rules
and make them as easy as possible with
the understanding that there is a
living, breathing GM there who can
intervene and say, but in this case, I
don't think that rule is going to apply
or this is how we're going to twist it.
That's the direction they've gone with
second edition as opposed to having a
lot of uh a lot of extra bookkeeping.
Like I I believe in in Pathfinder first
edition, you had to keep track of how
much damage was lethal and how much
damage was non-lethal. And there you had
to keep track of those two totals and
non-lethal damage healed at a faster
rate than than lethal damage. And
there's all these different rules that
doesn't exist in second edition.
By raw, all that matters is that last
hit that lowers them to zero hit points.
Um, so what happens if you do 99% of the
damage lethal and the last 1%
non-lethal?
The same as if you had done all the
damage as non-lethal. They fall
unconscious instead of dying by raw. Um,
also keep in mind that hit points hit
points don't represent how much blood is
in your body. Hit points represent your
ability to avoid dying.
So that 99% of lethal damage could have
been represented by you ducking,
dodging, taking minor cuts, uh
exhausting yourself by constantly having
to parry away a an otherwise lethal
attack at the very last second. And that
that exhausts you and wears you down.
Uh, so a lot of it comes down to how you
are describing the damage within the
narration. If you've been describing it
as you're literally running the person
through with a sword 20 times leading up
to that last hit, that's a little
different.
But, uh, bottom line, official rule, all
that matters is that very last hit. And
again, GMs can choose to rule
differently. There may be situations
where you say, well, this person
suffered all this lethal damage and the
last hit was non-lethal.
find a way to work with your players. Uh
maybe you say, "Yeah, they fall
unconscious,
but if you don't do something to
stabilize them within three rounds or
whatever you you think makes sense
within the narrative you've constructed,
they're going to start bleeding out and
suffer the dying condition." Um, that's
not a hard and fast rule. Again, these
are things that you can think about as a
GM to kind of find that balance between
the two extremes of the lethal damage
and the non-lethal situations. Another
question that uh comes up is what about
um energy damage? Uh you know, it makes
sense that if I'm pommel striking
somebody with my um with my sword that
it does non-lethal damage, but what if
I'm making a non-lethal attack with my
flaming sword? What happens there?
Again,
just like with the earlier example of of
a non-lethal fireball, the same true for
a flaming sword or an electrified sword
or whatever, the damage becomes
non-lethal. It still deals fire damage.
If you critically hit it, it can still
do persistent fire damage. All of this
damage is just nonlethal.
All that mean, and that doesn't mean
anything at all, except if that damage
reduces the target to zero, they fall
unconscious instead of dying. Um, that's
the RAW as usual. GMs, you can play with
that however you want. Um, but just be
aware that that is the official RAW
ruling. Uh, and another question that
comes up is, okay, so I can make a
non-lethal attack with a a weapon by
suffering a negative two circumstance
penalty. Okay, I can see that with again
the long sword doing the pommel strike.
You can see that with taking the battle
axe, turning on the side, and smacking
somebody with the flat of the blade
instead of the edge of the blade. But
how am I making a non-lethal attack with
my long bow?
So, uh this is another one of those
areas where you might want to have to
lean in a little bit to um to uh
roleplaying the result, see what the
result is, and then tweaking the
narrative to match that result.
Maybe that arrow
uh didn't shoot the target. Maybe it
instead cut through a rope that's
holding a big wooden uh chandelier-l
like handle holder that drops on the
target's head and knocks them
unconscious. Uh maybe that arrow uh
strikes their helmet in such a way where
the the arrow head does not penetrate
the skin, but it has enough force to
knock that helmet against their head and
concuss them. or you know, maybe it you
hit them in such a way that they stumble
back and knock their head against
something.
Again, this is an area where it's going
to take give and take between the GM and
the players to craft a narrative
explanation that makes sense, and GMs
are 100% free to play with this however
they wish.
uh they can rule that you can't do
non-lethal damage in certain situations,
but again, these are what the official
rules as written say. Okay, so that was
my uh look at non-lethal damage. Uh if
you have any questions about that,
please let me know in the comments
below. If you have any other situations
where you've encountered a need for
non-lethal damage in your games and had
uh to craft these fun little narratives
to figure out the explanation, share
those stories as well. We'd love to hear
from you. And as always, I want to take
a moment to say thank you to everybody
out there who supports me. Whether it's
by leaving those comments, clicking the
like button, subscribing to the channel,
subscribing to the Patreon like the good
person who sent me this uh initial
question. I appreciate everything you
folks do to support me. And with that,
thanks for watching. Take care and happy
gaming.
[Music]