Hello and welcome to skirmish encounters
in Pathfinder second edition remastered.
Skirmish encounters revolve around troop
combat. So it's highly recommended that
you watch my video on troops if you
haven't already as those rules are
necessary to understanding skirmishes
and I will not be covering all of the
troop rules in detail again here.
Skirmish encounters allow players to
take part in larger battles with dozens
or more combatants on each side of the
conflict without sacrificing their sense
of individuality at the game table. This
is not a full mass combat or war scale
system where the players look down on
the battlefield from a bird's eyee view
above, but instead puts them on the
battlefield itself and in command of
troops. Simply put, troops are large
groups of creatures that work together.
Although a troop is made up of lots of
smaller individuals, it mechanically
functions as a single large creature
with one stat block, sort of like a
swarm, but usually made of larger, more
intelligent creatures. In a typical
skirmish encounter, each player is
placed in command of their own troop.
So, if you have four players, you will
likely also have four troops, each one
controlled by a different player. And
not just mechanically speaking, within
the narrative, each player's character
has command of their own troop with the
members of that troop following their
orders. Establishing leadership of a
troop takes at least 10 minutes. And if
they spend a full day of downtime
together, they form a special skirmish
bond, which we'll talk about a little
bit later.
The skirmish encounter rules are
abstracted to a larger degree than the
usual combat rules, but function in much
the same way. When commanding a troop,
the player and the troop they command
combined together. The player character
is treated as if they are occupying all
of the troops spaces and segments
simultaneously. They can make attacks,
calculate range, determine cover, and so
on from any single space within the
troops area.
They need to choose which space they are
in to take an action like strike, but
they are only locked into that space for
the purposes of that one action. For
example, a troop's leader can spin an
action to make an attack from one space
within a troop's area and then spin
their next action to make another attack
from a square on the other side of the
troop or even in a different segment.
And note that this means emanation
abilities affect things within range
from one specific square of the troop
and do not extend outward from all of
the troop spaces.
Together, the PC leader and their troop
get five actions and two reactions each
round, which are divided into two sets.
One set has three actions and one
reaction, and the other set has two
actions and one reaction. Each turn, the
player decides how to allocate these
sets between the troop and its leader.
So, one round, the leader might have
three actions and the troop two actions,
and the next round the troop might have
three actions and the leader too.
Regardless, the leader and the troop
will always have one reaction of their
own. Any effect that adjusts the
creature's number of actions is applied
separately. For example, if a leader and
the troop are both subject to the
quickened condition, they each gain an
extra action. And the same would apply
if they are both slowed. They would each
lose an action.
Any move action a troop or leader takes
moves the entire unit. If the leader
spins an action to stride, then the
entire group moves even if the leader
speed score is higher than the troops.
And the same is true if the troop spins
an action to stride. It would move up to
its speed score and the leader would
move along with it. Again, because the
leader is occupying all of its same
spaces simultaneously. That said, the GM
is expected to manage this if the
differences in speed are great or the
leader has a mode of movement that the
troop doesn't, such as flight. And to
keep movement somewhat in check, no more
than three actions worth of their five
actions can be used to move the group in
one turn. This includes both move
actions like stride and activities that
include move actions. For example, if a
troop was led by a barbarian and that
leader used sudden charge, which doesn't
include the move trait itself, but does
cause the user to strike twice, the
group could only use one more action to
move during their turn. But that one
action could come from either the
barbarian leader or from their troop.
And if an ability lets the troop and its
leader move outside of their turn, the
unit can usually move only once. For
example, if they move because of a
reaction or because of a commander's
tactic that lets several squadmates
move, the leader in the troop could only
benefit from this one time because they
are one unit. And another note related
to movement. If a skirmish encounter
begins unexpectedly, for example, if the
players are taken by surprise, the
leader is automatically moved to their
troops space.
As mentioned earlier, if a leader spends
a full day of downtime working with and
drilling with their troop, they can form
a special bond. After one day of
downtime, the leader can select one
skirmish bond they meet the
prerequisites for and can change this
bond to a new one after another day of
downtime. For example, a leader who has
expert proficiency with a weapon could
select the combo attack bond. If they're
leading a Goblin Rabble troop, then any
enemy they hit with an attack will
suffer a negative one penalty when
saving against the goblin rabbles dog
pile attack. Or a leader who is expert
in diplomacy, intimidation, or
performance might choose desperate
fervor to inspire their troop when the
chips are down. And members of the
commander class have a special skirmish
bond available to them called under
command. This allows the commander to
treat the troop as one of their
squadmates and also allows the troop to
use their offensive abilities whenever
the commander's tactics call for a
strike.
When an enemy uses an effect that
targets a single creature, for example,
most melee attacks, the attacker chooses
if they wish to target the troop or the
player character leading the troop and
then resolves the effect as normal. And
again, the leader is considered to be
occupying all the same spaces as the
troop they lead simultaneously.
So all the enemy needs to be able to do
is target any one of the troop spaces,
regardless of whichever space was most
recently used to manage that leader's
actions. And since the leader and their
troop mechanically function as one
unified group, the troop does not grant
cover when an enemy attacks the leader,
nor does the troop impose cover on the
leader attacks. And this includes
situations where the leader is mounted
within a troop. The mount does not grant
lesser cover to their rider as it does
usually. Likewise, a leader cannot flink
with their own troop because they are
again one and the same. But if two
different troops are on opposite sides
or edges of an enemy, their leaders do
get flanking benefits. And if the leader
has a minion, such as an animal
companion, familiar, or summoned
creature, they also occupy the same
spaces as the troop, just like the
troop's leader does. This can be
dangerous for weaker minions, especially
familiars, but can be offset with the
troop mascot skirmish bond.
In skirmish encounters, troops can be
forced to flee from battle if their
morale drops too low. This is managed
through route checks, which is a type of
willsaving throw. Route checks are
rolled whenever the troop's hit points
are pushed past one of his thresholds
and whenever the troop's leader is
knocked unconscious. If both happen at
the same time, the troop only rolls one
route check. Route checks have the
emotion, fear, and mental traits. And
the DC for route checks is a standard DC
for the level of the creature who
damaged it. With a successful will save,
the troop is frightened one. On a
failure, the troop is frightened too.
And on a critical failure, the members
of the troop break formation and run
away, causing the entire troop to be
removed from battle. The result of a
route check applies only to the troop
and not its leader. And while the
troop's leader is conscious, the result
of this check is improved by one step.
When a leader's troop is defeated, the
leader is placed into any space the
troop previously occupied, and play
continues as normal. When a troop flees,
the leader may choose to flee with them
or abandon them to stay and fight. If
the leader abandons their fleeing troop,
they cannot become the leader of that
troop again within the same encounter.
And if the troop loses their leader,
either because the leader is knocked out
or unable to act for some reason, they
lose all benefits for having a leader,
such as skirmish bonds and improved
route checks. When this happens, the
troop keeps its place in initiative, but
only gains two actions at the start of
each of its turns. And when a troop
loses a leader, one of that leader's
allies can attempt to become its new
leader. This calls for the take the lead
activity which costs two actions to
perform a diplomacy check against a DC
equal to the easy DC for the troops
level. On a success, the character
becomes the troop's new leader, but the
troop does not regain their lost
skirmish bond or a new skirmish bond
because of having a new leader. On a
failure, nothing happens. and on a
critical failure, the troop must
immediately attempt a route check. If a
leader is knocked out and later revived,
that leader resumes command of their
troop with all the previous benefits. If
the troop gained a new leader in their
absence, then that new leader may step
down and return command to the original
leader without the need for that
original leader to roll a take the lead
check.
So, that's it for skirmish encounters.
Please share your questions in the
comments below. And as always, I want to
take a quick moment to say thank you to
everybody out there who supports me.
Whether that's by clicking the like
button, subscribing to the channel,
subscribing to the Patreon, or buying a
Superthanks. I greatly appreciate
everything you folks do to support me.
And as always, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[Music]