Hello and welcome to How It's Played
Labs, a series where I take inspiration
from nonPISO games and apply their
concepts to Pathfinder and Starfinder.
Today, we'll be borrowing the multi-art
opponents and phases rules from Fabula
Ultima to make our bosses more
narratively interesting and memorable.
If you've ever played a console JRPG,
then you're probably familiar with epic
boss fights where you have to target
specific limbs, cores, or heads to
disable attacks or reveal weaknesses.
And that's what we're aiming for today.
Turning a single boss monster into
something that has multiple targetable
parts that can be crippled along the
journey to defeating them. The core idea
we'll be adapting comes from Fabula
Ultima, specifically its natural fantasy
atlas supplement. For those not familiar
with Fabula Ultima, it is described as a
tabletop JRPG
and is heavily inspired by oldchool
Japanese console RPGs, most notably
Final Fantasy. If you're curious about
that system and want to know more, I'll
leave some links in the description to a
series of Fabula Ultima videos made by
friend of the channel, Bad Luck Gamer.
Now, Fabula Ultima and Pathfinder 2e are
different systems, so a direct port
doesn't work. What follows is a
framework for adapting this concept
using Pathfinder 2's existing mechanics
as building blocks. So, it's important
to note this is not official Piso
material and is just my attempt to apply
Fabula Ultima's concepts to Pathfinder.
As such, this is strictly fan-made
material, has not been thoroughly play
tested, and your mileage may vary. So,
think of this video as a fun thought
experiment instead of being hard rules.
So, what's the basic idea in Fabula
Ultima? Well, a multi-art opponent is a
single, often very large creature
treated as multiple distinct enemies in
terms of targeting and sometimes
defense. You might have a head, claws, a
tail, maybe some turrets on a techno
fantasy construct. The key is that
targeting and destroying each of these
parts has a direct impact. Maybe it
disables a specific attack, it changes
the creature's stats, or even triggers a
whole new phase of the fight.
To bring this into Pathfinder, we'll
need a framework that pulls inspiration
from Fabula Ultima, but still respects
Pathfinder's rules. First, your creature
still has a primary stat block. Armor
class, saves, skills, perception speed,
resistances, weaknesses, all of that
good stuff. It also has a main hit point
pull. This represents its overall life
force. Usually, the creature is only
truly defeated when this main hit points
pull hits zero. And to differentiate
this from the monster's different parts.
I'm going to refer to this as the
monster's main body. In addition, the
monster will have a number of parts.
Think head, claws, tails, wings, power
core, and so on. Each part has its own
separate hit points pull. And this is
key. Think of it as the durability of
just that one component. Maybe it has
25% to as much as 50% of the creature's
main hit points. That's usually a good
starting point depending on how many
parts there are and the purpose of each
part. Each part is also going to have
abilities. Tie specific strikes,
activities, reactions, or even passive
abilities to each part. A claw lists the
monster grab. The head has a breath
weapon and so on. If the part is broken,
then that ability goes away. And
optionally, you can add part defenses.
You could give parts slightly different
armor classes or unique weaknesses and
resistances compared to what the main
body has. For example, armored legs
might resist physical damage better than
the monster's fleshy torso does. But to
keep things simple at first, I recommend
just using the main armor class and
saving through bonuses for all parts,
that can work, too.
Players need to declare which part
they're targeting. If they just say, "I
attack the dragon," assume that they're
attacking the main body, or ask them for
more clarification. Using this system,
all monster parts are treated as
occupying all the same squares as the
monster. For example, you wouldn't take
the 3x3 token of a huge sized monster
and dictate that this square is the
right claw part and this square is the
left claw part. Since there are no
facing rules in Pathfinder and there are
existing precedents, for example, a
rider occupying all the same spaces as
their mount or the leader occupying all
the same spaces as their troop. In this
system, each monster part occupies all
the same spaces as the monster usually
occupies. Another consideration is even
though monster parts have their own hit
point pulls and are targeted separately
from the main body, they're all part of
the same creature. Meaning the creature
as a whole can only be targeted once per
effect. Let's take a look at chain
lightning as an example. Here it says
targets one creature plus any number of
additional creatures and the electricity
then arcs to another creature within 30
ft of the first target. Jumps to another
creature within 30 ft of the target and
so on. You can end the chain at any
point. You can't target the same
creature more than once. Since monster
parts are all the same singular
creature, you couldn't use chain
lightning to arc from a dragon's head to
its wings to its tail to each of its
claws and so on. You would choose either
one part of the dragon or its main body
to be targeted by chain lightning before
it arcs off to the next creature. So
bottom line, any effect may only target
a single part of the monster or its main
body, never more. And last, parts are
never targeted by area effects. Any
spell, bomb, or other ability that deals
area damage may only affect the
creature's main body. Explosions and
similar effects are simply too
unpredictable to aim at a specific body
part. But as always, DMs are free to
rule differently if doing so makes sense
in their games. And a general rule of
thumb is if you're not sure if an effect
could target a specific part, then apply
it to only the creature's main body.
Now, let's talk about damaging a part.
When a player hits a part and deals
damage, that damage is applied to both
the parts hit points and the creature's
main body hit points with each
location's resistances and weaknesses
applied separately. Why? Well, because
it ensures players always feel like
they're making progress towards ending
the fight, which is usually accomplished
by depleting the main body's hit points
while they're also working towards the
tactical goal of disabling a part. It
represents overall trauma. A big hit to
a limb hurts the whole creature. Also,
difficulty might spiral out of control
if each part is treated as an additional
layer of hit points on top of the
already existing main body hit points.
Let's look at an example.
Consider this clock or behemoth. Its
main body has 150 hit points and
resistance 10 to physical. It has an
arcane gym part with 30 hit points and
only resistance five to physical. A
player targets the gym with a Warhammer
and deals 14 bludgeoning damage. The gym
suffers nine damage, 14 raw damage minus
its resistance of five. Therefore, its
hit points drop to 21. At the same time,
the main body suffers four damage. the
original 14 applied by the Warhammer
minus the main body's resistance of 10.
So, its hit points drop to 146.
In this system, we have progress on both
fronts, lowering the main body hit
points while also lowering the parts hit
points. And each location has its own
resistances and weaknesses. Now, let's
make it a little more interesting. Let's
say the behemoth's main body is weak
five to electricity, but its arcane gym
is insulated and has resistance
electricity 10. A player targets the gem
with electric arc and deals 15
electricity damage. The gym suffers five
damage, 15 damage minus its resistance
10 to electricity, so its hit points
drop to 16. And the main body suffers 20
damage, 15 plus its weakness five to
electricity. So its hit points drop to
126. Again, all the damage is applied
separately to the targeted part and the
monster's main body. This may seem
complicated, but remember, in most
cases, the different parts will likely
have the same resistances and weaknesses
as the main body. But this rule also
allows creatures like a fiveheaded
chromatic dragon to have different
weaknesses and resistances for each of
its heads.
So what happens when a part's hit points
reach zero? Well, it becomes broken just
like any other object in Pathfinder. A
broken part loses its functionality. The
creature can't use any actions,
reactions, or abilities tied
specifically to that part. Optionally, a
broken part could also impose penalties,
like a broken leg, reducing speed. And
we should also take a moment to discuss
healing. Healing effects that typically
have targets can be used to heal either
the creature's main body or a single
part. And just like how damaging a part
applies the damage to both that part and
the main body, applying healing to a
part also heals the main body the same
amount. For example, the heal spell
targets one living creature. This could
be used to heal either the creature's
main body or a single part. And if it
targets a part, then the healing is
applied to both that part and to the
main body. Yes. A downside of this is
there's no benefit to targeting just the
main body, but this rule is simple and
consistent with how damaging a multi-art
opponent works. And area healing effects
like the three action version of the
heal spell only restore the creature's
main body. For other effects like fast
healing, these likely apply to all the
creatures parts and their main body
once. You wouldn't multiply the fast
healing per part and then apply that
total to the main body. But keep in mind
that under normal circumstances, a
broken part may not be made functional
again through normal healing. Once a
part's hit points are reduced to zero,
it becomes broken and it remains broken
for the remainder of the encounter. The
reason for this is twofold. First,
breaking apart should feel like a
significant moment in the narrative, and
players may feel cheated if that
accomplishment is taken away from them
by healing. And second, allowing a
broken part to be restored may
significantly increase the challenge of
the encounter. So, if a dragon's claw is
broken and the dragon's main body
receives healing, it may become
healthier overall, but its claw is still
crippled. Outside of combat, the GM can
decide how long it takes for this boss
monster to heal up and recover the use
of its broken parts.
Multi-art creatures still get their
usual three actions in one reaction per
turn. It just can't use actions that are
tied to broken parts. If it has two
claws and one is broken, it can still
attack with the other. Also apply
conditions like frightened, stunned, or
grabbed to the main creature as these
affect the creature as a whole. However,
you may want to allow part specific
conditions for dramatic effect and the
rule of cool. For example, you might
allow a barbarian to grab a dragon's
tail to prevent it from making tail
strikes or holding its mouth shut to
prevent it from using its breath weapon.
As usual, cases like these are entirely
left up to the GM to decide if they'll
allow them.
Okay, breaking parts is cool, but we can
make it even more dynamic with phases
and triggers, which are also inspired by
how Fabula Ultima handles some of their
multi-part bosses. A phase is just one
distinct stage of a fight. The boss
might change tactics, use new abilities,
or the environment around them might
shift. And a trigger is what causes the
shift into a new phase. Breaking a
specific part could be a perfect trigger
for these. Other triggers could be
hitting hit point thresholds, like
becoming bloodied at 50% of the main
body's hit points. Triggers could also
be players interacting with the
environment in a certain way or even
just after a certain number of rounds
have passed. But since this video is
about multi-part opponents, we're going
to focus on phase triggers being caused
by damage. So, let's go back to our
clockwork behemoth. We have a phase
trigger that says the arcane gem part
becomes broken. And when that is
triggered, a new phase starts. Phases
are all about change. So, what changes
when the behemoth's arcane gym is
shattered? Well, first the behemoth
loses its gem powered energy blast. It
gains a steam vent attack that deals
fire damage in a cone area. His tactics
changed to become a very aggressive
melee fighter and also it starts
grappling its enemies and his stats
change. The weakness to electricity is
gone. But now it has gained a weakness
to cold damage. So why do we use phases?
phases make boss fights feel like a
journey. They reward players for
achieving tactical goals like breaking
apart. They keep the fight from getting
stale. They ramp up the tension and they
allow for cool narrative moments.
So, we've established that attacking
parts let you do something cool and
powerful. You can disable specific
monster abilities. Normally, you can't
prevent a dragon from using his breath
weapon. But with this system, targeting
and breaking his head can achieve that.
But here's the crucial part of design
philosophy to make this work and keep
encounters challenging. It shouldn't
ever be a free lunch. And by that I mean
if attacking a part always gives you a
massive advantage in that it can disable
an ability and at the same time also
damages the main body just like a normal
hit. Then there's really no downside
here. The players will always attack the
parts and therefore that removes any
real tactical choice. So to maintain
balance and create interesting decisions
there needs to be a trade-off. The
significant benefit of disabling a
powerful monster ability should come
with a roughly equivalent cost, risk, or
consequence. Think of it like this. The
game is letting you do something
extraordinary like removing a breath
weapon. So, there should also be an
extraordinary consequence or challenge
involved.
This cost can come in two main forms.
First are frontend costs. These make
attacking the part itself harder or
riskier than attacking the main body.
For example, this could come in the form
of higher defenses. The part might have
a higher armor class and reflex bonus,
making it harder to hit accurately.
Maybe its head is smaller and moving
around in such a way that it becomes
harder to hit. This could come in the
form of resistances. the part could have
a resistance that the main body doesn't,
especially resistance physical, meaning
most of your hits have to overcome that
threshold first before they apply any
damage. For example, the dragon's head
could have larger scales that are angled
to deflect away physical attacks. And
another form of frontend cost could be
triggered reactions. Attacking the part
might provoke an immediate defensive
reaction. For example, striking a giant
scorpion's tail only for it to instantly
lash back at you with his stinger as a
reaction. Those are all frontend costs
that make attacking the part more
difficult or pose a narratively
interesting consequence for doing so.
Therefore, logically, the second type of
costs are backend costs. These are
consequences that happen after you
successfully break the part. First up
are dangerous phase triggers, and this
is a big one. Successfully breaking a
key part might push the monster into an
even more dangerous phase. You stopped
the breath weapon, but now the dragon is
enraged, so it's hitting faster with its
tail and claws. The second kind of
backend cost are negative effects.
Breaking apart could have a direct
negative consequence. Maybe shattering a
construct's power core causes an energy
explosion, damaging everyone nearby, or
breaking a spawning sack on a monster
releases a swarm of weaker minions into
the fight. And the last kind of backend
cost could be a shift in resistances and
weaknesses. Breaking apart might remove
one resistance but expose or create
another, thereby forcing the party to
have to adapt their tactics.
So, let's take one more look at our
example of a clockwork behemoth. The
benefit of breaking its arcane gem is
you disable its main energy blast, but
there needs to be a cost for this,
either on the front end or on the back
end. A potential front-end cost may be
giving the gem a bonus to armor class
and reflex saves as a smaller target.
So, his armor class and reflex bonus are
increased by two, three, or four points.
Or it could have a higher resistance
than the main body, meaning attacks
targeting it need to overcome a minimal
amount before they can start chipping
away at its hit points. Or another
possible front-end cost could be hitting
it causes a bright flash of light that
could dazzle the attacker. So those are
possible frontend costs, things that
make it less desirable to attack the
part in the first place. You could also
use a backend cost. For example, its
armor class and reflex bonus are the
same as the main body, but when the gem
breaks, it could explode, dealing fire
damage to everything within 5 ft and
also trigger a phase change or advance
steam and becomes a more melee focused
enemy. This could force the players into
narratively interesting and tactically
minded choices. Do you risk the
immediate explosion and a tougher melee
fight to stop its ranged energy blast?
Or is it safer to try and burn down its
main body hit points while dodging the
blast? Maybe because the gem has such
high resistances. And keep in mind,
regardless of how you design the
monster, the players may not know the
consequences of breaking apart unless
they pass a recall knowledge or
perception check. So find ways encourage
them to do so or don't. Surprises can be
fun, too. The key for GMs is finding
that sweet spot. The cost shouldn't be
so punishing that players never attack
the parts, but it should be significant
enough to make them pause and consider
if disabling that specific ability right
now is worth the associated risk or
consequence. This can turn a typical
boss fight from a simple hit point race
into a dynamic puzzle with meaningful
choices.
Now, with all of this in mind, let's try
converting an existing Pathfinder
monster into an epic multi-part boss.
For this, we'll be using Menare the
Great Worm, which I am adapting for an
upcoming session. So, if you're one of
my players, stop watching now. For this,
I'll be breaking the process down into a
series of steps. First, choose the base
creature. Next, identify parts and match
abilities. Third, define the parts
mechanically. Fourth, define broken
effects. Then, consider backend costs,
which could be phases and triggers. And
last, review, refine, and balance as
best you can. So, starting with step
one, we choose Manare as the base
creature. He is a level 23 gold dragon.
His main body has 575 hit points, an
armor class of 50, is immune to fire,
paralyze, and sleep, and has weakness 25
to cold damage. He also has a speed of
60 ft and fly speed of 200 ft. And he
has a frightful presence, can make jaws,
claws, tail, and horn attacks, has a
breath weapon that can be used to either
make a cone of flame or blast a
weakening gas, and can cast arcane
innate spells. Step two, identify parts
and match abilities. We break the
ancient dragon down into head, right
claw, left claw, tail, and wings. and
then assigned each part the abilities
for which it is responsible. We assign
frightful presence, jaws, horns, breath
weapon, and arcane spells to its head.
We assign one claw attack to each of its
claws. We assign its tail attack to its
tail, and we assign its fly speed to its
wings. All other characteristics are
assigned to his main body. Now, this is
a lot to manage. five distinct parts
plus the main body. This is making
things more cumbersome than is
necessary. So, let's only use parts for
what's most narratively interesting. The
two claws and the tail aren't really
bringing anything exciting to the party.
So, we won't worry about managing those
as parts, but the head and wings are
more interesting. So, we will manage
them as parts. We now have three aspects
of Manari that we need to manage. A head
part that controls its frightful
presence, jaws, horns, breath weapon,
and arcane spells. A wings part that
grants its ability to fly. And a main
body that covers everything else. Note
that since it takes both wings to fly,
we're combining them both into a single
mechanical part rather than having to
track a hit points pool for the left
wing and right wing separately. Step
three, we define the parts mechanically.
The head is a major concern. We don't
want it to be crippled too soon, and
should that happen, we want it to feel
like a major accomplishment. So, I'm
going to set its hit points at 40% of
the main body or 230 points. And the
wings are also important, but not as
important as the head. Plus, they're
mostly made of membranes. So, I set the
hit points pull for the wings at roughly
30% of the main body, or 170 hit points.
Note that if I was to impose front-end
costs like higher armor class, reflex
bonus, or resistances, I would define
those now during this step. But I think
I'm going to lean more into backend
costs like phase changes for this
encounter. So there's nothing more for
me to do during this step. That brings
us to step four. Define broken effects.
If the head becomes broken, Manari loses
his frightful presence, jaws, horns,
breath weapon, and the ability to cast
arcane spells. Note that breaking the
head does not mean his head is destroyed
and he instantly dies. It just means he
can no longer use the abilities that are
associated with his head part. And keep
in mind that all the damage the players
apply to the head is also dealt to his
main body. So repeatedly slicing his
head with a great axe does also bring
him closer to death. As for the wings
part, we decide that when the wings are
broken, he can no longer fly and falls
to the ground if he was flying at the
time his wings become broken. Step five,
consider backend costs, which are
usually phases and triggers. Because I
don't have front-end costs for breaking
the head or wings, I need to create
back-end costs that are roughly
equivalent in value to the ability
losses. First up, the wings. We create a
phase titled cornered beast. The trigger
for this phase is the wings part becomes
broken. And the description for this
phase says then kar falls if he is
flying. He becomes quickened able to use
the extra action only to make melee
attacks or destroy. So he loses his
ability to fly, which is a major
tactical advantage, but gains an extra
action each turn that can either be used
for striding or making an extra melee
attack. Within the narrative, he is
angered and shows that he is able to
adapt to the loss of his wings. Now, for
the head part, we create a phase called
Worm's Fury. The trigger for this phase
is the head part becomes broken. And the
description says, "Men loses
spellcasting, frightful presence, Jaws
attacks, horn attacks, and his breath
weapon. He immediately strides and makes
two claw strikes as a free action
against the creature who broke his head
if possible. He gains a plus two status
bonus to attack rolls and damage rolls
with claw and tail strikes. He gains the
adamantine scales reaction. The reaction
trigger is Manar is targeted by a
damaging effect requirement. Mari's head
part is broken and the reaction's effect
is Manari gains resistance all 15
against the triggering attack applied
only to his main body hit point
reduction. Manari also gains the stunned
one condition for the next two turns as
his focus shatters. So in this phase,
Manari becomes a purely physical enraged
combatant. He loses his ranged attacks,
magic, breath weapon, and horns, but
essentially increases one experience
level for his remaining melee attacks,
and gains the adamantine scales
reaction, which can reduce incoming
damage to his main body. And note that
since he has two reactions per turn, he
can use this reaction twice. I also
included the free stride and claw
strikes and the stunned one condition
for narrative effect since they most
likely cancel each other out. A couple
actions used immediately for the loss of
two actions over the next two turns. I
could probably end the conversion of
Mari there, but as mentioned before,
this is definitely not an exact science
and balancing will be a challenge. To
help with that, I'm going to create a
third phase and trigger, which I think
of as a backpocket phase in the sense
that I'm not required to use it. I have
it already prepared and in my so-called
back pocket, if it is needed, but if the
encounter is already too difficult, then
I don't need to use it. I'm calling this
phase righteous stand. The trigger is
Manari's main body is reduced to fewer
than 250 hit points. And the phase
effect says Manari uses a free action to
ignite in an aura of Draconic Radiance.
He gains a plus one status bonus to
armor class in all saves. All creatures
perceiving Manari through vision at the
time this phase is triggered and after
targeting Mari with a melee attack must
succeed a DC45 will save or be blinded
for 1 minute. On a successful save, the
creature is temporarily immune to this
effect for 1 minute. Righteous stand
ends after 1 minute or if Manari's main
body is reduced to zero hit points. So
when players push Mari below less than
50% of his hit points, I as the GM
should have a good idea for how this
fight is going. If the players have
broken his head and show no signs of
slowing down, even with Mari in his
worm's fury phase, I can choose to
activate this phase. But if the fight's
too difficult with the other phases in
effect, I can choose not to use this
phase. Or I can have it activate later,
like at 100 hit points to add to the
drama of the fight's conclusion. This is
just one example of how a backpocket
phase can help you balance multi-art
bosses. Air on the side of other phases
being light and have this ready to use
later, but only if it's needed.
So, those are the basics of the system,
but let's do a quick review with a few
considerations. First, complexity. Start
simple with maybe only two or three
parts. You don't want or need to break a
dragon into head, wings, tail, left
claw, right claw, and so on. Just pick
two so you're not forced into more
bookkeeping than is needed. Think about
clarity. Since this is outside the norm
for Pathfinder encounters, make sure
your players understand which parts
exist and that they can target them.
Visual aids can help, such as saying a
certain part of the monster's body is a
different color or is glowing. Also
encourage recall knowledge or perception
checks to get this information, but make
sure the players somehow come upon the
realization that they can target
different parts of the monster or all of
this work is wasted. As mentioned
before, balance is going to be a
challenge. It's going to be difficult to
manage and counterbalance when using the
system as so much of it will be up to
you as the GM to make a judgment call as
to what makes narrative sense and what
your players can handle. If you're
concerned that this is going to make the
encounter too difficult, then apply the
weak adjustment template to the creature
before you create a bunch of cool and
powerful phase changes. And also
consider having that back pocket phase
prepared just in case the fight turns
out to be easier than you planned. Also
think about impact. Breaking monster
parts should feel meaningful to the
players and doing so should change the
fight in a noticeable way. New abilities
can replace lost abilities and phase
changes can alter the creature's
tactics. And last, remember the
downsides. There should always be a
downside to targeting a part rather than
targeting the creature's main body.
Otherwise, there is little to no reason
for a player not to be targeting parts
as they apply damage to both the part
and the main body at the same time. And
these downsides should take into account
that breaking apart means removing the
monster's access to certain abilities
and therefore should have a cost
associated with doing so.
So, there you have it. A framework for
bringing dynamic multi-part boss
encounters inspired by Fabula Ultima
into your Pathfinder second edition
games. Give it a try in your own games
and let me know in the comments how it
goes or if you have any cool variations
or twist that you like to add to this
idea. And as always, thanks to everyone
who supports me, whether that be by
liking the videos, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon. I greatly
appreciate everything you do to support
me. And with that, thanks for watching.
Take care and happy gaming. [music]
[music]
>> [music]