Hello and welcome to Mythic Heroes and
Pathfinder Second Edition Remastered. If
you've ever wanted your character story
to feel like the stuff of ancient
legends, tales of heroes who defy
physics, challenge the gods, and shape
the narrative of the world around them,
then this system may be for you. We're
going to break down what mythic
characters are, how they work, and how
you can use them to tell truly epic
stories.
So, what exactly is a mythic character?
In a standard Pathfinder game, your
character is already a hero capable of
fighting monsters and saving kingdoms.
But mythic adventures are inspired by
stories that go even further. Think of
the legends of heroes who wrestle with
gods or alter the very landscape with
their power. Mythic characters possess
fantastical powers that are often
unbound by normal limits. The most
important distinction is that mythic
characters have a much more profound
ability to directly affect the narrative
of the game world. They are figures of a
legend and the rules give you the tools
to make that a mechanical reality.
So, how does a character become mythic?
This isn't something that you just
choose at first level. In fact, you
don't get to choose becoming mythic at
all. Instead, it's a decision the GM
makes for all the players in the
campaign. And it happens in the story
when your character experiences what is
known as their calling. This pivotal
moment can happen in many ways. Maybe
your character is directly infused with
power by a deity. Maybe they survive
exposure to a mythic artifact. Or maybe
they're caught in a worldshaking event
like the gods reign where the power of a
dead god spills across the land and
imbuss people with a divine spark.
However it happens, this calling is the
event that awakens your latent potential
and sets you on the path to legend. And
we'll talk more about callings in just a
moment. But first, there are a couple
mechanical rules we should discuss.
First, the fuel for your new abilities
is called mythic points. You spend them
to power your mythic feats, cast mythic
spells, or activate mythic items. And
this is important for a mythic
character. Mythic points replace your
hero points. You don't gain or use hero
points at all. You start every game
session with three mythic points, and
you can never have more than three at a
time. And then during a session, you can
regain mythic points by performing
legendary tasks. Slaying a mythic
opponent will restore two points to the
person who dealt the final blow and one
point to all the other mythic characters
in the party. Completing a mythic deed,
which could be a major narrative
challenge as defined by the GM, restores
all of your points. And finally, acting
in accordance with your specific mythic
calling can regain you one point. And
other legendary accomplishments or
sacrifices may also grant mythic points
as determined by the GM.
Another new mechanic that shapes mythic
characters is mythic proficiency. This
is a new proficiency rank that is one
step above legendary. When an ability
allows you to use it, your proficiency
bonus is 10 plus your level. To put that
in perspective, legendary proficiency is
only eight plus your level. But you
don't just gain this new level of mythic
proficiency in a skill the way you may
be used to increasing proficiency
levels. Instead, you use mythic
proficiency only when a specific mythic
ability tells you to, and it almost
always costs you a mythic point to do
so. For example, let's look at hands
that onw weave disaster. Say you are a
thirdle rogue and have expert
proficiency in the thievery skill for a
thievery bonus of plus 10. With this
feat, you can spend a mythic point to
make a disabled device check with mythic
proficiency for a plus 16 bonus, even if
the lock you are trying to pick requires
master proficiency.
Mythic characters are legends, and
legends are notoriously hard to kill.
Therefore, the mythic rules change how
dying works. Normally, when your dying
condition reaches four, you're dead. But
for a mythic character, that's not the
end. In the case of mythic characters,
when your dying value would reach four
or five if you have the die hard feet,
you instead stabilize with zero hit
points and increase your doomed value by
one. You're not dead, but you're one
step closer to a final end. A mythic
character only dies permanently when
their doomed value reaches four. And as
normal, a mythic character's doomed
value decreases by one each time they
get a full night's rest. So, this gives
you an incredible amount of resilience,
letting you survive what would kill any
normal hero.
And since this can be a little
confusing, let's break it down. When a
mythic character is reduced to zero hit
points, they fall unconscious as normal
and begin making recovery checks. Once
they fail enough recovery checks to die,
which is normally at dying four, they
instead stabilize, have zero hit points,
increase their doomed value by one, and
increase their wounded value by one.
Now, let's say they get healed in the
middle of the same fight and are back on
their feet. A few rounds later, they
again get reduced to zero hit points.
They fall unconscious and unless it was
a critical hit that brought them down,
they have the dying two condition. Dying
two because they are wounded one, which
increases the dying value as normal.
Also, since they are doomed one, the
threshold for death is now dying three
instead of dying four. If they fail a
recovery check, they move to dying
three, which would normally kill them.
But because they are mythic, they
instead stabilize again with zero hit
points and increase both their wounded
and doomed values by one, giving them
wounded two and doomed two. If they are
revived in the same fight and get
reduced to zero hit points yet again,
they start at dying three because of
their wounded two condition. And the
threshold for death is now dying too
because of the doomed two condition.
Meaning they immediately stabilize and
increase their wounded and doomed values
to three. And if they take any more
damage while down or are revived and
reduced to zero hit points again, they
finally die because their doomed value
would be increased to four. As mentioned
before, mythic characters no longer have
hero points and therefore no longer have
access to that mechanic to stabilize
them. In its place is the level six
mythic feat called divert destiny. This
allows you to spend a mythic point when
you would either be reduced to zero hit
points or killed and remain conscious in
standing with hit points equal to 10
plus your level. In addition, you
completely lose the wounded in dying
condition and you do not increase your
doomed condition, potentially making you
extremely hard to kill.
There are a lot of amazing abilities
that are granted by becoming mythic. But
before we get into those details, let's
cover mythic character progression. The
system is similar to the free archetype
rules if you're familiar with those.
Whenever your character is blessed with
mythic power within the narrative, which
could be at first level or anytime
later, at that moment, you choose your
mythic calling. Mechanically, this is a
first level choice that may be gained
retroactively.
Then, at every even level, from second
level to 10th level, you gain an extra
feat slot that can only be used for
mythic feats. Then at 12th level, you
choose your mythic destiny, which is
like a highlevel mythic archetype. You
must take this dedication feat in your
12th level mythic slot in place of the
usual even level mythic feat. And
finally, at levels 14, 16, 18, and 20,
you can use your bonus mythic feat slots
to take feats either from your mythic
destiny or from your mythic calling.
Regardless of when you become blessed
with mythic power, at that moment you
get to play catch-up and retroactively
choose your calling, feats, and destiny.
For example, if your character becomes
blessed with mythic power at 13th level,
you will immediately get to choose their
calling, mythic feats at 2, 4th, 6th,
8th, and 10th level, and a mythic
destiny at 12th level.
Your mythic calling is the first and
most important choice you'll make. This
defines the purpose of your mythic power
and why your character was selected for
this blessing. For example, when I
charged a group of heroes to close the
world wound, each of their players chose
their calling. A cleric in that group
may have chosen the caretaker's calling
to heal those in need, while a fighter
may have chosen the guardian's calling.
Each calling gives you a unique way to
spend a mythic point. For example, the
guardian's calling lets you spend a
point to attempt an athletics check to
shove, reposition, or disarm using your
mythic proficiency. And the sage's
calling let you spend a mythic point to
recall knowledge with mythic
proficiency.
Your calling also dictates how you
regain mythic points. Each calling has
edicts and anathema, similar to
worshiping a deity. Following your
edicts can restore one mythic point, but
if you violate your anathema, you
immediately lose all your mythic points.
Although this is temporary and at the
start of your next session, you will
start with three mythic points again.
So, this really helps tie your power to
your character story.
In addition to the unique ability
provided by your calling, all mythic
characters get a powerful ability called
rewrite fate. This essentially replaces
the main benefit of hero points, but
with a mythic twist. When you roll a
skill check or a saving throw that you
don't like the result of, you can spend
one mythic point to roll it. And when
you do, you use your mythic proficiency
on the new roll. Now note that since
mythic points replace hero points and
rewrite fate specifically applies only
to skill checks and saving throws,
mythic characters may no longer re-roll
attacks the way non- mythic characters
can by spending hero points. Of course,
your GM may house rule this, but it's
important to understand that the
official rule is mythic points may not
be spent to re-roll attacks. Another
expression of a mythic character's power
is mythic feats. You can take feats like
become shadow that lets you become
concealed and hide or sneak with mythic
proficiency. Or for combat, you could
take mythic strike to make an attack
roll with mythic proficiency or mythic
casting to boost the power [music] of
your spells.
Now, at 12th level, your mythic journey
takes a big step. Then, you will choose
a mythic destiny. These are special
highlevel archetypes that represent the
ultimate expression of your mythic power
and your character's final legendary
path. You must take the destiny's
dedication feat in your 12th level
mythic slot and you may choose mythic
feats from this destiny at 14th, 16th,
18th, and 20th level. Each destiny
offers a unique flavor and powerful
abilities that culminate in a 20th level
capstone, often granting your character
a form of true immortality, cementing
their place as a legend. These destinies
range from apocalypse riders who become
harbingers of the end times to ascended
celestials whose heroic deeds have
earned them a place among the angelic
hosts of the upper plains. And each
destiny includes that special 20th level
capstone. For example, at 20th level,
the eternal legend destiny grants you
immortality as long as stories of your
deeds continue to be shared. And at 20th
level, the godling destiny grants you
literal godhood and the ability to grant
divine powers to your followers.
And that's the overview of mythic
characters. It's a powerful and exciting
new way to play, allowing you to become
a true legend, defy death, and change
the very fabric of the story. So, what
do you think of these rules? What kind
of mythic character would you like to
build? Let me know in the comments down
below. And as always, I want to take a
moment to thank everyone who supports
this channel. Whether that be by leaving
a comment, liking the video, subscribing
to the channel, or subscribing to the
Patreon. I greatly appreciate everything
you do to support me. And with that,
thanks for watching. Take care and happy
gaming.
>> [music]