Hey everybody, Dave here with another
Pathfinder rule reminder for you. And
today we're going to be talking a little
bit about haunts. Uh it's been a while
since I've done one of these videos. So
if you're not familiar with the rule
reminders, these are resources that sort
of back up the regular houseplay videos.
a little more informal, a little more
casual, and I'll take questions from uh
Patreon and from the comments section
and just kind of cover anything else
that needs to uh be be said to reinforce
the already published videos. In this
case, this is going to be reinforcing a
lot of the information that was included
in the uh video on hazards, and I'll
make sure I include a link to that video
in the description of this video. But um
with the the recent release or somewhat
recent release of the cinematic starship
rules for Starfinder second edition,
which heavily use the hazard rules and
some questions I've received
specifically specifically about haunts,
uh I figured it'd make sense just to do
one of these quick little videos to talk
about it. Specifically, I was asked if I
could take a haunt and just kind of walk
through it from A to Z. you know, how it
works, what's in the stat block, how it
would be presented in a a game, and how
things might play out. So, um, before we
get too deep into haunts, we should
probably just talk about hazards in
general. Ha, a haunt is a specific kind
of hazard. So, maybe we should cover
what a hazard is first. Uh, a hazard is
basically anything in the game that
would be considered an obstacle or a
danger to the players that is not a
creature. So, uh, most of the conflict
traditionally in these games, especially
in like a dungeon crawl, is going to
come in the form of monsters for the
players to fight and vanquish. Uh, those
are creatures. They use the creature
rules, the creature combat rules. uh NPC
interactions would likely use the social
encounter rules. So, a hazard is going
to be basically anything other than
those creatures that is an obstacle or a
danger to the player. Now, I might want
to put a little asterk next to that.
There are other systems like uh victory
point systems, the chase subsystem and
so forth that are also used to manage uh
difficulties, obstacles, and dangers in
the game. but they usually look at
things either outside of encounter mode
or over several rounds of encounters to
accumulate points. Um, but a hazard is
going to be something that you deal with
in encounter mode uh right along with
battling monsters and everything else.
So, our our hazards are are going to
fall into basically three broad
categories. The first of those is a
trap. uh anything that a person is going
to create for I'm creating it tonight
right now and it's going to either blow
up or trigger or activate at a later
time usually to defend uh your house a
dungeon whatever uh a chest from opening
you're probably familiar with traps if
you've ever seen Raiders of the Lost
Dark you've seen the opening scene those
are traps those are hazards uh another
type of broad category of hazards is
going to be environmental al hazards. Uh
these are going to be uh earthquakes, uh
tsunamis, a a building falling down
around you. Uh typically environmental
hazards are experienced by everybody in
the um in the encounter, friend and foe,
and not just isolated just to a person
who quote triggers it or uh just to one
side of the combat. It's usually going
to be experienced by everybody. Although
a lot of times the uh the opponents in
an area might have a natural resistance
to whatever uh the given environmental
hazard is. But the third kind of hazard
is the kind we're going to be talking
about primarily today which is a haunt.
A haunt is I think of it as especially
mechanically speaking is it's like a
trap. A haunt is nothing but a spooky
trap. Right? So the the the only real
difference between a haunt spooky trap
and a traditional mechanical or magical
trap is traps are intentionally created
and they are armed and they are
intentionally placed and so forth. And
there's usually something physical about
them. you can interact with them
physically to either disarm them or uh
they're going to have a a physical
presence in the room. A haunt is more of
like the echoes of the dead have tainted
an area. It's a spectral phenomenon.
It's going to be something that is
typically not uh immediately dealt with
in a physical manner. is probably going
to be dealt with using other skills. Uh,
in fact, it might be even worth looking
at the three different kinds of hazards
by the kinds of skills that are
typically used to uh to disable them.
Although disable is a mechanical term.
Uh, when we're talking about physical
traps, you're talking about using
thievery disabled device to usually uh
disable them to deal with them. uh
magical traps you might be able to uh
cast a spell magic on, do other things
to counteract them. Environmental
hazards are typically quote disabled
using either your nature skill or your
survival skill. And like no, that
doesn't mean like I disable the entire
avalanche that's coming at me, but using
the survival skill, you might be able to
find a way to uh you know, lean against
a uh side of the mountain in such a way
that you're not going to get hit by the
brunt of it. That's that's what they
mean by disable in a uh environmental
sense. And your your hunts are typically
going to be dealt with using either
religion or a cult. Uh somewhat
depending on the nature of the hunt.
Sometimes the the haunts are uh based on
sort of undead elements in which case it
would be religion. In others is is like
the psychic mental anguish of something
and in those cases it might be more a
cult than it is religion. Um, you also
might typically use uh diplomacy or even
intimidate in haunts if there is a
spirit that is still conscious in the
area. Uh, using diplomacy to calm them
might be a way to disable that haunt.
And just like all of the hazards, uh,
haunts come in two varieties. There's
there are simple haunts and complex
haunts. Just like there are simple
traps, complex tracks traps, simple
hazards, complex hazards. The difference
between a simple hazard and a complex
one is that a simple hazard is one and
done. A simple hazard is a landmine. Uh
uh uh you either detect the the landmine
and you disable it or you step on it and
it explodes. But once that happens, it's
done. Uh it doesn't persist round after
round after round and it doesn't uh have
its own place in initiative. It operates
on a reaction.
But uh complex hazards are ones that are
typically triggered by a reaction or
possibly a free action with a trigger.
Uh the main difference there being that
if a hazard or a haunt has a reaction in
a trigger, it's it's one reaction and
then it goes into its uh its routine. If
it has a if it's triggered by a free
action, then free actions are not
limited to only once per turn. So if it
has a free action on it, it can do it
over and over and over again. I think
the example in the book is a is a
environmental hazard of quicksand. Uh
quicksand is going to trigger and
swallow as many people that step into
it, not just the first person who does.
So that is an example of why some of
these hazards have uh initial triggers
that are um free actions instead of
reactions. But anyway,
a haunt is basically mechanically
speaking going to function the same way
as any other hazard. It's best in my
mind to think of them as spooky traps.
And uh that can get a little weird
because they do have elements that are
similar to creatures. So there could be
a spectral figure or a ghost that's
involved in the haunt that you have a
conversation with and you diplomacize
with. And there also might be other
situations where that ghost is in the
game as a creature and not as a hazard.
Uh I think that the major distinction
between those two is if it's in the if
it's in the the game as a creature, it
is something that can be defeated
through combat. And if it's part of a
haunt, it probably cannot be defeated
through through combat. is going to be
dealt with through some other skills
that are laid out in the stat block for
that haunt. Um, another thing that's
worth mentioning with haunts is haunts
typically um always come back. So, uh,
you might disable them, but that disable
is going to be temporary. Sometimes they
they list an area of quote unfinished
business or that unfinished business is
is implied. And basically all that means
is unless you do a specific thing,
the haunt will return. You have to put
the souls of the spirits to rest in some
manner in order to completely deal with
a haunt. Whereas the other kinds of
hazards typically don't have those kind
of restrictions. Um mechanical traps
might come back and might have a reset
depending on how complex they are. Uh,
an avalanche is going to have a is going
to cease when it's done running out, but
haunts always come back unless uh their
unfinished business is dealt with. And
sometimes that unfinished business is
spelled out in the text and sometimes
you have to infer it on your own as a
GM. So, let's take a look at um at one
haunt uh and walk through it uh top to
bottom. And for this I'm going to be
using the eternal flame haunt out of GM
Core. So at the very top you can see is
it is a level seven hazard and it is uh
complex and it is a haunt. The first
area it says stealth plus 18 expert.
Okay. So, this gets into how do the
players realize
they're encountering a haunt before it
uh before it is triggered and does
whatever nasty thing is going to do. So
whenever players are in the general area
of a hazard and it's up to the GM just
to decide what they feel like is the
general area. The exact distance is
probably going to be different between a
small trap and uh again an avalanche,
right? So, uh, when players are in the
general vicinity of a hazard like
eternal flame here,
if the stealth rating does not have a
minimum proficiency here, it says
expert, but if it did not say expert,
then everybody automatically gets a free
uh perception check against the stealth
DC of that hazard to see if they can
notice that something is weird going on.
Now, here it says expert, which means
your players would not get that free
chance to to detect its presence.
Instead, they would have to actively
seek the area to detect it. [snorts] So,
we can see um well, let's take a look at
the description here. The description
here says, "A raging spectral inferno
arises out of thin air, strengthening
all undead creatures within its area.
This haunt most often arises from the
charred remains of a group of three
people who burn to death whether in a
terrible accident or a deliberate
execution and their unavvenged souls
burn with rage. All right, so we have
the charred remains of three bodies and
the uh psychic anguish of their death is
leaving this this aura in this area that
can uh manifest when living creatures
are are too close to it. So we could say
our players walk into a cave and inside
that cave they see three charred bodies.
Now that might be a hint to the players
immediately to start making perception
checks. So if at that point a player
says you know this this doesn't sound
right. I want to look around. I want to
make a a seek action.
As long as they have not triggered the
haunt or the hazard. Uh if we look down
a little bit, we can see uh that the uh
trigger for this is a living creature
approaches within 10 ft of the remains
of one of those victims.
So as long as they haven't moved their
mini within 10 ft of those bodies and
they say I want to make a perception
check to seek, then the GM is going to
make a secret perception check. uh apply
the perception of that character and if
it is in this case if that total is a 28
or higher then they succeed. Uh 28
because if your stealth bonus is plus 18
then your stealth DC is 28. Now uh a lot
of this comes down to mechanical
terminology. I'm not a huge fan of it
having stealth written here. I
understand why it is uh because of the
mechanics of the game, but it that seems
to give an impression that like oh the
the trap is hiding from people. It's
actively sneaking around. And I think
some people uh can misinterpret that as
meaning that there are three spirit
ghosts from the three charred remains
and those ghosts are in the room and the
ghosts are hiding from the players. And
that's not what it means. It just means
that uh it's not easy to realize that
there's more to these three chart bodies
than meets the eye. Now, if that player
rolls or or you roll on their behalf, I
should say, their perception check to
seek and they succeed, then you as the
GM have to explain to the player what it
is they're perceiving that might tip
them off that this is in fact a haunt.
So, you might say even though the the
bodies look like they're they are long
past burnt, like you know, this this had
to have taken place uh a year plus ago,
but you still smell you can still smell
the fire as if it was live or or maybe
you can hear the crackling of the flames
or or you can hear just a faint echo of
of the anguish of the people who are
burning. whatever it is, uh, that would
be appropriate to this area to signal to
that player that they succeeded their
perception check. And they know there's
more going on here than just the remains
of three bodies.
So, at that point, if they're
successful, a player will likely want to
know more about this. Now, the
perception check might let them know
that they're dealing with a hazard of
some kind, but that does not tell them
necessarily exactly what kind of hazard
or haunt and what's going to happen and
how and when. So, at that point, a
player would likely say, I want to do a
recall knowledge check and I want to,
you know, exam. I want to see if I could
figure anything else about this area.
Now, it's not spelled out um in the stat
blocks of what the recall knowledge
checks would be, but uh you would base
the DC on the level of the hazard. So,
this hazard is uh a seventh level
hazard. And if we look up in in GM Core,
a seventh level hazard has a standard DC
of 23. So, if a player wants to know
more about what they're looking at here,
you would do a recall knowledge check
for them. This would be a secret check
behind your screen, as all recall
knowledge checks are. And uh I typically
would use whatever skills are used to
disable it as the skill for recall
knowledge. So, in this case, it can be
disabled with a religion uh skill. A
religion is a type of knowledge skill.
So, I would be rolling uh a secret
religion check for that player DC23.
Uh I'll also say um something that I do
that's absolutely not in the rules. This
is not um official ro this is a house
rule territory. I also typically allow
those same knowledge skills that can be
used to disable the haunt to be used to
perceive the haunt. So, if someone has a
higher bonus to religion than they do to
perception, I might roll that as their
perception
um to let them detect the fact that
they're in the presence of a haunt. Uh
that seems to make a little more sense
in my mind and it also gives a little
more room for for niche characters. Like
if you only have one religion character
in the party, it gives them an extra
moment to shine. Uh, so that's something
that I do, but I do want to just be
clear that that is house rule territory.
That's not official. That's just
something that I do. But anyway,
you would you would roll that for them
in secret. And like with all recall
knowledge checks, you would ask them,
you know, like, give me a a question you
want to you want to have answered. And
that question might be, well, um, I want
to know, is this area dangerous? And if
so, what kind of danger are we facing?
Well, if they roll uh if you roll that
secret check for them, religion and
beast of DC23, I might say, well, you
you're pretty sure you're in the
presence of a haunt here, and you you
think that the the anguish of the three
charred uh people that their spirits are
still uh they're they're anchored here
to this location. And if you get too
close, you might experience a a psychic
or illusory manifestation of the same
tragedy that killed them. And that might
clue that player into, well, I better
not get I better not walk any closer or
I might catch on fire like they did or
what have you. So then let's say that
the player wants to make another recall
knowledge check. And this time is to
figure out, well, what do I need to do
to avoid the danger here? How can we,
you know, quote disable it? Um, how can
we put these souls and spirits to risk
so there's no more danger in this room?
And in that case, you're going to then
make another recall knowledge check.
Now, because you're making a second
recall knowledge check on the same
topic, then the DC is going to go up one
step, and in this case, it would go from
being a normal DC to a hard DC, which
adds two to it and raises raises the DC
from uh 23 to 25. If that sounds
confusing or is not uh clear to you,
I'll leave a link in the description to
my video that's all about recall
knowledge checks, and that might shed
some light on it. But basically uh
players can continuously do recall
knowledge checks over and over again uh
until they fail one in which case that
signals they no longer can get any more
information on the topic or they uh do a
uh the highest level of check. Um is
that a possible difficulty? I can't
remember the difficulty name but once
they get to the highest uh difficulty
level they can't make any more after
that. But anyway we'll we'll say that
they want to make another recall
knowledge check on this topic. you as
the GM, this is a a secret check, like
all recall knowledge checks, you roll
that behind the screen. And if they get
a uh a 25 or higher on that religion
check, then you can go over some of the
ways to disable the haunt. In this case,
it says a DC27 diplomacy expert to
temporarily calm the rage of one of the
three spirits or a DC30 religion trained
to exercise one of the spirits. Three
total successes are required to disable
the haunt.
Okay, so a couple things here. First of
those is that since both of these uh
checks have uh uh per uh proficiency
requirements in the parentheticals,
expert for diplomacy and trained in
religion, the characters must meet those
minimum proficiency levels in order to
do it. Someone who's merely trained in
diplomacy would not be able to compel
the uh spirits to calm down. uh someone
who's untrained in religion wouldn't
have the knowledge to exercise them from
the uh from the chamber. Uh and some of
the other things that talk about here
are a couple of the questions that came
along with the the request to go over
this. The first is does it take two
actions to disable a haunt with a
knowledge skill? Okay, so it takes two
actions to use thievery on disabled
device to disable a mechanical trap. Uh
we're not using a thievery and disabled
device here. Instead, we're using
skills. So, does it take uh two actions
to um to disable this haunt using
religion or diplomacy? Well, if we take
a look at the uh section on disabling a
hazard,
it says the specific skill and DC
required to disable a hazard listed in
the hazard stat block. Like using
disable a device, using these skills to
disable a trap is a twoaction activity
with the same degrees of success. Though
the activity might have different traits
determined by the GM. Okay, so this is
an area that might be a point of
contention with some people. Um,
going strictly by a raw reading of this,
it says like using disable a device,
using these skills to disable a trap
is a twoaction activity. Um,
a trap is a specific kind of hazard.
To me, that is pretty clear that the two
action activity only applies to
disabling traps. I feel like if they
wanted that to apply to haunts or if
they wanted it to apply to the nature
and uh survival checks that are used to
disable environmental hazards, then it
would say like using disabled device,
using these skills to disable a hazard
is a two action activity. Um but that's
not what it says. It specifically says
trap. So for me and my reading of that
is that if you're using a diplomacy or
you are using uh religion to um to
disable this haunt then it is one action
to use either of those to do so.
However, there is a notation here that
says three total successes are required.
So it's not a one and done. So therefore
it's going to be a minimum of three
actions assuming that you succeed on all
of the checks. Now uh another uh
question that came up with this was can
you use three straight actions if it is
uh religion?
Yes. Uh my reading since it is only one
action to use these to disable it. It
takes three successes. You could you
spend your entire turn, your three
actions doing uh diplomacy and or
religion in any any combination of
those. If you succeed on all three, then
you disable all of them um right off the
bat uh or at least before it's triggered
as long as you have not entered within
uh 10 ft of of it. Um,
and also it says, "Is it standard one
success removes the haunt unless
otherwise noted?" Uh, yes. If if there's
no nothing in the disable area that says
that uh it takes multiple successes,
like this one specifically says three
successes, then it would just be one
success to disable the haunt. And one
more thing to talk about uh disabling
with using these skills. Um, I have I
have seen it mentioned sometimes that
people confuse using religion here or
using a cultism in a haunt to be the
same as a recall knowledge check. And so
the the thought there is that if you
fail one, you cannot make any additional
ones. And if you uh and every time that
you succeed, the DC goes up. uh when
you're using those skills, those
knowledge skills to disable, you are not
making recall knowledge checks. They're
just normal straight up skill checks and
therefore they don't have those uh
limitations that are applied
specifically to recall knowledge. Unless
this has the words recall knowledge in
the disabled text, then this is just a
straight skill check, just a straight
normal check, not recall knowledge. you
don't need to worry about um about
having to increase the DC after every
check or having there be a ceiling to
it. All right, but let's say that the
players in this case did not succeed on
their their seek action to detect the
presence of danger and the presence of
the haunt or they failed at their skill
checks to recall knowledge and and one
of them walks within 10 ft of one of the
three corpses. What happens then? Well,
that's where we get into the actual
activation of the haunt. So, if we look
at uh searing agony here, we see it is a
reaction with the mental trait and has
the trigger. A living creature
approaches within 10 ft of the remains
of a victim of the original fire. And
the effect is memories of the pain
suffered by the fire's past victims
assault the triggering creature's mind.
The creature must attempt a DC25 will
save and the haunt then rolls
initiative. Okay, so uh as soon as that
person walks in within 10 ft of one of
those corpses, the haunt spins its
reaction. That person must make a will
save DC25.
If they succeed, they become quickened
one or I'm sorry, not not quickened,
they become sickened one. Uh if they
critically succeed, they're not
affected. If they fail, they are sick in
two. If they critically fail, they are
sick in three and it is offguard for as
long as it remains within the haunts
area and for three rounds thereafter.
Okay, so um that is laid out pretty
clear. Uh but some of the things that
people are somewhat interested in are
about initiative. Well, what do we roll
for the initiative? You're going to roll
stealth. So at the top, stealth bonuses
plus 18. So once you trigger this, it is
going to uh spin that reaction and
you're going to roll you're going to
roll stealth plus 18 for initiative.
It's slotted in wherever. That means
it's possible um it there there it is
possible that the turn hat will have
already passed and you know you have to
wait another round for it to come
around. But in a lot of cases this is
probably the event that causes the party
to roll for initiative. So it won't just
be the haunt that's rolling initiative
and being slotted in. It's everybody's
rolling initiative now. And um and it's
doing stealth for it and it goes in
wherever wherever makes sense.
Now another thing that uh sometimes
comes up is well how many times does it
do this reaction? Does it keep doing
this this reaction uh every time
somebody steps within 10 ft of it? Uh
no. on these hazards. The reaction is
the initial trigger that sets it off. In
the case of a simple hazard, it's a one
and done again like a landmine. In the
case of a complex hazard like this one,
it uh does it once. It triggers you to
roll initiative and then it goes into
its routine. So, let's take a look at
its routine. Says routine one action.
Phantom flames rage across the haunted
area, dealing 4d6 fire damage to each
living creature within the area. Uh,
DC23 basic will save. Undead creatures
in the area are infused with flames for
the following round. They gain the fire
trait and immunity to fire and all their
attacks deal an additional 1d6 fire
damage. Objects in the area are
unaffected. Okay. So, if a player gets
within uh so close to it, it's going to
initially trigger that reaction and then
when it comes to the eternal flames turn
in the initiative order, it's going to
have one action. Now, the parenthetical
one action means it has one action to
spend. Some haunts and hazards could
have three actions. They could have six
actions. They could have who knows how
many actions, but uh they're not
designed like creatures where the
assumption is three actions. Instead, it
spells it out here as one action and it
spins that one action on causing the
phantom flames to rage across the
haunted area. Um,
so it has one action and it spins it,
which means that this is the only thing
it does on its turn in initiative and it
does it one time. The one action doesn't
mean that the phantom flames costs one
action. Has three actions. Therefore, it
would do this three times. No, it has
one action. This costs one action.
Causes the phantom flames to to uh to
envelop this area. Now, the one thing
about this particular hazard that I
don't really like is it makes references
to quote unquote the haunted area, but I
don't really see anywhere in the text
that it very clearly defines what the
haunted area is. Uh, I personally am
going to take the haunted area to be uh
anywhere within 10 ft of the charred
remains of any of the victims of the
original fire because uh that's what the
trigger is. And that is the only thing I
see in the this text that talks about
area. Um, and it it I could just be
blind. Maybe there's something there
that I'm missing. If there is, let me
know. Uh, otherwise it could just be up
to your GM to, you know, make a
determination that this entire cave,
this room, whatever, you know, it is
this building that is haunted. And we're
going to call this the haunted area. But
mechanically speaking, I don't see
anything else here that uh clearly
defines what the haunted area is. Um,
keep in mind that these are phantom
flames. They're not, you know, actual
physical flames. Uh, so you're making
basic will saves for these and because
they are are fantasmal nature objects
are not affected. Now, another question
that sometimes comes up is with regards
to disable uh once it moves into its
routine, is it too late to disable it?
Um, and the answer is no. Um, as long as
the haunt is active in any form, uh, you
can attempt to disable it, not just
before it goes off, so to speak. So, you
go into a combat encounter, you're going
to be fighting some other in this area,
probably some skeletons, whatnot.
They're going to be buffed by this uh by
by this area. You're going to be dealing
with uh suffering damage. On your turn,
you can take your actions. And if those
can be those can be attacking the the
undead creatures. They can be making uh
disabled checks, what have you as normal
in encounter mode. Um but yeah, you can
continue to try to make those disabled
checks. And if you do make those uh
three successes in the middle of combat
is going to shut down the haunt. The
haunt just ceases to be active. But, uh,
as mentioned before, the weird thing
about haunts is they're never
permanently, uh, disabled and destroyed,
so to speak, unless a piece of
unfinished business is dealt with. And
so, we see at the very bottom here, it
says, "The flames cease one minute after
all living creatures leave the area, but
after 1 hour, the anger and pain simmer
up, and the haunt is ready to trigger
again."
So, even if you succeed on these these
three uh checks to disable it, one hour
later, it's going to become active
again. And if somebody comes within 10
ft of those bodies, uh they're going to
trigger the searing agony uh reaction
and then it's going to go into encounter
mode and it's going to or go into
initiative and it's going to roll
initiative using stealth just like
before and it just keeps repeating
itself.
So, the question becomes, well, uh, if
the only way to deal with a haunt is
through resolving the quote unquote
unfinished business, well, how do we do
that with Eternal Flame?
Some haunts might spell it out. Uh, more
often you would have like an adventure
module, an adventure path that in the
body descriptive text of that room, it
might tell you what the unfinished
business is and how to resolve it
outside of this stat block. This stat
block is just an example taken out of
out of GM course, so it doesn't have all
the narrative context and explanation
that you would get in a full adventure.
Uh, beyond that, it could just be up to
the GM to make a judgment call on this.
Uh, now when I look at the description,
the last sentence says uh, and I guess
the very last end of that last sentence,
it refers to them as being quote unquote
unavvened souls that are burning with
rage. So, uh, in the absence of any
clear text, as a GM, I would probably
say if a if a player wanted to do a, um,
a recall knowledge and figure out, well,
how can I permanently put this to rest?
Well, you're going to have to adventure
these these souls. So, you're going to
have to find the person, creature,
monster, whatever that was responsible
for these flames, and you're going to
have to bring them to justice, whatever
justice may mean, to finally put these
souls to rest. And if those souls feel
like they have been avenged, then this
eternal flame will no longer be a haunt.
You will have purified that area, so to
speak. It will no longer be a problem.
Uh, so that's haunts in uh, I guess a
pretty big nutshell at this point.
Sorry, I have a tendency to ramble, but
a haunt is just a type of a hazard. It
functions mechanically like any other
hazard. I think of them as spooky traps.
Uh, and that would be a trap that does
not have physical elements and physical
danger, but fantasmal, spectral, perhaps
even psionic, psychic or illusory
dangers. Um, if any of this is not
clear, if you have any questions, then
please leave those in the comments below
and I'll try to answer those as I can.
And as always, I want to thank everybody
for hanging out with me and uh leaving
the comments, clicking the like button,
subscribing to the channel, subscribing
to the Patreon, all that good stuff. I
really appreciate all you folks do to
support me. And with that, thanks for
watching. Take care and happy gaming.
[music]
Yeah.
Heat. [music]