Hello and welcome to magic in Pathfinder
second edition remastered part one the
magic traditions. This is the first part
in a series that will examine the full
set of spell-casting rules in Pathfinder
second edition. In this first video
we'll lay a foundation for the series
that will be followed by crunchier
topics in the weeks to come. And please
note that this is an updated version of
a previously released video. So much of
this may be familiar, but the key
difference that you should know between
the legacy edition and the remaster
edition is that schools of magic were
removed with the second edition
remaster.
To fully understand magic and
Pathfinder, you first need to understand
how the four essences of magic and the
different magical traditions all work
together to form a foundation for
spellcasting. Magical traditions
describe the source of the spell and
also provide some narrative description
as to how the spell is cast. Individual
spells may belong to several different
traditions. They would be the same rank
and have the same mechanics, but might
be flavored slightly differently. Also,
each tradition has its own spell list. A
spell list shows which spells at each
rank are available to each spellcaster.
A character who has the arcane
spell-casting class ability is able to
cast spells from the arcane traditions
spell list and only spells found on that
list unless they gain access to another
tradition such as with multiclass
archetypes. And gone are the days of
spell lists being dictated by class.
Second edition has simplified things by
having only four traditions and
therefore only four spell lists, but
also allows greater flexibility and
allowing some classes to choose between
which spell list they want to use. For
example, a sorcerer could cast spells
from any one of the traditions depending
on what their bloodline is. The four
traditions are arcane, divine, occult,
and primal. I tend to think of arcane
magic as sort of like magical science.
Those who practice this form of magic do
so after years of study. They conduct
extensive research, pour over massive
toms, and see a kind of order to magical
energies that they can manipulate.
Wizards are the most iconic of the
arcane spellcasters. Divine spells
represent the power of the gods and is
often represented as the character
praying to their god and asking them to
bless or smite their target or they're a
physical conduit to channel the wrath of
their god. Divine magic could also
manifest from celestial bloodlines such
as sorcerers who may have angelic or
infernal blood running through their
veins. Clerics are the best known divine
spellcasters.
Then there is primal magic that deals
with the natural world, plants, animals,
and weather. Primal magic is the realm
of druids, sorcerers who belong to the
fay and beast bloodlines, and witches
with primal patrons. And last is the
occult tradition. I find that occult
magic is the most difficult to explain.
Player core one explains occult magic
like this. The practitioners of occult
traditions seek to understand the
unexplainable, categorize the bizarre,
and otherwise access the ephemeral in a
systematic way. And when I read that to
players, their response is always the
same. They always ask, "What does that
actually mean?" Oult magic is the realm
of witches, hags, cosmic entities,
bizarre beings like great old ones and
althus and also spirits, haunted houses
and many creatures with the aberration
trait. One of my players has taken to
calling it spooky magic. And I think in
most cases that kind of sums up occult
magic nicely. Occult magic is spooky
magic. But bards also practice occult
magic. And they're not typically
considered to be spooky. And this leads
one of my groups to refer to oultism as
quote other magic. As in there's arcane,
divine, and primal magic. And if it
doesn't fit into one of those easier to
understand traditions, then it's occult
or other magic. Whether you want to
think of it as a cult or spooky or other
magic, just know that this form of magic
is primarily practiced by bards,
witches, and some sorcerers with the
aberant and hag bloodlines.
In addition to the traditions, there are
also four essences of magic. I'm not
going to spend too much time on this as
the essences don't really impact the
mechanics of the game, but it is helpful
to know what the essences are and how
they relate to the four magical
traditions. Commonly held beliefs in
Golarian say that all of existence and
reality is composed of some combination
of four essences and those are matter,
spirit, mind, and life. The essence of
matter or material essence deals with
the physical world. The essence of
spirit deals with the soul or the
non-material and immortal parts of a
living being. The mind essence allows
thinking creatures to have rational
thought and for animals to behave on
instinct. And the life essence
represents the animating universal force
within all living things. Whereas matter
provides the base materials for a body,
life keeps it alive and well. Now, the
reason why it's helpful for players to
know about the four essences is because
each tradition focuses on exactly two of
these. And understanding that
relationship will help shed some light
on what kind of spells each tradition
excels with. The arcane tradition
focuses on the matter and mind essences.
Arcane spellcasters have a very, very
broad selection of spells, but are
extremely limited when it comes to the
essences of life and spirit. So, they're
not very well equipped when it comes to
healing. That's not to say a wizard
can't cast some life or spirit essence
spells, but there are far fewer spells
of those essences on the arcane spell
list than spells that deal with the
matter and mind essences. The divine
tradition is the polar opposite of the
arcane tradition in that the divine
spell list focuses on the spirit and
life essences. Which isn't to say they
don't also have spells that lend
themselves to other essences, but divine
casters really shine when it comes to
matters of healing and the immortal
soul. The occult tradition focuses on
the spirit and mind essences. Therefore,
we can expect bards and witches to excel
at inspiring allies and demoralizing
their foes. And last, the primal
tradition is the opposite of the occult
tradition in that it deals with the
matter and life essences. So, druids
have more spells that focus on
manipulating the physical realm, like
growing claws, summoning animals, or
manipulating the weather, as well as
spells that enhance the life energy that
flows through all living things.
This video has served as a foundation to
help understand how magic is organized
within Pathfinder. And in the next part
of the series, we're going to dive
deeper into topics such as prepared
versus spontaneous spellcasting, spell
slots, and heightening spells. If you
have any questions, please leave them in
the comments below. And as always, I
want to take a brief moment to thank
everyone who supports me and this
channel. Whether you do that by liking
the video, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon, I appreciate
everything you do to support me. And
with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[music]