Hello and welcome to Magic and
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part two prepared and spontaneous
casting. Please note that this is an
updated version of a previously released
video. So much of this may be familiar
with the main difference being changes
in terminology such as spell levels
becoming spell ranks. In this video,
we're going to explore how prepared and
spontaneous spellcasters each function,
as well as spell slots and heightening.
And it's worth mentioning that this
video will focus on foundational
mechanics, and each class likely has its
own ways of altering these mechanics,
but covering all those exceptions is
beyond the scope of this video. I may
create class specific videos in the
future to cover those points.
In Pathfinder, spellcasters are limited
in the number of spells they can cast in
a single day, as well as the power of
those spells. This mechanic is dependent
on the character's spell slots, which
are dictated by their class and level.
Using bards as an example, in their
class listing, we find this table. For
example, we see here that a thirdle bard
has three first rank spell slots and two
second rank spell slots. Cantrips are a
special kind of spell that do not use
spell slots, and we'll discuss those in
a future video. When a character casts a
spell, that spell consumes one of their
spell slots, which means this thirdle
bard can cast three first rank spells
and two second rank spells before
needing to rest. After a full night's
rest and time spent in the morning for
daily preparations, the caster is reset
to their daily aotment of spell slots.
The caster can also cast lower rank
spells using higher rank spell slots
through a process called heightening.
When you cast a spell using a spell slot
that is higher than that spell's listed
rank, the spell is heightened and is
cast at a rank equal to the spell slot
that was used. For example, fireball is
a third rank spell and deals 6d6 damage,
but it can be cast using any spell slot
that is third rank or higher. If a
fireball is cast using a fifth rank
spell slot, then it becomes a fifth rank
fireball spell. And we see an entry at
the bottom of the description that reads
heightened plus one, the damage
increases by 2d6. And what this means is
every time a fireball spell's rank is
increased by one, its damage increases
by 2d6. So a fifth rank fireball spell
would deal 10d6 damage. 66 at its normal
third rank, plus two more dice when it
is heightened to fourth rank and two
more dice when it is heightened once
more to fifth rank. That's pretty easy.
But let's look at something like acid
grip. This is a second rank spell that
deals 2d8 acid damage plus 1d6
persistent damage. And we see a notation
at the bottom that says heightened
[snorts]
plus two. The initial damage increases
by 2d8 and the persistent damage
increases by 1d6. Since it says plus two
here, this bonus damage applies every
time the spell is heightened by two
ranks. So if acid grip is cast using a
third rank spell slot, it becomes a
third rank spell, but there is no change
to damage. And if it is cast with a
fourth rank spell slot, it becomes a
fourth rank spell. Deals 48 acid damage
plus another 2d6 persistent acid damage
because the damage increases every time
it is heightened by two ranks. At sixth
rank, acid group deals 68 damage and 3d6
persistent damage and so on. And next,
let's look at a spell like bless. This
is a first rank spell and has no
heightened entry at the bottom. A common
misconception is that the lack of a
heightened entry means it cannot be
heightened, and that's not correct.
Spellcasters may have limits to what
spells they are able to heighten, which
we're going to talk about in just a
minute, but it is possible to heighten
any spell, not just those with a special
heightened entry in their description.
So, if you cast bless with a sixth
ranked spell slot, it becomes a sixth
rank bless spell. But why would you do
that if it doesn't gain any bonuses for
being cast with a higher rank slot? And
the answer to that is counteracting. I
have a whole other video on the topic
which I will link in the description, so
I'm not going to go too deep into it
here, but the higher the spell rank, the
harder it is for someone to dispel it.
All spells can be counteracted by
certain things like dispel magic, but
bless in particular can also be
counteracted by the Bane spell. So, if a
caster wanted to be extra safe when
casting bliss to either aid their
friends or to counteract an enemy's bane
spell, they might heighten it by
spending a fourth rank spell slot. And
it would then face counteract checks at
fourth rank instead of first.
So, spell slots are used to cast spells.
And when a spell is cast using a slot
higher than it listed rank, it becomes
heightened to the same rank as the slot
that was used. But how these spell slots
are managed differs greatly between
prepared spellcasters and spontaneous
spellcasters.
Spellcasters and Pathfinder fall into
one of those categories which is
determined by their class. Prepared
spellcasters include the cleric, druid,
megas, witch, and wizard classes. And as
the name implies, prepared spellcasters
must plan their spells ahead of time. As
part of their daily preparations, they
must decide exactly how each spell slot
will be used in advance. For example, a
fifth level wizard has three first rank
spell slots, three second rank slots,
and two third rank slots. Every morning,
these slots start as empty, and the
wizard must choose how to fill them from
the spells available to them. This
wizard chooses Breathe Fire, Summon
Animal, and Force Barrage as their first
rank slots, then chooses Acid Grip,
Invisibility, and Breathe Fire
Heightened to second rank with their
second rank slots, and then fills their
third rank slots with two instances of
Fireball. As you can see, if a prepared
spellcaster wishes to cast the same
spell multiple times, they must prepare
it in multiple slots in the morning as
part of their daily preparations. Also,
prepared spellcasters automatically
heighten all their spells. If they know
how to cast the first rank version of a
spell, then they also know how to cast
the second rank, third rank, fourth
rank, and other versions, too. And it's
worth mentioning that some features or
abilities may allow a prepared cer to
swap out a spell they've already
prepared for another one. Those are
special circumstances. And for our
purposes in this video, we're going to
focus on the base rule, which is once a
spell is prepared, it cannot be changed
until the next day's preparations.
Spontaneous spellcasters like bards,
oracles, sorcerers, and summoners work a
little bit differently than prepared
casters. Instead of assigning their
spell slants at the start of each day
with the spells they plan to use,
spontaneous spellcasters get to choose
which spell they're using a spell slot
for at the moment they cast it. This
grants spontaneous spellcasters a lot of
freedom in how they choose to spend
their spell slots, but there are a
couple important limitations. First,
spontaneous casters are much more
limited in the variety of spells they
can cast. For example, a first level
bard has two spell slots and knows how
to cast two spells, ignoring their
cantrips. They don't have to decide in
advance if they want to cast each of
those spells once per day or cast the
same spell twice, but they're still
limited to just those two spells. A
first level wizard, on the other hand,
also starts with two spell slots, but
knows five different spells. They have
to choose in advance how those two spell
slots will be used each day, but they
have a more varied list of spell options
to choose from. And the second big
limitation is how spontaneous casters
handle heightened spells. Prepared
casters like our wizards and clerics are
able to freely heighten any spell they
know. If a cleric knows how to cast a
first rank heal spell, then they're able
to cast heal at any rank as long as they
prepare it in a slot at the start of the
day. But if a spontaneous caster like a
sorcerer with a divine bloodline wishes
to cast heal at different ranks, each
rank of heal counts as a completely
different spell in their repertoire. If
a fifth level angelic sorcerer knows how
to cast four first rank spells, four
second rank spells, and three third rank
spells. That list might look like this.
first rank, air bubble, alarm, heal, and
runic weapon. For second rank, they know
the second rank version of heal, the
second rank version of runic weapon,
spiritual armament, and translate. And
for third rank, they know the third rank
version of heal, holy light, and the
third rank version of translate.
Spontaneous casters know fewer spells
than prepared casters. And on top of
that, they have to treat every
individual rank of a spell as if it is a
completely different spell. Meaning that
in order to cast heal as a first rank
spell, a second rank spell, and as a
third rank spell, the spontaneous caster
needs to sacrifice three of their noon
spells in order to do so. But if a
prepared caster knows how to cast heal,
they automatically know how to cast
every other rank of heal, too. One very
important exception to this is signature
spells. Spontaneous casters can gain
signature spells as they level up. When
a spell is designated as a signature
spell, spontaneous casters can freely
heighten it the same as a prepared
caster. So, if the angelic sorcerer in
the previous example took heal as one of
their signature spells, then it would
only occupy one of their known spells,
and they would be able to heighten it to
cast at any rank. Spontaneous casters
can also cast a spell using a higher
rank spell slot without heightening it.
For example, a sorcerer knows the first
rank and third rank versions of Breathe
Fire, but not the second rank version.
This sorcerer could cast Breathe Fire
using a second rank spell slot, but it
wouldn't function any differently than
the normal first rank spell. This is
different from prepared spellcasters who
automatically heighten all their spells
to the rank of the spell slot that's
being used to cast it.
That's how prepared and spontaneous
spellcasters work in general. But
there's one more thing to consider. In
my experience GMing Pathfinder,
something I commonly encounter from new
players is their desire to play a
prepared spell-casting class using the
spontaneous spell-casting rules. This is
especially common amongst players coming
to the game from fifth edition Dn D. The
good news is that there is a way to
accommodate these players within the
rules, and that is a class archetype
found in Secrets of Magic called
flexible spellcasting. as a class
archetype. This must be declared at
first level and it will cost the players
second level class feat. With this
archetype, instead of assigning a
specific spell of a specific rank to
each spell slot as part of their daily
preparations, these spellcasters create
a collection of spells. And then during
the adventuring day, they can cast
spells from this collection the same as
a spontaneous cer where they choose the
spell and the spell slot at the moment
it is cast. There are however a couple
downsides to this in addition to
sacrificing the character's second level
spell feat. The main downside is
flexible spellcasters use a different
spells per day table than their classes
spells per day table. And the key
difference here is flexible spellcasters
have fewer spells per rank, maxing at
two instead of three. So basically the
main benefit of this archetype is the
ability to cast spells spontaneously and
the main drawback is fewer spells per
day. I should also mention that any
players interested in this archetype
should discuss it with their GM first as
it is not a core archetype, meaning they
should not assume that it is allowed in
every game.
This video has served as a foundation on
prepared and spontaneous spellcasting as
well as covering spell slots in
heightening. In the next part of this
series, we will dive into topics such as
casting time, duration, and the sustain
action. If you have any questions,
please leave them in the comments below.
And as always, I want to take a quick
moment to thank everyone out there who
supports me and this channel. Whether
you do that by liking the video, leaving
a comment, subscribing to the channel,
or subscribing to the Patreon. I
appreciate everything you folks do to
support me. And with that, thanks for
watching. Take care and happy gaming.
Heat.
[music]
Heat. [music]