Hello and welcome to Magic and
Pathfinder Second Edition Remastered
Part Three, Learning and Managing
Spells. In this video, we're going to
explore how players determine what
spells their character knows, how they
learn new spells, and how they manage
their spells. As with the previous
videos of this series, it's worth
mentioning that this video will focus on
foundational mechanics, and each class
likely has its own ways of altering
these mechanics, but covering all those
exceptions is beyond the scope of this
video. Also, this video only discusses
spells which use spell slots. Can trips
and focus spells will be covered in
future videos in this series. And last,
it is highly recommended that you watch
the previous video on prepared and
spontaneous spellcasters before
continuing. A link to that video is
provided in the description.
Some of the terminology found in the
books can be a little confusing. The
text refers to spell lists, known
spells, spell books, spell repertoire,
spells you have access to, and other
terms sometimes used interchangeably,
which makes it even worse. What you need
to know is before you can add a spell to
your spell book or to your spell
repertoire or whatever other method your
class may use for managing spells, you
first need to have access to that spell.
The rules refer to the spells you have
access to as quote your spell list,
which should not be confused with your
traditions spell list. The tradition
spell lists are printed in player core 1
and expanded in player core 2 and in
other source books, but your spell list
is unique just to your character. And as
such, I will refer to these as your
personal spell list just to make that
distinction more clear. At character
creation, all spellcasters have access
to the common rarity spells on their
tradition spell list. And note the word
common. It's typical for players to
believe that if a spell appears on their
tradition spell list, then they can
choose it when they level up, and that
is not correct. You may only select from
the spells you have access to, or in
other words, you may only choose from
the spells on your personal spell list.
By default, each spell-casting character
starts with a personal spell list that
includes all the common rarity spells
found on their tradition spell list.
Using Lim the Bard as an example, when
creating him at first level, he has a
personal spell list that includes all
the common rarity spells from the occult
spell list. You can tell which spells
are common because they do not have a U
superscript or R superscript next to
their name, which would flag that spell
as either uncommon or rare. So, at first
level, Lim has a personal spell list
that includes all the occult first rank
spells because none of them are uncommon
or rare. When he increases to third
level, he has access to all the second
rank occult spells. But when he reaches
fifth level, his personal spell list
does not include all of the third rank
spells. Why? Because locate, mind
readading, ring of truth, and veil of
privacy all have a U superscript next to
their name, meaning they are uncommon
spells. You can also tell they are
uncommon rarity by their traits. As
such, Lim would not be permitted to add
them to his spell repertoire. Instead,
Lim would need to do something to gain
access to these uncommon spells. Only
then would he add them to his personal
spell list, which would then make the
spells available for his repertoire. And
a quick note, some viewers out there may
be questioning whether all characters in
all circumstances need to adhere to
maintaining a personal spell list, as I
am recommending in this video. Keep in
mind that I'm trying to discuss magic in
general terms to avoid having to cover
every exception and every special case
from every different class. But in
general, the classes that do not use
spell books or a familiar to manage
their spells should probably maintain a
personal spell list to record what
spells they have access to. It may not
be 100% required in all cases, but I
find it's better to have it and not need
it than need it and not have it. Plus,
maintaining a personal spell list can
help you understand how this system
works.
So, this raises the question of how do
you gain access to spells? There are a
few general ways that I'll review, but
keep in mind that each class may have
their own methods of modifying how
spells are gained. So, specifics might
adjust these general methods. First, the
GM can grant access. For example, if
your character's backstory is that they
are a magical detective, your GM might
simply grant you access to locate, which
normally would not be available since it
is uncommon. Other typical reasons GMs
might grant access to uncommon spells is
if the character is from an ancestry,
culture, nationality, or organization
that is thematically tied to that spell.
Second, characters may gain access to
spells through class features. For
example, clerics gain access to spells
from their deity. A cleric who worships
abidor would add illusory object
creation and planer palace to their
personal spell list even though they are
not on the divine tradition spell list
and planer palace is not common rarity.
Likewise, oracles would add their
mystery spells to their personal spell
list. Sorcerers would add their
bloodline sorceress gifts to their
personal spell list if they're not
already there. Wizards add their
school's curriculum spells and so on.
Note that several class options
specifically instruct you to add the
spell to the character's repertoire or
spell book. In these cases, the spell
would be added to both the character's
personal spell list and to their classes
method of managing spells. And the third
method of gaining access to spells is
probably the most common after character
creation, and that's the learn a spell
activity.
This is the universal method for gaining
access to uncommon or rare spells or
spells that are not automatically
granted by your class progression. To
use learn a spell, you must first be
provided a source from which to learn
the spell and the spell must be on your
tradition spell list. The source can
take many forms. It could be someone who
is willing to teach the spell to you. It
could be a written text like a spell
book or a spell scroll. or it could be a
special process provided by your class,
like learning a spell from a fellow
witch's familiar. Regardless of what
form the source takes, you must spend
one hour per rank of the spell in the
presence of that source, either being
taught or studying a magical text and
have an amount of materials available
per the learning a spell table on page
231 of player core 1. For example, if
Lim the bard wishes to learn Ring of
Truth, he must first find a source for
it, which may be someone willing to
teach him or discovering a written copy
of it while adventuring. And second, he
must have 16 gold pieces worth of
materials since Ring of Truth is a third
rank spell. Note that the rules do not
specify what these materials are or how
to find them in much the same way as the
crafting rules do not specify what
specific materials are needed to craft
most items. In general, I suspect the
materials are magical inks, special
parchments, perhaps incense to meditate
on the divine with, and so on. I think
in most games, this would be handwaved,
and as long as Lim has 16 gold in his
pocket, he'd be able to proceed. But
some GMs might want to enforce stricter
rules, especially in cases where the
desired spell is rare or holds a special
place in the narrative. Also note that
the cost for learning the spell is
strictly materials. If learning the
spell from someone else, that person
might charge for their services. There
is no hard rule for this, but I think
the income earned table on page 229 of
player core 1 is a good guideline. For
example, if Limb's teacher is seventh
level with expert proficiency in
oultism, they might charge two and a
half gold for their services. They might
also charge the cost of a scroll
containing the desired spell. But if
that is the case, then GMs make sure
that the player gets to keep that scroll
afterwards. And after spending one hour
per rank of the spell, the player rolls
whichever skill is appropriate for their
tradition, either arcana, nature,
occultism, or religion, and compares the
result against the typical DC found on
the learning a spell table adjusted by
the rarity of the spell being learned,
plus two for uncommon spells or plus
five for rare spells. So using our
example with Lim the Bard, if he was
learning Ring of Truth, which is a third
rank spell, he would spend 3 hours
studying, after which he would roll an
oultism check versus DC22
20 per the learning a spell table plus
two for being an uncommon spell. If he
rolls a critical success, he learns the
spell and adds it to his personal spell
list. He also gets half of the materials
back. In this case, that would be eight
gold pieces. If he rolls a normal
success, he learns the spell and adds it
to his personal spell list, but gets no
money back. If he rolls a failure, he
fails to learn the spell, gets all of
his materials back, and can try again
after he levels up. And on a critical
failure, he fails to learn the spell,
loses half of his materials, and can
still try again after the next time he
levels up. And note that success means
he gains access to the spell, not that
he can immediately cast it. In other
words, Ring of Truth is added to Lim's
personal spell list, but not to his
spell repertoire. We'll discuss a little
bit later in this video what he needs to
do to then add it to his spell
repertoire so he can cast it. So, those
are the basics of learn a spell. But one
question that often comes up when
learning spells is if you learn a spell
from a scroll, is that scroll destroyed?
This was the way it worked in older
editions of the game. If a wizard found
a scroll while adventuring, they could
either use it to cast the spell from it
one time or transcribe the spell into
their spell book using a process that
destroyed the scroll. But in Pathfinder
second edition, that is not the case.
You can learn a spell from a scroll and
still use that scroll to cast the spell
later, at which point it would be
consumed as normal. There is one
important exception to this, however,
and that is for witches. A witch's
familiar may learn spells from a scroll,
but must physically consume the scroll
in order to do so.
Once you have access to spells per your
personal spell list, whether they are
common spells you start with, spells
provided by class features such as your
deity, or you have used the learn a
spell activity, your class might then
need to have a way of managing them
before they can be cast using spell
slots. For example, you might carry a
spell book or have a spell repertoire.
I'll try to make this brief, but keep in
mind again that every class has features
and feats that likely modify things, but
I will only be covering the general
information here. And I will also only
be covering classes that have been
introduced to or updated for the
remaster edition at the time of this
recording.
Let's start with the classes that use a
spell repertoire. All spontaneous
casters use a spell repertoire. So,
we're talking primarily about bards,
oracles, and sorcerers. A spell
repertoire is basically a list of the
spells they can cast using spell slots.
If the spell is not on their repertoire,
then they can't cast it. And if the
spell is not on their personal spell
list, then they can't add it to their
repertoire. But during the adventuring
day, they can spend their spell slots
whenever they like to cast spells that
are found on their repertoire. Also, the
number of spells contained in each cer's
repertoire is strictly limited. As the
caster levels up, they get to add new
spells to their repertoire so they can
keep pace with the amount of new spell
slots they get. And every time they
level up, they can adjust the spells in
their repertoire by swapping one spell
out that they don't want for another
spell of an equal rank. But this is very
limited. It's only one spell and only
done when leveling up. If they want to
adjust their repertoire more than that,
they'll need to formally retrain using
downtime. This calls for a week of
downtime to swap one spell in the
repertoire for another of equal rank and
may require a teacher and a monetary
cost at the GM's discretion. So, in our
earlier example of Lim the Bard, who
used the learn a spell activity to get
access to Ring of Truth, here is the way
that he would then move it from his
personal spell list to his repertoire.
He could either do that the next time he
levels up or he would have to spend a
week of downtime retraining and swap out
one spell from his repertoire for Ring
of Truth. And also note that some
classes provide spells that cannot be
swapped out. For example, certain spells
provided by a sorcerer's bloodline or an
Oracle's mystery. They have to stay on
the repertoire. But the bottom line is,
if your class uses a spell repertoire,
you can only cast spells included in
that repertoire, and those spells must
be spells you have access to, which is
why it's often a good idea to maintain a
separate personal spell list.
The next method of spell management we
should discuss is spell books.
Spellbooks are used primarily by wizards
and contain all the spells the wizard is
able to prepare each day. Unlike with
spell repertoars, there is no hard limit
to how many spells a typical spell book
can hold, which grants a wizard much
more variety in the spells they know,
but are limited by being able to only
prepare a limited number of spells each
day. So, wizards can only cast spells
they have prepared and can only prepare
spells found in their spell book. And
that spell book may only contain spells
that they have access to per their
personal spell list. But now, let's take
a moment to discuss every wizard's worst
nightmare. What happens if they lose
their spell book? There really are not a
lot of hard and fast rules for this, but
it appears that should this happen, the
wizard would be able to cast any spells
they already have prepared, but would
not be able to fill their spell slots
during their daily preparations. In
other words, they would not be able to
prepare any new spells. By raw, they
would need to use learn a spell to add
their lost spells to a new spell book,
but would need to find a source for each
spell, either a teacher or a scroll, for
every spell, even the most common of
cantrips, and would need to pay the
costs and pass the skill checks. Some
GMs may allow wizards in this situation
to transfer any spells they currently
have prepared to a new spell book for
free, but the spell slot is consumed in
the process. Other GMs may allow spells
that were lost to be added to a new
spell book at half the usual cost or
without the need for a teacher. And in
Pathfinder first edition, wizards could
copy their spell books at half the cost
of learning spells and then store these
backup books in a secure location. These
are all special considerations that are
not hardcoded into the rules by raw and
will come down to whatever your GM
thinks is best for the game.
Next, let's talk about witches. Witches
basically work the same way as wizards,
except instead of keeping a spell book,
they have a familiar. Technically,
witches themselves do not know any
spells, but instead their familiar does,
and they must commune with their
familiar to prepare the spells they will
cast each day. This is why many people
refer to familiars as living spell
books. And they work pretty much the
same way. A witch can't cast a spell
they don't have prepared. They can't
prepare a spell their familiar doesn't
know, and their familiar can only learn
spells the witch has access to per a
personal spell list. The two key
differences for witches, though, are
unlike wizards, when they learn a spell
from a scroll, that scroll is destroyed
in the process. And should a witch lose
their familiar or their familiar dies,
their patron replaces that familiar the
next day, and the replacement familiar
knows all the spells the previous
familiar did. So there's significantly
less danger involved than a wizard who
loses their spell book.
Then we have clerics and druids. These
are the easiest to discuss because they
don't have any special requirements for
managing their spells. They don't need
to keep a spell repertoire or maintain a
spell book or do anything else. They get
their spells directly from the gods or
by communing with nature. So, if the
spell appears on their personal spell
list, then they can prepare it. It's
it's that easy.
And one last class to consider is the
animist. Animists are sort of a hybrid
spellcaster with the ability to cast
both prepared and spontaneous spells.
The animist draws magic from the divine
tradition, but they access it through
two different channels. The first is
called animist spellcasting. This is
their own ability to cast spells through
a prepared process similar to clerics.
Their second form of spell-casting is
called apparition spellcasting. Animus
bond with different spirits and each day
they can spontaneously cast spells
provided by these apparitions. The
spells per day table on page 13 of War
of Immortals shows how many spell slots
they receive for each type of spell
casting. The number before the plus
shows how many prepared spell slots they
have for their own animous spell
casting. And the number after the plus
shows how many spontaneous spell slots
they have for apparition spellcasting.
So every morning as part of their daily
preparations, the animist will prepare
divine spells from their personal spell
list just like a cleric would and will
also choose a limited number of
apparitions found on pages 17 through 21
of War of Immortals. Each of these
apparitions provide a list of spells and
all these spells together form a
repertoire from which the animist can
cast spontaneous spells each day. And
note that the animist can usually choose
new apparitions each day and every spell
provided by an apparition is considered
a signature spell that can be freely
heightened. But one important drawback
is the animist can only use the learn a
spell activity to learn new spells they
cast themselves with animous spell
casting. These would be the spells that
they use their prepared spell slots for.
They cannot simply learn a new spell to
cast with one of their spontaneous spell
slots. Instead, the animist will need to
find and attune with a new apparition
that provides the spell they want.
This video has served as a foundation on
how spellcasters learn and manage their
spells. In the next part of the series,
we'll dive into topics such as casting
time, duration, and the sustain action.
If you have any questions, please leave
them in the comments below. And as
always, I want to take a brief moment to
thank everyone who supports me in this
channel. Whether you do that by liking
the video, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon, I appreciate
everything you do to support me. And
with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[music]
Yeah.
Heat.
[music]