Hello and welcome to Magic in Pathfinder
second edition remastered part 4. In the
previous videos, we covered magic
traditions, how prepared and spontaneous
casters use spell slots to cast their
spells, and the process used for
learning and managing spells. And in
this video, we're going to begin
discussing spell mechanics, starting
with casting time and spell durations.
The cast entry in a spell description
lists the amount of time needed to cast
the spell. This is usually displayed as
a number of actions to be spent in
encounter mode, but could also be a
number of minutes, such as the case with
Raised Dead if the spell is intended to
be used in exploration mode. And some
spells, like breath of life, can be cast
as a reaction. Most encounter spells
require two actions to cast, but many
spells that cause things to manifest and
persist in the environment, like blessed
boundaries, summon spells, wall spells,
and certain illusions, require three
actions. But those are just rules of
thumb. Always check the spell
description to be certain.
The cast entry in a spell's description
tells you how long it takes to activate
the spell, and the duration entry tells
you how long it will persist after that.
If a spell has no listed duration, then
it's instantaneous. It starts and ends
on the caster's turn, but may have
effects that last longer than that. For
example, noise blast has no listed
duration and therefore is instantaneous,
but the target might become deafened or
stunned for 10 more rounds. When an
effect lasts longer than the duration,
like in this case, the effect is not
considered to be magical, and therefore
something like dispel magic could not be
used to cure the victim's deafness. And
when the duration is listed as a number
of rounds, the number of rounds
remaining decreases by one at the start
of each of the spellcasters turns and
ends when that duration reaches zero.
Some spells have a list duration which
include the word sustain. When you cast
a sustained spell, it is due to expire
at the end of your next turn after you
cast it, unless you spend an action on
that turn to extend the spell's duration
by another round. To do this, you spend
one action to use sustain a spell, which
allows you to add enough magic energy
and thought into the spell to keep it
going for another round. Now, the spell
will cease at the end of your next turn
unless you spin an action on that round
to sustain it again and so on. And note
that a common question is what happens
if the caster falls unconscious or dies
before the duration is up. And the
answer is well, nothing happens. The
spell continues to persist even if the
caster dies before its duration is up.
Think of it like fuel. enough magic fuel
was put into the spell when it was cast
to keep it going until it runs out when
the spell's duration ends. And this also
means that by raw, a person could cast a
sustained spell, get knocked
unconscious, and as long as they get
revived before their next turn, they
could use sustain a spell again to keep
the spell going. Also, most spells that
allow you to sustain them have a maximum
duration, like 1 minute, that you can't
sustain beyond that. And if a maximum
duration is not listed, then you can
sustain it for up to 10 minutes or 100
rounds, after which you become fatigued
and cannot sustain it anymore. If you
want to cast it again, you'll need to
use a spell slot like normal.
Now, when it comes to sustaining spells,
there are a few more questions that seem
to pop up. The first of those is, can I
sustain multiple spells at the same
time? And the answer to that is yes, you
can. If you somehow have three active
spells that all have a duration of
sustain and have not passed their
maximum durations, then you could spend
three actions and continue to sustain
all three of them. The second question
is, can I sustain the same spell
multiple times in the same round? And
the answer to this is also yes. So on
the round following the casting of a
sustained spell, you can spend three
actions to sustain the spell three times
and trigger its effect three times. A
good example of this would be spiritual
arament where each time you sustain it,
it attacks another time. However, some
spells like floating flame include
special notations. Here it says a given
creature can take damage from floating
flame only once per round. So, there's
nothing preventing you from using three
actions to sustain floating flame three
times. But if you deal damage to a
target the first time, you'll need to
use the remaining sustain actions to
target other enemies.
Some spells like environmental endurance
have durations that say until your next
daily preparations. What this means is
on your next day as part of your daily
preparations, you can choose to not
regain that spell slot. Doing so
basically sustains the spell and extends
its duration for another day until your
next daily preparations. This lets you
sustain the spell over very long periods
of time. But if you ever do choose to
regain that spell slot during daily
preparations, then the spell immediately
ends. If you are ever unconscious or
dead at the 24-hour mark after the last
preparations, you cannot sustain it and
the spell ends. Also, the spell must
have been cast using a spell slot, and
you must use spell slots to continue it.
So, for example, you can't use charges
from a staff or use a magic wand or any
other magic item for this purpose of
extending the duration. Last, if a spell
has a duration of unlimited, like embed
message, you don't need to reserve spell
slots in this way to continue it. If the
duration is unlimited, then it lasts
until it is either counteracted or you
dismiss it. And speaking of dismissing,
dismissing a spell allows you to end it
early before its listed duration is up.
Doing so costs one action, but note that
by raw, only spells that specifically
say they can be dismissed can be
dismissed. For example, the confusion
spell shows this. But if a spell does
not specifically state that it can be
dismissed, then you'll need to wait
until its duration is up in order for it
to end.
This video has served as a foundation on
spellcasting mechanics such as casting
time, duration, and the sustain action.
In the next video of this series, we'll
explore spell range and area. If you
have any questions, please leave them in
the comments below. And as always, I
want to take a brief moment to thank
everyone who supports me and this
channel. Whether you do that by liking
the video, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon, I appreciate
everything you folks do to support me.
And with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[music]
>> [music]