Hello and welcome to Magic and
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part five range and area.
Each spell's description has a line that
displays its range and targets. When a
spell has a listed range, its effects
can only manifest within that listed
space. A spell with a range of touch
requires the caster to touch the target
with some part of their hand, even if
that hand is covered in a glove or
holding something. So, the spell's range
is usually the same as their unarmed
attack range, 5T for small and medium
creatures, and 10 ft or longer for
creatures that are at least size large.
The act of touching itself does not
require any rolls, but the spells often
allow the target to make a save or
require the caster to make a spell
attack roll.
The range might also be listed as an
area such as a burst, cone, imination,
or line. Note that for each of these, I
will provide some explanation for how to
draw the area yourself. But remember,
you can always use the templates found
on page 429 of player core 1 if that's
easier. When casting a spell with a
burst area, you select an intersection
of squares within the spell's listed
range and then draw a number of feet
away from that point in all directions.
So, a 5-ft burst is the same as a 2x two
square area. And a 10-ft burst would
look like this. You select an
intersection and then all squares within
10 ft of that point. Remember,
alternating diagonal squares count as 10
ft. So, a 10-ft burst will not hit a
target that is two squares away
diagonally.
Cone areas can be a little tricky. When
casting a spell with a cone area, you
select either a corner or intersection
of squares like you would with a burst,
or you can select the entire side of one
of your squares. In both cases, the
caster must be adjacent to the point of
origin without standing inside the area
of the cone. And the area will expand
the further it moves from the caster in
one quarter direction. When drawing a
cone area diagonally, you select one
quarter of the square you occupy and
then choose one quarter direction and
all squares within range of that point
in that direction are affected by the
spell. Let's illustrate that with an
example. Ezren is surrounded by goblins
and wants to target as many as possible
with breathe fire, which is a 15 ft
cone. His first option is to draw the
cone diagonally. In this case, he will
choose one of the corners of the square
he occupies, and all squares within 15
feet of that point in one quarter
direction will be hit by the spell. Or
another way to think of it is if you're
making a 15- ft cone, 15 ft is three
squares. So, start by drawing two three
square lines at a 90° angle from your
selected corner first, and then fill in
the middle square so that all squares
within 15 ft from the point of origin
are affected.
That's drawing a cone diagonally. The
other way to draw a cone is orthogonal.
In this case, you don't select a corner
of your square, but instead choose an
entire side of your square. And the
design of these cones, unfortunately,
becomes more complex. 15- ft cones are
easy enough. the area expands outward
from you and hits a 3x3 area centered on
the side of the square that you select
except for the other two squares that
are adjacent to you. In this example,
only the gold squares are hit by breathe
fire. The two other adjacent squares are
safe. Imagine it's a cone that's
widening as it moves away from you. But
the design of orthogonal cones becomes
pretty complex beyond 15 feet because 30
foot and 60 foot orthogonal cones
actually begin decreasing in size after
a certain point whereas diagonal cones
do not do that. So I would recommend you
bookmark page 429 of player core 1 and
refer there when drawing orthogonal
cones that are greater than 15 ft.
Next are iminations. And these are
thankfully very simple. They work like
bursts except instead of choosing an
intersection of squares, the area
originates from you. So a 5-ft imination
affects every square adjacent to you.
And a 10-ft imination hits everything
within 10 ft of you. And note that the
person who cast the spell and is
standing in the center of his area gets
to choose whether they want to be
affected by that spell or not.
And last are lines. Lines,
unfortunately, are more complicated than
you might think. A line is 5 ft wide and
travels in one direction for the number
of feet that's listed. You start by
selecting the first square and then
select an ending square. that is the
number of listed feet away and then
connect those squares with the line
moving in one direction. Meaning that
every square the line passes through
must be both further from the point of
origin and closer to the final square
than the square before it. The line can
move through squares diagonally as long
as it's always diagonally in the same
direction. And those diagonal breaks
should be as equidistant as possible.
Basically, this means a 30-foot line
might look like this,
or like this,
or it might even look like this.
And believe it or not, a 30foot line
could look like this, or even like this.
In my opinion, as long as each square of
the line is connected and each square is
further from the starting square and
closer to the final square, it should
count. Or if you really want to keep
life easy, just stick to lines that are
perfectly straight orthagonally or
diagonally.
And one more note about area effects. If
the spell originates from the caster,
then it only has an area, but other
spells might include both a range and an
area, such as with fireball. In this
case, it has a range of 500 ft and
affects a 20ft burst area. What this
means is the intersection of squares
that is chosen as the point of origin
for the spell must be within 500 ft. 500
ft is 100 squares which is way too much
for me to fit on the screen here. But
let's just say that this line marks 500
ft from the wizard who is casting
fireball. They can target any
intersection or corner of squares below
this line. Any area above the line is
out of range, but only the point of
origin needs to be within range. So they
could target this intersection, which
would cause a 20 ft burst area and
affect all targets within 20 ft of the
targeted intersection, even those
squares that are beyond the 500 ft range
from the caster.
This video has served as a foundation on
spell-casting mechanics such as range
and area. In the next video of this
series, we'll explore the rules for
casting spells, including concepts such
as targeting spells, line of effect,
disrupting spells, spell attack roles,
and saving throws. If you have any
questions, please leave them in the
comments below. And as always, I want to
take a brief moment to thank everyone
who supports me and this channel.
Whether you do that by liking the video,
leaving a comment, subscribing to the
channel, or subscribing to the Patreon,
I appreciate everything you folks do to
support me. And with that, thanks for
watching. Take care and happy gaming.
>> [music]