Hello and welcome to Magic in Pathfinder
second edition remastered part 6,
casting spells and spell attacks.
Casting spells works much the same way
as other activities in the game. You
must have the spell prepared in advance
or have a valid spell slot available in
the case of spontaneous casters. And
then you spend a number of actions
listed in the spell's description. As
mentioned in a previous video, most
spells intended for encounter mode
require two actions. except for those
that cause something to physically
manifest and persist in the world, which
usually take three actions, but those
are just guidelines. So, always check
the spell's description. Once the action
cost has been met, the spell effect
occurs immediately. Some spells are not
intended for use in encounter mode and
instead have their casting times listed
in terms of minutes or hours. You cannot
use any other actions or reactions while
casting these spells, but the GM might
allow you to speak while casting. And
although not displayed in the spells
description, all spells that have
casting times listed as minutes or hours
automatically receive the exploration
trait. And since they have the
exploration trait, they cannot be cast
at all in encounter mode. So, if the
casting time is 1 minute, by raw, you
can't spend 10 encounter rounds to cast
it, even though 10 combat rounds equals
1 minute. And if combat breaks out in
the middle of casting an exploration
spell, then the spell is immediately
disrupted.
Some abilities and circumstances can
cause a spell to be disrupted and lost.
A common example is being struck by a
reactive strike while casting. The
triggers for reactive strike are a
creature within your reach uses a
manipulate action or a move action,
makes a ranged attack, or leaves a
square during a move action it's using.
The key piece of this that applies to
spellcasting is using a manipulate
action. The manipulate trait says you
must physically manipulate an item or
make gestures to use an action with this
trait. Creatures without a suitable
appendage cannot perform actions with
this trait. Manipulate actions often
trigger reactions. And you'll notice
that if a spell requires actions to be
spent casting it, then it almost always
has the manipulate trait. And if the
spell is cast using a reaction, then it
almost always does not have the
manipulate trait. So most of the time
when you cast a spell in combat, it will
have the manipulate trait and therefore
may trigger reactions from enemies like
reactive strike. And if that reactive
strike is a critical hit, then the spell
you're casting is disrupted. When a
spell is disrupted, it is lost along
with all resources that were committed
to the casting of that spell. Meaning
you lose all of the required actions. If
it was a spell that cost three actions
and it's immediately disrupted by an
enemy's reactive strike, then you lose
all three actions. The reactive strike
doesn't occur after your first of those
actions, leaving you two that you can
spend on other activities. All three
actions would be lost, and all other
resources are also lost. You lose the
spell slot that was committed, as well
as any material cost for the spell. And
when an attempt to sustain a spell is
disrupted, not only is that action lost,
but the spell you are attempting to
sustain immediately ends.
Let's review the rules for targeting.
This applies to all attacks, but can
become especially confusing when casting
spells due to how people imagine them
manifesting within the narrative of the
game. where sometimes there's a massive
fireball that physically travels to the
target and other times a spell manifests
like a Jedi mind trick that confuses the
target without anything physical passing
between the caster and their target. By
raw, the rules work the same way in both
cases without any special consideration
given to spells that have no physical
manifestation. When you cast the spell,
you must have line of effect to the
target. And in order to have line of
effect, there must be an unobstructed
path to the target. And generally, as
long as the target is not behind a solid
wall that blocks all physical access to
them, then you have line of effect. If
the target is only partially behind a
solid object, like behind a crate or a
port cullis, then there is still line of
effect and you can target them, but they
also have cover if you cast an area
effect with a point of origin on your
side of the gate. And the rule of thumb
provided by player core 1 is that a 1 ft
square gap in a barrier is all that is
needed to allow line of effect. But as
always, the GM has the final say. Also
be aware that when casting a spell with
an area effect, the caster needs a line
of effect to where they are placing the
origin of the effect and all affected
creatures and objects needs line of
effect to that point. For example, if
you cast a fireball spell, you need line
of effect to the point of detonation for
the fireball. And in order for an enemy
to be hit by that fireball, there needs
to be line of effect from that point and
them. If the path to them is not
completely blocked, then there would be
line of effect and they would likely
receive cover. And note that the rule
for line of effect says visibility
doesn't matter for line of effect.
Meaning it doesn't matter if you can see
the target or not. If the target is
inside a building behind a closed
window, you may be able to see them, but
your line of effect stops at the closed
window. Therefore, you wouldn't be able
to target them with a spell- like
confusion, even though there is nothing
physically traveling between you and
them. Now, this often raises a lot of
questions about line of sight and how it
applies. I have another video that goes
over the four degrees of perception and
how they affect targeting creatures. So,
I'm not going to repeat all of that
content here, but I will briefly cover a
few examples. And if you need more
information about how this works, there
is a link to that video on perception in
this video's description. First, let's
talk about what I call general spells.
These are the ones that simply say
things like targets one creature. For
example, divine lance. For this spell,
you need a line of effect to the target,
but don't necessarily need to be able to
see them. If they have the concealed or
hidden conditions, you can still try to
attack them with divine lance, but will
need to pass a flat check or you
automatically miss. Next, there are
spells that specify you must be able to
see the target. For example, vengeful
glare states in its targets entry, one
creature you can see. Therefore, you
could target a creature with a concealed
condition, but would need to pass the
DC5 flat check because that target is
concealed. But you would not be able to
target a creature with the hidden
condition because hidden specifically
states you cannot see them. Then we have
area effects. What happens if you cast a
fireball as someone who is standing
behind a closed window? Again, your line
of effect would end at the closed
window. So you would need to place the
point of origin for the fireball's
detonation somewhere on your side of the
window. And by raw, there would be no
line of effect to the person behind the
closed window. Therefore, they would not
need to roll a reflex save or worry
about suffering any damage. And again,
that's the raw explanation. But that
said, GMs are encouraged to adjust the
rules however is best for their game. So
in this case, the GM might instead grant
the target cover and deduct the hit
point value of the window from the
damage applied by the fireball. And
last, some spells adjust or remove the
requirement for line of effect. For
example, familiar's face has a range of
one mile and targets one willing
creature that's your animal companion or
familiar. So, normally you would need
line of effect to your familiar to cast
this on them. But the spells text
includes a special notation that says
you don't need line of sight or a line
of effect to your target when you cast
this spell. So, in this case, you would
only need to be within one mile of your
animal companion or familiar to target
them with familiar's face.
In the first example, team Pathfinder is
battling a tribe of goblins in a
corridor. For our purposes, the red bars
represent closed doors and the green
bars represent open doors. Her friends
are taking a beating. So on Kyra's turn,
she casts heal using three actions so
that it heals all living creatures
within 30 ft of her. This is a 30-foot
imination centered on her square and
again heals all willing creatures within
that range. So here we can see all of
the targets within the range of that
spell. But next we need to apply line of
effect. In order for there to be line of
effect, there must be an unobstructed
path from the point of origin, which in
this case is Kaira, to the target. When
debating if there is line of effect, I
like to apply the flashlight rule, which
says if Kyra could shine a flashlight on
a target from where she's standing, then
there is line of effect. So, let's apply
that rule. Starting with the easy ones,
Valeros and Mauricio. She easily could
shine the light on Valeros. And even
though there is a goblin between her and
Mara, the goblin doesn't completely
obscure her and Cairo would still be
able to hit her with a flashlight. So
there is line of effect to both of them.
Next, let's consider Ezin and Cion.
Those doors are open and even though it
might be difficult, I believe Kyra could
shine her flashlight on both of them as
well. So they do have line of effect,
too. Lim, on the other hand, is behind a
closed door. Kyra could not shine a
light on him. So there is no line of
effect. And it's worth mentioning that
it would not make any difference at all
if the door was made of glass and was
transparent. That would allow line of
sight, but not line of effect. It would
still be a physical barrier that
obstructs the path to the target. That
also means that the flashlight rule
isn't a 100% perfect illustration, but
it works for me in most situations.
Now comes the hard one. Sila, is there
line of effect from Kyra to her? By raw,
no, there is not. Kyra would not be able
to shine a flashlight on her from her
current space as Sila is completely
obscured behind a wall, but the door is
open and she's next to the door. And
this is where a lot of GMs will put
their own spin on things. Some would say
that the radiant light from the heel
spell spills through the doorway and
around the corner and does affect Sila.
That's not supported by the rules as
written, but as a GM, that's absolutely
in their right to decide differently.
And what about the goblins? There is
clear line of effect to several of them,
but will they be healed, too? And the
answer is yes, they would. They are
living creatures, and one would likely
assume they are willing to be healed, so
they would be healed. However, clerics
can take the selective energy feat to
avoid healing their enemies.
In our next example, Kyra casts Noise
Blast to attack the goblins. Noise Blast
is a 10- ft burst area attack with a 30
ft range. Instead of the spell effect
emanating away from her, she instead
needs to target an intersection of
squares that is within 30 ft of her, and
all squares within 10 ft of that point
of origin will be within the area of
effect. For example, if she wishes to
attack the goblins to the left of her,
she might target this intersection,
which is both within 30 ft of her and
there is an unobstructed path from her
to it. So, this is valid. And the noise
blast would originate from that point
and affect everything within 10 ft of it
as we see here. But then we need to
adjust for line of effect from the point
of origin to each of the goblins. These
three have clear line of effect to the
point of origin and would be affected by
the spell. The northern goblin is behind
a closed door which means there is no
line of effect to them and would not be
affected by the spell. Now that might
beg the question of is the door damaged
and if it is destroyed would any damage
left over pass on to the goblin standing
behind it? And that's a longer
discussion that's beyond the scope of
this video. But the rule specifically
use an example of a fireball spell and
says that a door would stop all damage
from it from passing through. But each
GM is free to roll however they believe
is most appropriate. Now that just
leaves the goblin in the bottom left. Is
there a line of effect from the point of
origin to that goblin? If someone was
standing on the point of origin, could
they shine a flashlight and hit this
goblin? Even though a line from the
intersection does run along the right
hand edge of the goblin square and
through a completely open door, I don't
see this as passing the flashlight test
and would rule that this goblin is safe
from the sound burst spell.
Next, let's consider the goblins to the
bottom right of the screen. For our
purposes, we'll assume she is aware all
of these goblins are grouped there, even
if she doesn't have line of sight to
them. Now, maybe she just crossed that
intersection with her first action and
now she wants to attack them with noise
blast. If she places the 10-ft burst
here, it would hit them all. But
unfortunately, in order to do that, she
would need to place the point of origin
here at this intersection, which she
can't do because she does not have line
of effect to that point. She needs to
have an unobstructed path to the point
of origin and that intersection is
blocked by a wall. So she would need to
place the point of origin here and the
bottom two goblins would not be within
range of the blast.
Some spells require you to succeed at an
attack role to affect the target. Just
like weapon attacks, spell attack roles
are opposed by the target's armor class.
Spell attacks are a type of attack and
therefore they're modified by any
bonuses or penalties that affect attack
roles. For example, victims of a bane
spell suffer a negative one penalty to
all attack roles. This does include
spell attack roles, too. Whatever
effects say that they modify just
attacks without specifying a specific
type of attack, they affect spell
attacks, too. But if the effect calls
out a specific type of attack like
weapon attacks, then obviously those
would not apply to spell attacks. Now,
one specific penalty that definitely
needs to be discussed is the multiple
attack penalty. This applies to all
actions with the attack trait. For
example, divine lance requires a spell
attack role and has the attack trait.
Therefore, it is affected by and
contributes to the multiple attack
penalty. When making a spell attack
roll, your modifier is equal to your
spell-casting ability modifier plus your
spell-casting proficiency bonus. The
ability modifier that is used depends on
how you gain access to the spell you're
casting. If your class granted the
ability to cast the spell, then you use
that class's spell-casting ability
modifier, which is often the class's key
ability modifier. Bars and sorcerers use
charisma. Clerics and druids use wisdom.
Witches and wizards use intelligence,
and so on.
Innate spells, which we'll talk about in
an upcoming video, use the caster's
charisma modifier. And other sources of
spells can specify what ability modifier
to use for their spells. But the rule of
thumb is when in doubt, use charisma.
And this can lead to situations where a
caster uses different ability modifiers
to cast different spells. For example, a
cleric would use their wisdom modifier
when casting divine spells granted by
their class, but would use charisma when
casting innate spells. And if that
cleric was also multiclust into wizard,
then they would use intelligence as the
modifier for their arcane wizard spells.
Spell-casting classes also grant
proficiency in casting spells, just like
how a marshall class grants proficiency
in using weapons. For example, starting
druids have trained proficiency in spell
attacks and in spell DC. And this bonus
works the same as any other proficiency
bonus. Trained proficiency grants two
plus your level, expert grants four plus
your level, master grants six plus your
level, and legendary grants eight plus
your level. And note that in the
remaster, spellcasting proficiency
levels are no longer divided among the
four magical traditions. You only have
one spell attack proficiency level and
one spell DC proficiency level. And in
virtually all cases, they will be the
same. Each spell will detail what
happens on a hit or miss. For example,
divine lance deals 2d4 spirit damage on
a hit. On a critical hit, you would
double this to 44 damage, and nothing
happens on a failure or critical
failure.
Some spells will call for the target to
make a saving throw, such as a reflex
save to avoid a fireball blast or a will
save to fight against mental
manipulation. The DC for these saves is
the same as the caster spell DC, which
is easy to calculate. It's your base
spell attack bonus plus 10. As a result,
if a character can cast spells from
multiple sources, they have different
DCs, just like their spell attacks use
different ability scores and have
different bonuses. Each spell's
description will either provide details
as to what happens on a successful or
failed save, or it will refer to it as a
quote basic saving throw. These are very
common for damaging effects. And what
basic saving throw means is if you
succeed, you only suffer half the listed
damage. If you critically succeed, you
take no damage. If you fail, you take
normal damage. And if you critically
fail, you suffer double damage. With
that in mind, let's look at a few common
examples. Fireball calls for a basic
saving throw. When cast, all targets in
the burst area must each roll a reflex
saving throw versus the caster's spell
DC. On a success, they suffer half
damage. On a failure, they take full
damage. On a critical success, they take
no damage. And on a critical failure,
they suffer double damage. You would
only roll the damage once though and
apply that damage total individually to
each target depending on their reflex
saves level of success or failure.
All right, now let's break this down
with a couple of more examples to
illustrate all of this. Valon is a first
level elven cloistered cleric of Abidor.
He has a plus two intelligence modifier,
plus three wisdom, and plus one
charisma. and he has trained proficiency
in spell attacks and spell DC and
trained proficiency in the religion
skill. He wants to cast divine lance at
the goblin. First, we need to calculate
his spell attack bonus, which is ability
modifier plus proficiency. As a cleric,
he uses wisdom as his spell-casting
ability. He has a plus three wisdom
modifier, and he has trained proficiency
in spell attack. Train proficiency is
two plus level. He's first level, so
that's one more for a total spell attack
bonus of plus six. When he casts the
spell, he makes a ranged spell attack
roll 1d20 + 6. And that total is
compared to the goblin's armor class of
17. We'll say he rolls an 11 on the die
for a total of 17, which is just enough
to hit the goblin. Then on the next
round, Valon attempts to cast Infeeble
on the goblin. In this case, Valon will
not make a spell attack roll and instead
the Goblin will need to pass a fortitude
save. The DC for this save will be
Valon's divine spell DC. To calculate
this, you simply add 10 to his spell
attack bonus of plus six for a DC of 16.
Now the goblin must roll a fortitude
save and meet or beat balance divine
spell DC of 16 to succeed. On a success,
the goblin becomes infeebled one. On a
failure, they're infeebled two. On a
critical success, nothing happens. And
on a critical failure, the goblin
becomes infeebled three.
Let's fast forward a little bit. And now
Valon is third level. The first thing we
want to do is adjust his divine spell
attack bonus and DC. Since those are
both based on proficiency, and
proficiency increases with level, his
divine spell attack bonus is now plus 8,
and that means his divine spell DC is
18. Also, at third level, he gets to
increase one skill to expert
proficiency. He chooses to boost his
religion skill to expert, which
increases his religion bonus to plus 10.
This increase to expert proficiency with
religion has no impact at all on his
divine spell attack bonus or DC. Even
though religion is the key skill for
divine magic, it is wholly separate from
spell-casting proficiency and valance
spell-casting proficiency level is
trained. Now, let's fast forward again
to fifth level. Every time you increase
level, you need to adjust your spell
attack bonus and DC. But before we do
that, there are a couple other things to
consider. First, at fifth level, you get
to increase four of your ability scores.
Valon chooses decks, intelligence,
wisdom, and charisma. This changes his
final ability scores to plus three
intelligence, plus four wisdom, and plus
two charisma. Next, we need to adjust
his divine spell-casting attack bonus
and DC. The calculation is ability
modifier plus proficiency. His wisdom
bonus is plus4 and train proficiency is
two plus level. Four + two plus fifth
level grants a final divine spell attack
bonus of plus 11 and that makes his
divine spell DC 21. Also at fifth
leveling gets to choose a new ancestry
feat. He selects otherworldly magic
which lets him cast one arcane cantrip
as an innate spell. He chooses electric
arc as that spell. And since this is an
innate spell, he does not cast it with
the same bonuses he uses for cleric
divine spells. Those are based on wisdom
as the key ability modifier, but innate
spells use charisma. So, let's calculate
his spell DC for electric arc. Spell DC
is 10 plus spell attack. So, let's start
there. Spell attack is ability modifier
plus proficiency. His charisma bonus is
plus two. And he has trained proficiency
with spell attacks and DCs, which is two
plus level. So two for charisma, plus
two for trained, plus five for level
equals a final innate spell bonus of
plus 9. And 10 more than that makes an
innate spell DC of 19. So to sum up,
when Valon casts a spell from the divine
spell list, he has a spell attack bonus
of plus 11 and spell DC of 21. But when
he casts electric arc, which is his
innate spell, he has a spell attack
bonus of plus 9 and spell DC of 19.
Let's jump forward one more time to
sixth level with his class feat. This
level, he decides to multiclass into
wizard by selecting that dedication
feat. This now grants him the ability to
cast arcane spells at trained
proficiency. His spell attack bonus for
these spells will be based on
intelligence which is plus three. So is
calculated as three for intelligence,
plus two for being trained, plus six for
his level for a total bonus of plus 11,
and a spell DC of 21. So, as a sixth
level cleric, multiclassed with wizard
and able to cast electric arc innately
from his ancestry, Valon cast his cleric
spells with a plus 12 attack bonus and
spell DC of 22. He casts electric arc as
an innate spell with a spell DC of 20.
And he casts his wizard spells with a
plus 11 attack bonus and a spell DC of
21. three different sources for spell
casting with three different attack
bonuses and DCs.
And then at seventh level, Valon gains
expert proficiency in spell attacks and
DCs. This now makes his spell attack
bonus with divine spells plus 15 and a
spell DC of 25. He can cast electric arc
with a spell DC of 23. The reason why
it's 23 and not 21 is because when you
gain proficiency in spell attacks and
DCs from multiple sources, as is the
case here with Valon, who gained
spell-casting proficiency from his
class, from an archetype, and from an
ancestry feat, you always use the
highest available spell-casting
proficiency bonus. So when he reaches
seventh level and gains expert
spell-casting proficiency from his
class, that increases his spell-casting
proficiency across the board, not just
when casting divine spells. This is a
change with the remaster edition. In the
legacy edition, you had to track a
different spell-casting proficiency
level for each of the four magical
traditions. So this also means he casts
his wizard arcane spells with expert
proficiency, too. plus 14 to attack and
a spell DC of 24. Always using the same
spell casting proficiency level does
simplify things, but remember since each
source of spellcasting uses a different
ability modifier, you still need to
track different attack bonuses and DCs.
This video has served as a foundation
for casting spells and making spell
attacks. In the next video of this
series, we'll explore the rules for
spells that do not use spell slots, such
as cantrips and focus spells, and we'll
also explore innate spellcasting, which
are spells granted by things other than
your class, such as having an ancestry
that grants access to spellcasting. If
you have any questions, please leave
them in the comments below. And as
always, I want to take a brief moment to
thank everyone who supports me and this
channel. Whether you do that by liking
the video, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon, I appreciate
everything you do to support me. And
with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
[music]