Hello and welcome to Magic and
Pathfinder second edition remastered
part 7. So far in this series, we've
mainly discussed spells that consume
spell slots or what we might call
regular spells for a lack of a better
term. And in this video, we're going to
expand that discussion to include other
types of spells, including focus spells,
innate spells, and cantrips.
A cantrip is a special kind of spell
that is usually a little bit weaker than
regular spells, but can be cast more
often and with greater flexibility.
There are two key features of cantrips
that separate them from other spells.
First, cantrips do not use spell slots
and therefore can be cast at will an
unlimited number of times per day. For
example, electric arc. Cantrips have
minimum casting ranks just like regular
spells. And we can see here electric arc
has a minimum casting rank of one.
That's by far the norm. But there are
times when a cantrip will have a higher
minimum casting rank. For example, Durge
of Doom. This is a cantrip available to
barge that has a minimum casting rank of
third. Although cantrips don't use spell
slots, these rank requirements reflect
the minimum spell slot you're able to
cast. So you would need to be at least a
fifth level bard who is able to cast
third rank spells in order to cast Durge
of Doom. Even though it is a cantrip,
that's pretty much the same as regular
spells, but what's different is since
this is a cantrip, it can be cast an
unlimited number of times each day and
does not consume any spell slots when
doing so. The second key feature of
cantrips is that they are automatically
heightened to half the caster's level
rounded up. In the case of most
spell-casting classes, this means you
can cast your cantrips at the same rank
as your highest spell slots. So, if
fifth rank spells are the highest rank
spells you can cast, you can cast your
cantrips at fifth rank too. That makes
this very easy to remember, but may not
apply if you don't belong to one of the
full spell-casting classes or receive
your spells from an archetype or some
other source. For spontaneous casters,
this means cantrips work like signature
spells in that they are freely
heightened, but still need to be
included in their spell repertoire. And
prepared spellcasters still need to
prepare their cantrips before they can
be cast. But once they're prepared or in
a spell rope patrol, the caners can be
cast as often as the player likes.
Focus spells are a special kind of spell
that is granted by certain class
features and feats. Just like with
cantrips, they're automatically
heightened to a rank that is half your
level rounded up and do not use spell
slots when they're cast. Instead, the
caster must spend a focus point to cast
a focus spell. Your focus pool capacity
automatically equals the total number of
spells you know that cost focus points
up to a maximum cap of three focus
points. And note that it says spells
that cost focus points. Not all focus
spells cost focus points. For example,
bards and witches both have focus
cantrips. Only focus spells that cost
focus points count towards the size of
your focus pool. Also, be aware that you
only have one focus pool. Meaning, if
you multiclass and receive focus points
from multiple sources, they're all
combined into one pool of resources. You
don't have to track that you got two
focus points from your witch class and
one from multiclassing into champion.
Instead, you have a single pull of three
focus points that can be spent however
you like on the focus spells you have
access to from all the different
sources. These points are fully
replenished as part of your daily
preparations, just like spell slots are.
But a major benefit of focus spells is
you don't have to wait until the next
morning to get them back. The refocus
exploration activity can be used to
regain spent focus points. This takes 10
minutes after which you regain one focus
point. And unlike with the legacy
edition in the remaster, there are no
limits to this. If you spend all three
focus points during an encounter, you
can spend 30 minutes after the encounter
performing the refocus activity three
times to get the ball back. Also, it's
worth noting that when a member of a
non-sp spell-casting class gains focus
spells, for example, monks with the key
strike feat, they gain the ability to
use the cast a spell activity so they
can cast these focus spells. But the
ability to cast these focus spells does
not make them a quote spellcaster. In
other words, if you are a monk who uses
focus spells, you do not qualify for any
feats or other rules that would require
you to be a quote spellcaster.
Innate spells are another special type
of spell we should discuss. These spells
are often considered to be natural
talent and are usually granted by a
character's ancestry or by an item and
allow a character to cast spells without
belonging to a spell-casting class. For
example, an elf who chooses the
otherworldly magic feat can cast any one
arcane cantrip as an innate spell. This
represents a natural talent for magic
and has nothing to do with their class.
They can be a fighter and still cast a
single cantrip thanks to this feat. When
you gain access to an innate spell,
whatever ability granted that access
will tell you how often you can cast it.
For example, other worldly magic lets
you cast your innate spell at will,
meaning as often as you like. But a
dwarf with the stone walker feet can
only cast their innate spell, one with
stone, once per day. And innate cantrips
are automatically heightened as normal
for cantrips, but not other innate
spells. When you gain access to an
innate spell, you can cast it, even if
it is a higher rank than you normally
would be able to cast. This is
especially common with monsters who can
cast innate spells. You always have at
least trained proficiency in spell
attacks and spell DC for your innate
spells, which automatically increases to
expert at 12th level. This guarantees
that non-sp spell-casting classes like
fighter remain capable with their innate
spells at higher levels without needing
a spell-casting class to scale their
proficiency level. And you use charisma
as the ability modifier when calculating
the spell attack bonus and spell DC for
innate spells, even if you use a
different ability to cast spells granted
by your class. See part six of this
series of videos for a complete
illustration of how that works. I'll
include a link to that video in this
video's description.
This video has served as a foundation
for casting less traditional spells such
as cantrips, focus spells, and innate
spells. In the next video of the series,
we'll explore the rules for rituals,
which are spells that are cast in
exploration mode with casting times
ranging from several minutes to entire
days and often require multiple
spellcasters to work together. If you
have any questions, please leave them in
the comments below. And as always, I
want to take a brief moment to thank
everyone who supports me and this
channel. Whether you do that by liking
the video, leaving a comment,
subscribing to the channel, or
subscribing to the Patreon, I appreciate
everything you do to support me. And
with that, thanks for watching. Take
care and happy gaming.
Oh,